<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.33.0-wmf.6</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Aotearoa International Ltd v Scancarriers A/S</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>43936208</id>
    <revision>
      <id>807306216</id>
      <parentid>752901903</parentid>
      <timestamp>2017-10-27T04:28:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Sodacan</username>
        <id>8272776</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>name change; criterion 1 ([[Commons:Commons:GlobalReplace|GlobalReplace v0.6.5]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="2616">{{Orphan|date=March 2015}}

{{Infobox court case
| name = Aotearoa International Ltd v Scancarriers A/S
| court = [[Privy Council]]
| date_filed = 
| image = Coat of arms of New Zealand.svg
| date decided = 18 July 1985
| full name = Aotearoa International Ltd v Scancarriers A/S
| citations = [1985] 1 NZLR 513
| judges = [[Lord Keith]], [[Lord Roskill]], [[Lord Brightman]], [[John Megaw|Sir John Megaw]], [[Owen Woodhouse|Sir Owen Woodhouse]]
| prior actions =   
| subsequent actions = 
| opinions = 
| transcripts =  [http://www.bailii.org/uk/cases/UKPC/1985/1985_26.pdf Privy Council judgment]
| Keywords = 
}}
'''Aotearoa International Ltd v Scancarriers A/S''' [1985] 1 NZLR 513  is a cited case in New Zealand regarding contract formation.&lt;ref name="Chetwin, Graw, Tiong"&gt;{{cite book |title=An introduction to the Law of Contract in New Zealand |edition=4th |last1=Chetwin |first1=Maree |last2=Graw |first2=Stephen |last3=Tiong |first3=Raymond |publisher=Thomson Brookers |ISBN=0-86472-555-8 |year=2006 |page={{page needed|date=January 2014}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Walker"&gt;{{cite book |title=Butterworths Student Companion Contract |edition=4th |last1=Walker |first1=Campbell |publisher=LexisNexis |ISBN=0-408-71770-X|year=2004 |page=27-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Background==
Aotearoa International was in the business of paper recycling, and were looking to expand by exporting to India, and was discussing with Scancarriers of shipping 4 shiploads of 1,000 tons each.

As a result of these negotiations, Scancarriers sent the following telex "FLWG OUR DISCUSSION ON FRIDAY [...] WE AGREE TO A PROMOTIONAL RATE OF US$120 [...] AND THIS RATE WILL BE HELD UNTIL 29/7/82 [...]."

However, when Aotearoa delivered the first shipment of 919 tons, Scancarriers only had space to ship some of the paper, with the remaining 271 tons being shipped on a subsequent ship.

The split sailings caused cashflow problems for Aotearoa, leaving them unable to pay for the shipping costs for the second shipment resulting in Sancarriers selling the paper to recoup the shipping costs.

Aotearoa sued for breach of contract.

==Held==
The Court ruled that the telex was merely a quote, and not an offer, as Aotearoa's manager admitted during cross examination that the normal shipping practice was that a freight contract only starts when the freight is delivered to the port and accepted for loading.

==References==
{{reflist}}

[[Category:New Zealand contract case law]]
[[Category:1985 in case law]]
[[Category:1985 in New Zealand law]]
[[Category:Judicial Committee of the Privy Council cases on appeal from New Zealand]]


{{law-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>p1yj20k0egr4txu0s35zptdg4049rw4</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Articles of impeachment</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2301803</id>
    <revision>
      <id>862729578</id>
      <parentid>852009681</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-10-06T08:46:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>DroitDeDroit</username>
        <id>33658201</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>incorrect constitutional law corrected.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="2971">The '''articles of impeachment''' are the set of charges drafted against a public official to initiate the [[impeachment]] process.  The articles of impeachment do not result in the removal of the official, but instead require the enacting body to take further action, such as bringing the articles to a vote before the full body

In the [[United States]], the articles of impeachment are drafted by the [[United States House of Representatives|House of Representatives]] for cases involving federal officials.  Once drafted, a [[supermajority]] of the [[United States Senate]] is required to convict based on the articles.

A person of a high office can be impeached if they have committed a high misdemeanor, a felony, or treason. An impeachment trial is carried out in the Senate, with the [[Chief Justice of the United States|Chief Justice of the Supreme Court]] presiding if the impeachment involves the President. Impeachment can expand beyond senior members of the White House. A [[Supreme Court of the United States]] Justice may be impeached for committing a high misdemeanor, treason, or a felony. Impeachment charges must be drafted in the House of Representatives. The trial for the person undergoing such occurs in the Senate, requiring 60 votes or more of 100 senators to successfully impeach a public official.

== See also ==
* [[Impeachment in the United States]]
* [[Impeachment investigations of United States federal judges]]
* [[Impeachment investigations of United States federal officials]]

==Further reading==
* [http://sherman.house.gov/sites/sherman.house.gov/files/FINAL%20Article%20of%20Impeachment.pdf Articles of Impeachment Against Donald J. Trump, 2017]
==External links==
* [http://watergate.info/impeachment/impeachment-articles.shtml Articles of Impeachment against Richard Nixon, 1974]. See also: [[Impeachment process against Richard Nixon]]
* [http://frwebgate.access.gpo.gov/cgi-bin/getdoc.cgi?dbname=106_cong_documents&amp;docid=f:sd3v194.106.pdf Articles of Impeachment Against Judge Harry E. Claiborne, 1986]
* [http://frwebgate.access.gpo.gov/cgi-bin/getdoc.cgi?dbname=106_cong_documents&amp;docid=f:sd3v195.106.pdf Articles of Impeachment Against Judge Alcee L. Hastings, 1988]
* [http://frwebgate.access.gpo.gov/cgi-bin/getdoc.cgi?dbname=106_cong_documents&amp;docid=f:sd3v196.106.pdf Articles of Impeachment Against Judge Walter L. Nixon, 1989]
* [https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-srv/politics/special/clinton/stories/articles122098.htm Articles of Impeachment against Bill Clinton, 1998]. See also: [[Impeachment of Bill Clinton]]
* [[s:Articles of Impeachment Against United States District Court Judge Samuel B. Kent|Articles of Impeachment Against Judge Samuel B. Kent, 2009]]
* [[s:Articles of Impeachment Against United States District Court Judge G. Thomas Porteous, Jr.|Articles of Impeachment Against Judge Thomas Porteous, 2010]]

[[Category:Impeachment in the United States]]
[[Category:Constitutional law]]

{{US-gov-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>j3ztvaxvnvm3ui4l5uyksv2jmxglzl4</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Burlaw court</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>15944487</id>
    <revision>
      <id>719261818</id>
      <parentid>590232860</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-05-08T16:07:12Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Anythingyouwant</username>
        <id>61960</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Add wlink.  The number of wlinks has doubled since tag was added, so removing tag.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="954">'''Burlaw court''', ''{{lang-ru|Товарищеский суд}}'' (verb. "court of comrades") was a special form of collective justice that existed in the [[Soviet Union]]. Burlaw courts were elected for the term of two years by open voting of [[Collectivization in the Soviet Union|working collective]] members, and were entitled to consider minor offences and to impose fines up to 50 [[Soviet ruble]]s (compared to the average monthly salary of 120 rubles) or to pass the case for consideration to regular courts of justice. After the breakdown of the Soviet Union burlaw courts were no longer elected and were finally abolished by adoption of [[Criminal Code of Russia|Russia's new Criminal Code]] in 1997.

== References ==
* Филиппов Е. И., Комментарий к Положению о товарищеских судах, М., 1972
* Товарищеские суды, М., 1974

[[Category:Soviet law]]


{{law-stub}}
{{USSR-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>4d6ht4j0y87hafwp756y9gsx6jz2uwl</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Do not resuscitate</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>166811</id>
    <revision>
      <id>867439728</id>
      <parentid>867304528</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-11-05T18:59:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Smyth</username>
        <id>85019</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>"information"??</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="22571">{{For|the television episode|Do Not Resuscitate (The Sopranos)}}
{{Infobox medical intervention
| name         = Do Not Resuscitate
| image        = Virginia Sample DDNR.jpg
| caption      = DNR form used in [[Virginia]]
| alt          = 
| pronounce    =  
| synonyms     = Do not attempt resuscitation, allow natural death, no code
| ICD10        = 
| ICD9         = 
| ICD9unlinked = 
| MeshID       = 
| LOINC        = 
| other_codes  = 
| MedlinePlus  = 
| eMedicine    = 
}}

'''Do Not Resuscitate''' ('''DNR'''), also known as '''no code''' or '''allow natural death''', is a legal order written either in the hospital or on a legal form to withhold [[cardiopulmonary resuscitation]] (CPR) or [[advanced cardiac life support]] (ACLS), in respect of the wishes of a patient in case their [[Asystole|heart were to stop]] or they were to [[Apnea|stop breathing]]. The DNR request is usually made by the patient or health care [[power of attorney]] and allows the medical teams taking care of them to respect their wishes. In the health care community, [[allow natural death]] (AND) is a term that is quickly gaining favor as it focuses on what is being done, not what is being avoided.{{citation needed|date=October 2014}} Some criticize the term "do not resuscitate" because of the implication of important treatment being withheld, while research shows that only about 5% of patients who require CPR outside the hospital and only 15% of patients who require CPR while in the hospital survive.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | pmid = 17174021 | doi=10.1016/j.resuscitation.2006.06.135 | volume=72 | issue=3 | title=Epidemiology and outcomes of out-of-hospital cardiac arrest in Rochester, New York | date=March 2007 | author=Fairbanks RJ, Shah MN, Lerner EB, Ilangovan K, Pennington EC, Schneider SM | journal=Resuscitation | pages=415–24}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | pmid = 10888971 | volume=160 | issue=13 | title=Short- and long-term survival after cardiopulmonary resuscitation |date=July 2000 |vauthors=Zoch TW, Desbiens NA, DeStefano F, Stueland DT, Layde PM | journal=Arch. Intern. Med. | pages=1969–73 | doi=10.1001/archinte.160.13.1969}}&lt;/ref&gt; Patients who are elderly, are living in nursing homes, have multiple medical problems, or who have advanced cancer are much less likely to survive.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | pmid = 19571280 | doi=10.1056/NEJMoa0810245 | volume=361 | issue=1 | title=Epidemiologic study of in-hospital cardiopulmonary resuscitation in the elderly | pmc=2917337 |date=July 2009  |vauthors=Ehlenbach WJ, Barnato AE, Curtis JR, etal | journal=N. Engl. J. Med. | pages=22–31}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A DNR does not affect any treatment other than that which would require [[tracheal intubation|intubation]] or [[CPR]]. Patients who are DNR can continue to get chemotherapy, antibiotics, dialysis, or any other appropriate treatments.
{{TOC limit|3}}

== Terminology ==
''DNR'' and ''Do Not Resuscitate'' are common terms in the United States, Canada, New Zealand and the United Kingdom. This may be clarified in some regions with the addition of ''DNI'' (Do Not Intubate), although in some hospitals ''DNR'' alone will imply no [[tracheal intubation|intubation]]. Clinically, the vast majority of people requiring resuscitation will require intubation, making a DNI alone problematic. Hospitals sometimes use the expression ''no code'', which refers to the jargon term ''code'', short for ''[[Hospital emergency codes#Code Blue|Code Blue]]'', an alert a hospital's resuscitation team.

Some areas of the United States and the United Kingdom include the letter A, as in ''DNAR'', to clarify "Do Not ''Attempt'' Resuscitation." This alteration is so that it is not presumed by the patient or family that an attempt at resuscitation will be successful. Since the term DNR implies the omission of action, and therefore "giving up", some have advocated for these orders to be retermed ''Allow Natural Death''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hospicepatients.org/and.html Alternative to "DNR" Designation: "Allow Natural Death" - Making Sense in the Health Care Industry&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;].&lt;/ref&gt; New Zealand and Australia, and some hospitals in the UK, use the term ''NFR'' or ''Not For Resuscitation''. Typically these abbreviations are not punctuated, e.g., ''DNR'' rather than ''D.N.R.''

Resuscitation orders, or lack thereof, can also be referred to in the United States as a part of [[Physician Orders for Life-Sustaining Treatment|Physician Orders for Life Sustaining Treatment (POLST)]] or [[Medical Orders for Life-Sustaining Treatment|Medical Orders for Life Sustaining Treatment (MOLST)]] orders&lt;ref&gt;Pollak, Andrew.  ''Emergency Care and Transportation of the Sick and Injured''.  Jones &amp; Bartlett Learning, 2017, isbn 978-1-284-10690-9, Page 540.&lt;/ref&gt;, typically created with input from next of kin when the patient or client is not able to communicate their wishes.

Another synonymous term is "''not to be resuscitated''" (''NTBR'').&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Vincent JL, Van Vooren JP | date = Dec 2002 | title = [NTBR (Not to Be Resuscitated) in 10 questions] | url = | journal = Rev Med Brux. | volume = 23 | issue = 6| pages = 497–9 | pmid = 12584945 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Until recently in the UK it was common to write "Not for 222" or conversationally, "Not for twos." This was implicitly a hospital DNR order, where 222 (or similar) is the hospital telephone number for the emergency resuscitation or crash team.{{Citation needed|date=July 2011}}

==Advance directive and living will==
[[Advance directives]] and [[living wills]] are documents written by individuals themselves, so as to state their wishes for care, if they are no longer able to speak for themselves. In contrast, it is a physician or hospital staff member who writes a DNR "physician's order," based upon the wishes previously expressed by the individual in his or her advance directive or living will. Similarly, at a time when the individual is unable to express his wishes, but has previously used an advance directive to appoint an agent, then a physician can write such a DNR "physician's order" at the request of that individual's agent. These various situations are clearly enumerated in the "sample" DNR order presented on this page.

It should be stressed that, in the United States, an advance directive or living will is not sufficient to ensure a patient is treated under the DNR protocol, even if it is their wish, as neither an advance directive nor a living will is a legally binding document.

== Ethics ==
DNR orders in certain situations have been subject to ethical debate. In many institutions it is customary for a patient going to surgery to have their DNR automatically rescinded. Though the rationale for this may be valid, as outcomes from [[CPR]] in the operating room are substantially better than general survival outcomes after CPR, the impact on patient autonomy has been debated. It is suggested that facilities engage patients or their decision makers in a  'reconsideration of DNR orders' instead of automatically making a forced decision.&lt;ref&gt;Dugan D, Riseman J. Do-Not-Resuscitate Orders in an Operating Room Setting #292. Journal of Palliative Medicine [serial online]. July 2015;18(7):638-639.&lt;/ref&gt;

There is accumulating evidence of a racial bias in DNR adoption. A 2014 study of end stage cancer patients found that non-Latino white patients were significantly more likely to have a DNR order (45%) than black (25%) and Latino (20%) patients. The correlation between preferences against life-prolonging care and the increased likelihood of advance care planning is consistent across ethnic groups.&lt;ref&gt;Garrido M, Harrington S, Prigerson H. End-of-life treatment preferences: A key to reducing ethnic/racial disparities in advance care planning?. Cancer (0008543X) [serial online]. December 15, 2014;120(24):3981-3986.&lt;/ref&gt;

Ethical dilemmas occur when a patient with a DNR attempts suicide and the necessary treatment involves ventilation or CPR. In these cases it has been argued that the principle of beneficence takes precedence over patient autonomy and the DNR can be revoked by the physician.&lt;ref&gt;Humble M. Do-Not-Resuscitate Orders and Suicide Attempts. National Catholic Bioethics Quarterly [serial online]. Winter2014 2014;14(4):661-671.&lt;/ref&gt; Another dilemma occurs when a medical error happens to a patient with a DNR. If the error is reversible only with CPR or ventilation there is no consensus if resuscitation should take place or not.&lt;ref&gt;Hébert P, Selby D. Should a reversible, but lethal, incident not be treated when a patient has a do-not-resuscitate order?. CMAJ: Canadian Medical Association Journal [serial online]. April 15, 2014;186(7):528-530.&lt;/ref&gt;

There are also ethical concerns around how patients reach the decision to make themselves a DNR. One study found that when questioned in more detail, many patients who were DNR actually would have wanted the excluded interventions depending on the scenario. Most would prefer life saving intubation in the scenario of [[angioedema]] which typically resolves in days. One fifth of the DNR patients would want resuscitation for [[cardiac arrest]] but to have care withdrawn after a week. It is possible that providers are having a "leading conversation" with patients or mistakenly leaving crucial information out when discussing DNR.&lt;ref&gt;Capone R. PROBLEMS WITH DNR AND DNI ORDERS. (Cover story). Ethics &amp; Medics [serial online]. March 2014;39(3):1-3.&lt;/ref&gt; One study reported that physicians repeatedly give high intensity care to patients while deciding they themselves would be DNR under similar circumstances.&lt;ref&gt;Physicians provide high-intensity end-of-life care for patients, but "no code" for themselves.
Medical Ethics Advisor Volume: 30 Issue 10 (2014) {{ISSN|0886-0653}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There is also the ethical issue of discontinuation of an [[implantable cardioverter defibrillator]] (ICD) in DNR patients in cases of medical futility. A large survey of [[Electrophysiology]] practitioners, the heart specialists who implant [[pacemakers]] and ICD's noted that the practitioners felt that deactivating an ICD was not ethically distinct from withholding CPR thus consistent with DNR. Most felt that deactivating a pacemaker was a separate issue and could not be broadly ethically endorsed. Pacemakers were felt to be unique devices, or ethically taking a role of "keeping a patient alive" like [[dialysis]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Daeschler M, Verdino RJ, Caplan AL, Kirkpatrick JN | year = 2015 | title = Defibrillator Deactivation against a Patient's Wishes: Perspectives of Electrophysiology Practitioners | url = | journal = Pacing and Clinical Electrophysiology | volume = 38 | issue = 8| pages = 917–924 | doi = 10.1111/pace.12614 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Usage by country==
DNR documents are widespread in some countries and unavailable in others. In countries where a DNR is unavailable the decision to end resuscitation is made solely by physicians.

=== Middle East ===
DNRs are not recognized by [[Jordan]]. Physicians attempt to resuscitate all patients regardless of individual or familial wishes.&lt;ref name="The Globe and Mail "&gt;{{cite news |title = Mideast med-school camp: divided by conflict, united by profession
|url = https://www.theglobeandmail.com/life/health/mideast-med-school-camp-divided-by-conflict-united-by-profession/article1257723/ |accessdate = 2009-08-22 |date = August 2009 |work = The Globe and Mail |quote = In hospitals in Jordan and Palestine, neither families nor social workers are allowed in the operating room to observe resuscitation, says Mohamad Yousef, a sixth-year medical student from Jordan. There are also no DNRs. “If it was within the law, I would always work to save a patient, even if they didn't want me to,” he says. }}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[UAE]] have laws forcing healthcare staff to resuscitate a patient even if the patient has a DNR or does not wish to live. There are penalties for breaching the laws.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thenational.ae/news/uae-news/courts/nurses-deny-knowledge-of-do-not-resuscitate-order-in-patients-death|title=Nurses deny knowledge of 'do not resuscitate' order in patient's death|author=|date=|website=thenational.ae|accessdate=12 April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Saudi Arabia]] patients cannot legally sign a DNR, but DNR accepted by order of primary physician in case of terminally ill patients.
In [[Israel]], it is possible to sign a DNR form as long as the patient is dying and aware of their actions.{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}}

=== United Kingdom ===
[[File:Scotland DNACPR - obverse.png|thumbnail|DNACPR form as used in Scotland]]

==== England and Wales ====
In [[England and Wales]], CPR is presumed in the event of a [[cardiac arrest]] unless a ''do not resuscitate'' order is in place. If they have capacity as defined under the [[Mental Capacity Act 2005]] the patient may decline resuscitation, however any discussion is not in reference to consent to resuscitation and instead should be an explanation.&lt;ref name="Resus Council Consent."&gt;{{cite web|title=Decisions relating to cardiopulmonary resuscitation: A joint statement from the British Medical Association, the Resuscitation Council (UK) and the Royal College of Nursing|url=http://www.resus.org.uk/pages/dnar.pdf|website=Resus.org.uk|publisher=Resuscitation Council (UK)|accessdate=17 June 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Patients may also specify their wishes and/or devolve their decision-making to a proxy using an [[advance directive]], which are commonly referred to as '[[Living Wills]]'. Patients and relatives cannot demand treatment (including CPR) which the doctor believes is futile and in this situation, it is their doctor's duty to act in their 'best interest', whether that means continuing or discontinuing treatment, using their clinical judgment. If they lack capacity relatives will often be asked for their opinion out of [[respect]].

==== Scotland ====
In [[Scotland]], the terminology used is "Do Not Attempt Cardiopulmonary Resuscitation" or "DNACPR". There is a single policy used across all of [[NHS Scotland]]. The legal standing is similar to that in England and Wales, in that CPR is viewed as a treatment and, although there is a general presumption that CPR will be performed in the case of cardiac arrest, this is not the case if it is viewed by the treating [[clinician]] to be futile. Patients and families cannot demand CPR to be performed if it is felt to be futile (as with any medical treatment) and a DNACPR can be issued despite disagreement, although it is good practice to involve all parties in the discussion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Do Not Attempt Cardiopulmonary Resuscitation (DNACPR): Integrated Adult Policy|author=Scottish Government|publisher=NHS Scotland|date=May 2010|url=http://www.scotland.gov.uk/Resource/Doc/312784/0098903.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== United States ===
In the United States the documentation is especially complicated in that each state accepts different forms, and [[advance directives]] and [[living wills]] may not be accepted by [[Emergency medical services|EMS]] as legally valid forms. If a patient has a living will that specifies the patient requests of DNR but does not have a properly filled out state-sponsored form that is co-signed by a physician, EMS may attempt resuscitation.

The DNR decision by patients was first litigated in 1976 in [[In re Quinlan]]. The New Jersey Supreme Court upheld the right of Karen Ann Quinlan's parents to order her removal from [[artificial ventilation]]. In 1991 Congress passed into law the [[Patient Self-Determination Act]] that mandated hospitals honor an individual's decision in their healthcare.&lt;ref name="The continuing ethical dilemma of the do-not-resuscitate order "&gt;{{cite news |title = The continuing ethical dilemma of the do-not-resuscitate order |url = http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m0FSL/is_n4_v67/ai_20972811/ |accessdate = 2009-08-23 |date = April 1998 |work = AORN Journal |quote = The right to refuse or terminate medical treatment began evolving in 1976 with the case of Karen Ann Quinlan v New Jersey (70NJ10, 355 A2d, 647 [NJ 1976]). This spawned subsequent cases leading to the use of the DNR order.(4) In 1991, the Patient Self-Determination Act mandated hospitals ensure that a patient's right to make personal health care decisions is upheld. According to the act, a patient has the right to refuse treatment, as well as the right to refuse resuscitative measures.(5) This right usually is accomplished by the use of the DNR order. | first=Evelyn | last=Eckberg}}&lt;/ref&gt; Forty-nine states currently permit the next of kin to make medical decisions of incapacitated relatives, the exception being [[Missouri]].  Missouri has a Living Will Statute that requires two witnesses to any signed advance directive that results in a DNR/DNI code status in the hospital.

In the United States, [[cardiopulmonary resuscitation]] (CPR) and [[advanced cardiac life support]] (ACLS) will not be performed if a valid written "DNR" order is present. Many states do not recognize [[living wills]] or [[health care proxy|health care proxies]] in the prehospital setting and prehospital personnel in those areas may be required to initiate resuscitation measures unless a specific state-sponsored form is properly filled out and cosigned by a physician.&lt;ref name="DO NOT RESUSCITATE – ADVANCE DIRECTIVES FOR EMS

Frequently Asked Questions and Answers "&gt;{{cite news|title=DO NOT RESUSCITATE – ADVANCE DIRECTIVES FOR EMS Frequently Asked Questions and Answers |url=http://www.emsa.ca.gov/personnel/DNR_faq.asp |accessdate=2009-08-23 |year=2007 |work=State of California Emergency Medical Services Authority |quote=# What if the EMT cannot find the DNR form or evidence of a MedicAlert medallion? Will they withhold resuscitative measures if my family asks them to? No. EMS personnel are taught to proceed with CPR when needed, unless they are absolutely certain that a qualified DNR advance directive exists for that patient. If, after spending a reasonable (very short) amount of time looking for the form or medallion, they do not see it, they will proceed with lifesaving measures. |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090823161856/http://www.emsa.ca.gov/personnel/DNR_faq.asp |archivedate=2009-08-23 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Frequently Asked Questions re: DNR's "&gt;{{cite news |title = Frequently Asked Questions re: DNR's |url =http://www.health.state.ny.us/nysdoh/ems/policy/99-10.htm |accessdate = 2009-08-23 |date = 1999-12-30 |work = New York State Department of Health |quote = May EMS providers accept living wills or health care proxies? A living will or health care proxy is NOT valid in the prehospital setting  }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Canada===

Do not resuscitate orders are similar to those used in the United States. In 1995, the [[Canadian Medical Association]], [[Canadian Hospital Association]], [[Canadian Nursing Association]], and [[Catholic Health Association of Canada]] worked with [[Canadian Bar Association]] clarify and create a '''Joint Statement on Resuscitative Interventions''' guideline for use to determine when and how DNR orders are assigned.&lt;ref name="caringtotheend.ca"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.caringtotheend.ca/body.php?id%3D515%26cc%3D1 |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2012-12-05 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140715000749/http://www.caringtotheend.ca/body.php?id=515&amp;cc=1 |archivedate=2014-07-15 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt; DNR orders must be discussed by doctors with the patient or patient agents or patient's significant others. Unilateral DNR by medical professionals can only be used if the patient is in a vegetative state.&lt;ref name="caringtotheend.ca"/&gt;

===Australia===

In Australia, Do Not Resuscitate orders are covered by legislation on a state-by-state basis.

In Victoria, a Refusal of Medical Treatment certificate is a legal means to refuse medical treatments of current medical conditions.  It does not apply to palliative care (reasonable pain relief; food and drink).  An Advanced Care Directive legally defines the medical treatments that a person may choose to receive (or not to receive) in various defined circumstances.  It can be used to refuse resuscitation, so as avoid needless suffering.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.dwdv.org.au/resources/dwdv-forms|title=Respect for the right to choose - Resources|publisher= Dying with dignity, Victoria|date=2017|accessdate=2017-06-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In NSW, a Resuscitation Plan is a medically authorised order to use or withhold resuscitation measures, and which documents other aspects of treatment relevant at end of life.  Such plans are only valid for patients of a doctor who is a NSW Health staff member.  The plan allows for the refusal of any and all life-sustaining treatments, the advance refusal for a time of future incapacity, and the decision to move to purely palliative care.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www1.health.nsw.gov.au/pds/ActivePDSDocuments/PD2014_030.pdf|title=Using resuscitation plans in end of life decisions|publisher=NSW government health department|date=2014-09-08|accessdate=2017-06-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Italy ===
DNRs are not recognized by [[Italy]]. Physicians must attempt to resuscitate all patients regardless of individual or familial wishes. Italian laws force healthcare staff to resuscitate a patient even if the patient has a DNR or does not wish to live. There are jail penalties (from 6 to 15 years) for healthcare staff breaching this law, e.g. "omicidio del consenziente".&lt;ref&gt;[[:it:Omicidio del consenziente (ordinamento penale italiano)]]&lt;/ref&gt;{{Better source|reason=per WP:CIRCULAR|date=May 2018}} Therefore in [[Italy]] a signed DNR has no legal value.

==See also==
{{Portal|Medicine}}
{{columns-list|colwidth=30em|
*[[Advance health care directive|Advance Health Care Directive]]
*[[Cardiac arrest]]
*[[Power of attorney]]
*[[Letting die]]
*[[Euthanasia]]
*[[Uniform Rights of the Terminally Ill Act]]
*[[Patient Self-Determination Act]]
*[[Slow code]]
*[[Medical ethics]]
}}

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

==External links==
*[https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/patientinstructions/000473.htm Do Not Resuscitate Orders] Published by the U.S. National Library of Medicine 
*[http://www.resus.org.uk/pages/dnar.htm Decisions Relating to Cardiopulmonary Resuscitation] Published by the Resuscitation Council (UK)

[[Category:Cardiopulmonary resuscitation]]
[[Category:Euthanasia]]
[[Category:Legal aspects of death]]
[[Category:Ethically disputed medical practices]]

[[de:Patientenverfügung]]
[[pl:DNAR]]
[[tr:Diriltmeyin]]</text>
      <sha1>1cj1p6js06brroexl6disnlihkl6kvk</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Elections Act 1958</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>50246668</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750592423</id>
      <parentid>731246742</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-20T18:39:33Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Narky Blert</username>
        <id>22041646</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Link to DAB page -&gt; repaired hatnote</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="5729">{{other uses|Elections Act (disambiguation){{!}}Elections Act}}
{{unreferenced|date=April 2016}}

{{Infobox legislation
|short_title            = Elections Act 1958
|legislature            = 
|image                  = 
|imagesize              = 
|imagealt               = 
|caption                = 
|long_title             = An Act providing for the elections to the Dewan Rakyat and to the Legislative Assemblies of the States.
|citation               = [http://www.agc.gov.my/agcportal/uploads/files/Publications/LOM/EN/Act%2019%20-%20Elections%20Act%201958.pdf Act 19]
|territorial_extent     = Throughout [[Malaysia]]
|considered_by          =
|enacted_by             = 
|date_enacted           = 1958 (Ordinance No. 33 of 1958)&lt;br&gt;Revised: 1970 (Act 19 w.e.f. 11 January 1971)
|date_passed            = 
|enacted_by2            = 
|date_enacted2          = 
|date_passed2           = 
|date_assented          = 
|royal_assent           =
|date_signed            = 
|signed_by              = 
|date_commenced         = 
|date_effective         = Peninsular Malaysia, Federal Territory of Putrajaya{{efn|Note—See section 6 of Act A1095.}}—28 August 1958, L.N. 250/1958;&lt;br&gt;Sabah{{efn|Note—For extension and modification of Act to Sabah, see P.U. 56/1966, P.U. 144/1966,
 P.U. 498/1966, P.U. 348/1967.}}, Federal Territory of Labuan{{efn|Note—See section 6 of Act A585.}}—1 August 1965, P.U. 176/1966;&lt;br&gt;Sarawak{{efn|Note—For extension and modification of Act to Sarawak, see P.U. 497/1966, P.U. 349/1967,
 P.U. 55/1968.}}—1 November 1966, P.U. 227/1967
|date_of_expiry         = 
|date_repealed          = 
|administered_by        = 
|bill                   = 
|bill_citation          = 
|bill_date              = 
|introduced_by          = 
|1st_reading            = 
|2nd_reading            = 
|3rd_reading            = 
|conf_committee_passed  = 
|committee_report       = 
|bill2                  = 
|bill_citation2         = 
|bill_date2             = 
|introduced_by2         = 
|1st_reading2           = 
|2nd_reading2           =  
|3rd_reading2           = 
|conf_committee_passed2 = 
|committee_report2      = 
|date_conf_committee    = 
|white_paper            = 
|amendments             = Constitution (Amendment) Act 1962 [Act 14/1962]&lt;br&gt;Election Act 1963 [Act 13/1963]&lt;br&gt;Elections (Amendment) Act 1965 [Act 7/1965]&lt;br&gt;Modification of Laws (Election Offences and Elections) (Extension to Sabah) Order 1966 [P.U. 56/1966]&lt;br&gt;Modification of Laws (Election Offences and Elections) (Extension to Sabah) Order 1966 [P.U. 144/1966]&lt;br&gt;Modification of Laws (Election Offences and Elections) (Extension to Sarawak) Order 1966 [P.U. 497/1966]&lt;br&gt;Modification of Laws (Election Offences and Elections) (Extension to Sabah) (Amendment) Order 1966 [P.U. 498/1966]&lt;br&gt;Modification of Laws (Election Offences and Elections) (Extension to Sabah) (Amendment) Order 1967 [P.U. 348/1967]&lt;br&gt;Modification of Laws (Election Offences and Elections) (Extension to Sarawak) (Amendment) Order 1967 [P.U. 349/1967]&lt;br&gt;Modification of Laws (Election Offences and Elections) (Extension to Sarawak) (Amendment) Order 1968 [P.U. 55/1968]&lt;br&gt;Elections (Amendment) Act 1972 [Act A95]&lt;br&gt;Malaysian Currency (Ringgit) Act 1975 [Act 160]&lt;br&gt;Notification under Titles of Office Ordinance 1949 [P.U. (B) 57/1982]&lt;br&gt;Elections (Amendment) Act 1986 [Act A639]&lt;br&gt;Elections (Amendment) Act 1990 [Act A768]&lt;br&gt;Elections (Amendment) Act 1994 [Act A889]&lt;br&gt;Elections (Amendment) Act 2002 [Act A1155]&lt;br&gt;Elections (Amendment) Act 2003 [Act A1205]&lt;br&gt;Elections (Amendment) Act 2007 [Act A1317]

|repeals                = 
|related_legislation    = 
|summary                = 
|keywords               = [[Election]], [[election officer]], [[constituency]], [[voter registration]], [[election writ]], [[polling place]]
|status                 = In force
}}
The '''Elections Act 1958''' ({{lang-ms|Akta Pilihan Raya 1958}}) is a [[Malaysia]]n law which enacted to provide for the elections to the [[Dewan Rakyat]] and [[Dewan Undangan Negeri]].

==Structure==
The Elections Act 1958, in its current form (1 December 2011), consists of 6 Parts containing 17 sections and no schedule (including 19 amendments).
* Part I: Preliminary
** Section 1: Short title
** Section 2: Interpretation
* Part II: Supervision of Elections
** Section 3: Appointments of officers
** Section 3A: General powers and duties of Secretary, Deputy Secretary and Assistant Secretaries
** Section 4: Powers of officers
** Section 5: General powers and duties of Election Commission 
* Part III: Constituencies
** Section 6: (Deleted)
** Section 7: Polling districts and polling centres
* Part IV: Registration of Electors
** Section 8: Appointment of officers
** Section 9: Preparation, publication and revision of electoral rolls
** Section 9A: Certified or re-certified electoral roll shall be deemed to be final
** Section 10: Registration in one constituency only
** Section 11: (Deleted)
* Part V: Conduct of Elections
** Section 12: Writs of election
** Section 13: Election of candidates
** Section 14: Use of schools and public buildings and premises as polling centres
* Part VI: Regulations
** Section 15: Power to make regulations relating to the registration of electors
** Section 16: Power to make regulations relating to the conduct of elections
** Section 17: Regulations to be laid before the Dewan Rakyat

==Footnotes==
{{notelist}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.agc.gov.my/agcportal/uploads/files/Publications/LOM/EN/Act%2019%20-%20Elections%20Act%201958.pdf Elections Act 1958] {{PD-notice}}

{{law-stub}}
[[Category:1958 in Malayan law]]
[[Category:Malaysian federal legislation]]
[[Category:Elections in Malaysia]]</text>
      <sha1>gyuur8fzh0hwbvtj9cp2r8ta9pxwnsk</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Gazette officielle du Québec</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>35885391</id>
    <revision>
      <id>858975047</id>
      <parentid>852931756</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-09-10T21:42:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Veryproicelandic</username>
        <id>23790359</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>added a couple of links, removed that flag...</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="1490">{{Use mdy dates|date=March 2016}}
{{more citations needed|date=February 2017}}
{{Italic title}}
The '''''Gazette officielle du Québec''''' is an official publication of the [[Government of Quebec|Quebec government]]. It is used to promulgate new [[law]]s and [[regulation]]s, which thereby become official. It was founded on January 16, 1869.

An earlier ''Gazette de Québec'' was an unofficial publication created in 1764, and was replaced by ''Gazette officielle du Québec'' in 1823. Archived versions of the ''Gazette'' from 1869 to 1995 are available. An annual subscription to the Gazette costs $1185 ($500 and $685, for part 1 and 2, respectively) per year, for both parts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www3.publicationsduquebec.gouv.qc.ca/gazetteofficielle/abonnement.fr.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; One copy costs $10.71.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www3.publicationsduquebec.gouv.qc.ca/gazetteofficielle/abonnement.fr.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* ''[[Canada Gazette]]''

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* http://www3.publicationsduquebec.gouv.qc.ca/gazetteofficielle.fr.html
* http://bibnum2.banq.qc.ca/bna/goq/ Archives 1869–1995

{{Canada Gazette}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Gazette officielle du Quebec}}
[[Category:Government of Quebec]]
[[Category:Government gazettes|Quebec]]
[[Category:Legal research]]
[[Category:Quebec provincial legislation]]
[[Category:Legal literature]]
[[Category:Publications established in 1869]]
[[Category:1869 establishments in Quebec]]


{{Canada-law-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>h8zb97qw7klnbzd8nlg60yi39ihss5b</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Imperative mandate (Ukraine)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>12655390</id>
    <revision>
      <id>830184514</id>
      <parentid>822102841</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-03-13T08:13:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>DinoBenn</username>
        <id>21437547</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* 2014 reinstatement */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="8061">{{Politics of Ukraine}}
'''Imperative mandate''' ({{lang-uk|Імперативний мандат}}) commonly refers to a provision in the [[Constitution of Ukraine|Constitution]] of [[Ukraine]] in which members of the [[Verkhovna Rada]] (Ukrainian parliament) are bound by the constitution and laws of Ukraine to remain members of the parliamentary faction or bloc in which they were elected. Imperative mandate provisions were defined in the Constitution in articles [[s:Constitution of Ukraine#Article 78|Articles 78]] and [[s:Constitution of Ukraine#Article 81|81]].

==History==
The provision was introduced in the Constitution during the [[Constitution of Ukraine#Amendments|2004 Constitutional Amendments]] on December 8, 2004.&lt;ref name=PACEcrt&gt;[http://www.kyivpost.com/news/opinion/op_ed/detail/85146/ Parliamentary Assembly of the Council of Europe: The functioning of democratic institutions in Ukraine], [[Kyiv Post]] (October 5, 2010)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite Ukrainian law|type=Verkhovna Rada decree|number=2222-IV|law=2222-15|name=About the amendments to the Constitution of Ukraine|date=2004-12-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the [[2006 Ukrainian political crisis]] by [[President of Ukraine|President]] [[Viktor Yushchenko]] applied the provision while dissolving the parliament in April 2007 after members of the opposition [[party switching|crossed party lines]] to join the [[Alliance of National Unity]] to undermine his authority and reach a 300-MP constitutional majority.&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=uWLfGt3eiRkC&amp;pg=PA38 Ukraine on Its Way to Europe, Interim Results of the Orange Revolution] by [[Juliane Besters-Dilger]], [[Peter Lang (publisher)|Peter Lang]], 2009, {{ISBN|3631588895}} (page 38)&lt;/ref&gt;

On October 1, 2010 the [[Constitutional Court of Ukraine]] overturned the 2004 Constitutional Amendments, considering them unconstitutional.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kyivpost.com/news/politics/detail/84619/ Update: Return to 1996 Constitution strengthens president, raises legal questions], [[Kyiv Post]] (October 1, 2010)&lt;/ref&gt; Several individual joined other factions already on October 5, 2010.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.interfax.com.ua/eng/main/50057/ Seven individual MPs join Regions Party faction, Our Ukraine MP joins Lytvyn Bloc] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120120153322/http://www.interfax.com.ua/eng/main/50057/ |date=January 20, 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt; But the Verkhovna Rada canceled the law's provision after amending the regulations of its activities on October 8, 2010;&lt;ref name=FINANCIAL&gt;[http://www.finchannel.com/Main_News/Ukraine/72720_Rada_Approves_Cancellation_Of_Rule_That_Bans_Deputies_From_Switching_Factions_/ Rada Approves Cancellation Of Rule That Bans Deputies From Switching Factions] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20101009194535/http://www.finchannel.com/Main_News/Ukraine/72720_Rada_Approves_Cancellation_Of_Rule_That_Bans_Deputies_From_Switching_Factions_/ |date=October 9, 2010 }}, [[The Financial]] (October 8, 2010)&lt;/ref&gt; since then only 15 or more deputies can form a parliamentary faction, a lawmaker can join only one faction (the chairman and his two assistants cannot head factions of deputies)&lt;ref name=FINANCIAL/&gt;&lt;ref name=1996rulesagain&gt;[http://www.kyivpost.com/news/politics/detail/85569/ Rada amends regulations of its activities], [[Kyiv Post]] (October 8, 2010)&lt;/ref&gt; and deputies who are expelled from factions or decide to leave them become individual lawmakers; individual deputies are allowed to unite into parliamentary groups of people's deputies then again at least 15 deputies are required for the formation of such groups.&lt;ref name=FINANCIAL/&gt;&lt;ref name=1996rulesagain/&gt;

===2014 reinstatement===

On 21 February 2014 the parliament passed a law that reinstated the December 8, 2004 amendments of the constitution.&lt;ref name="bt2004UCIU21214"/&gt; This was passed under simplified procedure without any decision of the relevant committee and was passed in the first and the second reading in one voting by 386 deputies.&lt;ref name="bt2004UCIU21214"/&gt; The law was approved by 140 MPs of the [[Party of Regions]], 89 MPs of [[Batkivshchyna]], 40 MPs of [[UDAR]], 32 of the [[Communist Party of Ukraine|Communist Party]], and 50 independent lawmakers.&lt;ref name="bt2004UCIU21214"&gt;[http://en.interfax.com.ua/news/general/191727.html Ukrainian parliament reinstates 2004 Constitution], [[Interfax-Ukraine]] (21 February 2014)&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Petro Poroshenko Bloc]] MPs [[Mykola Tomenko]] and [[Yehor Firsov]] parliamentary mandates were terminated (due to a decision by the Petro Poroshenko Bloc party congress) by the provision in March 2016.&lt;ref name="TouVrJ16IM"&gt;{{ru icon}} [http://www.pravda.com.ua/rus/news/2016/07/28/7116192/ Tomenko lost the court of its mandate and will complain to Europe], [[Ukrayinska Pravda]] (28 July 2016)&lt;br&gt;[http://www.unian.info/politics/1300725-bpp-congress-moves-to-terminate-powers-of-mps-tomenko-firsov.html BPP Congress moves to terminate powers of MPs Tomenko, Firsov], [[UNIAN]] (25 March 2016)&lt;br&gt;{{cite web|title=People's deputy of Ukraine VIII convocation Mykola Tomenko|url=http://w1.c1.rada.gov.ua/pls/site2/p_deputat?d_id=5415&amp;skl=9|website=Official portal|publisher=[[Verkhovna Rada|Verkhovna Rada of Ukraine]]|accessdate=9 October 2016|language=Ukrainian}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In practice the Imperative mandate causes the deprivation of the mandate of deputies who leave their faction by their own initiative while  deputies who are removed from their faction become an independent MP.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.unian.info/m/politics/2284531-operation-embarrassment.html Operation "Embarrassment"], [[UNIAN]] (7 December 2017)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Criticism==
The Imperative mandate provisions had been the subject of criticism by the [[Parliamentary Assembly of the Council of Europe]] as being undemocratic till its end.&lt;ref name=PACEcrt/&gt; In the Assembly's 2007 report on the Parliamentary Assembly of the Council of Europe - Resolution 1549 (2007) Functioning of democratic institutions in Ukraine &lt;sup&gt;(items 8 and 9)&lt;/sup&gt; it wrote:

{{Cquote|The Assembly calls on the political forces of Ukraine, as a matter of urgency, to resume working on the improvement of the Constitution of Ukraine and the related legislation in order to establish at last an effective system of checks and balances and bring constitutional provisions in line with European standards. Constitutional reform should be part of the discussions aimed at the resolution of the current political crisis. The Assembly expresses its expectation that the Venice Commission will be actively involved in the process of drafting constitutional reform proposals.

The Assembly reaffirms that the recall of people's representatives by the political parties ("imperative mandate") is unacceptable in a democratic state. The relevant constitutional provisions need to be abrogated in line with the recommendations of the Venice Commission in 2004; similar provisions also need to be deleted from ordinary legislation. The Assembly believes that a consistent political programme, responsible and committed party membership and scrupulous screening of parties' candidates are more effective tools for encouraging party and faction discipline.}}

==See also==
*[[Imperative mandate]]
*[[Elections in Ukraine]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20071116103456/http://assembly.coe.int/Mainf.asp?link=%2FDocuments%2FAdoptedText%2Fta07%2FERES1549.htm Council of Europe] — resolution Functioning of democratic institutions in Ukraine April 19, 2007
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20070705000656/http://assembly.coe.int/Main.asp?link=%2FDocuments%2FWorkingDocs%2FDoc07%2FEDOC11255.htm Council of Europe] — Explanatory memorandum April 17, 2007
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20061127211741/http://www.venice.coe.int/site/dynamics/N_Country_ef.asp?C=47&amp;L=E Council of Europe] — Venice Commission:Ukraine

[[Category:Verkhovna Rada]]
[[Category:Politics of Ukraine]]
[[Category:Constitutional law]]
[[Category:Legal history of Ukraine]]
[[Category:Constitutions of Ukraine]]</text>
      <sha1>juwax749ovc37jqopok29ge0072jdnf</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Law as integrity</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>21507515</id>
    <revision>
      <id>805153486</id>
      <parentid>780023484</parentid>
      <timestamp>2017-10-13T12:26:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ZettaComposer</username>
        <id>27284496</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Added links</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="1207">{{Underlinked|date=September 2016}}

In [[philosophy of law]], '''law as integrity''' is a theory of [[law]] put forward by the legal philosopher [[Ronald Dworkin]]. In general, it can be described as interpreting the law according to a [[community]].&lt;ref&gt;

{{Cite journal
| issn = 0143-6503
| volume = 8
| issue = 2
| pages = 266–277
| last = Allan
| first = T. R. S.
| title = Review: Dworkin and Dicey: The Rule of Law as Integrity
| journal = Oxford Journal of Legal Studies| year = 1988
| jstor = 764314
| doi = 10.1093/ojls/8.2.266
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;

== External links ==
*https://web.archive.org/web/20111001143024/http://law.queensu.ca/facultyAndStaff/facultyDirectory/walters/legalHumanismAndLawAsIntegrityPublishedEd.pdf
*http://www.dailymotion.com/video/x9obxh_the-rule-of-law-as-integrity-and-th_news
*http://mellenpress.com/mellenpress.cfm?bookid=834&amp;pc=9
*http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/lawphil-nature/
*http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/rights/#5.1
*http://ivr-enc.info/index.php?title=Law_as_Integrity
*http://theoryofjurisprudence.blogspot.com/2007/12/ronald-dworkin-law-as-integrity.html

[[Category:Philosophy of law]]
[[Category:Theories of law]]


{{law-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>onj3f2ivojffyzki32msta2bjqh9zwp</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Supreme Court of Justice of Colombia</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>11177498</id>
    <revision>
      <id>859435958</id>
      <parentid>856352932</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-09-14T01:37:42Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Daniel.lopez.17</username>
        <id>29628642</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="6242">{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2013}}
{{Infobox high court
| court_name      = Supreme Court of Justice Colombia
| image           = Corte Suprema de Justicia de Colombia.svg
| imagesize       = 
| caption         = Seal of Supreme Court of Colombia
| established     = 1886
| country         = Colombia
| location        = [[Bogotá]]
| coordinates     = {{Coord|04|35|56.4|N|74|04|31.8|W|region:CO-DC_type:landmark_scale:5000|display=inline}}
| type            = Nominated by the [[Superior Council of the Judiciary of Colombia|Superior Council of the Judiciary]], elected by the Supreme Court of Justice.
| authority       = [[Colombian Constitution of 1991|Constitution of Colombia]]
| appeals         = &lt;!-- appeals of from this court go where --&gt;
| terms           = non-renewable 8 years
| positions       = 23, by statute
| website         = {{URL|http://www.cortesuprema.gov.co/}}
| chiefjudgetitle = President of the Supreme Court of Justice
| chiefjudgename  = {{nowrap|José Luis Barceló}}
| termstart       = 8 June 2018
| chiefjudgetitle2= Vice President of the Supreme Court of Justice
| chiefjudgename2 = {{nowrap|Álvaro Fernando García Restrepo}}
| termstart2      = 8 June 2018
}}

The '''Supreme Court of Colombia''' ({{lang-es|Corte Suprema de Justicia de Colombia}}) in [[Bogotá]] is the [[Supreme court|highest judicial body in civil and penal matters and issues of criminal and civil procedure]] in [[Colombia]]. The Supreme Court of Colombia is the highest authority in regard to the interpretation of administrative law, constitutional law, and the administration of the judiciary&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://www.alcaldiabogota.gov.co/sisjur/normas/Norma1.jsp?i=4125|title = Constitución Política de Colombia.|date = Article 237, Article 239.|accessdate = |website = Alcaldia de Bogota|publisher = |last = |first = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Supreme court|court]] consists of twenty three magistrates, elected by the same institution in list conformed by the [[Superior Council of the Judiciary]] for individual terms of eight years. The court meets at the [[Palace of Justice of Colombia|Palace of Justice]] in the [[Bolívar Square]] of [[Bogota]].

==History==
After the [[Colombian Declaration of Independence|Colombian first declaration of independence]] from [[Spain]] on 20 July 1810, a number of independent States like [[Tunja]] (1811), [[Antioquia Department|Antioquia]] (1812), [[Cartagena de Indias]] (1812) and [[Free and Independent State of Cundinamarca|Cundinamarca]] (1812) were established. Each State had its own body in charge of the administration of justice. Later, when these States established the ''Provincias Unidas de la Nueva Granada'' ([[United Provinces of New Granada]]), on 23 September 1814, the ''Alto Tribunal de Justicia'' (High Tribunal of Justice) was established. In 1819, the Republic of Colombia (the [[Gran Colombia]]) was born. A Court was created according to the provisions its Constitution of 30 August 1821, named ''Alta Corte de Justicia'' (High Court of Justice). In 1830, the Gran Colombia was dissolved and the [[Republic of New Granada]] was formed. As per the provisions of its Constitution of 29 February 1832, the ''Corte Suprema de Justicia'' (Supreme Court of Justice) was established. On 20 May 1853, it became the ''Corte Suprema de la Nación'' (Supreme Court of the Nation). In 1858, the [[Grenadine Confederation]] was founded. On adoption of its Constitution of 22 May 1858, the ''Courte Suprema'' (Supreme Court) became the body in charge of the administration of justice. In 1863, the Grenadine Confederation was replaced by the ''Estados Unidos de Colombia'' ([[United States of Colombia]]). On adoption of its Constitution of 8 May 1863, the ''Corte Suprema Federal'' (Supreme Federal Court) was established. Finally, after the establishment of the ''República de Colombia'' ([[Republic of Colombia]]) and on adoption of its [[Colombian Constitution of 1886|Constitution of August 4, 1886]], the body was renamed as the present, the ''Corte Suprema de Justicia'' (Supreme Court of Justice) on 3 September 1886. Its first President was Rito Antonio Martínez.

In 1985 in the [[Palace of Justice siege]], members of the [[19th of April Movement|M-19]] guerrilla group took over the Palace of Justice, and held the Supreme Court [[hostage]], intending to put [[President of Colombia|President]] [[Belisario Betancur]] ''on trial''. Hours later, after a military raid, the incident left all the rebels and 11 of the 25 Supreme Court Justices dead.

==Current Magistrates==
[[File:PalacioDeJusticia2004-7-9Bogota.jpg|thumb|300px|Palace of Justice]]
*President: '''[[José Luis Barceló]]'''
*Vice-president: '''Álvaro Fernando García Restrepo'''

===Civil and Agrarian Cassation Chamber===
*President: Aroldo Wilson Quiroz
*Ariel Salazar Ramírez
*Luis Armando Tolosa Villabona
*Margarita Cabello Blanco
*Álvaro Fernando García Restrepo
*Luis Alonso Rico Puerta
*Octavio Augusto Tejeiro Duque

===Labor Cassation Chamber===
*President: Fernando Castillo Cadena
*Jorge Mauricio Burgos
*Rigoberto Echeverri Bueno
*Clara Cecilia Dueñas Quevedo
*Luis Gabriel Miranda Buelvas
*Jorge Luis Quiroz
*Gerardo Botero Zuluaga

===Penal Cassation Chamber===
*President: Luis Antonio Hernández Barbosa
*Eyder Patiño Cabrera
*Luis Guillermo Salazar Otero
*Fernando Alberto Castro Caballero
*Gustavo Malo Fernández
*Patricia Salazar Cuéllar
*José Francisco Acuña Vizcaya
*José Luis Barceló Camacho
* Eugenio Fernández Carlier

==References==
{{Reflist}}
*{{es icon}} [http://www.ramajudicial.gov.co/csj_portal/jsp/contenido/plantillaFrame.jsp?idsitio=3 Colombian Judicial Branch of Power] Margot Hernandez
*{{es icon}} [http://www.ramajudicial.gov.co/csj_portal/jsp/frames/index.jsp?idsitio=3 Colombian Judicial Branch of power; magistrates]

==External links==
* [http://www.cortesuprema.gov.co/ The Supreme Court of Colombia website]

{{South America topic|Supreme Court of|title=Supreme Courts of South America|countries_only=yes}}

{{Colombia topics}}

[[Category:Constitutional law]]
[[Category:National supreme courts|Colombia]]
[[Category:Supreme Court of Colombia]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of Boyaca]]
[[Category:Government buildings in Colombia]]</text>
      <sha1>fdnbp6zp5ckrzca1lvgjx9lnw02b96n</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>United Arab Emirates Legal Process</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>42612939</id>
    <revision>
      <id>864986448</id>
      <parentid>850454918</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-10-20T22:39:31Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Tom.Reding</username>
        <id>9784415</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[WP:AWB/T|All typo fixes]] on, [[WP:AWB/T|typo(s) fixed]]: i’s → i's (8)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="16475">{{multiple issues|
{{POV |date=April 2014}}
{{Citation style|date=March 2018}} 
}}

The [[United Arab Emirates]] is a middle-eastern country, located at the end of the [[Arabian Peninsula]] on the Persian Gulf, consisting of seven emirates known as [[Abu Dhabi]], [[Dubai]], [[Sharjah (emirate)|Sharjah]], [[Ajman]], [[Umm al-Quwain]], [[Ras al-Khaimah]] and [[Fujairah]]. Each emirate is governed by an emir who jointly forms the Federal Supreme Council (FSC). The Federal System of government includes the Supreme Council, Cabinet, Council of Ministers, parliamentary body, Federal National Council and independent judiciary. The Federal Supreme Council is the highest constitutional authority that has legislative and executive powers with the ability to ratify federal laws, decrees, and plans general policies. Its jurisdictions are derived from French, Roman, Egyptian and Islamic law.

==Judicial branch of the government==
There are three main branches of the court structure: civil, criminal, and sharia or Islamic (1) (the precepts are set forth in the Quranic verses and example set by the Islamic prophet Muhammad in the Sunnah). (2) Sharia or Islamic courts work alongside the civil and criminal courts. The responsibilities include civil matters between Muslims. Non-Muslims will not appear before a Sharia court in any matter due to the differences in religious beliefs. (3) Sharia or Islamic courts have the exclusive jurisdiction over family disputes divorce, inheritance, child custody, child abuse, and guardianship of minors. (3) However, at the federal level the Sharia court may hear appeals of criminal cases including rape, robbery, and driving under the influence of alcohol. (3)
Dubai is its own sovereign nation with its own federal judicial system with separate court systems that are not subjected to the federal Supreme Court. Dubai's court structure consists of:

# Court of First Instances- hears all claims ranging from commercial matters, debt recovery to maritime disputes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Al Hanaee|title=Commitment of the maritime carrier|url=http://www.alhanaee.com/our-team/|accessdate=30 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
# Court of Appeal- parties have the right to appeal on factual or legal grounds within thirty days from the judgment date.
# Court of Cessations- (highest court in Dubai) composed of five judges and all judgments are finals and not subject to appeal; only hear disputes on matters of the law and can act as an appellate court with respect to decisions made from lower courts. Also, can supervise lower courts ensuring the law is interpreted accurately. (3)

==Legal process==
Criminal actions commence with a police investigation which is transferred to the prosecutor's office within 48 hours of filing a complaint. The prosecutor will then hear and document statements from witnesses to determine if charges will be pressed or dropped, which must be completed 14 days from receiving the case from the police. Once the prosecutor has decided if charges will be pressed, the parties can proceed in hiring an attorney. All attorneys must be licensed to practice law and must be approved by an official deed notarized by a notary public to try the case. (3)

===Trial procedures===
Under the United Arab Emirates constitution all defendants are innocent until proven guilty. All trials are public except for national security cases trials that the honoring judge can rule to be conducted in privates if any evidence, testimonies or results are detrimental to societal morality. (4) Being that majority of the trials are public the emirs decided on having no juries in place in the courtroom. Also, all proceedings are delivered in the native language. Except the sentencing portion, translators are available for those who are not fluent in Arabic. For all indignant persons who are charged with felonies punishable by 3–15 years with no attorney, may have counsel provided for them upon the governments discretion. (4) Unlike the United States court system, the UAE prosecutors and defense lawyers have the ability to withhold any investigation from each other involving the case. (4) After, deliberations have been made of indictments, detainees may be released on bail informally. Authorities will accept a cash deposit, passport or an unsecured personal guarantee statement signed by a third party as a form of payment. Diya or blood money also qualifies as debt to a crime committed.

==Diya or blood money==
If one causes the death or injury of another person accidentally or intentionally he or she must pay the victim's family, what is known as [[diyya|diya]] or "blood money".  It is a means of compensation to the loss or harm for the loved ones. The payment of diya protects the rights of the family in the event of further threats from any accomplices or known associates of the defendant.  Diya is only payable if the defendant is found guilty under the criminal procedure or legally responsible for committing the crime. (5) However, if the defendant is found defending themselves, family, or property, diya will not be paid. Males rate of diya is Dh 200,000 (approx. US$54,450) and Dh 100,000 (approx. US$27,225) for females regardless of religion or nationality. (5)

==Free trial and free press==
Section 2 A of the United Arab Emirates constitution provides freedom of speech and press. However, the law prohibits criticism and slander of public officials that may create or encourage social uproar. (4) Journalists undergo strict boundaries implemented from the government. A variety of information can be published and distributed without the content being harmful or insulting to others. All sources must be reliable and will not be published until a full investigation has been performed to phish out any fabricated information. (6) Writers have the full right to document and publish info gathered from the courtroom due to trials being open to the public (judges can ask for privacy). Writers are prohibited from publishing the names of the accused, victims, or witnesses. (6)

==Women and the law==
Women in the UAE have progressed through the years with rights that they haven’t had prior to the declaration. However, many are concerned with how women are treated in this country. In marriage, the women are bound by a marital contract that clearly states that she is to abide by her husband, take care of home and the children. If the women disobeys or neglect her duties as a wife, by law the husband has the right to use physical means including violence to correct her disdaining acts. (4) Nevertheless, some domestic abuse cases can be filed as an assault without the intent to kill that is punishable by 10 years in prison of death results, 7 years for permanent disability, or 1 year for temporary injury. (4) Rape in the UAE is not tolerated and is punishable by immediate death. However, many women do not report being raped because they could be accused of adultery which results in flogging or death by stoning and brings shame to the family. (7) Divorce is rare in the UAE due to the stipulations that derive from it. Article 110 of the Personal Status Code states, women can request to be divorced with the exception that she surrenders all of her finances; otherwise known as the "khul" divorce procedure. (7) If the divorce is processed, the custody of the children is determined. Women are considered to be physical guardians and only have the right to custody up to the age of 13 for girls and 10 for boys. Once that age has been reached the Sharia courts can reassess for further custody. If the woman decides to remarry she automatically forfeits her rights of custody for her children from the previous marriage. (7)

==Juveniles and the law==
Like the women if minors disobey or act out, the male has the right to utilize corporal punishment. Criminal responsibility begins at age seven. (8) Sharia principles permit corporal punishment of young children including flogging, amputation, and retaliation similar to the pain reflected on the victim. Article 8 of the Juvenile Delinquent and Vagrant Act states, that if a juvenile is over the age of 16 and commits an offence, under the Penal Code at the judge's discretion they may sentence them to the measures provided in crime, instead of the prescribed penalty. (9) Article 9 states, "a juvenile may not be condemned to capital punishment". Juveniles who reach 16 are to be punished under the penal code substituting a sentence of detention not to exceed 10 years. (10)

==Customs and culture==
It is apparent that the UAE has applied firm penalties in accordance with maintaining the country's respect. Its vast success from new contemporary ideas has inspired other countries to engage in the innovations. With respect to UAE's religion, any showing of body parts such as buttocks, leg breast is deemed indecent and is strictly prohibited. Punishment for indecent exposure if jail or deportation. The body and romantic relationship is sacred and affection should be kept behind closed doors. Public affection is not allowed regardless of relationship status. Kissing and embracing of significant others is offensive and will be reported; holding hands is only affection acceptable.

==Crimes punishable by death==
The death penalty's purpose is to not only punish, but to rehabilitate criminals{{Clarify|date=June 2014}} and if possible prevent others from committing the same crime. (13) The main goal of the United Arab Emirates is to protect the lives, religion, parentage, intellect, and property of its citizens through rules and regulations that are strictly enforced with no tolerance. There are five crimes that the death penalty is automatically administered for: adultery, rape, armed highway robbery, murder, and apostasy.

In the Middle East, men are lawfully allowed to marry up to four women provided that he equally divides his time and money to take care of the family needs. (13) If the wives believe they haven’t received their share of his time or expenses than they have the right to ask for a divorce, due to the lack of marital support. The concept of having multiple spouses is to discourage men from committing adultery, having any sexual intercourse outside of marriage. Basically to avoid any bastard children, this in turn can create confusion within the family. The child will not be considered to have a father because his mother was not legally married to him and places the child in a difficult position, psychologically. Adultery is forbidden in order to uphold is mission to protect the livelihood of its citizens.

Rape, is extremely unacceptable in this country. The age of sexual maturity is fourteen. (13) Both women and men can be considered the culprit. To be sentenced to the death penalty full intercourse must have occurred. (13) In contrast, it is difficult to prove based on the circumstances of how women are treated in the law. If a women confesses that she has been attack without consent she must immediately alert local authorities in order to assess the crime, if not she will be deemed as agreeing and being full fledge on in non-marital sex and sentenced to death. In addition, if a women is pregnant at the time of her sentencing she is allowed to give birth and suckle the child for two years before her death is complete. (13)
Armed highway robbery is the impression of taking money from another under the threat of force of arms, thus imposing physical or financial assault. (13) Theft (Al Haraboh) occurs when an individual or group of people prey on others in attempt to take their valuables or property. Citizens have the natural right to obtain anything they have without the threat of someone without authority revoking it from them. The perpetrator who breaks that natural right is going against the ideologies of the country, which no pardon can be given.

Under Book 1, Article 1 of the Penal Code retributive penalties can apply under the Sharia law. The United Arab Emirates courts follow the Maliki School of Sunni Islam for the use of authority and interpretation from other schools to pronounce the sentences for murder cases. Islamic law defines any sane person who intentionally kills another with a weapon, is a sinner deserving perdition according to the Quran and the murderer is subject to retaliation. (11) Aggravated Murder, in the case of "deliberate design" or premeditated purpose is also punishable by death. (11) Unlawful killing such as: killing by fire, drowning in water, throwing from a high place, crushing by pushing down a wall, strangling, prevention of food and water, or exposing to a predatory animal are all likely to cause death, in the event death will be the punishment. (13) Homicides of public employees including ministries, government authorities, and members of the armed forces are considered an attack on the country itself and will be immediately prosecuted.

Apostasy or Al Reda is one who turns away from the Islamic religion, whether he or she embraces another religion or says they disbelieve after once believing. This crime is characterized and an intentional act unless under the individual is not at their sound capacity. (13) Any Muslim that denies one of the holy books, the prophets, or rejects any methods of the Islamic worship including prayer, paying Zakat (obligatory payment made annually under Islamic law on certain kinds of property and used for charitable and religious purpose), or fasting will be condemned to life for not abiding by the ordinances set in place for the country. (13) Moreover, if the person proclaims that they are in disbelief but is unaware of their statements they will be questioned once they regain their normal state of mind. Once they have gain clarity of themselves and deny any statements made in that stage than they will not be held liable for their action or comments. (13)

Other crimes that can be accountable for readmission for the death penalty are perjury/calumny, inciting suicide, drinking (the use of drug-induced state of mind to incite a person to commit an offense; drinking and driving results in jail, fines, and deportation, (12) arson, kidnapping, drug trafficking (severe crime with a zero tolerance policy toward illegal drug use) (12), and human trafficking.

All of these crimes have been committed but are infrequent due to the punishment of death. During the process of execution a deputy of the ministry, doctor, convict's lawyer and one of the member of the public prosecution are present. Relatives of the criminal are able to visit that day prior to the implementation of the sentence.

==References==
{{Reflist}}
References:
(1)"The Story of the UAE." Zayed University, United Arab Emirates. N.p., n.d. Web. 23 Mar. 2014.

(2)Berg, Herbert (2005). "Islamic Law" Berkshire Encyclopedia of World History 3. Pg. 1030.

(3)"The UAE Court System."dubai.usconsulate.gov. N.p., n.d. Web. 18 Mar. 2014.

(4)United Arab Emirates.&lt;http://www.state.gov.documents/oganization/160079.pdf{{dead link|date=July 2016 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&gt;.N.p.,n.d. Web. 25 Mar. 2014.

(5)Al Jandaly, Bassma. "Blood Money In Islamic Law." Gulfnews.com. N.p., 20 Jan. 2009. Web 12 Apr. 2014.

(6)"Protection of News Sources in UAE." Free Trial and News Sources. N.p., n.d. Web. 12 Apr. 2014 http://uaemedialaw.wikispaces.com

(7)"Women’s Rights in the UAE." International Federation of Human Rights. N.p., Jan. 2010. http://fidh.org

(8)Philippe, Marie. "Realizing  Children’s Rights in the United Arab Emirates." Humanium. N.p., 14 February 2013. Web. 25 March 2014 https://web.archive.org/web/20120608053806/http://humanium.org/

(9)Juvenile Delinquent and Vagrant Act. Article 8. N.p., Web. 6 April 2014. &lt;http://support.fatmaalmoosa.com&gt;.

(10)"Inhuman Sentencing of Children in UAE." Child Rights International Network. N.p., Web 6 April 2014 www.crin.org/docs/UAE_Final.pdf

(11)"United Arab Emirates." Death Penalty Worldwide. N.p., 7 February 2011. Web. 25 March 2014. https://web.archive.org/web/20140329053557/http://www.deathpenaltyworldwide.org/

(12)"United Arab Emirates Crime and Safety Report: Abu Dhabi." OSAC. N.p., n.d. Web. 15 April 2013. https://web.archive.org/web/20101104231152/http://www.osac.gov/

(13)Abdulla, Saleh, and Mirad Abdulla. "The Use of the Death Penalty Under the Law of the United Arab Emirates." Diss. [[University of Aberystwyth]], 2012. Print.

[[Category:Legal systems]]
[[Category:Emirati law]]</text>
      <sha1>bg346cgmr9vo10wvxa55qmo9ueyb4lj</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
