<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.33.0-wmf.6</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Chirality</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>32703814</id>
    <revision>
      <id>866076029</id>
      <parentid>865608168</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-10-28T02:51:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Afroscience</username>
        <id>34976350</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Clarified that it is not in all cases that enantiomers have different biological effects. Added missing references.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="20260">{{other uses}}
[[Image:Chirality with hands.svg|200px|thumb|Two enantiomers of a generic [[amino acid]] that is '''chiral''']]

'''Chirality''' {{IPAc-en|k|aɪ|ˈ|r|æ|l|ɪ|t|iː}} is a property of [[asymmetry]] important in several branches of science. The word ''chirality'' is derived from the [[Greek language|Greek]] {{lang|el|χειρ}} (''kheir''), "hand," a familiar chiral object.

An object or a system is ''chiral'' if it is distinguishable from its [[mirror image]]; that is, it cannot be [[wikt:superposed|superposed]] onto it.  Conversely, a mirror image of an ''achiral'' object, such as a sphere, cannot be distinguished from the object. A chiral object and its mirror image are called ''enantiomorphs'' (Greek, "opposite forms") or, when referring to molecules, ''[[enantiomers]]''. A non-chiral object is called ''achiral'' (sometimes also ''amphichiral'') and can be superposed on its mirror image. If the object is non-chiral and is imagined as being colored blue and its mirror image is imagined as colored yellow, then by a series of rotations and translations the two can be superposed, producing green, with none of the original colors remaining.

The term was first used by [[William Thomson, 1st Baron Kelvin|Lord Kelvin]] in 1893 in the second [[Robert Boyle Lecture]] at the [[Oxford University Junior Scientific Club]] which was published in 1894:

{{quote|I call any geometrical figure, or group of points, 'chiral', and say that it has chirality if its image in a plane mirror, ideally realized, cannot be brought to coincide with itself.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=The Molecular Tactics of a Crystal |author=Sir William Thomson Lord Kelvin | year=1894 | publisher=[[Clarendon Press]] | url=https://archive.org/details/moleculartactic00kelvgoog}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Human [[hand]]s are perhaps the most universally recognized example of chirality. The left hand is a non-superimposable mirror image of the right hand; no matter how the two hands are oriented, it is impossible for all the major features of both hands to coincide across all axes.&lt;ref name="OCATUA"&gt;Georges Henry Wagnière, ''On Chirality and the Universal Asymmetry: Reflections on Image and Mirror Image'' (2007).&lt;/ref&gt; This difference in symmetry becomes obvious if someone attempts to shake the right hand of a person using their left hand, or if a left-handed glove is placed on a right hand. In mathematics, ''chirality'' is the property of a figure that is not identical to its mirror image.

==Mathematics==
[[File:Orbifold 2X.2.svg|thumb|200px|An achiral 3D object without central symmetry or a plane of symmetry]]
[[Image:Knot table.svg|thumb|200px|right|A table of all [[prime knot]]s with seven [[Crossing number (knot theory)|crossings]] or fewer (not including mirror images).]]
{{main|Chirality (mathematics)}}

In [[mathematics]], a figure is chiral (and said to have chirality) if it cannot be mapped to its mirror image by [[Rotation (mathematics)|rotation]]s and [[Translation (geometry)|translation]]s alone.  For example, a right shoe is different from a left shoe, and clockwise is different from anticlockwise. See &lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Petitjean, M. | title = Chirality in metric spaces. In memoriam Michel Deza | journal = Optimization Letters | year = 2017 | doi = 10.1007/s11590-017-1189-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; for a full mathematical definition.

A chiral object and its mirror image are said to be enantiomorphs. The word ''enantiomorph'' stems from the Greek {{lang|grc|ἐναντίος}} (enantios) 'opposite' + {{lang|grc|μορφή}} (morphe) 'form'.  A non-chiral figure is called achiral or amphichiral.

The [[helix]] (and by extension a spun string, a screw, a propeller, etc.) and [[Möbius strip]] are chiral two-dimensional objects in three-dimensional ambient space. The J, L, S and Z-shaped ''[[tetromino]]es'' of the popular video game [[Tetris]] also exhibit chirality, but only in a two-dimensional space.

Many other familiar objects exhibit the same chiral symmetry of the human body, such as gloves, glasses (where two lenses differ in prescription), and shoes. A similar notion of chirality is considered in [[knot theory]], as explained below.

Some chiral three-dimensional objects, such as the helix, can be assigned a right or left handedness, according to the [[right-hand rule]].

===Geometry===
In [[geometry]] a figure is achiral if and only if its [[symmetry group]] contains at least one ''orientation-reversing'' isometry.
In two dimensions, every figure that possesses an [[axis of symmetry]] is achiral, and it can be shown that every ''bounded'' achiral figure must have an axis of symmetry.
In three dimensions, every figure that possesses a [[plane of symmetry]] or a center of symmetry is achiral. There are, however, achiral figures lacking both plane and center of symmetry.
In terms of [[point groups]], all chiral figures lack an improper axis of rotation (S&lt;sub&gt;n&lt;/sub&gt;). This means that they cannot contain a center of inversion (i) or a mirror plane (σ). Only figures with a point group designation of C&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;, C&lt;sub&gt;n&lt;/sub&gt;, D&lt;sub&gt;n&lt;/sub&gt;, T, O, or I can be chiral.

===Knot theory===&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Figure-eight knot (mathematics)]] --&gt;

A [[knot (mathematics)|knot]] is called [[amphichiral knot|achiral]] if it can be continuously deformed into its mirror image, otherwise it is called chiral. For example, the [[unknot]] and the [[figure-eight knot (mathematics)|figure-eight knot]] are achiral, whereas the [[trefoil knot]] is chiral.

{{clear|both}}

==Physics==
[[Image:Circular.Polarization.Circularly.Polarized.Light Right.Handed.Animation.305x190.255Colors.gif|thumb|200px|&lt;span style="font-size:87%;"&gt;Animation of left-handed (anticlockwise),  [[circularly polarized]],  [[light]] as viewed in the direction of the source, in agreement with [[physics]] and [[astronomy]] conventions.&lt;/span&gt;]]
{{main|Chirality (physics)}}

In physics, chirality may be found in the [[Spin (physics)|spin]] of a particle, where the handedness of the object is determined by the direction in which the particle spins.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://discovermagazine.com/1995/nov/lookingfortherig591|title=Looking for the Right Hand - DiscoverMagazine.com|author=|date=|website=discovermagazine.com|accessdate=23 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; Not to be confused with [[Helicity (particle physics)|helicity]], which is the projection of the spin along the linear momentum of a subatomic particle, chirality is a purely quantum mechanical phenomenon like spin. Although both can have left-handed or right-handed properties, only in the massless case do they have a simple relation.&lt;ref name="quantumdiaries.org"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.quantumdiaries.org/2011/06/19/helicity-chirality-mass-and-the-higgs/|title=Quantum Diaries|author=|date=|website=www.quantumdiaries.org|accessdate=23 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; In particular for a massless particle the helicity is the same as the chirality while for an antiparticle they have opposite sign.

The ''handedness'' in both chirality and helicity relate to the rotation of a particle while it proceeds in linear motion with reference to the human hands. The thumb of the hand points towards the direction of linear motion whilst the fingers curl into the palm, representing the direction of rotation of the particle (i.e. clockwise and counterclockwise). Depending on the linear and rotational motion, the particle can either be defined by left-handedness (ex. translating leftwards and rotating counterclockwise) or right-handedness (ex. translating in the right direction and rotating clockwise).&lt;ref name="quantumdiaries.org"/&gt; A symmetry transformation between the two is called [[parity (physics)|parity]]. Invariance under parity by a [[Dirac fermion]] is called ''chiral symmetry''.

===Electromagnetism===

{{main|Chirality (electromagnetism)}}

[[Electromagnetic radiation|Electromagnetic]] wave [[Wave propagation|propagation]] as [[handedness]] is wave [[Polarization (waves)|polarization]] and described in terms of [[Circular dichroism|helicity]] (occurs as a helix). Polarization of an [[electromagnetic wave]] is the property that describes the [[Orientation (geometry)|orientation]], i.e., the [[periodic function|time-varying]], direction ([[Euclidean vector|vector]]), and [[amplitude]] of the [[electric field]] vector. For a depiction, see the adjacent image.

==Chemistry==
[[File:Zwitterion-Alanine.png|thumb|right|200px|(''S'')-Alanine (left) and (''R'')-alanine (right) in zwitterionic form at neutral pH]]
{{main|Chirality (chemistry)}}

A ''chiral molecule'' is a type of [[molecule]] that has a non-superposable [[mirror image]]. The feature that is most often the cause of chirality in molecules is the presence of an [[asymmetric carbon|asymmetric carbon atom]].&lt;ref&gt;''Organic Chemistry'' (4th Edition) Paula Y. Bruice.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Organic Chemistry'' (3rd Edition) Marye Anne Fox, James K. Whitesell.&lt;/ref&gt;

The term "chiral" in general is used to describe the object that is non-superposable on its mirror image.&lt;ref&gt;{{GoldBookRef|title=chirality|file=C01058}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In chemistry, chirality usually refers to molecules. Two mirror images of a chiral molecule are called [[enantiomer]]s or optical [[isomer]]s. Pairs of enantiomers are often designated as "[[right-handed|right-]]", "left-handed" or if it has no bias achiral. As polarized light passes through a chiral molecule, the plane of polarization, when viewed along the axis toward the source, will be rotated in a clockwise (to the right) or anticlockwise (to the left). A right handed rotation is dextrorotary (d); that to the left is levorotary (l). The d- and l-isomers are the same compound but are called [[enantiomers]]. An equimolar mixture of the two optical isomers will produce no net rotation of polarized light as it passes through.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Chang|first1=Raymond|title=Chemistry|publisher=[[Random House]]|isbn=0-394-32983-X|page=660|edition=second}}&lt;/ref&gt; Left handed molecules have l- prefixed to their names; d- is prefixed to right handed molecules.

Molecular chirality is of interest because of its application to [[stereochemistry]] in [[inorganic chemistry]], [[organic chemistry]], [[physical chemistry]], [[biochemistry]], and [[supramolecular chemistry]].

More recent developments in chiral chemistry include the development of chiral inorganic nanoparticles that may have the similar tetrahedral geometry as chiral centers associated with sp3 carbon atoms traditionally associated with chiral compounds, but at larger scale.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Moloney|first=Mícheál P.|last2=Gun'ko|first2=Yurii K.|last3=Kelly|first3=John M.|date=2007-09-26|title=Chiral highly luminescent CdS quantum dots|url=https://doi.org/10.1039/b704636g|journal=Chemical Communications|language=en|volume=0|issue=38|doi=10.1039/b704636g|issn=1364-548X}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Schaaff|first=T. Gregory|last2=Knight|first2=Grady|last3=Shafigullin|first3=Marat N.|last4=Borkman|first4=Raymond F.|last5=Whetten|first5=Robert L.|date=1998-12-01|title=Isolation and Selected Properties of a 10.4 kDa Gold:Glutathione Cluster Compound|url=https://dx.doi.org/10.1021/jp9830528|journal=The Journal of Physical Chemistry B|volume=102|issue=52|pages=10643–10646|doi=10.1021/jp9830528|issn=1520-6106}}&lt;/ref&gt;   Helical and other symmetries of chiral nanomaterials were also obtained.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Ma|first=Wei|last2=Xu|first2=Liguang|last3=de Moura|first3=André F.|last4=Wu|first4=Xiaoling|last5=Kuang|first5=Hua|last6=Xu|first6=Chuanlai|last7=Kotov|first7=Nicholas A.|date=2017-06-28|title=Chiral Inorganic Nanostructures|url=https://dx.doi.org/10.1021/acs.chemrev.6b00755|journal=Chemical Reviews|volume=117|issue=12|pages=8041–8093|doi=10.1021/acs.chemrev.6b00755|issn=0009-2665}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Biology==
{{See also|Homochirality}}

All of the known life-forms show specific chiral properties in chemical structures as well as macroscopic anatomy, development and behavior.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Xiao|first=Wende|last2=Ernst|first2=Karl-Heinz|last3=Palotas|first3=Krisztian|last4=Zhang|first4=Yuyang|last5=Bruyer|first5=Emilie|last6=Peng|first6=Lingqing|last7=Greber|first7=Thomas|last8=Hofer|first8=Werner A.|last9=Scott|first9=Lawrence T.|date=2016-02-08|title=Microscopic origin of chiral shape induction in achiral crystals|url=http://www.nature.com/articles/nchem.2449|journal=Nature Chemistry|language=En|volume=8|issue=4|pages=326–330|doi=10.1038/nchem.2449|issn=1755-4330}}&lt;/ref&gt; In any specific organism or evolutionarily related set thereof, individual compounds, organs, or behavior are found in the same single enantiomorphic form. Deviation (having the opposite form) could be found in a small number of chemical compounds, or certain organ or behavior but that variation strictly depends upon the genetic make up of the organism. From chemical level (molecular scale), biological systems show extreme stereospecificity in synthesis, uptake, sensing, metabolic processing. A living system usually deals with two enantiomers of same compound in a drastically different way.

In biology, homochirality is a common property of [[Amino acid#Isomerism|amino acids]] and [[Monosaccharide#Open-chain stereoisomers|carbohydrates]]. The chiral [[Proteinogenic amino acid|protein-making amino acids]], which are translated through the ribosome from genetic coding, occur in the &lt;small&gt;L&lt;/small&gt; form. However, &lt;small&gt;D&lt;/small&gt;-amino acids are also found in nature. The monosaccharides (carbohydrate-units) are commonly found in &lt;small&gt;D&lt;/small&gt;-configuration. DNA double helix is chiral (as any kind of [[Helix#Types|helix]] is chiral), and [[B-DNA|B-form of DNA]] shows a right-handed turn.

{{multiple image
|image1   = R-Limonene.png
|width1   = 75
|caption1 = ''R''-(+)-Limonene found in orange
|image2   = S-Limonene.png
|width2   = 75
|caption2 = ''S''-(–)-Limonene found in lemon
}}

Sometimes, when two enantiomers of a compound found in organisms, they significantly differ in their taste, smell and other biological actions. For example, (+)-Limonene found in orange (causing its smell), and (–)-Limonene found in Lemons (causing its smell), show different smells&lt;ref&gt;Solomon and Fryhles organic chemistry, Ed 10, Wiley (Students edition), Chapter 5 (Stereochemistry), Section 5.5 More about biological significance of chirality&lt;/ref&gt; due to different biochemical interactions at human nose. (+)-Carvone is responsible for the smell of [[Caraway]] seed oil whereas (–)-carvone is responsible for smell of [[Spearmint]] oil.&lt;ref&gt;Solomon and Fryhles organic chemistry, Ed 10, Wiley (Students edition), Chapter 5 (Stereochemistry), review problem 5.14&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Carvone-enantiomers1.jpg|thumb|S-(+)-Carvone occurs in Caraway seed oil, and R-(-)-Carvone occurs in spearmint|296x296px]]

{{multiple image
|image1   = Dextropropoxyphene structure.svg
|width1   = 200
|caption1 = Dextropropoxyphene or Darvon, a painkiller
|image2   = Levopropoxyphene structure.svg
|width2   = 200
|caption2 = Levopropoxyphene or Novrad, an anticough agent
}}

Also, for artificial compounds, including medicines, in case of chiral drugs, the two enantiomers sometimes show remarkable difference in effect of their biological actions.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Sanganyado|first=Edmond|last2=Lu|first2=Zhijiang|last3=Fu|first3=Qiuguo|last4=Schlenk|first4=Daniel|last5=Gan|first5=Jay|date=2017|title=Chiral pharmaceuticals: A review on their environmental occurrence and fate processes|url=https://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S0043135417306565|journal=Water Research|volume=124|pages=527–542|doi=10.1016/j.watres.2017.08.003|issn=0043-1354|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Darvon ([[Dextropropoxyphene]]) is a painkiller, whereas its enantiomer, Novrad ([[Levopropoxyphene]]) is an anti-cough agent. In case of [[Penicillamine]], the S-isomer used in treatment of primary chronic arthritis, Whereas the R-isomer has no therapeutic effect as well as being highly toxic.&lt;ref&gt;Solomon and Fryhles organic chemistry, Ed 10, Wiley (Students edition), Chapter 5 (Stereochemistry), section 5.11(chiral drugs)&lt;/ref&gt; In some cases the less therapeutically active enantiomer can cause side effects. For example, S-naproxen is an analgesic but the R-isomer cause renal problems.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Suzuki|first=Toshinari|last2=Kosugi|first2=Yuki|last3=Hosaka|first3=Mitsugu|last4=Nishimura|first4=Tetsuji|last5=Nakae|first5=Dai|date=2014-10-08|title=Occurrence and behavior of the chiral anti-inflammatory drug naproxen in an aquatic environment|url=https://setac.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1002/etc.2741|journal=Environmental Toxicology and Chemistry|language=en|volume=33|issue=12|pages=2671–2678|doi=10.1002/etc.2741|issn=0730-7268}}&lt;/ref&gt; The naturally occurring plant form of alpha-tocopherol ([[vitamin E]]) is RRR-α-tocopherol whereas the synthetic form (all-racemic vitamin E, or dl-tocopherol) is equal parts of the stereoisomers RRR, RRS, RSS, SSS, RSR, SRS, SRR and SSR with progressively decreasing biological equivalency, so that 1.36&amp;nbsp;mg of dl-tocopherol is considered equivalent to 1.0&amp;nbsp;mg of d-tocopherol.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Manolescu B, Atanasiu V, Cercasov C, Stoian I, Oprea E, Buşu C |title=So many options but one choice: the human body prefers alpha-tocopherol. A matter of stereochemistry |journal=J Med Life |volume=1 |issue=4 |pages=376–382 |date=2008 |pmid=20108516 |pmc=5654212 |doi= |url=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:DirkvdM natural spiral.jpg|thumb|A natural left-handed helix, made by a certain climber plant's [[tendril]]. |171x171px]]
Macroscopic example of Chirality is found in plant kingdom, animal kingdom and all other groups of organism. A simple example is the coiling direction of any climber plants. It may be one of two possible type of helix.

[[File:Neptunea - links&amp;rechts gewonden.jpg|thumb|200px|Shells of two different species of sea snail: on the left is the normally sinistral (left-handed) shell of ''[[Neptunea angulata]]'', on the right is the normally dextral (right-handed) shell of ''[[Neptunea despecta]]'']]
In anatomy, chirality is found in the imperfect mirror image symmetry of many kinds of animal bodies. Organisms such as [[gastropod]]s exhibit chirality in their coiled shells, resulting in an asymmetrical appearance. Over 90% of gastropod species &lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Schilthuizen | first1 = M. | last2 = Davison | first2 = A. | year = 2005 | title = The convoluted evolution of snail chirality | url = | journal = [[Naturwissenschaften]] | volume = 92 | issue = 11| pages = 504–515 | doi =  10.1007/s00114-05-0045-2| bibcode = 2005NW.....92..504S }}&lt;/ref&gt; have ''dextral'' (right-handed) shells in their coiling, but a small minority of species and genera are virtually always ''sinistral'' (left-handed). A very few species (for example ''[[Amphidromus perversus]]''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jaxshells.org/052ddr.htm|title=Amphidromus perversus (Linnaeus, 1758)|author=|date=|website=www.jaxshells.org|accessdate=23 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;) show an equal mixture of dextral and sinistral individuals.

In humans, chirality (also referred to as ''handedness'' or ''laterality'') is an attribute of humans defined by their unequal distribution of [[fine motor skill]] between the left and right [[hands]]. An individual who is more [[Dexterity|dexterous]] with the right hand is called ''[[right-handed]]'', and one who is more skilled with the left is said to be ''[[left-handed]]''. Chirality is also seen in the study of [[facial asymmetry]].

In flatfish, the [[Summer flounder]] or fluke are left-eyed, while [[halibut]] are right-eyed.

==See also==
* [[Asymmetry]]
* [[Handedness]]
* [[Metachirality]]
* [[Orientation (mathematics)]]
* [[Right-hand rule]]
* [[Sinistral and dextral]]
* [[Stereochemistry]]
* [[Tendril perversion]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* The Handedness of the Universe by Roger A Hegstrom and Dilip K Kondepudi http://quantummechanics.ucsd.edu/ph87/ScientificAmerican/Sciam/Hegstrom_The_Handedness_of_the_universe.pdf

{{Wiktionary}}
{{Navbox stereochemistry}}

[[Category:Biochemistry]]
[[Category:Life]]
[[Category:Origin of life]]
[[Category:Stereochemistry]]
[[Category:Chirality| ]]
[[Category:Pharmacology]]</text>
      <sha1>dr1h13j0sckhe9jc8seoekcdsnhofns</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Coleridge's theory of life</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>44262036</id>
    <revision>
      <id>862055902</id>
      <parentid>852935973</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-10-01T21:42:42Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Headbomb</username>
        <id>1461430</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* top */clean up, replaced: CUP Arrchive → CUP Archive</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="29127">{{essay-like|date=October 2014}}

[[Romanticism]] grew largely out of an attempt to understand not just inert nature, but also vital nature. Romantic works in the realm of art and [[medicine|Romantic medicine]] were a response to the general failure of the application of method of inertial science to reveal the foundational laws and operant principles of vital nature. German romantic science and medicine sought to understand the nature of the life principle identified by John Hunter as distinct from matter itself via [[Blumenbach|Johan Friedrich Blumenbach]]'s ''Bildungstrieb'' and [[Hahnemann|Romantic medicine]]'s ''Lebenskraft'', as well as Röschlaub's development of the [[Brunonian|Brunonian system of medicine]] system of John Brown, in his ''excitation theory'' of life (German:''Erregbarkeit theorie''), working also with  Schelling's ''Naturphilosophie'', the work of [[Goethe]] regarding morphology, and the first dynamic conception of physiology of [[Richard Saumarez]]. But it is in [[Samuel Taylor Coleridge]] that we find the question of life and vital nature most intensely and comprehensively examined, particularly in his '''''Hints towards the Formation of a more Comprehensive Theory of Life'''''&lt;!--boldface per WP:R#PLA--&gt; (1818), providing the foundation for [[Romanticism and epistemology|Romantic philosophy]], science and medicine.&lt;ref name=Levere&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Levere|first1=Trevor H.|title=Coleridge and the Sciences|journal=CUP Archive|date=June 28, 1990|pages=295–306|url=https://books.google.bs/books?id=0jc4AAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA295&amp;dq=Owen+Barfield+Hints+Towards+a+More+Comprehensive+Theory+of+Life&amp;source=gbs_toc_r&amp;cad=3#v=onepage&amp;q=Owen%20Barfield%20Hints%20Towards%20a%20More%20Comprehensive%20Theory%20of%20Life&amp;f=false|accessdate=31 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; The work is key to understanding the relationship of Romantic literature and science.&lt;ref name=JSTOR&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Male|first1=Roy R. Jr|title=The Background of Coleridge's Theory of Life|journal=|date=1954|volume=33|issue=The University of Texas Studies in English|page=60|jstor=20776075}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Background ==
The Enlightenment had developed a philosophy and science supported by formidable twin pillars: the first the Cartesian split of mind and matter, the second Newtonian physics, with its conquest of inert nature, both of which focused the mind's gaze on things or objects. For Cartesian philosophy, life existed on the side of matter, not mind; and for the physical sciences, the method that had been so productive for revealing the secrets of inert nature, should be equally productive in examining vital nature. The initial attempt to seek the cause and principle of life in matter was challenged by John Hunter, who held that the principle of life was not to be found nor confined within matter, but existed independently of matter itself, and informed or animated it, that is, he implied, it was the unifying or antecedent cause of the things or what Aristotelean philosophy termed ''natura naturata'' (the outer appearances of nature).
 
This reduction of the question of life to matter, and the corollary, that the method of the inertial sciences was the way to understand the very phenomenon of life, that is, its very nature and essence as a power (''natura naturans''), not as manifestations through sense-perceptible appearances (''natura naturata''), also reduced the individual to a material-mechanical 'thing' and seemed to render human freedom an untenable concept. It was this that Romanticism challenged, seeking instead to find an approach to the essence of nature as being also vital not simply inert, through a systematic method involving not just physics, but physiology (living functions). For Coleridge, quantitative analysis was anti-realist and needed to be grounded in qualitative analysis ('-ologies') (as was the case with Goethe's approach).&lt;ref name=Dyssebeia&gt;{{cite web|title=Two Metaphors In Coleridge's Theory of Life|url=http://dyssebeia.wordpress.com/2013/10/17/two-metaphors-in-coleridges-theory-of-life/|website=Dyssebeia|publisher=[[Wordpress]]|accessdate=31 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 
At the same time, the Romantics had to deal with the idealistic view that life was a 'somewhat' outside of things, such that the things themselves lost any real existence, a stream coming through Hume and Kant, and also infusing the German natural philosophical stream, German idealism, and in particular ''naturphilosophie'', eventuating scientifically in the doctrine of 'vitalism'. For the Romantics, life is independent of and antecedent to nature, but also infused and suspended in nature, not apart from it, As David Bohm expresses it in more modern terms "In nature nothing remains constant…everything comes from other things and gives rise to other things. This principle is…at the foundation of the possibility of our understanding nature in a rational way."&lt;ref name=Bohm&gt;{{cite book|last1=Bohm|first1=David|title=Causality and Chance in Modern Physics|publisher=[[University of Pennsylvania Press]]|location=1957|page=1|url=https://books.google.bs/books?id=nweG_wrUHuAC&amp;q=foundation#v=snippet&amp;q=foundation&amp;f=false|accessdate=31 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

And as Coleridge explained, 'this antecedent unity, or cause and principle of each union, it has since the time of Bacon and Kepler been customary to call a law."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Barfield|first1=Owen|title=What Coleridge Thought|date=1971|publisher=[[Wesleyan University Press]]|location=Middletown, CT|page=44, note 7}}&lt;/ref&gt; And as law, "we derive from it a progressive insight into the necessity and generation of the phenomena of which it is the law."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Barfield|first1=Owen|title=What Coleridge Thought|date=1971|publisher=Wesleyan University Press|location=Middletown, CT|page=45, fn 8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Coleridge’s theory of life ==

Coleridge's was the dominant mind on many issues involving the philosophy and science in his time, as John Stuart Mill acknowledged, along with others since who have studied the history of Romanticism.

:The name of Coleridge is one of the few English names of our time which are likely to be oftener pronounced, and to become symbolical of more important things, in proportion as the inward workings of the age manifest themselves more and more in outward facts.&lt;ref name=Mill&gt;{{cite book|last1=Mill|first1=John Stuart|title=Collected Works of John Stuart Mill|edition=Vol. 10|url=http://oll.libertyfund.org/?option=com_staticxt&amp;staticfile=show.php%3Ftitle=241&amp;chapter=21494&amp;layout=html&amp;Itemid=27|accessdate=31 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;]

For Coleridge, as for many of his romantic contemporaries, the idea that matter itself can begat life only dealt with the various changes in the arrangement of particles and did not explain life itself as a principle or power that lay behind the material manifestations, ''natura naturans'' or "the productive power suspended and, as it were, quenched in the product" Until this were addressed, according to Coleridge, "we have not yet attained to a science of nature."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Barfield|first1=Owen|title=What Coleridge Thought|date=1971|publisher=Wesleyan University Press|location=Middletown, CT|page=24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

This productive power is above sense experience, but not above nature herself, that is, supersensible, but not supernatural, and, thus, not 'occult' as was the case with vitalism. Vitalism failed to distinguish between spirit and nature, and then within nature, between the visible appearances and the invisible, yet very real and not simply hypothesized notion, essence or motivating principle (''natura naturans''). Even Newton spoke of things invisible in themselves (though not in their manifestations), such as force, though Comte, the thorough materialist, complained of the use of such terms as the 'force of gravity' as being relics of animism.&lt;ref name="What Coleridge Thought"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Barfield|first1=Owen|title=What Coleridge Thought|date=1971|publisher=Wesleyan University Press|location=Middletown, CT|page=25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Matter was not a 'datum' or thing in and of itself, but rather a product or effect, and for Coleridge, looking at life in its broadest sense, it was the product of a polarity of forces and energies, but derived from a unity which is itself a power, not an abstract or nominal concept, that is Life, and this polar nature of forces within the power of Life is the very law or 'Idea' (in the Platonic sense) of Creation.&lt;ref name="What Coleridge Thought"/&gt;

== Life as polarity/function/motion ==

For Coleridge the essence of the universe is motion and motion is driven by a dynamic polarity of forces that is both inherent in the world as potential and acting inherently in all manifestations. This polarity is the very dynamic that acts throughout all of nature, including into the more particular form of 'life biological', as well as of mind and consciousness.
 
:The tendency having been ascertained, what is its most general law? I answer—polarity, or the essential dualism of Nature, arising out of its productive unity, and still tending to reaffirm it, either as equilibrium, indifference, or identity.&lt;ref name="Theory of Life"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Coleridge|first1=Samuel Taylor|title=Hints Towards a More Comprehensive Theory of Life|date=1848|publisher=Lea and Blanchard|url=https://books.google.bs/books?id=AXcNAAAAYAAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=coleridge+theory+of+life&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=vGNTVLG8E8OogwSsvoCgDw&amp;ved=0CBoQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|accessdate=31 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

And this polarity is dynamic, that is real, though not visible, and not simply logical or abstract. Thus, the polarity results in manifestations that are real, as the opposite powers are not contradictory, but counteracting and inter-penetrating.

:...first, that two forces should be conceived which counteract each other by their essential nature; not only not in consequence of the accidental direction of each, but as prior to all direction, nay, as the primary forces from which the conditions of all possible directions are derivative and deducible: secondly, that these forces should be assumed to be both alike infinite, both alike indestructible... this one power with its two inherent indestructible yet counteracting forces, and the results or generations to which their inter-penetration gives existence, in the living principle and in the process of our own self-consciousness.&lt;ref name=BL&gt;{{cite book|last1=Coleridge|first1=Samuel Taylor|title=Biographia Literaria|date=1834|publisher=Leavitt, Lord &amp; Company|url=https://books.google.bs/books?id=QHdaAAAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA174&amp;dq=coleridge+biographia+literaria&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=j2RTVMaCA4aeNtPPgMAN&amp;ved=0CCEQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=biographia%20literaria&amp;f=false|accessdate=31 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Thus, then, Life itself is not a thing—a self-subsistent hypostasis—but an act and process...&lt;ref name="BL"/&gt;

And in that sense Coleridge re-phrases the question "What is Life?" to "What is not Life that really is?"&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Barfield|first1=Owen|title=What Coleridge Thought|date=1971|publisher=Wesleyan University Press|location=Middletown, CT|page=49}}&lt;/ref&gt;

This dynamic polar essence of nature in all its functions and manifestations is a universal law in the order of the law of gravity and other physical laws of inert nature. And, critically, this dynamic polarity of constituent powers of life at all levels is not outside or above nature, but is within nature (''natura naturans''), not as a part of the visible product, but as the ulterior natural functions that produce such products or things.

:a Power, acting in and by its Product or Representative to a predetermined purpose is a Function…

:The first product of its energy is the thing itself… Still, however, its productive energy is not exhausted in this product, but overflows, or is effluent, as the specific forces, properties, faculties, of the product. It reappears, in short, as the function of the body.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Barfield|first1=Owen|title=What Coleridge Thought|date=1971|publisher=Wesleyan University Press|location=Middletown, CT|page=34, fn 17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It is these functions that provided the bridge being sought by Romantic science and medicine, in particular by Andreas Röschlaub and the [[Brunonian system|Brunonian system of medicine]], between the inertial science of inert nature (physics) and the vital science of vital nature (physiology) and its therapeutic application or physic (the domain of the physician).

=== Romanticism and vitalism ===

Coleridge was influenced by German philosophy, in particular Kant, Fichte and Schelling (Naturphilosophie), as well as the physiology of Blumenbach and the dynamic excitation theory of life of the Brunonian system. He sought a path that was neither the mystical tendency of the earlier vitalists nor the materialistic reductionist approach to natural science, but a dynamic one.

:What Coleridge was after was definitely not animism or naive vitalism based on vital substance, or mechanical philosophy based on material substance. He was trying to find a general law...that explicates its self-regulating internal power.&lt;ref name=Hawk&gt;{{cite book|last1=Hawk|first1=Byron|title=A Counter-history of Composition: Toward Methodologies of Complexity|date=2007|publisher=University of Pittsburgh Press|pages=142–144|url=https://books.google.bs/books?id=dnHFgu43x1oC&amp;pg=PA281&amp;lpg=PA281&amp;dq=Coleridge%27s+theory+of+life&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=UljAqrEoxP&amp;sig=ojuS_BPEC--PNpfZVQ15yb1PUIs&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=tfpTVODlMsebNpTGgsgE&amp;ved=0CGQQ6AEwCQ#v=onepage&amp;q=Coleridge%27s%20theory%20of%20life&amp;f=false|accessdate=31 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Coleridge's challenge was to describe something that was dynamic neither in mystical terms not materialistic ones, but via analogy, drawing from the examples of inertial science. As one writer explains, he uses the examples of electricity, magnetism and gravity not because they are like life, but because they offer a way of understanding powers, forces and energies, which lie at the heart of life. And using these analogies, Coleridge seeks to demonstrate that life is not a material force, but a product of relations amongst forces. Life is not linear and static, but dynamic process of self-regulation and [[emergence|Emergent evolution]] that results in increasing complexity and individuation.&lt;ref name=Hawk/&gt; This spiral, upward movement (cf. Goethe's ideas) creates a force for organization that unifies, and is most intense and powerful in that which is most complex and most individual - the self-regulating, enlightened, developed individual mind. But at the same time, this process of life increases interdependence (like the law of comparative advantage in economics) and associational powers of the mind. Thus, he is not talking about an isolated, individual subjective mind, but about the evolution of a higher level of consciousness and thought at the core of the process of life.&lt;ref name=Hawk/&gt;

== Life and liberty ==

And the direction of this motion is towards increasing individuation, that is the creation of specific, individual units of things. At the same time, given the dynamic polarity of the world, there must always be an equal and opposite tendency, in this case, that of connection. So, a given of our experience is that man is both an individual, tending in each life and in history generally to greater and greater individualization, and a social creature seeking interaction and connection. It is the dynamic interplay between the individuation and connecting forces that leads to higher and higher individuation.
 
:By Life I everywhere mean the true Idea of Life,… the tendency to individuation… [which] cannot be conceived without the opposite tendency to connect, even as the centrifugal power supposes the centripetal, or as the two opposite poles constitute each other, and are the constituent acts of one and the same power in the magnet…. Again, if the tendency be at once to individuate and to connect, to detach, but so as either to retain or to reproduce attachment, the individuation itself must be a tendency to the ultimate production of the highest and most comprehensive individuality. This must be the one great end of Nature, her ultimate object, or by whatever other word we may designate that something which bears to a final cause the same relation that Nature herself bears to the Supreme Intelligence.&lt;ref name="BL"/&gt;

== Creative life and vital nature ==

Coleridge makes a further distinction between mathematics and life, the latter being productive or creative, that is, living, and the former ideal. Thus, the mathematical approach that works so well with inert nature, is not suitable for vital nature.

:In its productive power, of which the product is the only measure, consists its incompatibility with mathematical calculus. For the full applicability of an abstract science ceases, the moment reality begins.

:This productive or generative power of life exists in all manifestations of life. These manifestations are the finite product of the dynamic interaction of infinite and non-destructible forces, but the forces are not extinguished in the product - they take on a different role, namely that of functions. Thus, the very nature of the “given” is contained in its manifestations such that the whole is contained in all the parts. 
The counteraction then of the two assumed forces does not depend on their meeting from opposite directions; the power which acts in them is indestructible; it is therefore inexhaustibly re-ebullient; and as something must be the result of these two forces, both alike infinite, and both alike indestructible; and as rest or neutralization cannot be this result; no other conception is possible, but that the product must be a tertium aliquid, [a third thing] or finite generation. Consequently this conception is necessary. Now this tertium aliquid can be no other than an inter-penetration of the counteracting powers, partaking of both… Consequently the 'constituent powers', that have given rise to a body, may then reappear in it as its function: "a Power, acting in and by its Product or Representative to a predetermined purpose is a Function...the first product of its energy is the thing itself: ''ipsa se posuit et iam facta est ens positum''. Still, however, its productive energy is not exhausted in this product, but overflows, or is effluent, as the specific forces, properties, faculties, of the product. It reappears, in short, as the function of the body...The vital functions are consequents of the ''Vis Vitae Principium Vitale'', and presuppose the Organs, as the Functionaries.&lt;ref name="BL"/&gt;

Life, that is, the essential polarity in unity (multeity in unity) in Coleridge’s sense also has a four beat cycle, different from the arid dialectics of abstraction - namely the tension of the polar forces themselves, the charge of their synthesis, the discharge of their product (indifference) and the resting state of this new form (predominance). The product is not a neutralization, but a new form of the essential forces, these forces remaining within, though now as the functions of the form.

:But as little can we conceive the oneness, except as the mid-point producing itself on each side; that is, manifesting itself on two opposite poles. Thus, from identity we derive duality, and from both together we obtain polarity, synthesis, indifference, predominance. (BL)
To make it adequate, we must substitute the idea of positive production for that of rest, or mere neutralization. To the fancy alone it is the null-point, or zero, but to the reason it is the punctum saliens, and the power itself in its eminence.&lt;ref name="BL"/&gt;

== Life and matter ==

This dynamic polarity that is Life is expressed at different levels. At its most basic it is Space-Time, with its product - motion. The interplay of both gives us either a line or a circle, and then there are different degrees possible within a given form or “predominance” of forces. Geometry is not conceivable except as the dynamic interplay of space (periphery) and time (point). Space, time and motion are also geometrically represented by width, length (breadth) and depth. And this correspondence is repeated throughout the scale of Life.

:We have been thus full and express on this subject, because these simple ideas of time, space, and motion, of length, breadth, and depth, are not only the simplest and universal, but the necessary symbols of all philosophic construction. They will be found the primary factors and elementary forms of every calculus and of every diagram in the algebra and geometry of a scientific physiology. Accordingly, we shall recognise the same forms under other names; but at each return more specific and intense; and the whole process repeated with ascending gradations of reality, exempli gratiâ: Time + space = motion; Tm + space = line + breadth = depth; depth + motion = force; Lf + Bf = Df; LDf + BDf = attraction + repulsion = gravitation; and so on, even till they pass into outward phenomena, and form the intermediate link between productive powers and fixed products in light, heat, and electricity.&lt;ref name="BL"/&gt;

Matter, then, is the product of the dynamic forces - repulsion (centrifugal), and attraction (centripetal); it is not itself a productive power. It is also the mass of a given body.
 
:If we pass to the construction of matter, we find it as the product, or tertium aliquid, of antagonist powers of repulsion and attraction. Remove these powers, and the conception of matter vanishes into space—conceive repulsion only, and you have the same result. For infinite repulsion, uncounteracted and alone, is tantamount to infinite, dimensionless diffusion, and this again to infinite weakness; viz., to space. Conceive attraction alone, and as an infinite contraction, its product amounts to the absolute point, viz., to time. Conceive the synthesis of both, and you have matter as a fluxional antecedent, which, in the very act of formation, passes into body by its gravity, and yet in all bodies it still remains as their mass...&lt;ref name="BL"/&gt;

Coleridge’s understanding of life is contrasted with the materialist view which is essentially reduced to defining life as that which is the opposite of not-life, or that which resists death, that is, that which is life.

:By an easy logic, each of the two divisions has been made to define the others by a mere assertion of their assumed contrariety. The theorist has explained Y+X by informing us that it is the opposite of Y-X: and if we ask, what then is Y-X, we are told that it is the opposite of Y+X! A reciprocation of good services....I turn to a work by the eminent French physiologist, Bichat, where I find this definition: Life is the sum of all the functions by which death is resisted....that is, that life consists in being able to live!...as if four more inveterate abstractions could be brought together than the words life, death, function, and resistance.&lt;ref name="BL"/&gt;

== Cognition and life ==

The problem for Coleridge and the Romantics was that the intellect, 'left to itself' as Bacon stated, was capable of apprehending only the outer forms of nature (natura naturata) and not the inmost, living functions (natura naturans) giving rise to these forms. Thus, effects can only be 'explained' in terms of other effects, not causes. It takes a different capacity to 'see' these living functions, which is an imaginative activity. For Coleridge, there is an innate, primitive or 'primary' imagination that configures invisibly sense-experience into perception, but a rational perception, that is, one raised into consciousness and awareness and then rationally presentable, requires a higher level, what he termed 'secondary imagination', which is able to connect with the thing being experienced, penetrate to its essence in terms of the living dynamics upholding its outer form, and then present the phenomena as and within its natural law, and further, using reason, develop the various principles of its operation.

This cognitive capacity involved what Coleridge termed the 'inmost sense' or what Goethe termed the '''Gemüt'''. It also involved the reactivation of the old Greek noetic capacity, and the ability to 'see' or produce the theory (Greek ''theoria'' from the verb 'to see') dynamic polarities, or natural Laws, the dynamic transcendent (foundational) entities that Plato termed 'Ideas' (''eidos'').

Since ''natura naturata'' is sustained by ''natura naturans'', and the creative power of ''natura naturans'' is one of a kind with the human mind, itself creative, then there must be a correspondence or connection between the mind and the things we perceive, such that we can overcome the apparent separation between the object and the representation in the mind of the object that came to bedevil Enlightenment thought (Hume, Kant). As one commentator noted "to speak at all of the unity of intelligence and nature is of course flatly to contradict Descartes."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Barfield|first1=Owen|title=What Coleridge Thought|date=1971|publisher=Wesleyan University Press|location=Middletown, CT|page=62}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Life and evolution ==

For Coleridge the power of life lies in every seed as a potential to be unfolded as a result of interaction with the environment (heat, light, air, moisture, etc.), an insight which allowed him to see in the Brunonian system a dynamic polarity in excitation theory.
 
Coleridge also saw that there was a progressive movement through time and space of life or the law of polarity, from the level of physics (space and time) and the mineral or inert nature (law of gravity, operating through forces of attraction and repulsion), up to man, with his law of resonance in terms of his innate desire to be himself (force of individuation) and to also connect with like-minded (force of connection), as Goethe expressed in his novel ''Elective Affinities'' (''Wahlverwandschaften'') as well as in his own life's experience.
 
Evolution occurred because the original polarity of creation, the very 'Law of Creation', itself gives birth to subsequent polarities, as each pole is itself a unity that can be further polarized (what Wilhelm Reich later termed 'orgonomic functionalism' and what at the biological level constitutes physiology),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Barfield|first1=Owen|title=What Coleridge Thought|date=1971|publisher=Wesleyan University Press|location=Middletown, CT|page=53}}&lt;/ref&gt; an insight that would later be taken up by the concept of emergent evolution, including the emergence of mind and consciousness.

:the productive power, or ''vis naturans'', which in the sensible world, or n''atura naturata'', is what we mean by the word, nature, when we speak of the same as an agent, is essentially one (that is, of one kind) with the intelligence, which is in the human mind above nature."&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Barfield|first1=Owen|title=What Coleridge Thought|date=1971|publisher=Wesleyan University Press|location=Middletown, CT|page=61}}&lt;/ref&gt;

And that this is so, is also an intimate and shared experience of all humans, as is set out in Reid's Common Sense philosophy. As Coleridge states

:but for the confidence which we place in the assertions of our reason and our conscience, we could have no certainty of the reality and actual outness of the material world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Barfield|first1=Owen|title=What Coleridge Thought|date=1971|publisher=Wesleyan University Press|location=Middletown, CT|page=64}}&lt;/ref&gt;

That nature evolves towards a purpose, and that is the unfolding of the human mind and consciousness in all its levels and degrees, is not teleological but a function of the very nature of the law of polarity or creation itself, namely that of increasing individuation of an original unity, what Coleridge termed 'multeity in unity'. As he states, "without assigning to nature as nature, a conscious purpose" we must still "distinguish her agency from a blind and lifeless mechanism."&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"/&gt;

While man contains and is subject to the various laws of nature, man as a self-conscious being is also the summa of a process of creation leading to greater mind and consciousness, that is, a creative capacity of imagination. Instead of being a creature of circumstance, man is the creator of them, or at least has that potential.
 
:Naked and helpless cometh man into the world. Such has been the complaint from eldest time; but we complain of our chief privilege, our ornament, and the connate mark of our sovereignty. Porphyrigeniti summus! …Henceforth he is referred to himself, delivered up to his own charge…&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Barfield|first1=Owen|title=What Coleridge Thought|date=1971|publisher=Wesleyan University Press|location=Middletown, CT|page=29, fn 29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Romantic epistemology]]
* [[Superseded scientific theories]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

[[Category:Life]]
[[Category:Ontology]]
[[Category:Romanticism]]</text>
      <sha1>a2qhy9avrfvei914wyv2ncj7p9b0gvo</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Digital immortality</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>23347654</id>
    <revision>
      <id>865575436</id>
      <parentid>848175696</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-10-24T19:26:54Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>199.159.49.228</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>added reference to fictional series Altered Carbon</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="12815">'''Digital immortality''' (or "'''virtual immortality'''") is the hypothetical concept of storing (or transferring) a person's personality in more durable media, i.e., a computer. The result might look like an [[Avatar (computing)|avatar]] behaving, reacting, and thinking like a person on the basis of that person's digital archive.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Parkin|first1=Simon|title=Back-up brains: The era of digital immortality|url=http://www.bbc.com/future/story/20150122-the-secret-to-immortality|publisher=BBC|accessdate=7 June 2015|date=23 January 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="vhum"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Rothblatt|first1=Martine|title=Virtually Human: The Promiseand the Perilof Digital Immortality|date=2014|isbn=978-1491532911|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Y7JzAwAAQBAJ}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="dyi"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Sofka|first1=Carla|title=Dying, Death, and Grief in an Online Universe: For Counselors and Educators|date=February 2012|isbn=978-0826107329|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=MkcGiLeATe8C&amp;pg=PA25&amp;dq=digital+immortality}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=DeGroot|first1=Doug|title=Intelligent Virtual Agents: 4th International Workshop, IVA 2003, Kloster Irsee, Germany, September 15-17, 2003, Proceedings (Lecture Notes in ... / Lecture Notes in Artificial Intelligence)|date=5 November 2003|isbn=978-3540200031|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=NzZtCQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA136&amp;dq=digital+immortality|accessdate=7 June 2015|chapter=VideoDIMs as a framework for Digital Immortality Applications}}&lt;/ref&gt; After the death of the individual, this avatar could remain static or continue to learn and develop autonomously.

A considerable portion of [[transhumanists]] and [[singularitarians]] place great hope into the belief that they may become [[Immortality|immortal]] by the year 2045,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Cohan|first1=Peter|title=Google's Engineering Director: 32 Years To Digital Immortality|url=https://www.forbes.com/sites/petercohan/2013/06/20/googles-engineering-director-32-years-to-digital-immortality/|accessdate=7 June 2015|date=20 June 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; by creating one or many non-biological functional copies of their brains, thereby leaving their "biological shell". These copies may then "live eternally" in a version of digital "heaven" or paradise.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Lewis|first1=Tanya|title=The Singularity Is Near: Mind Uploading by 2045?|url=http://www.livescience.com/37499-immortality-by-2045-conference.html|website=livescience.com|accessdate=7 June 2015|date=17 June 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Strickland|first1=Jonathan|title=How Digital Immortality Works|url=http://electronics.howstuffworks.com/gadgets/high-tech-gadgets/digital-immortality.htm|website=howstuffworks.com|accessdate=7 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== The realism of the concept ==
The [[National Science Foundation]] has awarded a half-million-dollar grant to the universities of Central Florida at Orlando and Illinois at Chicago to explore how researchers might use [[artificial intelligence]], archiving, and computer imaging to create convincing, digital versions of real people, a possible first step toward virtual immortality.&lt;ref&gt;[http://bioethics.com/?p=2717 US Government funds virtual reality research], bioethics.com, 14 June 2007 &lt;/ref&gt;

The Digital Immortality Institute explores three factors necessary for digital immortality. First, at whatever level of implementation, avatars require guaranteed [[Internet]] accessibility. Next, avatars must be what users specify, and they must remain so. Finally, future representations must be secured before the living users are no more.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.digital-immortality.org/whatis.html |title=What is Digital Immortality? |publisher=Digital-immortality.org |date= |accessdate=2012-03-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The aim of [[Dmitry Itskov]]'s [[2045 Initiative]] is to "create technologies enabling the transfer of an individual’s personality to a non-biological carrier, and extending existence, including to the point of immortality".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Eördögh|first1=Fruzsina|title=Russian Billionaire Dmitry Itskov Plans on Becoming Immortal by 2045|url=http://motherboard.vice.com/blog/russian-billionaire-dmitry-itskov-plans-on-becoming-immortal-by-2045|accessdate=7 June 2015|date=7 May 2013|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150524041430/http://motherboard.vice.com/blog/russian-billionaire-dmitry-itskov-plans-on-becoming-immortal-by-2045|archivedate=24 May 2015|df=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Method ==
Reaching digital immortality is a two-step process:
#  archiving and [[digitizing]] people,
#  making the avatar live

=== Archiving and digitizing people ===
According to [[Gordon Bell]] and [[Jim Gray (computer scientist)|Jim Gray]] from [[Microsoft Research]], retaining every conversation that a person has ever heard is already realistic: it needs less than a [[terabyte]] of [[computer data storage|storage]] (for adequate quality).&lt;ref&gt;[http://research.microsoft.com/pubs/69927/tr-2000-101.pdf Digital Immortality], by Gordon Bell and Jim Gray, Microsoft Research&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Bainbridge|first1=William Sims|title=Personality Capture and Emulation|date=November 2013|isbn=978-1-4471-5604-8|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=hiq8BAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA2&amp;dq=digital+immortality}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[speech recognition|speech]] or [[optical character recognition|text recognition]] technologies are one of the biggest challenges of the concept.

A second possibility would be to archive and analyze social Internet use to map the personality of people. By analyzing social Internet use during 50 years, it would be possible to model a society's culture, a society's way of thinking, and a society's interests.

Rothblatt envisions the creation of "mindfiles" – collections of data from all kinds of sources, including the photos we upload to Facebook, the discussions and opinions we share on forums or blogs, and other social media interactions that reflect our life experiences and our unique self.&lt;ref name="vhum"/&gt;&lt;ref name="esc"&gt;{{cite web|last1=Desat|first1=Marla|title=Would You Clone Your Mind to Live Forever? Virtually Human|url=http://www.escapistmagazine.com/articles/view/scienceandtech/12297-Review-Maxime-Rothblatt-s-Virtually-Human-Digital-Immortality|publisher=The Escapist|accessdate=7 June 2015|date=23 September 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Richard Grandmorin&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://twitter.com/soon_immortal |title=soon immortal (@soon_immortal) op Twitter |publisher=Twitter.com |date= |accessdate=2012-03-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; summarized the concept of digital immortality by the following equation: "semantic analysis + social internet use + Artificial Intelligence = immortality".

Some find that photos, videos, soundclips, social media posts and other data of oneself could already be regarded as such an archiving.&lt;ref name="sterkul"&gt;{{cite book|title=Computertechnik und Sterbekultur|isbn=978-3-643-11071-8|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=chnMBQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA129&amp;lpg=PA129&amp;dq=caprica+digital+immortality|accessdate=7 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="vhum"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=McQuade|first1=Zan|title=What happens to us on the internet when we die?|url=https://theweek.com/articles/554466/what-happens-internet-when-die|publisher=The Week|accessdate=7 June 2015|date=16 May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="esc"/&gt;

Susanne Asche states:
{{pull quote|text=As a hopefully minimalistic definition then, digital immortality can be roughly considered as involving a person-centric repository containing a copy of everything that a person sees, hears, says, or engenders over his or her lifespan, including photographs, videos, audio recordings, movies, television shows, music albums/CDs, newspapers, documents, diaries and journals, interviews, meetings, love letters, notes, papers, art pieces, and so on, and so on; and if not everything, then at least as much as the person has and takes the time and trouble to include. The person’s personality, emotion profiles, thoughts, beliefs, and appearance are also captured and integrated into an artificially intelligent, interactive, con-versational agent/avatar. This avatar is placed in charge of (and perhaps "equated" with) the collected material in the repository so that the agent can present the illusion of having the factual memories, thoughts, and beliefs of the person him/herself.|author=Susanne Asche|source=Kulturelles Gedächtnis im 21. Jahrhundert: Tagungsband des internationalen Symposiums, Digital Immortality &amp; Runaway Technology&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Asche|first1=Susanne|title=Kulturelles Gedächtnis im 21. Jahrhundert: Tagungsband des internationalen Symposiums|date=23 April 2005|publisher=KIT Scientific Publishing|url=http://digbib.ubka.uni-karlsruhe.de/volltexte/documents/3296701|accessdate=7 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

=== Making the avatar alive ===
{{unclear|date=March 2016}}

Defining the avatar to be alive allows it to communicate with the future in the sense that it continues to learn, evolve and interact with people, if they still exist. Technically, the operation exists to implement an artificial intelligence system to the avatar.{{Citation needed|date=July 2015}} This artificial intelligence system is then assumed to think and will react on the base of the archive.

Rothblatt proposes the term "mindware" for software that is being developed with the goal of generating conscious AIs. Such software would read a person's "mindfile" to generate a "mindclone." Rothblatt also proposes a certain level of governmental approval for mindware, like an FDA certification, to ensure that the resulting mindclones are well made.&lt;ref name="vhum"/&gt;&lt;ref name="esc"/&gt;

=== Calibration process ===
During the calibration process, the biological people are living at the same time as their artifact in silicon. The artifact in silicon is calibrated to be as close as possible to the person in question.
During this process ongoing updates, synchronization, and interaction between the two minds would maintain the twin minds as one.&lt;ref name="vhum"/&gt;&lt;ref name="esc"/&gt;

== In fiction ==
{{Further|Mind uploading in fiction}}
* In the TV series ''[[Caprica (TV series)|Caprica]]'' a digital copy of a person is created and outlives its real counterpart after the person dies in a terrorist attack.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=MacIver|first1=Malcolm|title=Caprica Puzzle: If a Digital You Lives Forever, Are You Immortal?|url=https://blogs.discovermagazine.com/sciencenotfiction/2010/10/05/caprica-puzzle-if-a-digital-you-lives-forever-are-you-immortal/|website=discovermagazine.com|accessdate=7 June 2015|date=5 October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!--(needs improvement)--&gt;&lt;ref name="news"&gt;{{cite web|last1=Geddes|first1=Linda|title=Immortal avatars: Back up your brain, never die|url=https://www.newscientist.com/article/mg20627631.100-immortal-avatars-back-up-your-brain-never-die.html|publisher=New Scientist|accessdate=7 June 2015|date=7 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In [[Greg Egan]]'s ''[[Permutation city]]'' people can achieve quasi digital immortality by [[mind uploading]] a digital copy of themselves into a [[simulated reality]].&lt;ref name="sterkul"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Pickover|first1=Clifford A.|title=A Beginner's Guide to Immortality: Extraordinary People, Alien Brains, and Quantum Resurrection|isbn=978-1560259848|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=lfl4_StP_EIC&amp;pg=PA78&amp;lpg=PA78&amp;dq=permutation+city+simulated+reality}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''[[Memories with Maya]]'' is a novel on the concept of digital immortality.
* ''[[Charles Platt (author)#Novels and novellas|The Silicon Man]]'' describes [[Cryonics]] as a precursor to digital immortality.
* In the 1998 novel ''[[Vast (novel)|Vast]]'' by [[Linda Nagata]] "ghosts" are recorded memories and personalities that can be transferred to another body or kept in electronic storage, granting a limited form of immortality.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Vast Review|url=https://www.sfsite.com/06b/vast83.htm|publisher=SF Site|accessdate=17 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In the TV series ''[[Captain Power and the Soldiers of the Future]]'', Overmind and Lord Dread planned to digitize all human beings to be able to create a new world.
* In the TV series ''[[Black Mirror]]'' the episode ''[[San Junipero]]'' features a digital, simulated reality of 1987 used to upload minds before death.
*In the novel/Netflix series [[Altered Carbon (TV series)|Altered Carbon]], a person's memories and consciousness can be stored in a disk-shaped device called a ''cortical stack'', which is implanted into the cervical vertebrae.

== See also ==
* [[Blue brain]]
* [[Ship of Theseus]]
* [[Immortality]]
* [[Technological resurrection]]
* [[Uploaded astronaut]]

== References ==
{{reflist}}

{{Longevity}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Digital Immortality}}
[[Category:Life extension]]
[[Category:Transhumanism]]
[[Category:Immortality]]
[[Category:Hypothetical technology]]</text>
      <sha1>7mkrlg4fdex12sm33kgjwoap0hdtr32</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Everyday life</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2667092</id>
    <revision>
      <id>868777700</id>
      <parentid>867259328</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-11-14T11:01:58Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Cydebot</username>
        <id>1215485</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Robot - Speedily moving category Self care to [[:Category:Self-care]] per [[WP:CFDS|CFDS]].</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="11652">{{about|the concept of the person|the rapcore band|Every Day Life}}
[[File:Man sleeping striped-sheets.JPG|thumb|[[Sleep]]ing]]
[[File:Studying Star Wars.jpg|thumb|Children reading books.]]
[[File:The Combing of Granddaughter.jpg|thumb|Grooming]]
[[File:FamilyWatchingTV1958crop.jpg|thumb|Watching television]]

'''Everyday life''', '''daily life''' or '''routine life''' comprises the ways in which people typically act, think, and feel on a daily basis.  Everyday life may be described as mundane, routine, natural, habitual, or [[Normality (behavior)|normal]].

Human [[diurnality]] means most people sleep at least part of the night and are active in daytime. Most eat two or three meals in a day.  [[Working time]] (apart from [[shift work]]) mostly involves a daily schedule, beginning in the [[morning]].  This produces the daily [[rush hour]]s experienced by many millions, and the [[drive time]] focused on by radio broadcasters.  [[Evening]] is often [[leisure]] time. [[Bathing]] every day is a custom for many.

Beyond these broad similarities, lifestyles vary and different people spend their days differently. [[Nomad]]ic life differs from [[sedentism]], and among the sedentary, [[Urban area|urban]] people live differently from [[Rural area|rural]] folk. Differences in the lives of the [[wealth|rich]] and the [[poverty|poor]], or between [[factory worker]]&lt;nowiki/&gt;s and [[intellectual]]s, may go beyond their [[working hours]]. Many women spend their day in activities greatly different from those of men, and everywhere [[children]] do different things than adults.

==Sociological perspectives==
[[File:The Psychopathology of Everyday Life.jpg|thumb|''[[The Psychopathology of Everyday Life]]'']]

Everyday life is a key concept in [[cultural studies]] and is a specialized subject in the field of [[sociology]].  Some argue that, motivated by [[capitalism]] and [[industrialism]]'s degrading effects on human existence and perception, writers and artists of the 19th century turned more towards [[self-reflection]] and the portrayal of everyday life represented in their writings and art to a noticeably greater degree than in past works, for example [[Renaissance literature]]'s interest in [[hagiography]] and politics.&lt;ref name="felski"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Felski|first1=Rita|title=The Invention of Everyday Life|date=1999|publisher=Lawrence &amp; Wishart|location=London|isbn=9780853159018|pages=15–31|url=http://people.virginia.edu/~rf6d/felski.the-invention-of-everyday-life.pdf|accessdate=15 November 2014|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!--page 16--&gt;  Other theorists dispute this argument based on a long history of writings about daily life which can be seen in works from [[Ancient Greece]], [[Medieval art|medieval Christianity]] and the [[Age of Enlightenment]].&lt;ref name="lefebvre"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Lefebvre|first1=Henri|title=Everyday life in the modern world|date=1984|publisher=Transaction Books|location=New Brunswick, N.J., U.S.A.|isbn=978-0878559725|accessdate=15 November 2014|page=38}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="coser"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Coser|first1=[edited by] Lewis A.|title=The idea of social structure : papers in honor of Robert K. Merton|date=2012|publisher=Transaction Publishers|location=New Brunswick, N.J.|isbn=978-1412847414|url=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the study of everyday life gender has been an important factor in its conceptions.  Some theorists regard [[women]] as the quintessential representatives and victims of everyday life.&lt;ref name="lefebvre"/&gt;&lt;!--page73--&gt;  

The connotation of everyday life is often negative and is distinctively separated from exceptional moments by its lack of [[distinction (sociology)|distinction]] and differentiation, ultimately defined as the essential, taken-for-granted continuum of [[mundane]] activity that outlines forays into more [[esoteric]] experiences.  It is the non-negotiable [[reality]] that exists amongst all social groupings without discrimination and is an unavoidable basis for which all human endeavor exists.&lt;ref name="felski" /&gt;

Much of everyday life is automatic in that it is driven by current environmental features as mediated by automatic [[cognitive processing]] of those features, and without any mediation by conscious choice, according to social psychologist [[John Bargh|John A. Bargh]].&lt;ref&gt;Wyer/Bargh 1997, p. 2.&lt;/ref&gt; Daily life is also studied by sociologists to investigate how it is organised and given meaning. A sociological journal called the ''[[Journal of Mundane Behavior]]'', published 2000 - 2004, studied these everyday actions.

{{see also|Ritual|Commoner|Average Joe|Hoi polloi|Dominant ideology}}

== Leisure ==
{{Main|Leisure}}

Daily [[entertainment]] once consisted mainly of telling stories in the evening. This [[Convention (norm)|custom]] developed into the [[theatre of ancient Greece]] and other professional entertainments. [[Reading (process)|Reading]] later became less a mysterious specialty of [[scholar]]s, and more a common pleasure for people who could afford books. During the 20th century [[mass media]] became prevalent in rich countries, creating among other things a daily [[prime time]] to consume [[fiction]] and other professionally produced works.

Different media forms serve different purposes in different individuals' everyday lives—which give people the opportunities to make [[choice]]s about what media form(s)--watching [[television]], using the [[Internet]], listening to the [[radio]], or reading newspapers or magazines—most effectively help them to accomplish their tasks.&lt;ref name="Baym"&gt;Baym, N. (2010), ‘Making New Media Make Sense’ in Personal Connections in the Digital Age, Polity Press, Ch. 2.&lt;/ref&gt;  Many people have steadily increased their daily use of the Internet, over all other media forms.   Fearing changes promoted by mass entertainment, [[social conservative]]&lt;nowiki/&gt;s have long censored books and films, called television a [[vast wasteland]], and predicted that [[social media]] and other Internet sites would distract people from good [[personal relationship]]s or valuable interactions.  These concerns did not prevent the progressively wider popularity of these innovations.

==Language==
People's everyday lives are shaped through [[language]] and [[communication]]. They choose what to do with their time based on opinions and ideals formed through the [[discourse]] they are exposed to.&lt;ref&gt;Roger Silverstone (1994), Television and Everyday Life, p. 18-19&lt;/ref&gt; Much of the dialogue people are subject to comes from the [[mass media]], which is an important factor in what shapes [[human experience]].&lt;ref&gt;Marie Gillepsie and Eugene McLaughlin (2008), Media and the Shaping of Public Attitudes, p. 8&lt;/ref&gt; The media uses language to make an impact on one’s everyday life, whether that be as small as helping to decide where to eat or as big as choosing a [[Representative democracy|representative]] in government.

To improve people's everyday life, Phaedra Pezzullo, professor in the Department of Communication and Culture at [[Indiana University Bloomington]], says people should seek to understand the [[rhetoric]] that so often and unnoticeably changes their lives. She writes that “...rhetoric enables us to make connections... It's about understanding how we engage with the world.”&lt;ref&gt;Elizabeth Rosdeitcher (2006), "[http://www.indiana.edu/~rcapub/v29n1/rhetoric.shtml The Rhetoric of Everyday Life]", ''Humanities, Then and Now'' 29, no. 1 (Fall).&lt;/ref&gt;

==Activities of Daily Living==

[[Activities of daily living]] (ADL) is a term used in healthcare to refer to daily [[self care]] activities within an individual's place of residence, in outdoor environments, or both. [[Health professional]]s routinely refer to the ability or inability to perform ADLs as a measurement of the functional status of a person, particularly in regard to people with [[Disability|disabilities]] and the [[Old age|elderly]].&lt;ref name=EN&gt;"Activities of Daily Living Evaluation." ''Encyclopedia of Nursing &amp; Allied Health''. ed. Kristine Krapp. Gale Group, Inc., 2002. eNotes.com. 2006.[http://www.enotes.com/nursing-encyclopedia/activities-daily-living-evaluation Enotes Nursing Encyclopedia] Accessed on: 11 Oct, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; ADLs are defined as "the things we normally do...such as [[Meal|feeding ourselves]], bathing, dressing, grooming, work, homemaking, and leisure."&lt;ref name =MN&gt;[http://www.medterms.com/script/main/art.asp?articlekey=2152 MedicineNet.com Medical Dictionary]&lt;/ref&gt; The ability and the extent to which the elderly can perform these activities is at the focus of [[gerontology]] and understandings of later life.&lt;ref&gt;Katz, Stephen. [http://is.muni.cz/el/1423/podzim2013/SOC570/um/Katz_Busy_Bodies_2000.pdf ''Busy bodies: Activities, aging, and the management of everyday life'']. - Journal of aging studies, Elsevier, 2000. p. 136.&lt;/ref&gt; In an 'active society' which sees mobility as an important norm, constant physical activity has replaced the striving towards personal growth in later life.&lt;ref&gt;Katz, Stephen. [http://is.muni.cz/el/1423/podzim2013/SOC570/um/Katz_Busy_Bodies_2000.pdf ''Busy bodies: Activities, aging, and the management of everyday life'']. - Journal of aging studies, Elsevier, 2000. p. 148.&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{Portal|Sociology|Health}}
{{div col|colwidth=30em}}
* ''[[Being in the World]]''
* [[Existentiell]]
* [[Genre art]]
* [[Genre painting]]
* [[Homelessness]]
* [[Lifestyle (sociology)]]
* [[Lifeworld]]
* [[Personal life]]
* [[Realism (arts)]]
* [[Shibui]]
* [[Simple living]]
* [[Technics and Time, 1]]
* ''[[Technology and the Character of Contemporary Life]]''
* ''[[The Practice of Everyday Life]]''
* ''[[The Revolution of Everyday Life]]''
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Bibliography==
* Wyer, Robert S.; [[John Bargh|Bargh, John A.]] (1997). [https://books.google.com/books?hl=ja&amp;lr=&amp;id=K_GNA4Du0tYC&amp;oi=fnd&amp;pg=PR7&amp;dq=everyday+life&amp;ots=TVN-TzQaoL&amp;sig=bFiAtMPi42h4XI4D9BQ9YS48l7A#v=onepage&amp;q=everyday%20life&amp;f=false ''The Automaticity of Everyday life'']. Lawrence Erlbaum Associates. {{ISBN|0805816992}}

==Further reading==
* [[Sigmund Freud]] (1901), [http://www-ccd.usc.edu/assets/sites/208/docs/Ouellette.Wood.1998.pdf ''The Psychopathology of Everyday Life''], [http://www.answers.com/topic/psychopathology-of-everyday-life-the]
* [[Henri Lefebvre]] (1947), ''Critique of Everyday Life''
* [[Raoul Vaneigem]] (1967), ''[[The Revolution of Everyday Life]]''
* [[Michel de Certeau]] (1974), ''[[The Practice of Everyday Life]]''
* [[John Shotter|Shotter, John]] (1993), ''Cultural politics of everyday life: [[Social constructionism]], rhetoric and knowing of the third kind.''[http://psycnet.apa.org/psycinfo/1993-98490-000]
* ''The Everyday Life Reader'' (2001) edited by Ben Highmore. {{ISBN|0-415-23025-X}}
* [[Erving Goffman]] (2002), ''[[The Presentation of Self in Everyday Life]]'', in CONTEMPORARY SOCIOLOGICAL THEORY. [https://books.google.com/books?hl=ja&amp;lr=&amp;id=MzGV9A5qLzgC&amp;oi=fnd&amp;pg=PA51&amp;dq=everyday+life&amp;ots=3Dv3y1rSkr&amp;sig=DR_2MFoDe8TATLQw_d2pP34AsKk#v=onepage&amp;q=everyday%20life&amp;f=false]
* [[Kristine Hughes]], ''The Writer's Guide to Everyday Life in Regency and Victorian England from 1811-1901'' [https://www.scribd.com/doc/33352487/The-Writer-s-Guide-to-Everyday-Life-in-Regency-and-Victorian-England-Kristine-Hughes]
* [[Candy Moulton]], ''Everyday Life Among the American Indians 1800 to 1900''.  {{ISBN|0-89879-996-1}} {{ISBN|1582974713}}
* [[Ágnes Heller]], ''Everyday Life ''.  {{ISBN|978-0-7100-9701-9}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Everyday Life}}
[[Category:Personal life]]
[[Category:Philosophy of life]]
[[Category:Self-care|Self care]]

[[he:שגרה]]</text>
      <sha1>c2kvswdemm1kybsiqg1cbwxpbkfzcic</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Kay 9ice</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>59010226</id>
    <revision>
      <id>868927877</id>
      <parentid>868145709</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-11-15T08:33:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ghost122</username>
        <id>31432566</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Achievement */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="5836">{{Infobox musical artist
| honorific_prefix = 
| honorific_suffix = 
| image =
| image_size = 
| landscape = &lt;!-- yes, if wide image, otherwise leave blank --&gt;
| name = Kay 9ice
| caption = 
| background = solo_singer
| native_name = 
| native_name_lang = 
| birth_name = Philip Kissi
| alias = 
| birth_date = {{Birth date and age|df=yes|1990|05|27}}
| birth_place = [[Accra]], [[Ghana]]
| origin = [[Ghanaian]]
| genre = [[Afrobeats]], [[Hiplife]]
| occupation = Singer, Songwriter
| years_active = 2015–present
| label = '''GHOZT MUSIK''' &amp; '''+816 STUDIO'''
| associated_acts = 
| website = &lt;!---{{URL|website}}---&gt;
}}
'''Philip Kwaku Kissi''' popularly known as '''Kay 9ice''', was born on May 27, 1990 in Accra, Ghana. a [[Ghanaian people|Ghanaian]] [[Hiplife]] and [[Afrobeats]] artiste. Kay 9ice currently signed to GHOZT MUSIK&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://ezone57.com/get-familiar-kay-9ice-bbc-music-artist/ | title=KAY 9ICE SIGN TO GHOZT MUSIK | publisher= Kofighozt | date= | author= | accessdate=23 August 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; a record label based in [[Ghana]] &amp; +816 studios.

==Biography==
Philip hails from Akoefe in the Volta Region of Ghana. Growing up, [[afrobeats]] music became his favorite at the junior high school level Ashaiman Government School.
He won himself the pleasure to be the first Ghanaian to be introduced by BBC Music and to feature on BBC6 Music Mixtape.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/blogs/introducing/entries/6a33f87e-bbfa-4843-86e2-6f5aa1c6ea86| title=BBC Music Introducing Mixtape 26 March 2018|publisher= Tom Robison | date= | author= | accessdate=23 August 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Kay |first1=9ice |title=Kay 9ice wobeti bbc |url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/music/tracks/n5zpn3 |website=bbc |publisher=Tom Robison |accessdate=3 September 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Kay 9ice became part of a musical group called Rekx Bois (Real Entertainment Knocked Down Extremely). Due to his hard work musically he had his first big appearance during Flowking Stone's oseikrom shutdown show in Kumasi, Ghana. With his hard work, he got nominated for the median edition for Ashaiman Music Awards 2018 and Ghana Music Awards South Africa for which he got 7 nominations&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Kay 9ice |first1=7 nominations |title=Kay 9ice 7 nominations |agency=ModernGhana |ref=https://www.modernghana.com/entertainment/52027/kay-9ice-bags-7-nominations-at-the-maiden-amas.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; and promising Artist Of The Year 2018&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=2018 Ghana Music Awards South Africa: Check |first1=The Full List of Nominees |title=2018 Ghana Music Awards South Africa: Check The Full List of Nominees |agency=NYDJ live |ref=https://www.nydjlive.com/2018-ghana-music-awards-south-africa-check-the-full-list-of-nominees/}}&lt;/ref&gt; respectively.

== Achievement ==
He won the Afro-Song Of The Year category in The median edition Of the Ashaiman Music Awards 2018 and was also nominated for ghana Music awards south africa. He is also the first ghanaian to be feature on BBC 6 Music Introducing Mixtape.

==Singles==
{{Expand list|date=August 2017}}
{|class="wikitable"
!Music
!Ref
!Year
!Producer
|-

|''Wobeti''
|&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ezone57.com/lil-kay-wobeti-sarkodie-covermixed-yungbeatz///|title=kay 9ice – Wobeti |website=ezone57.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|2017
|Mixed by YungBeat
|-

|''Odo''
|&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://itunes.apple.com/us/album/odo-single/1324504486/|title=Lil kay - Odo |date=22 December 2017|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|2017
|Mixed by YungBeat
|-

|''My Babe''
|&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://soundcloud.com/ghozt_musik/kayice_mybabe|title=My babe - Kay 9ice |website=Soundclound}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|2017
|Mixed by YungBeatz
|-
|''Lighter (MJ Riddim)''
|&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://soundcloud.com/ghozt_musik/lighter-mixed-by-uptic |title=Kay 9ice - Lighter One dread riddim |publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|2018
|Mixed by Uptic
|-
|''Sika B3ba''
|&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://beeniewords.com/new-music-kay-9ice-sika-b3ba-prod-by-b2-mixed-by-yungbeat/|title=Kay 9ice - Sika B3ba(Mixed by YungBeat)|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|2018
|Mixed by YungBeat
|-
|''Chokor''
|&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://numberone.ng/2018/08/kay-9ice-choko-wizkid-cover/|title=Kay 9ice - Chokor(Wizkid Cover)|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|2018
|Mixed By Uptic
|-
|''House Party''
|&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://soundcloud.com/ghozt_musik/kay-9ice-house-party-mixed-by-saffz-beat/|title=Kay 9ice - houseparty|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|2018
|Mixed By SaffzBeat
|}

== Awards and nominations ==
{{awards table}}
|-
|rowspan="1"|2018
|rowspan="1"|Ashaiman Music Awards
|Afrobeat Artist Of The Year&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=https://loudingh.com/2018-ashaiman-music-awards-full-list-of-nominees/ | title=2018 Ashaiman Music Awards; Full List Of Nominees | date=August 8, 2018 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|{{Won}}
|-
|rowspan="1"|2018
|rowspan="1"|Ashaiman Music Awards
|Songwritter Of The Year&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=https://loudingh.com/2018-ashaiman-music-awards-full-list-of-nominees/ | title=2018 Ashaiman Music Awards; Full List Of Nominees | date=August 8, 2018 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|{{Nominated}}
|-
|rowspan="1"|2018
|rowspan="1"|Ashaiman Music Awards
|Most Popular Song Of The Year&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=https://www.modernghana.com/entertainment/52027/kay-9ice-bags-7-nominations-at-the-maiden-amas.html | title=Kay 9ice Bags 7 Nominations At The Maiden A.M.A’s | date=August 8, 2018 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|{{Nominated}}
|-

|rowspan="1"|2018
|rowspan="1"|Ghana Music Awards South Africa
|Promising Artiste at the Year&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=https://www.modernghana.com/entertainment/52151/see-full-list-of-nominees-for-2018-ghana-music-awards-south.html | title= GSee Full List Of Nominees For 2018 Ghana Music Awards South Africa  | date=August 22, 2018 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|{{Nominated}}

{{end}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:9ice, Kay}}
[[Category:1990 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:People from Accra]]</text>
      <sha1>brwe22x9kyuasacwc4a8y2tr3xrsxve</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Near-death experience</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>19008500</id>
    <revision>
      <id>871559961</id>
      <parentid>865429345</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-12-01T22:49:49Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jkshrews</username>
        <id>1465750</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>added a line about negative experience to the introduction.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="52430">{{other uses}}
{{redirect|NDE}}
{{redirect|Near death|the comic book|Near Death (comics)}}
{{Merge from|Near-death studies|date=August 2018}}

A '''near-death experience''' ('''NDE''') is a [[personal experience]] associated with death or impending [[death]]. When positive, such experiences may encompass a variety of sensations including detachment from the body, feelings of levitation, total serenity, security, warmth, the experience of absolute dissolution, and the presence of a light. When negative, such experiences may include sensations of torment and torture. &lt;ref name=Sleutjes2014rev&gt;{{cite journal | pmid = 25357254 | doi=10.1097/NMD.0000000000000205 | volume=202 | issue=11 | title=Almost 40 years investigating near-death experiences: an overview of mainstream scientific journals | year=2014 | journal=J. Nerv. Ment. Dis. | pages=833–6 | last1 = Sleutjes | first1 = A | last2 = Moreira-Almeida | first2 = A | last3 = Greyson | first3 = B}}&lt;/ref&gt; NDEs are a recognized part of some [[transcendence (philosophy)|transcendental]] and [[Transcendence (religion)|religious]] beliefs in an [[afterlife]].&lt;ref name=Sleutjes2014rev/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | pmc=2790400 | pmid=20011577 | volume=6 | issue=10 | title=Near-death experiences and psychotherapy | year=2009 | journal=Psychiatry (Edgmont) | pages=35–42 | last1 = Griffith | first1 = LJ}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Mauro1992pop/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Vanhaudenhuyse|first1=A.|last2=Thonnard|first2=M.|last3=Laureys|first3=S.|editor1-last=Vincent|editor1-first=Jean-Louis|title=Yearbook of Intensive Care and Emergency Medicine|date=2009|publisher=Springer Berlin Heidelberg|location=Berlin, Heidelberg|isbn=978-3-540-92276-6|url=http://www.coma.ulg.ac.be/papers/vs/vanhaudenhuyse_NDE2010.pdf|chapter=Towards a Neuro-scientific Explanation of Near-death Experiences?}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Different models have been described to explain NDEs.&lt;ref name="French2005rev" /&gt; [[Neuroscience]] research suggests that an NDE is a [[wikt:subjective#Adjective|subjective]] phenomenon resulting from "disturbed bodily multisensory integration" that occurs during life-threatening events.&lt;ref name=blanke2009&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Neurology of Consciousness|last=Blanke|first=Olaf|publisher=London: Academic Publishers, 2009|year=2009|isbn=978-0-12-374168-4|location=London|pages=303–324}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Etymology==
[[File:Hieronymus Bosch 013.jpg|right|thumb|''[[Ascent of the Blessed]]'' by [[Hieronymus Bosch]] is associated by some NDE researchers with aspects of the NDE.&lt;ref name="Lommel2010"&gt;{{cite book |author=Pim van Lommel |title=Consciousness Beyond Life: The science of the near-death experience |publisher=HarperOne |year=2010 |isbn=978-0-06-177725-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Evelyn Elsaesser Valarino |title=On the Other Side of Life: Exploring the phenomenon of the near-death experience |year=1997 |publisher=Perseus Publishing |isbn=978-0-7382-0625-7 |page=203}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]

The equivalent [[french language|French]] term ''expérience de mort imminente'' (experience of imminent death) was proposed by the French [[psychologist]] and [[epistemology|epistemologist]] [[Victor Egger]] as a result of discussions in the 1890s among [[philosopher]]s and psychologists concerning [[Climbing|climbers']] stories of the panoramic life review during falls.&lt;ref&gt;Egger, Victor (1896). "Le moi des mourants", ''Revue Philosophique'', XLI : 26–38.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Neurological Disorders in Famous Artists, Part 3 |author=J. Bogousslavsky, M. G. Hennerici, H Bazner, C. Bassetti (Eds.) |publisher=Karger Publishers |year=2010 |page=189 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=NTmyjVWIrTYC&amp;pg=PA189&amp;lpg=PA189#v=onepage|isbn=9783805593304 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1892 a series of subjective observations by workers falling from scaffolds, war soldiers who suffered injuries, climbers who had fallen from heights or other individuals who had come close to death (near drownings, accidents) was reported by [[Albert Heim]]. This was also the first time the phenomenon was described as clinical syndrome.&lt;ref name=Greyson2014/&gt; In 1968 [[Celia Green]] published an analysis of 400 first-hand accounts of [[out-of-body experiences]].&lt;ref&gt;Green, C., ''Out-of-the-body Experiences'', London: Hamish Hamilton, 1968.&lt;/ref&gt; This represented the first attempt to provide a [[Taxonomy (general)|taxonomy]] of such experiences, viewed simply as anomalous perceptual experiences, or [[hallucinations]]. In 1969, Swiss-American [[psychiatrist]] and pioneer in near-death studies [[Elisabeth Kübler-Ross|Elisabeth Kubler-Ross]] published her groundbreaking book ''[[On Death and Dying|On Death and Dying: What the dying have to teach doctors, nurses, clergy, and their own families.]]'' These experiences were also popularized by the work of [[psychiatrist]] [[Raymond Moody]], who in 1975 coined the term "near-death experience" (NDE) as an umbrella term for the different elements (out of body experiences, the "panoramic life review," the Light, the tunnel, or the border). &lt;ref name="Greyson2014" /&gt; The term "near-death experience" had already been used by [[John C. Lilly]] in 1972.&lt;ref&gt;Schlieter, Jens (2018). What is it like to be Dead? Near-death Experiences, Christianity, and the Occult. New York: Oxford University Press, pp. 205-6.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Characteristics==

===Common elements===
[[Research]]ers have identified the common elements that define near-death experiences.&lt;ref name=Mauro1992pop&gt;Mauro, James. "Bright lights, big mystery", ''Psychology Today'', July 1992.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Bruce Greyson]] argues that the general features of the experience include impressions of being outside one's physical body, visions of deceased relatives and religious figures, and transcendence of egotic and spatiotemporal boundaries.&lt;ref&gt;Greyson, Bruce (2003) "Near-Death Experiences in a Psychiatric Outpatient Clinic Population". Psychiatric Services, December, Vol. 54 No. 12. The American Psychiatric Association&lt;/ref&gt; Many common elements have been reported, although the person's interpretation of these events often corresponds with the [[Culture|cultural]], [[philosophy|philosophical]], or [[religion|religious]] beliefs of the person experiencing it. For example, in the US, where 46% of the population believes in [[guardian angel]]s, they will often be identified as angels or deceased loved ones (or will be unidentified), while Hindus will often identify them as messengers of the god of death.&lt;ref name="handbook" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Kennard, Mary J 1998"&gt;Kennard, Mary J. "A Visit from an Angel." The American Journal of Nursing 98.3 (1998): 48–51&lt;/ref&gt;

Common traits that have been reported by NDErs are as follows:
* A sense/awareness of being dead.&lt;ref name=Mauro1992pop/&gt;
* A sense of [[peace]], [[well-being]] and painlessness. Positive [[emotion]]s. A sense of removal from the world.&lt;ref name=Mauro1992pop/&gt;
* An [[out-of-body experience]]. A perception of one's body from an outside position, sometimes observing medical professionals performing resuscitation efforts.&lt;ref name=Mauro1992pop/&gt;&lt;ref name="Morse M. 1985"&gt;{{cite journal | pmid = 4003364 | volume=139 | issue=6 | title=Near-death experiences in a pediatric population. A preliminary report | date=June 1985 | journal=Am. J. Dis. Child. | pages=595–600 | last1 = Morse | first1 = M | last2 = Conner | first2 = D | last3 = Tyler | first3 = D | doi=10.1001/archpedi.1985.02140080065034}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* A "tunnel experience" or entering a darkness. A sense of moving up, or through, a passageway or staircase.&lt;ref name=Mauro1992pop/&gt;&lt;ref name="Morse M. 1985"/&gt;
* A rapid movement toward and/or sudden immersion in a powerful light (or "Being of Light") which communicates with the person.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://iands.org/ndes/nde-stories/iands-nde-accounts/1067-three-beings-of-light.html|title=Three Beings of Light|last=Lovins|first=LaDonna|website=iands.org|language=en-gb|access-date=2018-03-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* An intense feeling of [[unconditional love]] and [[acceptance]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/acts-of-faith/wp/2016/06/29/people-who-had-near-death-experiences-consistently-report-one-thing-gods-love/|title=Opinion {{!}} Stories of God's love common among those who almost die, says doctor who studies them|last=Long|first=Dr Jeffrey|date=2016-06-29|work=Washington Post|access-date=2018-03-27|language=en-US|issn=0190-8286}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Encountering "Beings of Light", "Beings dressed in white", or similar. Also, the possibility of being reunited with deceased loved ones.&lt;ref name=Mauro1992pop/&gt;&lt;ref name="Morse M. 1985"/&gt;
* Receiving a [[life review]], commonly referred to as "seeing one's life flash before one's eyes".&lt;ref name=Mauro1992pop/&gt;
* Approaching a border or a decision by oneself or others to return to one's body, often accompanied by a reluctance to return.&lt;ref name=Mauro1992pop/&gt;&lt;ref name="Morse M. 1985"/&gt;
* Suddenly finding oneself back inside one's body.&lt;ref name= "Moody1975"&gt;{{cite book|last=Moody|first=Raymond|title=Life After Life|year=1975|isbn=978-0-89176-037-5|publisher=Mockingbird Books}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Connection to the cultural beliefs held by the individual, which seem to dictate some of the phenomena experienced in the NDE and particularly the later interpretation thereof.&lt;ref name="handbook"&gt;{{cite book|editor1-last=Holden|editor1-first=Janice Miner|editor2-last=Greyson|editor2-first=Bruce|editor3-last=James|editor3-first=Debbie|title=The handbook of near-death experiences thirty years of investigation|date=2009|publisher=Praeger Publishers|location=Westport, Conn.|isbn=978-0-313-35865-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{page needed|date=August 2017}}

===Stages===
[[Kenneth Ring]] (1980) subdivided the NDE on a five-stage [[continuum (theory)|continuum]]. The subdivisions were:&lt;ref&gt;Ring, K. (1980). Life at death: A scientific investigation of the near-death experience. New York: Coward, McCann, &amp; Geoghegan., p. 40&lt;/ref&gt;
# Peace
# Body separation
# Entering darkness
# Seeing the light
# Entering the light

Charlotte Martial, a neuropsychologist from the [[University of Liège|University of Liège and University Hospital of Liège]] who led a team that investigated 154 NDE cases, concluded that there is not a fixed sequence of events.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.newsweek.com/near-death-experiences-what-happens-when-you-die-643032|title=What happens when you die? Scientists attempt to find out how similar near-death experiences really are|date=2017-07-27|work=Newsweek|access-date=2018-09-26|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Clinical circumstances===
Kenneth Ring argues that attempted suicides do not lead more often to unpleasant NDEs than unintended near-death situations.&lt;ref&gt;Ring, Kenneth. ''Heading toward Omega. In search of the Meaning of Near-Death Experience'', 1984, p. 45. "Subsequent research on suicide-related NDEs by Stephen Franklin and myself [Ring] and by Bruce Greyson has also confirmed my earlier tentative findings the NDEs following suicide attempts, however induced, conform to the classic prototype."&lt;/ref&gt;

===After-effects===
NDEs are associated with changes in personality and outlook on life.&lt;ref name=Mauro1992pop/&gt; Ring has identified a consistent set of value and belief changes associated with people who have had a near-death experience. Among these changes, he found a greater appreciation for life, higher self-esteem, greater compassion for others, less concern for acquiring material wealth, a heightened sense of purpose and self-understanding, desire to learn, elevated spirituality, greater ecological sensitivity and planetary concern, and a feeling of being more intuitive.&lt;ref name=Mauro1992pop/&gt; However, not all after-effects are beneficial&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | pmid = 7754094 | volume=18 | issue=3 | title=The meaning of survival: the early aftermath of a near-death experience | date=June 1995 | journal=Res Nurs Health | pages=239–47 | last1 = Orne | first1 = RM | doi=10.1002/nur.4770180307}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Greyson describes circumstances where changes in attitudes and behavior can lead to psychosocial and psychospiritual problems.&lt;ref name=Greyson1997&gt;{{cite journal | pmid = 9171810 | volume=185 | issue=5 | title=The near-death experience as a focus of clinical attention | date=May 1997 | journal=J. Nerv. Ment. Dis. | pages=327–34 | last1 = Greyson | first1 = B | doi=10.1097/00005053-199705000-00007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Historical reports, incidence and prevalence ==

NDEs have been recorded since ancient times.&lt;ref name="HandBook-Field"&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books/about/The_Handbook_of_Near_Death_Experiences.html?id=9MdUPgAACAAJ|title=The Handbook of Near-Death Experiences: Thirty Years of Investigation|date=Jun 22, 2009|publisher=Greenwood Publishing Group|isbn=978-0-313-35864-7|editor-last=Holden|editor-first=Janice Miner|pages=1–16|chapter=The Field of Near-Death Studies: Past, Present and Future|editor2-last=Greyson|editor2-first=Bruce|editor3-last=James|editor3-first=Debbie|chapterurl=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The oldest known medical report of near-death experiences was written by Pierre-Jean du Monchaux, an 18th century French military doctor who described such a case in his book "Anecdotes de Médecine."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.livescience.com/46993-oldest-medical-report-of-near-death-experience.html|title=Oldest Medical Report of Near-Death Experience Discovered|date=July 24, 2014|first=Bahar|last=Gholipour|work=Live Science|accessdate=October 16, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the 19th century a few studies moved beyond individual cases - one privately done by the Mormons and one in Switzerland. Up to 2005, 95% of world cultures are known to have made some mention of NDEs.&lt;ref name="HandBook-Field" /&gt;

A number of more contemporary sources report incidences of near death experiences of:
* 17% amongst critically ill patients, in nine prospective studies from 4 different countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Pleasurable Western adult near-death experiences: features, circumstances, and incidence. (In: Holden JM, Greyson B, James D, editors. The Handbook of Near-Death Experiences: Thirty Years of Investigation.) |last=Zingrone |first=NL |date=2009 |publisher=SantaBarbara, CA: Praeger/ABC-CLIO|year=|isbn=978-0313358647|edition=2009|location=|pages=17–40|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 10-20% of people who have come close to death.&lt;ref name=Greyson2014&gt;{{cite book|last1=Greyson|first1=Bruce|editor1-last=Cardeña|editor1-first=Etzel|editor2-last=Lynn|editor2-first=Steven Jay|editor3-last=Krippner|editor3-first=Stanley|title=Varieties of anomalous experience : examining the scientific evidence|date=2014|publisher=American Psychological Association|location=Washington, D.C.|isbn=978-1-4338-1529-4|edition=Second|chapter=Chapter 12: Near-Death Experiences|pages=333–367}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Research==
===Near-death studies===
{{Main|Near-death studies}}
[[Bruce Greyson]] ([[psychiatrist]]), [[Kenneth Ring]] ([[psychologist]]), and [[Michael Sabom]] ([[cardiologist]]), helped to launch the field of [[near-death studies]] and introduced the study of near-death experiences to the academic setting. From 1975 to 2005, some 2,500 self-reported individuals in the US had been reviewed in retrospective studies of the phenomena&lt;ref name="HandBook-Field" /&gt; with an additional 600 outside the US in the West,&lt;ref name="HandBook-Field" /&gt; and 70 in Asia.&lt;ref name="HandBook-Field" /&gt; Additionally, prospective studies had identified 270 individuals. Prospective studies review groups of individuals (e.g., selected emergency room patients) and then find who had an NDE during the study's time; such studies cost more to perform.&lt;ref name="HandBook-Field" /&gt; In all, close to 3,500 individual cases between 1975 and 2005 had been reviewed in one or another study. All these studies were carried out by some 55 researchers or teams of researchers.&lt;ref name="HandBook-Field" /&gt;

[[Melvin L. Morse|Melvin Morse]], head of the Institute for the Scientific Study of Consciousness, and colleagues&lt;ref name="Morse M. 1985" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Morse M, Castillo P, Venecia D, Milstein J, Tyler DC. (1986) "Childhood near-death experiences". ''American Journal of Diseases of Children'', Nov;140(11):1110–4.&lt;/ref&gt; have investigated near-death experiences in a pediatric population.

=== Clinical research in cardiac arrest patients ===
==== Parnia 2001 study ====
In 2001, [[Sam Parnia]] and colleagues published the results of a year-long study of cardiac arrest survivors that was conducted at Southampton General Hospital. 63 survivors were interviewed. They had been resuscitated after being [[clinical death|clinically dead]] with no pulse, no respiration, and fixed dilated pupils. Parnia and colleagues investigated [[out-of-body experience]] claims by placing figures on suspended boards facing the ceiling, not visible from the floor.  Four had experiences that, according to the study criteria, were NDEs but none of them experienced the [[out-of-body experience]]. Thus, they were not able to identify the figures.&lt;ref name=Parnia2001primary&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Parnia|first=S.|last2=Waller|first2=D. G.|last3=Yeates|first3=R.|last4=Fenwick|first4=P.|date=2001-02-01|title=A qualitative and quantitative study of the incidence, features and aetiology of near death experiences in cardiac arrest survivors |journal=Resuscitation |volume=48 
|issue=2 |pages=149–156  |pmid=11426476 |doi=10.1016/s0300-9572(00)00328-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=French2005rev&gt;{{Cite book |last=French |first=Christopher C. |date=2005-01-01|title=Near-death experiences in cardiac arrest survivors|journal=Progress in Brain Research|volume=150|pages=351–367 
|doi=10.1016/S0079-6123(05)50025-6 |pmid=16186035|isbn=9780444518514 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Parnia2014rev&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Parnia|first=Sam|date=2014-11-01 |title=Death and consciousness--an overview of the mental and cognitive experience of death|journal=Annals of the New York Academy of Sciences |volume=1330 |pages=75–93 |doi=10.1111/nyas.12582|pmid=25418460}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Psychologist [[Chris French]] wrote regarding the study "unfortunately, and somewhat atypically, none of the survivors in this sample experienced an OBE".&lt;ref name=French2005rev/&gt;

==== Van Lommel's study ====
[[File:Pim van Lommel-1.jpg|250x250px|thumb|[[Pim van Lommel]]]]
In 2001 [[Pim van Lommel]], a cardiologist from the Netherlands, and his team conducted a study on NDEs including 344 cardiac arrest patients who had been successfully resuscitated in 10 Dutch hospitals. Patients not reporting NDEs were used as controls for patients who did, and psychological (e.g. fear before cardiac arrest), demographic (e.g. age, sex), medical (e.g. more than one [[cardiopulmonary resuscitation]] (CPR)) and pharmacological data were compared between the 2 groups. The work also included a longitudinal study where the 2 groups (those who had had an NDE and those who had not had one) were compared at 2 and 8 years, for life changes. One patient had a conventional out of body experience. He reported being able to watch and recall events during the time of his cardiac arrest. His claims were confirmed by hospital personnel. "This did not appear consistent with hallucinatory or illusory experiences, as the recollections were compatible with real and verifiable rather than imagined events".&lt;ref name=Parnia2014rev/&gt;&lt;ref name=Lommel2001primary&gt;{{cite journal|last1=van Lommel|first1=P|last2=van Wees| first2=R|last3=Meyers|first3=V|last4=Elfferich|first4=I|title=Near-death experience in survivors of cardiac arrest: a prospective study in the Netherlands| journal=Lancet |date=15 December 2001 |volume=358 |issue=9298 |pages=2039–45|doi=10.1016/S0140-6736(01)07100-8|pmid=11755611}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Awareness during Resuscitation (AWARE) study ====
While at University of Southampton, Parnia was the principal investigator of the AWARE Study, which was launched in 2008.&lt;sup&gt;[[Sam Parnia#cite note-TIME magazine 2008-13|[13]]]&lt;/sup&gt; This study which concluded in 2012 included 33 investigators across 15 medical centers in the UK, Austria and the US and tested consciousness, memories and awareness during cardiac arrest. The accuracy of claims of visual and auditory awareness was examined using specific tests.&lt;ref name=Parnia2015primary&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Parnia|first=Sam|last2=Spearpoint|first2=Ken|last3=de Vos|first3=Gabriele |last4=Fenwick |first4=Peter |last5=Goldberg |first5=Diana|last6=Yang|first6=Jie|last7=Zhu|first7=Jiawen|last8=Baker|first8=Katie|last9=Killingback|first9=Hayley|date=2014-12-01 |title=AWARE-AWAreness during REsuscitation-a prospective study |journal=Resuscitation|volume=85|issue=12|pages=1799–1805 |doi=10.1016/j.resuscitation.2014.09.004 |pmid=25301715}}&lt;/ref&gt; One such test consisted in installing shelves, bearing a variety of images and facing the ceiling, hence not visible by hospital staff, in rooms where cardiac-arrest patients were more likely to occur. The results of the study were published in October 2014; both the launch and the study results were widely discussed in the media.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2015/04/the-science-of-near-death-experiences/386231/ |title=The science of near-death experiences: Empirically investigating brushes with the afterlife|last=Lichfield|first=Gideon|date=April 2015|website=The Atlantic|publisher=The Atlantic|access-date=10 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.psychologytoday.com/articles/201409/seeing-the-light|title=Seeing the light |last=Weintraub |first=Pamela |date=September 2014 |website=Psychology Today|publisher=Psychology Today|access-date=10 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A review article analyzing the results reports that, out of 2060 cardiac arrest events, 101 of 140 cardiac arrest survivors could complete the questionnaires. Of these 101 patients 9% could be classified as near death experiences. 2 more patients (2% of those completing the questionnaires) described "seeing and hearing actual events related to the period of cardiac arrest". These two patients' cardiac arrests did not occur in areas equipped with ceiling shelves hence no images could be used to objectively test for visual awareness claims. One of the two patients was too sick and the accuracy of her recount could not be verified. For the second patient instead, it was possible to verify the accuracy of the experience and to show that awareness occurred paradoxically some minutes after the heart stopped, at a time when "the brain ordinarily stops functioning and cortical activity becomes isoelectric." The experience was not compatible with an illusion, imaginary event or hallucination since visual (other than of ceiling shelves' images) and auditory awareness could be corroborated.&lt;ref name=Parnia2014rev/&gt;

==== AWARE II ====
{{as of|2016|May}}, a posting at the UK Clinical Trials Gateway website described plans for [[Out-of-body experience#AWARE Study II|AWARE II]], a two-year multicenter observational study of 900-1500 patients experiencing cardiac arrest, which said that subject recruitment had started on 1 August 2014 and that the scheduled end date was 31 May 2017.&lt;ref&gt;UK Clinical Trials Gateway. [https://web.archive.org/web/20160509201054/https://www.ukctg.nihr.ac.uk/trials/trial-details/trial-details?trialId=31651 Primary Trial ID Number 17129], entitled "AWARE II (AWAreness during REsuscitation) A Multi-Centre Observational Study of the Relationship between the Quality of Brain Resuscitation and Consciousness, Neurological, Functional and Cognitive Outcomes following Cardiac Arrest" Last updated May 3, 2016. Page archived May 9, 2016&lt;/ref&gt; The study was extended, and it is currently expected to end in 2020.&lt;ref&gt;https://psi-encyclopedia.spr.ac.uk/articles/aware-nde-study&lt;/ref&gt;

== Explanatory models ==
In a review article, psychologist [[Chris French]]&lt;ref name="French2005rev"/&gt; has grouped approaches to explain NDEs in three broad groups which "are not distinct and independent, but instead show considerable overlap": spiritual theories (also called transcendental), psychological theories, and physiological theories that provide a physical explanation for NDEs.

=== Spiritual or transcendental theories ===
French summarizes this model by saying : "the most popular interpretation is that the NDE is exactly what it appears to be to the person having the experience".&lt;ref name="French2005rev"/&gt; The NDE would then represent evidence of the supposedly immaterial existence of a soul or mind, which would leave the body upon death. An NDE would then provide information about an immaterial world where the soul would journey upon ending its physical existence on earth.&lt;ref name="French2005rev"/&gt;

According to Greyson&lt;ref name=Greyson2014/&gt; some NDE phenomena cannot be easily explained with our current knowledge of human physiology and psychology. For instance, at a time when they were unconscious patients could accurately describe events as well as report being able to view their bodies "from an out-of-body spatial perspective". In two different studies of patients who had survived a cardiac arrest, those who had reported leaving their bodies could describe accurately their resuscitation procedures or unexpected events, whereas others "described incorrect equipment and procedures".&lt;ref name=Greyson2014/&gt; Sam Parnia also refers to two cardiac arrest studies and one deep hypothermic circulatory arrest study where patients reported visual and/or auditory awareness occurring when their brain function had ceased. These reports "were corroborated with actual and real events".&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Parnia|first=Sam|date=February 2017|title=Understanding the cognitive experience of death and the near-death experience|url=https://academic.oup.com/qjmed/article-abstract/110/2/67/2681812?redirectedFrom=fulltext|journal=QJM: An International Journal of Medicine|volume=110(2)|pages=67–69|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Parnia2014rev" /&gt;

Five prospective studies have been carried out, to test the accuracy of out of body perceptions by placing "unusual targets in locations likely to be seen by persons having NDEs, such as in an upper corner of a room in the emergency department, the coronary care unit, or the intensive care unit of a hospital." Twelve patients reported leaving their bodies, but unfortunately none could describe the hidden visual targets. Although this is a small sample, the failure of purported out-of-body experiencers to describe the hidden targets raises questions about the accuracy of the anecdotal reports described above.&lt;ref name=Greyson2014/&gt;

Psychologist [[James Alcock]] has described the afterlife claims of NDE researchers as [[Pseudoscience|pseudoscientific]]. Alcock has written the spiritual or transcendental interpretation "is based on belief in search of data rather than observation in search of explanation."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Frazier|first1=Kendrick|title=Paranormal Borderlands of Science|date=1981|publisher=Prometheus Books|location=Buffalo, N.Y.|isbn=978-0-87975-148-7|pages=153–169}}&lt;/ref&gt; Chris French has noted that "the survivalist approach does not appear to generate clear and testable hypotheses. Because of the vagueness and imprecision of the survivalist account, it can be made to explain any possible set of findings and is therefore unfalsifiable and unscientific."&lt;ref&gt;[[Chris French|French, Chris]]. (2009). ''[https://www.novapublishers.com/catalog/product_info.php?products_id=10186 Near-Death Experiences and the Brain]''. In Craig Murray. ''Psychological Scientific Perspectives on Out-of-Body and Near-Death Experiences''. Nova Science Publishers. pp.&amp;nbsp;187–203. {{ISBN|978-1-60741-705-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Psychological explanations ===
French summarises the main psychological explanations which include: the depersonalization, the expectancy and the dissociation models.&lt;ref name="French2005rev"/&gt;

==== Depersonalization model ====
A depersonalization model was proposed in the 1970s by professor of psychiatry Russell Noyes and clinical psychologist Roy Kletti, which suggested that the NDE is a form of [[depersonalization]] experienced under emotional conditions such as life-threatening danger, potentially inescapable danger, and that the NDE can best be understood as an hallucination.&lt;ref name=French2005rev/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1 = Noyes |first1 = R |year = 1972 |title = The experience of dying |url = |journal = Psychiatry |volume = 35 |issue = 2|pages = 174–184 |doi=10.1080/00332747.1972.11023710}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1 = Noyes |first1 = R. |last2 = Kletti |first2 = R. |year = 1976 |title = Depersonalisation in the face of life-threatening danger: an interpretation |url = |journal = Omega |volume = 7 |issue = 2|pages = 103–114 |doi=10.2190/7qet-2vau-ycdt-tj9r}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1 = Noyes |first1 = R. |last2 = Kletti |first2 = R. |year = 1977 |title = Depersonalisation in the face of life-threatening danger |url = |journal = Compr. Psychiat |volume = 18 |issue = |pages = 375–384}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Noyes, R. and Slymen, D. (1978–1979) ''The subjective response to life-threatening danger''. ''Omega'' 9: 313–321.&lt;/ref&gt; According to this model, those who face their impending death become detached from the surroundings and their own bodies, no longer feel emotions, and experience time distortions.&lt;ref name=Greyson2014/&gt;

This model suffers from a number of limitations to explain NDEs for subjects who do not experience a sensation of being out of their bodies; unlike NDEs, experiences are dreamlike, unpleasant and characterized by "anxiety, panic and emptiness".&lt;ref name=Greyson2014/&gt; Also, during NDEs subjects remain very lucid of their identities, their sense of identify is not changed unlike those experiencing depersonalization.&lt;ref name=Greyson2014/&gt;

==== Expectancy model ====
Another psychological theory is called the expectancy model. It has been suggested that although these experiences could appear very real, they had actually been constructed in the mind, either consciously or subconsciously, in response to the stress of an encounter with death (or perceived encounter with death), and did not correspond to a real event. In a way, they are similar to wish-fulfillment: because someone thought they were about to die, they experienced certain things in accordance with what they expected or wanted to occur. Imagining a heavenly place was in effect a way for them to soothe themselves through the stress of knowing that they were close to death.&lt;ref name=French2005rev /&gt; Subjects use their own personal and cultural expectations to imagine a scenario that would protect them against an imminent threat to their lives.&lt;ref name="Greyson2014" /&gt;

Subjects' accounts often differed from their own "religious and personal expectations regarding death" which contradicts the hypothesis they may have imagined a scenario based on their cultural and personal background.&lt;ref name="Greyson2014" /&gt;

Although the term NDE was first coined in 1975 and the experience first described then, recent descriptions of NDEs do not differ from those reported earlier than 1975. The only exception is the more frequent description of a tunnel.  Hence, the fact that information about these experiences could be more easily obtained after 1975, did not influence people's reports of the experiences.&lt;ref name="Greyson2014" /&gt;

Another flaw of this model can be found in children's accounts of NDEs. These are similar to adults', and this despite children being less affected by religious or cultural influences about death.&lt;ref name="Greyson2014" /&gt;

==== Dissociation model ====
The dissociation model proposes that NDE is a form of withdrawal to protect an individual from a stressful event. Under extreme circumstances some people may detach from certain unwanted feelings in order to avoid experiencing their emotional impact and suffering associated with them. The person also detaches from one's immediate surroundings.&lt;ref name=French2005rev /&gt;

==== Birth model ====
The birth model suggests that near death experiences could be a form of reliving the trauma of birth. Since a baby travels from the darkness of the womb to light and is greeted by the love and warmth of the nursing and medical staff, and so, it was proposed, the dying brain could be recreating the passage through a tunnel to light, warmth and affection.&lt;ref name=French2005rev /&gt;

Reports of leaving the body through a tunnel are equally frequent among subjects who were born by cesarean section and natural birth. Also, newborns do not possess "the visual acuity, spatial stability of their visual images, mental alertness, and cortical coding capacity to register memories of the birth experience".&lt;ref name="Greyson2014" /&gt;

=== Physiological explanations (organic theories) ===
A wide range of physiological theories of the NDE have been put forward including those based upon [[cerebral hypoxia]], anoxia, and [[hypercapnia]]; endorphins and other neurotransmitters; and abnormal activity in the [[temporal lobe]]s.&lt;ref name=French2005rev /&gt;

Neurobiological factors in the experience have been investigated by researchers in the field of medical science and psychiatry.&lt;ref&gt;Mayank and Mukesh, 2004; Jansen, 1995; Thomas, 2004; Fenwick and Fenwick 2008&lt;/ref&gt; Among the researchers and commentators who tend to emphasize a naturalistic and neurological base for the experience are the [[Great Britain|British]] [[psychologist]] [[Susan Blackmore]] (1993), with her "dying brain hypothesis".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Bassham |first1=Gregory|title=Critical Thinking: A Student's Untroduction|date=2005|publisher=McGraw-Hill|location=Boston|isbn=978-0-07-287959-9 |page=485 |edition=2nd}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====  Neuroanatomical models ====
Neuroscientists Olaf Blanke and Sebastian Dieguez (2009),&lt;ref&gt;Leaving Body And Life Behind:[http://lnco.epfl.ch/files/content/sites/lnco/files/shared/publications/lnco/2009_Dieguez_NC(chap)_leaving%20body%20and%20life%20behind-out%20of%20body%20and%20near%20death%20experience.pdf lnco.epfl.ch]&lt;/ref&gt; from the ''[[Ecole Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne]]'', [[Switzerland]], propose a brain based model with two types of NDEs : 
* "type 1 NDEs are due to bilateral frontal and occipital, but predominantly right hemispheric brain damage affecting the right temporal parietal junction and characterized by out of body experiences, altered sense of time, sensations of flying, lightness vection and flying" &lt;ref name="blanke2009" /&gt;
* "type 2 NDEs are also due to bilateral frontal and occipital, but predominantly left hemispheric brain damage affecting the left temporal parietal junction and characterized by feeling of a presence, meeting and communication with spirits, seeing of glowing bodies, as well as voices, sounds, and music without vection" &lt;ref name="blanke2009" /&gt;
They suggest that damage to the bilateral [[Occipital lobe|occipital cortex]] may lead to visual features of NDEs such as seeing a tunnel or lights, and "damage to unilateral or bilateral temporal lobe structures such as the [[hippocampus]] and amygdala" may lead to emotional experiences, memory flashbacks or a life review. They concluded that future neuroscientific studies are likely to reveal the neuroanatomical basis of the NDE which will lead to the demystification of the subject without needing paranormal explanations.&lt;ref name="blanke2009" /&gt;

[[File:Temporal lobe animation.gif|thumb|160px|left|Animation of the human left temporal lobe]]

French has written that the "temporal lobe is almost certain to be involved in NDEs, given that both damage to and direct cortical stimulation of this area are known to produce a number of experiences corresponding to those of the NDE, including OBEs, hallucinations, and memory flashbacks".&lt;ref name=French2005rev /&gt;

Vanhaudenhuyse ''et al''. 2009 reported that recent studies employing [[deep brain stimulation]] and [[neuroimaging]] have demonstrated that out-of-body experiences result from a deficient [[multisensory integration]] at the [[temporoparietal junction]] and that ongoing studies aim to further identify the functional neuroanatomy of near-death experiences by means of standardized EEG recordings.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Intensive Care Medicine |date=2009|publisher=Springer New York | isbn=978-0-387-92277-5 |location=[S.l.] |pages=961–968 |last1=Vincent |first1=Jean-Louis|doi=10.1007/978-3-540-92276-6_85|chapter=Towards a Neuro-scientific Explanation of Near-death Experiences?|citeseerx=10.1.1.368.4580}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 
According to Greyson&lt;ref name="Greyson2014" /&gt; multiple neuroanatomical models have been proposed where NDEs have been hypothesized to originate from different anatomical areas of the brain, namely: the limbic system, the hippocampus, the left temporal lobe, Reissen's fiber in the central canal of the spinal cord, the prefrontal cortex, the right temporal lobe.

Blanke et al.&lt;ref name="blanke2009" /&gt; admit that their model remains speculative to the lack of data. Likewise Greyson&lt;ref name="Greyson2014" /&gt; writes that although some or any of the neuroanatomical models proposed may serve to explain NDEs and pathways through which they are expressed, they remain speculative at this stage since they have not been tested in empirical studies.&lt;ref name="Greyson2014" /&gt;

==== Neurochemical models ====
Some theories hypothesize that drugs used during resuscitation induced NDEs, for example, [[ketamine]] or as resulting from endogeneous chemicals that transmit signals between brain cells, [[neurotransmitter]]s:&lt;ref name=French2005rev/&gt;
* In the early eighties, Daniel Carr wrote that NDE has characteristics are suggestive of a [[limbic lobe]] syndrome and that the NDE can be explained by the release of [[endorphins]] and [[enkephalin]]s in the brain.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Carr | first1 = Daniel | year = 1981 | title = Endorphins at the Approach of Death | url = |journal = Lancet | volume = 317 | issue = 8216| page = 390 | doi=10.1016/s0140-6736(81)91714-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Carr |first1 = Daniel | year = 1982 | title = Pathophysiology of Stress-Induced Limbic Lobe Dysfunction: A Hypothesis Relevant to Near-Death Experiences | url = | journal = Anabiosis: The Journal of Near-Death Studies | volume = 2 | issue = | pages = 75–89 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Endorphins are endogenous molecules "released in times of stress and lead to a reduction in pain perception and a pleasant, even blissful, emotional state." &lt;ref name="French2005rev" /&gt; 
* Judson and Wiltshaw (1983) noted how the administration of endorphin-blocking agents such as [[naloxone]] had been occasionally reported to produce "hellish" NDEs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last2=Wiltshaw|first2=E.|year=1983|title=A near-death experience|url=|journal=Lancet|issue=8349|doi=10.1016/s0140-6736(83)90582-2 |pages=561–562|last1=Judson|first1=I. R|volume=322}}&lt;/ref&gt; This would be coherent with endorphins' role in causing a "positive emotional tone of most NDEs".&lt;ref name="French2005rev" /&gt; 
* Morse ''et al''. 1989 proposed a model arguing that [[serotonin]] played a more important role than endorphins in generating NDEs &lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Morse | first1 = M. L | last2 = Venecia | first2 = D | last3 = Milstein | first3 = J. | year = 1989 | title = Near-death experiences: A neurophysiological explanatory model | url = | journal = Journal of Near-Death Studies | volume = 8 | issue = | pages = 45–53 }}&lt;/ref&gt; "at least with respect to mystical hallucinations and OBEs".&lt;ref name="French2005rev" /&gt;

According to Parnia, neurochemical models are not backed by data. This is true for "NMDA receptor activation, serotonin, and endorphin release" models.&lt;ref name="Parnia2014rev" /&gt; Parnia writes that no data has been collected via thorough and careful experimentation to back "a possible causal relationship or even an association" between neurochemical agents and NDE experiences.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

==== Multi-factorial models ====
The first formal neurobiological model for NDE, included endorphins, neurotransmitters of the [[limbic system]], the temporal lobe and other parts of the brain.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last2=Gómez-Jeria|first2=Juan S.|year=1989|title=A Neurobiological Model for Near-Death Experiences|url=http://200.89.70.78:8080/jspui/handle/2250/14775|journal=Journal of Near-Death Studies|volume=7|issue=4|pages=205–222|doi=10.1007/bf01074007|last1=Saavedra-Aguilar|first1=J.C.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Extensions and variations of their model came from other scientists such as Louis Appleby (1989).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|year=1989|title=Near·death experience: Analogous to other stress induced psychological phenomena|url=|journal=British Medical Journal|volume=298|issue=|pages=976–977|last1=Appleby|first1=L}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other authors suggest that all components of near-death experiences can be explained in their entirety via psychological or neurophysiological mechanisms, although the authors admit that these hypotheses have to be tested by science.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Mobbs|first=Dean|last2=Watt|first2=Caroline|date=October 2011|title=There is nothing paranormal about near-death experiences: how neuroscience can explain seeing bright lights, meeting the dead, or being convinced you are one of them|url=|journal=Trends in Cognitive Sciences|volume=15|issue=10|pages=447–449|doi=10.1016/j.tics.2011.07.010|pmid=21852181}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====  Low oxygen levels (and G-LOC) model  ====
Low oxygen levels in the blood (hypoxia or anoxia) have been hypothesized to induce hallucinations and hence possibly explain NDEs.&lt;ref name="handbook" /&gt;&lt;ref name=French2005rev/&gt; This is because low oxygen levels characterize life-threatening situations and also by the apparent similarities between NDEs and G-force induced loss of consciousness ([[G-LOC]]) episodes.

These episodes are observed with fighter pilots experiencing very rapid and intense acceleration that result in lack of sufficient blood supply to the brain. Whinnery&lt;ref name="Whinnery"&gt;Whinnery, J. E. (1997). ''Psychophysiologic correlates of unconsciousness and near-death experiences''. J. Near Death Stud 15: 231–258.&lt;/ref&gt; studied almost 1000 cases and noted how the experiences often involved "tunnel vision and bright lights, floating sensations, automatic movement, autoscopy, OBEs, not wanting to be disturbed, paralysis, vivid dreamlets of beautiful places, pleasurable sensations, psychological alterations of euphoria and dissociation, inclusion of friends and family, inclusion of prior memories and thoughts, the experience being very memorable (when it can be remembered), confabulation, and a strong urge to understand the experience."&lt;ref name="French2005rev" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Whinnery" /&gt;

However, hypoxia-induced acceleration's primary characteristics are "rythmic jerking of the limbs, compromised memory of events just prior to the onset of unconsciousness, tingling of extremities ..." that are not observed during NDEs.&lt;ref name="handbook" /&gt; Also G-LOC episodes do not feature life reviews, mystical experiences and "long-lasting transformational aftereffects", although this may be due to the fact that subjects have no expectation of dying.&lt;ref name="French2005rev" /&gt;

Also, hypoxic hallucinations are characterized by "distress and agitation" and this is very different from near death experiences which subjects report as being pleasant.&lt;ref name="Greyson2014" /&gt;

==== Altered blood gas levels models ====
Some investigators have studied whether [[wikt:hypercarbia|hypercarbia]] or higher than normal carbon dioxide levels, could explain the occurrence of NDEs. However, studies are difficult to interpret since NDEs have been observed both with increased levels as well as decreased levels of carbon dioxide, and finally some other studies have observed NDEs when levels had not changed, and there is little data.&lt;ref name="handbook" /&gt;

==== Other models ====
French said that at least some reports of NDEs might be based upon [[False memory syndrome|false memories]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = French | first1 = Chris | authorlink = Chris French | year = 2001 | title = Dying to Know the Truth: Visions of a Dying Brain, or False Memories? | url = | journal = Lancet | volume = 358 | issue = 9298| pages = 2010–2011 | doi=10.1016/s0140-6736(01)07133-1| pmid = 11755600 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Engmann (2008) near-death experiences of people who are [[clinical death|clinically dead]] are psychopathological symptoms caused by a severe malfunction of the brain resulting from the cessation of cerebral blood circulation.&lt;ref&gt;Engmann, Birk. (2008). ''Near-death Experiences: A review on the thesis of pathoclisis, neurotransmitter abnormalities, and psychological aspects''. MMW-Fortschr.Med.Nr.51-52/2008(150.Jg.) pp.42–43. {{PMID|19156957}}&lt;/ref&gt; An important question is whether it is possible to "translate" the bloomy experiences of the reanimated survivors into psychopathologically basic phenomena, e.g., acoasms (nonverbal auditory hallucinations), central narrowing of the visual field, [[autoscopy|autoscopia]], [[visual hallucinations]], activation of limbic and memory structures according to Moody's stages. The symptoms suppose a primary affliction of the [[occipital lobe|occipital]] and [[temporal lobe|temporal]] cortices under clinical death. This basis could be congruent with the thesis of [[pathoclisis]]—the inclination of special parts of the brain to be the first to be damaged in case of disease, lack of oxygen, or malnutrition—established eighty years ago by [[Cécile Vogt-Mugnier|Cécile]] and [[Oskar Vogt]].&lt;ref&gt;Vogt C, Vogt O. (1922). ''Erkrankungen der Großhirnrinde im Lichte der Topistik, Pathoklise und Pathoarchitektonik''. Journal für Psychologie und Neurologie; Bd. 28. Joh.- Ambr.- Barth- Verlag. Leipzig. (German).&lt;/ref&gt;

Professor of neurology [[Terence Hines]] (2003) claimed that near-death experiences are hallucinations caused by [[Cerebral hypoxia|cerebral anoxia]], drugs, or brain damage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Hines|first1=Terence|title=Pseudoscience and the Paranormal|date=2002|publisher=Prometheus Books|location=Amherst, N.Y.|isbn=978-1-57392-979-0|pages=101–104|edition=2nd}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Cross-cultural aspects==
Gregory Shushan published an analysis of the afterlife beliefs of five ancient civilisations (Old and Middle Kingdom Egypt, Sumerian and Old Babylonian Mesopotamia, Vedic India, pre-Buddhist China, and pre-Columbian Mesoamerica) and compared them with historical and contemporary reports of near-death experiences, and [[shamanism|shaman]]ic afterlife "journeys". Shushan found similarities across time, place, and culture that he found could not be explained by coincidence; he also found elements that were specific to cultures; Shushan concludes that some form of mutual influence between experiences of an afterlife and culture probably influence one another and that this inheritance in turn influences individual NDEs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Shushan|first1=Gregory|title=Conceptions of the Afterlife in Early Civilizations: Universalism, Constructivism, and Near-Death Experience|date=2009|publisher=Continuum|location=London|isbn=978-0-8264-4073-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; In contrast, it has been argued that near-death experiences and many of their elements (vision of God, judgment, the tunnel, or the life review) are closely related to religious and spiritual traditions of the West. It was mainly Christian visionaries, Spiritualists, Occultists, and Theosophists of the 19th and 20th century that reported them (Schlieter 2018).

According to Parnia, near death experiences' interpretations are influenced by religious, social, cultural backgrounds. However, the core elements appear to transcend borders and can be considered universal. In fact, some of these core elements have even been reported by children &lt;3 years old (this occurred over many months, whilst playing and communicated using children's language). In other words, at an age where they should not have been influenced by culture or tradition.&lt;ref name="Parnia2014rev" /&gt;

Also, according to Greyson,&lt;ref name="Greyson2014" /&gt; the central features of NDEs are universal and have not been influenced by time. These have been observed throughout history and in different cultures. This notwithstanding, cultural influences have probably played a role in some NDEs' reported descriptions.

==See also==

* [[Beyond and Back]]
* [[Deathbed phenomena]]
* [[Terminal lucidity]]
* [[Form constant]]
* [[Lazarus Phenomenon|Lazarus phenomenon]]
* [[Near-death studies]]
* [[After-death communication]]
* [[Neurotheology]]
* [[Out-of-body experience]]
* [[Psychedelic experience]]
* [[Resurrection]]
* [[Cognitive science of religion]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{commons category|Near-death experiences}}
{{commons category|Near-death experiences}}
*[http://www.iands.org/ "International Association for Near-Death Studies (IANDS)"]

==Further reading==
*[[James Alcock]]. (1979). ''Psychology and Near-Death Experiences''. Skeptical Inquirer 3: 25–41.
*Lee Worth Bailey; Jenny Yates. (1996). ''The Near-Death Experience: A Reader''. Routledge. {{ISBN|0-415-91431-0}} 
*{{cite book|last1=Blackmore|first1=Susan|editor1-last=Shermer|editor1-first=Ed. M.|title=The Skeptic Encyclopedia of Pseudoscience|date=2002|publisher=ABC-Clio,|location=Santa Barbara, CA.|isbn=9781576076538|pages=152–157|url=https://www.susanblackmore.co.uk/chapters/near-death-experiences/|chapter=Near-Death Experiences}}
*{{cite journal|last1=Choi|first1=Charles Q.|title=Peace of Mind: Near-Death Experiences Now Found to Have Scientific Explanations|journal=Scientific American|date=September 12, 2011|url=https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/peace-of-mind-near-death/|language=en}}
*{{cite web|last1=Carroll|first1=Robert T.|title=Near-death experience (NDE)|url=http://www.skepdic.com/nde.html|publisher=The Skeptic's Dictionary|accessdate=21 August 2017|date=12 September 2014}}
*{{cite book|last1=Engmann|first1=Birk|title=Near-death experiences : heavenly insight or human illusion?|date=2014|publisher=Imprint: Springer|location=|isbn=978-3-319-03727-1}}
*[[Bruce Greyson]], Charles Flynn. (1984). ''The Near-Death Experience: Problems, Prospects, Perspectives''. Springfield. {{ISBN|0-398-05008-2}}
*{{cite book|title=Making sense of near-death experiences : a handbook for clinicians|first1=|date=2012|publisher=Jessica Kingsley Publishers|isbn=978-1-84905-149-1|editor1-last=Perera|editor1-first=Mahendra|location=London|editor2-last=Jagadheesan|editor2-first=Karuppiah|editor3-last=Peake|editor3-first=Anthony}}
*{{cite journal | last1 = Roberts | first1 = Glenn | last2 = Owen | first2 = John | year = 1988 | title = The Near-Death Experience | url = | journal = British Journal of Psychiatry | volume = 153 | issue = 5| pages = 607–617 | doi=10.1192/bjp.153.5.607|pmid=3076496}}
*{{cite journal|last1=Shermer|first1=Michael|title=Proof of Hallucination|journal=Scientific American|date=April 1, 2013|volume=308|issue=4|pages=86|doi=10.1038/scientificamerican0413-86|pmid=23539795|url=https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/why-near-death-experience-isnt-proof-heaven/|language=en}}
* {{cite journal|last1=Woerlee|first1=G.M.|title=Darkness, Tunnels, and Light|journal=Skeptical Inquirer|date=May 2004|volume=28|issue=3|url=http://www.csicop.org/si/show/darkness_tunnels_and_light}}
*{{cite book|last1=Woerlee|first1=G.M.|title=Mortal minds : the biology of near-death experiences|date=2005|publisher=Prometheus Books|location=Amherst, NY|isbn=978-1-59102-283-1}}
*{{cite book|last1=Lommel|first1=Pim van|title=After life : a scientific approach to near-death experiences|date=2010|publisher=HarperOne|location=New York|isbn=978-0-06-177725-7|edition=1st}}
*{{cite book|last1=Schlieter|first1=Jens|title=What is it like to be dead? : Near-death experiences, Christianity, and the Occult times|date=2018|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=New York|isbn=978-0-19-088884-8|edition=Hardcover}}
*{{cite book|last1=Zaleski|first1=Carol|title=Otherworld journeys : accounts of near-death experience in medieval and modern times|date=1987|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=New York|isbn=978-0-19-503915-3|edition=Paperback}}

{{Parapsychology}}
{{Death}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Near Death Experience}}
[[Category:Near-death experiences| ]]
[[Category:Death]]
[[Category:New Age]]
[[Category:Parapsychology]]
[[Category:Afterlife]]
[[Category:Neuroscience]]
[[Category:Psychiatric research]]
[[Category:Scientific controversies]]</text>
      <sha1>8nh8jsbien5gj062g2rodd9yvza6slk</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Philosophy of suicide</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3064846</id>
    <revision>
      <id>864195518</id>
      <parentid>864182917</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-10-15T18:24:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Koavf</username>
        <id>205121</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contribs/198.150.162.12|198.150.162.12]] ([[User talk:198.150.162.12|talk]]) to last version by Nøkkenbuer</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="21184">{{Short description|philosophical aspects of suicide and arguments for and against it}}
{{Use American English|date=September 2018}}
{{Multiple issues|
{{More citations needed|date=September 2018}}
{{Original research|date=September 2018}}
}}
{{Suicide sidebar}}
In [[ethics]] and other branches of [[philosophy]], [[suicide]] poses difficult questions, answered differently by various philosophers. The French essayist, novelist, and playwright [[Albert Camus]] (1913–1960) began his philosophical essay ''[[The Myth of Sisyphus]]'' with the famous line "There is but one truly serious philosophical problem and that is suicide" ({{lang-fr|Il n'y a qu'un problème philosophique vraiment sérieux : c'est le suicide}}).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Camus |first=Albert |translator-last=O'Brien |translator-first=Justin |date=1942 |title=The Myth of Sisyphus |url= |location= |publisher=Penguin Group |page= |isbn=978-0-141-18200-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Arguments in favor of suicide==
There are arguments in favor of allowing an individual to choose between life and suicide. Those in favor of suicide as a personal choice reject the thought that suicide is always or usually irrational, but is instead a solution to real problems; a line of last resort that can legitimately be taken when the alternative is considered worse. They believe that no being should be made to suffer unnecessarily, and suicide provides an escape from suffering.

===Idealism===
{{See also|Idealism}}
[[Herodotus]] wrote: "When life is so burdensome, death has become for man a sought-after refuge". Schopenhauer affirmed: "They tell us that suicide is the greatest act of cowardice... that suicide is wrong; when it is quite obvious that there is nothing in the world to which every man has a more unassailable title than to his own life and person."

Schopenhauer's main work, ''[[The World as Will and Representation]]'', occasionally uses the act in its examples. He denied that suicide was immoral and saw it as one's right to take one's life. In an allegory, he compared ending one's life, when subject to great suffering, to waking up from sleep when experiencing a terrible nightmare. However, most suicides were seen as an act of the [[Will (philosophy)|will]], as it takes place when one denies life's pains, and is thus different from ascetic renunciation of the will, which denies life's pleasures.

According to Schopenhauer, moral freedom—the highest ethical aim—is to be obtained only by a denial of the will to live. Far from being a denial, suicide is an emphatic assertion of this will. For it is in fleeing from the pleasures, not from the sufferings of life, that this denial consists. When a man destroys his existence as an individual, he is not by any means destroying his will to live. On the contrary, he would like to live if he could do so with satisfaction to himself; if he could assert his will against the power of circumstance; but circumstance is too strong for him.

===Liberalism=== &lt;!--should this be Libertarianism?--&gt;
[[Liberalism]] asserts that a person's life belongs only to them, and no other person has the right to force their own ideals that life must be lived. Rather, only the individual involved can make such a decision, and whatever decision they make should be respected.

Philosopher and psychiatrist [[Thomas Szasz]] goes further, arguing that suicide is the most basic right of all. If freedom is [[self-ownership]]—ownership over one's own life and body—then the right to end that life is the most basic of all. If others can force you to live, you do not own yourself and belong to them.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=Suicide as a Moral Issue|author=Thomas Szasz|url=http://www.szasz.com/iol2.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Jean Améry]], in his book ''On Suicide: a Discourse on Voluntary Death'' (originally published in German in 1976), provides a moving insight into the suicidal mind. He argues forcefully and almost romantically that suicide represents the ultimate freedom of humanity, justifying the act with phrases such as "we only arrive at ourselves in a freely chosen death" and lamenting "ridiculously everyday life and its alienation". {{Citation needed|date=March 2012}} Améry killed himself in 1978.

Philosophical thinking in the 19th and 20th century has led, in some cases, beyond thinking in terms of pro-choice, to the point that suicide is no longer a last resort, or even something that one must justify, but something that one must justify {{em|not}} doing. Many forms of [[Existentialism|existentialist]] thinking essentially begin with the premise that life is objectively meaningless, and proceed to the question of why one should not just kill oneself; they then answer this question by suggesting that the individual has the power to give personal meaning to life.

===Stoicism===
Although [[George Lyman Kittredge]] states that "the Stoics held that suicide is cowardly and wrong," the most famous [[Stoicism|stoics]]—[[Seneca the Younger]], [[Epictetus]], and [[Marcus Aurelius]]—maintain that death by one's own hand is always an option and frequently more honorable than a life of protracted misery.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=Suicide and Brutus' Philosophy in Julius Caesar|author=Mark Sacharoff|publisher=Journal of the History of Ideas|volume=33|number=1|date=Jan–Mar 1972|pages=115–122|jstor=2709060}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Stoics accepted that [[suicide]] was permissible for the wise person in circumstances that might prevent them from living a virtuous life.&lt;ref name="marietta153"&gt;Don E. Marietta, (1998), ''Introduction to ancient philosophy'', pages 153–4. Sharpe&lt;/ref&gt; [[Plutarch]] held that accepting life under tyranny would have compromised [[Cato the Younger|Cato]]'s self-consistency ({{lang-la|constantia}}) as a Stoic and impaired his freedom to make the honorable moral choices.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title=Cato's suicide in Plutarch AV Zadorojnyi|publisher=The Classical Quarterly|year=2007|url=http://journals.cambridge.org/abstract_S0009838807000195|postscript=&lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to "." for the cite to end in a ".", as necessary. --&gt;{{inconsistent citations}}}}&lt;/ref&gt; Suicide could be justified if one fell victim to severe pain or disease,&lt;ref name="marietta153"/&gt; but otherwise suicide would usually be seen as a rejection of one's social duty.&lt;ref name="irvine200"&gt;William Braxton Irvine, (2009), ''A guide to the good life: the ancient art of Stoic joy'', page 200. Oxford University Press&lt;/ref&gt;

===Confucianism===
{{see also|Suicide in China}}
[[Confucianism]] holds that failure to follow certain values is worse than death; hence, suicide can be morally permissible, and even praiseworthy, if it is done for the sake of those values. The Confucian emphasis on loyalty, self-sacrifice, and honour has tended to encourage [[altruistic suicide]].&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=Stress and Suicide in Japan|journal=Transcultural Psychiatric Research Review|author1=Iga, Mamoura|author2=KS Adam (abstract)|publisher=Transcultural Psychiatry|year=1980|url=http://tps.sagepub.com/cgi/reprint/17/4/243.pdf|volume=17|issue=4|pages=243–244|doi=10.1177/136346158001700405}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Confucius]] wrote, "For gentlemen of purpose and men of [[Ren (Confucianism)|ren]] while it is inconceivable that they should seek to stay alive at the expense of ren, it may happen that they have to accept death in order to have ren accomplished."&lt;ref&gt;Analects, trans. D.C. Lau, second edition, (Hong Kong: Chinese University Press, 1992), XV:9D&lt;/ref&gt; [[Mencius]] wrote:&lt;ref&gt;Mencius, trans. D.C. Lau, (Hong Kong: Chinese University Press, 1984), VI A:10&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Quote|Fish is what I want; bear's palm is also what I want. If I cannot have both, I would rather take bear's palm than fish. Life is what I want; [[Yi (Confucianism)|yi]] is also what I want. If I cannot have both, I would rather take yi than life. On the one hand, though life is what I want, there is something I want more than life. That is why I do not cling to life at all cost. On the other hand, though death is what I loathe, there is something I loathe more than death. That is why there are dangers I do not avoid ... Yet there are ways of remaining alive and ways of avoiding death to which a person will not resort. In other words, there are things a person wants more than life and there are also things he or she loathes more than death.}}

==Arguments against suicide==
Common philosophical opinion of suicide since modernization reflected a spread in cultural beliefs of western societies that suicide is immoral and unethical. One popular argument is that many of the reasons for committing [[suicide]]—such as [[Clinical depression|depression]], emotional pain, or economic hardship—are transitory and can be ameliorated by therapy and through making changes to some aspects of one's life. A common [[adage]] in the discourse surrounding [[suicide prevention]] sums up this view: "Suicide is a permanent solution to a temporary problem." However, the argument against this is that while emotional pain may seem transitory to most people, and in many cases it is, in other cases it may be extremely difficult or even impossible to resolve, even through counseling or lifestyle change, depending upon the severity of the affliction and the person's ability to cope with their pain. Examples of this are incurable disease or lifelong mental illness.&lt;ref&gt;Paterson, Craig. Assisted Suicide and Euthanasia. Ashgate, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Absurdism===
The [[French Algeria]]n absurdist philosopher [[Albert Camus]] saw the goal of [[absurdism]] in establishing whether suicide is a necessary response to a world which appears to be mute both on the question of God's existence (and thus what such an existence might answer) and for our search for meaning and purpose in the world. For Camus, suicide was the rejection of freedom. He thinks that fleeing from the absurdity of reality into [[illusion]]s, [[religion]], or [[death]] is not the way out. Instead of fleeing the [[Albert Camus#Camus' ideas on the Absurd|absurd]] meaninglessness of life, we should embrace life passionately.

Existentialist [[Sartre]] describes the position of Meursault, the protagonist of Camus' ''[[The Stranger (Camus novel)|The Stranger]]'' who is condemned to death, in the following way:

{{Quote|"The absurd man will not commit suicide; he wants to live, without relinquishing any of his certainty, without a future, without hope, without illusions ... and without resignation either. He stares at death with passionate attention and this fascination liberates him. He experiences the "divine irresponsibility" of the condemned man."&lt;ref&gt;Sartre analysis of Mersault, in Literary and Philosophical Essays, 1943&lt;/ref&gt;}}

===Christian-inspired philosophy===
{{See also|Christian philosophy}}
[[G. K. Chesterton]] calls suicide "the ultimate and absolute evil, the refusal to take an interest in existence". He argues that a person who kills himself, as far as he is concerned, destroys the entire world (apparently exactly repeating [[Maimonides]]' view).

===Liberalism===
[[John Stuart Mill]] argued, in his influential essay "[[On Liberty]]", that since the {{lang|la|[[sine qua non]]}} of liberty is the power of the individual to make choices, any choice that one might make that would deprive one of the ability to make further choices should be prevented. &lt;!-- As it stands, that assertion is worthless, since {{em|every}} choice one makes deprives one of {{em|some}} further choices; perhaps the writer means to say "all further choices", as is consistent with the next sentence. --&gt;Thus, for Mill, selling oneself into [[slavery]] should be prevented in order to avoid precluding the ability to make further choices. Concerning these matters, Mill writes in "On Liberty"

{{Quote|Not only persons are not held to engagements which violate the rights of third parties, but it is sometimes considered a sufficient reason for releasing them from an engagement, that it is injurious to themselves. In this and most other civilized countries, for example, an engagement by which a person should sell himself, or allow himself to be sold, as a slave, would be null and void; neither enforced by law nor by opinion. The ground for thus limiting his power of voluntarily disposing of his own lot in life, is apparent, and is very clearly seen in this extreme case. The reason for not interfering, unless for the sake of others, with a person's voluntary acts, is consideration for his liberty. His voluntary choice is evidence that what he so chooses is desirable, or at the least endurable, to him, and his good is on the whole best provided for by allowing him to take his own means of pursuing it. But by selling himself for a slave, he abdicates his liberty; he forgoes any future use of it, beyond that single act. He therefore defeats, in his own case, the very purpose which is the justification of allowing him to dispose of himself. He is no longer free; but is thenceforth in a position which has no longer the presumption in its favour, that would be afforded by his voluntarily remaining in it. The principle of freedom cannot require that he should be free not to be free. It is not freedom, to be allowed to alienate his freedom.}}

It could be argued that suicide prevents further choices in the same way slavery does. However, it can also be argued that there are significant differences in not having any further involvement in decisions about your life and not having any further life to make decisions about. Suicide essentially removes the condition of being alive, not the condition of making choices about your life. 

Mill believes the individual to be the best guardian of their own interests. He uses the example of a man about to cross a broken bridge: we can forcibly stop that person and warn him of the danger, but ultimately should not prevent him from crossing the bridge—for only ''he'' knows the worth of his life balanced against the danger of crossing the bridge.

Too much should not be read into "disposing of his own lot in life" in the passage as this is not necessarily talking about anything other than slavery. Indeed, it would be odd if Mill had intended it to be about suicide but not explored the issue fully.

===Deontology===
From a [[deontological]] perspective, [[Immanuel Kant]] argues against suicide in ''Fundamental Principles of The Metaphysic of Morals''. In accordance with the second formulation of his [[categorical imperative]], Kant argues that, "He who contemplates suicide should ask himself whether his action can be consistent with the idea of humanity as an end in itself." Kant's theory looks at the act only, and not at its outcomes and consequences, and claims that one is ethically required to consider whether one would be willing to ''universalise'' the act: to claim ''everyone'' should behave that way. Kant argues that choosing to commit suicide entails considering oneself as a means to an end, which he rejects: a person, he says, must ''not'' be used "merely as means, but must in all actions always be considered as an end in himself." Therefore, it is unethical to commit suicide to satisfy oneself.

===Social contract===
The [[social contract]], according to [[Jean-Jacques Rousseau]], is such that every man has "a right to risk his own life in order to preserve it."

[[Thomas Hobbes|Hobbes]] and [[John Locke|Locke]] reject the right of individuals to take their own life. Hobbes claims in his ''[[Leviathan (Hobbes book)|Leviathan]]'' that natural law forbids every man "to do, that which is destructive of his life, or take away the means of preserving the same." Breaking this natural law is irrational and immoral. Hobbes also states that it is intuitively rational for men to want felicity and to fear death most.

==Neutral and situational stances==
===Honor===
Japan has a form of suicide called [[seppuku]], which is considered an honorable way to redeem oneself for transgressions or personal defeats. It was widely accepted in the days of the Samurai and even before that. It was generally seen as a privilege granted only to the samurai class; civilian criminals would thus not have this 'honor' and be executed. This reflects a view of suicide as brave and correct rather than cowardly and wrong.{{Citation needed|date=October 2011}}

===Utilitarianism===
[[Utilitarianism]] can be used as a justification for, or an argument against, suicide. Though the death of a depressed person ends their suffering, the person's family and friends may grieve.{{Citation needed|date=October 2011}}

===Other arguments===
[[David Hume]] left an essay on suicide to be published after his death.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.anselm.edu/homepage/dbanach/suicide.htm|title=''Essays on Suicide and the Immortality of the Soul: The Complete 1783 Edition''|accessdate=2008-09-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; Most of it is concerned with the claim that suicide is an affront to God. Hume argues that suicide is no more a rebellion against God than is saving the life of someone who would otherwise die, or changing the position of anything in one's surroundings. He spends much less time dismissing arguments that it is an affront to one's duty to others or to oneself. Hume claims that suicide can be compared to retiring from society and becoming a total recluse, which is not normally considered to be immoral, although the comparison would not seem to justify a suicide that leaves in its wake children or dependents who are thereby rendered vulnerable. As for duty to self, Hume takes it to be obvious that there can be times when suicide is desirable, though he also thinks it ridiculous that anyone would consider suicide unless they first considered every other option.&lt;!-- I am not sure that my edit has captured the gist of Hume's position; an editor familiar with H.'s essay will need to review this. --&gt;

Those who support the [[right to die]] argue that suicide is acceptable under certain circumstances, such as incurable disease and old age. The idea is that although life is, in general, good, people who face irreversible suffering should not be forced to continue suffering.

[[Leonard Peikoff]] states in his book ''[[Objectivism: The Philosophy of Ayn Rand]]'':

{{Quote|Suicide is justified when man's life, owing to circumstances outside of a person's control, is no longer possible; an example might be a person with a painful terminal illness, or a prisoner in a concentration camp who sees no chance of escape. In cases such as these, suicide is not necessarily a philosophic rejection of life or of reality. On the contrary, it may very well be their tragic reaffirmation. Self-destruction in such contexts may amount to the tortured cry: "Man's life means so much to me that I will not settle for anything less. I will not accept a living death as a substitute."}}

Bioethicist [[Jacob M. Appel|Jacob Appel]] has criticized "arbitrary" ethical systems that allow patients to refuse care when they are physically ill, while denying the mentally ill the right to suicide.&lt;ref&gt;Appel, JM. A Suicide Right for the Mentally Ill? A Swiss Case Opens a New Debate, The Hastings Center Report. 2007;37(3):21–23&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Wesley J. Smith]], Death on Demand: The assisted-suicide movement sheds its fig leaf, ''The Weekly Standard'', June 5, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Advocacy of suicide]]
* [[Altruistic suicide]]
* [[Assisted suicide]]
* [[Fatalism]]
* [[Micromort]]
* [[Nihilism]]
* [[Pessimism]]
* [[Johan Robeck]]
* [[Self-immolation]]
* [[Suicide attack]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Further reading==
*{{cite book|last=Hecht|first=Jennifer Michael|title=Stay: A History of Suicide and the Philosophies Against It|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=TZb9AQAAQBAJ|year=2013|publisher=Yale University Press|isbn=978-0-300-18709-0}}
*{{Cite encyclopedia|author-last=Cholbi|author-first=Michael|editor-last=Zalta|editor-first=Edward N.|editor-link=Edward N. Zalta|encyclopedia=[[Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy]]|title=Suicide|url=https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/suicide/|access-date=20 September 2018|edition=Fall 2017|orig-year=First published 18 May 2004|publisher=The Metaphysics Research Lab|publication-place=Stanford University|publication-date=21 July 2017|issn=1095-5054|archive-url=https://plato.stanford.edu/archives/fall2017/entries/suicide/|archive-date=21 July 2017|dead-url=no}}

==External links==
* [http://ssrn.com/abstract=1029229 Paterson, Craig, "A History of Ideas Concerning Suicide, Assisted Suicide and Euthanasia"]
* Video lectures from [[Yale University]] delivered by [[Shelly Kagan]] (requires [[Adobe Flash]]) from www.videolectures.net:
** [http://videolectures.net/yalephil176s07_kagan_lec24/ Suicide, Part I: The Rationality of Suicide]
** [http://videolectures.net/yalephil176s07_kagan_lec25/ Suicide, Part II: Deciding Under Uncertainty]
** [http://videolectures.net/yalephil176s07_kagan_lec26/ Suicide, Part III: The Morality of Suicide]

{{Suicide navbox}}
{{Portal bar|Death|Ethics|Philosophy}}

[[Category:Death]]
[[Category:Ethics]]
[[Category:Issues in ethics]]
[[Category:Philosophy of life|Suicide]]
[[Category:Suicide]]</text>
      <sha1>b9hb8266r3ehpns9inv7z1obcd13srr</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Rational egoism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3117750</id>
    <revision>
      <id>867428005</id>
      <parentid>867427806</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-11-05T17:26:51Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>JackintheBox</username>
        <id>30011325</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/98.172.123.105|98.172.123.105]] ([[User talk:98.172.123.105|talk]]) to last revision by Jackfork. ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="9749">{{For|other forms of egoism|Egoism}}
{{Individualism sidebar}}
'''Rational egoism''' (also called '''rational selfishness''') is the principle that an action is rational if and only if it maximizes one's self-interest.&lt;ref name="auto"&gt;Baier (1990), p. 201; Gert (1998), p. 69; Shaver (2002), §3; Moseley (2006), §2.&lt;/ref&gt; The view is a [[Norm (philosophy)|normative]] form of [[wikt:egoism|egoism]]. It is distinct from [[psychological egoism]] (according to which people are ''motivated'' only to act in their own self-interest) and [[ethical egoism]] (that moral agents ''ought'' only to do what is in their own self-interest).&lt;ref name="auto"/&gt;

== Philosophy ==
Rational egoism was embodied by Russian author [[Nikolay Chernyshevsky]] in the 1863 book ''[[What Is to Be Done? (novel)|What Is to Be Done?]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Andrzej Walicki|author2=Hilda Andrews-Rusiecka|title=A History of Russian Thought: From the Enlightenment to Marxism|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Ev4ad5wKI9oC&amp;pg=PA196|year=1979|publisher=Stanford University Press|isbn=978-0-8047-1132-6|pages=196}}&lt;/ref&gt; Chernyshevsky's standpoint was ultimately socialistic, and was criticised by [[Fyodor Dostoyevsky]] in the 1864 book ''[[Notes from Underground]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=The Case against Rational Egoism in Dostoevsky's Notes from Underground |author=James P. Scanlan |journal=Journal of the History of Ideas |volume=60 |issue=3 |date=July 1999 |pages=549–67 |doi=10.1353/jhi.1999.0028}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.sparknotes.com/lit/underground/context.html |title=SparkNotes: Notes from Underground: Context |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |date= |website=[[SparkNotes]] |publisher= |access-date=2015-05-30 |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

English philosopher [[Henry Sidgwick]] discussed rational egoism in his book ''[[The Methods of Ethics]]'', first published in 1872.&lt;ref&gt;Sidgwick (1907)&lt;/ref&gt; A method of ethics is "any rational procedure by which we determine what individual human beings 'ought' – or what it is 'right' for them – to do, or seek to realize by voluntary action".&lt;ref&gt;Sidgwick (1907), p. 1&lt;/ref&gt; Sidgwick considers three such procedures, namely, rational egoism, dogmatic intuitionism, and [[utilitarianism]]. Rational egoism is the view that, if rational, "an agent regards quantity of consequent pleasure and pain to himself alone important in choosing between alternatives of action; and seeks always the greatest attainable surplus of pleasure over pain".&lt;ref&gt;Sidgwick (1907), p. 95&lt;/ref&gt;

Sidgwick found it difficult to find any persuasive reason for preferring rational egoism over [[utilitarianism]]. Although utilitarianism can be provided with a rational basis and reconciled with the morality of common sense, rational egoism appears to be an equally plausible doctrine regarding what we have most reason to do. Thus we must "admit an ultimate and fundamental contradiction in our apparent intuitions of what is Reasonable in conduct; and from this admission it would seem to follow that the apparently intuitive operation of Practical Reason, manifested in these contradictory judgments, is after all illusory".&lt;ref&gt;Sidgwick (1907), p. 508&lt;/ref&gt;

== Ayn Rand ==
The author and philosopher [[Ayn Rand]] also discusses a theory that she called 'rational egoism'. She holds that it is both irrational and immoral to act against one's self-interest.&lt;ref&gt;Smith (2006); Moseley (2006), §2a.&lt;/ref&gt; Thus, her view is a conjunction of both rational egoism (in the standard sense) and [[ethical egoism]], because according to [[Objectivism (Ayn Rand)|Objectivist philosophy]], egoism cannot be properly justified without an [[epistemology]] based on [[rationality|reason]]:

Her book ''[[The Virtue of Selfishness]]'' (1964) explains the concept of rational egoism in depth. According to Rand, a rational man holds his own life as his highest value, rationality as his highest [[virtue]], and his happiness as the final purpose of his life.

Conversely, Rand was sharply critical of the [[ethical altruism|ethical doctrine of altruism]]:

{{quote|Do not confuse altruism with kindness, good will or respect for the rights of others. These are not primaries, but consequences, which, in fact, altruism makes impossible. The irreducible primary of altruism, the basic absolute is ''self-sacrifice'' – which means self-immolation, self-abnegation, self-denial self-destruction – which means the ''self'' as a standard of evil, the ''selfless'' as a standard of the good.
Do not hide behind such superficialities as whether you should or should not give a dime to a beggar. This is not the issue. The issue is whether you ''do'' or do ''not'' have the right to exist ''without'' giving him that dime. The issue is whether you must keep buying your life, dime by dime, from any beggar who might choose to approach you. The issue is whether the need of others is the first mortgage on your life and the moral purpose of your existence. The issue is whether man is to be regarded as a sacrificial animal. Any man of self-esteem will answer: ''No.'' Altruism says: ''Yes.''"&lt;ref&gt;Ayn Rand, "Faith and Force: Destroyers of the Modern World," ''Philosophy: Who Needs it'', 1982, New American Library, p. 74.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==Criticism==
Two objections to rational egoism are given by the English philosopher [[Derek Parfit]], who discusses the theory at length in ''[[Reasons and Persons]]'' (1984).&lt;ref&gt;D. Parfit (1984), parts II and III&lt;/ref&gt; First, from the rational egoist point of view, it is rational to contribute to a [[pension scheme]] now, even though this is detrimental to one's present interests (which are to spend the money now). But it seems equally reasonable to maximize one's interests now, given that one's reasons are not only relative to him, but to him as he is now (and not his future self, who is argued to be a "different" person). Parfit also argues that since the connections between the present mental state and the mental state of one's future self may decrease, it is not plausible to claim that one should be indifferent between one's present and future self.

The "[[Gene-centered view of evolution|selfish gene]]" model of [[evolution]] suggests that human (and animal) behaviors that seem altruistic are actually selfish, if viewed from the perspective of [[Gene|genes]]/[[Phenotype|phenotypes]].  People help each other "selflessly" because copies of their own genes also exist in others, so behaviors that help the genes survive are [[Natural selection|selected]] for, with the altruistic drive [[Kin selection|decreasing with genetic distance]].

==See also==
{{colbegin}}
* [[Cārvāka]]
* [[Egoist anarchism]]
* [[Enlightened self-interest]]
* [[Hedonism]]
* ''[[Homo economicus]]''
* [[Instrumental rationality]]
* [[Invisible hand]]
* [[Practical reason]]
* [[Praxeology]]
* [[Preference (economics)]]
* [[Prisoner's dilemma]]

{{colend}}

==Notes==
&lt;!--This article uses the Cite.php citation mechanism. If you would like more information on how to add footnotes to this article, please see http://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/Cite/Cite.php --&gt;
&lt;references /&gt;

==References and further reading==
* Baier, Kurt (1990). "Egoism" in ''A Companion to Ethics''. Peter Singer (ed.), Blackwell: Oxford.
* Brink, D. 1992, "Sidgwick and the Rationale for Rational Egoism," in Essays on Henry Sidgwick, ed. B. Schultz, Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.
* [[David Gauthier|Gauthier, David]] (1986). ''[[Morals by Agreement]]''. Oxford: Oxford University Press.
* Gert, Bernard (1998). ''Morality: Its Nature and Justification''. Oxford University Press.
* Kagan, S., 1986, "The Present-Aim Theory of Rationality," Ethics 96: 746–59. {{JSTOR|2381097}}
* McKenzie, Alexander J. (2003). "Evolutionary Game Theory". ''The Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy'' (Summer Edition), Edward N. Zalta (ed.). [http://plato.stanford.edu/archives/sum2003/entries/game-evolutionary/ link]
* Moseley, Alexander (2006). "Egoism". ''The Internet Encyclopedia of Philosophy''. J. Fieser &amp; B. Dowden (eds.). [http://www.utm.edu/research/iep/e/egoism.htm link]
* Mueller, D. (1989). ''Public Choice II''. Cambridge, UK: Cambridge University Press.
* Parfit, D., 1984, [[Reasons and Persons]], Oxford: Oxford University Press.
* Parfit, D., 1986, Reply to Kagan, Ethics, 96: 843–46, 868–69.
* Paul, E. &amp; F. Miller &amp; J. Paul (1997). ''Self-Interest''. Cambridge University Press
* Shaver, Robert (1998). [http://www.cambridge.org/9780521119962 ''Rational Egoism: A Selective and Critical History'']. Cambridge University Press.
* Shaver, Robert (2002). "Egoism". ''The Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy'' (Winter Edition), Edward N. Zalta (ed.). [http://plato.stanford.edu/archives/win2002/entries/egoism/ link]
* Sigwick, H., [http://www.laits.utexas.edu/poltheory/sidgwick/ ''The Methods of Ethics'']. London, 1874, 7th ed. 1907.
* Smith, Tara (2006). [http://www.cambridge.org/9780521705462 ''Ayn Rand's Normative Ethics'']. Cambridge University Press.
* Sober, E. &amp; D.S. Wilson (1998). ''Unto Others: The Evolution and Psychology of Unselfish Behavior''. Harvard University Press.

==External links==
* [http://www.utm.edu/research/iep/e/egoism.htm Egoism] in the [[Internet Encyclopedia of Philosophy]]
* [http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/egoism/ Egoism] in the [[Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy]]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20070929090734/http://www.cs.csbsju.edu/~lziegler/redblack.html The Red/Black Game]
* [http://www.objectivistcenter.org/cth--1195-Game_Theory_and_Objectivism.aspx Game Theory and Objectivism]

[[Category:Egoism]]
[[Category:Capitalism]]
[[Category:Epistemology]]
[[Category:Rational choice theory]]
[[Category:Ethical theories]]
[[Category:Philosophy of life]]</text>
      <sha1>9gy78nggio6gnba2i0pdk8vyew7ap0z</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Self-replicating machine</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1600053</id>
    <revision>
      <id>847054088</id>
      <parentid>846760246</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-06-22T16:11:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Floridada</username>
        <id>32352586</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* History */ Adding Lionel Penrose's contribution in the 1950s</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="44318">[[File:Advanced Automation for Space Missions figure 5-29.gif|thumb|right|A simple form of machine self-replication]]

A '''self-replicating machine''' is a type of [[autonomous robot]] that is capable of reproducing itself autonomously using raw materials found in the environment, thus exhibiting [[self-replication]] in a way analogous to that found in [[nature]]. The concept of self-replicating machines has been advanced and examined by [[Homer Jacobsen]], [[Edward F. Moore]], [[Freeman Dyson]], [[John von Neumann]] and in more recent times by [[K. Eric Drexler]] in his book on [[nanotechnology]], ''[[Engines of Creation]]'' (coining the term '''clanking replicator ''' for such machines) and by [[Robert Freitas]] and [[Ralph Merkle]] in their review ''Kinematic Self-Replicating Machines''&lt;ref name="Freitas 2004"&gt;{{cite book| last=Freitas| first=Robert A.|author2=Ralph C. Merkle | title=Kinematic Self-Replicating Machines| year=2004| publisher=Landes Bioscience| location=Georgetown, Texas| isbn=1-57059-690-5| url=http://www.MolecularAssembler.com/KSRM.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; which provided the first comprehensive analysis of the entire replicator design space. The future development of such technology is an integral part of several plans involving the mining of [[moon]]s and [[asteroid]] belts for ore and other materials, the creation of lunar factories, and even the construction of [[solar power satellite]]s in space. The possibly misnamed [[von Neumann probe]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.MolecularAssembler.com/KSRM/3.11.htm#p3 |title=3.11 Freitas Interstellar Probe Replicator (1979-1980) |publisher=Molecularassembler.com |date=2005-08-01 |accessdate=2009-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; is one theoretical example of such a machine. Von Neumann also worked on what he called the [[Von Neumann universal constructor|universal constructor]], a self-replicating machine that would operate in a [[cellular automaton|cellular automata]] environment.

A self-replicating machine is an artificial [[self-replication|self-replicating]] system that relies on conventional large-scale technology and automation. Certain idiosyncratic terms are occasionally found in the literature. For example, the term clanking replicator was once used by Drexler&lt;ref name=EoC&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.e-drexler.com/d/06/00/EOC/EOC_Chapter_4.html#section01of03| title=Engines of Abundance (Chapter 4) Clanking Replicators| work=Engines of Creation| first=K. Eric| last=Drexler| year=1986}}&lt;/ref&gt; to distinguish macroscale replicating systems from the microscopic [[nanorobot]]s or "[[assembler (nanotechnology)|assemblers]]" that [[nanotechnology]] may make possible, but the term is informal and is rarely used by others in popular or technical discussions. Replicators have also been called "von Neumann machines" after John von Neumann, who first rigorously studied the idea. However, the term "von Neumann machine" is less specific and also refers to a completely unrelated [[Von Neumann architecture|computer architecture]] that von Neumann proposed and so its use is discouraged where accuracy is important.&lt;ref name="Freitas 2004"/&gt; Von Neumann himself used the term [[Von Neumann universal constructor|universal constructor]] to describe such self-replicating machines.

Historians of [[machine tool]]s, even before the [[numerical control]] era, sometimes figuratively said that machine tools were a unique class of machines because they have the ability to "reproduce themselves"&lt;ref name="Colvin1947pp6-7"&gt;{{Harvnb|Colvin|1947|pp=6–7}}.&lt;/ref&gt; by copying all of their parts. Implicit in these discussions is that a human would direct the cutting processes (later planning and programming the machines), and would then be assembling the parts. The same is true for [[RepRap Project|RepRaps]], which are another class of machines sometimes mentioned in reference to such non-autonomous "self-replication". In contrast, machines that are ''truly autonomously'' self-replicating (like [[Molecular machine#Biological|biological machines]]) are the main subject discussed here.

==History==

The general concept of artificial machines capable of producing copies of themselves dates back at least several hundred years. An early reference is an anecdote regarding the philosopher [[René Descartes]], who suggested to Queen [[Christina of Sweden]] that the human body could be regarded as a machine; she responded by pointing to a clock and ordering "see to it that it reproduces offspring."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|journal=Scientific American| title=Build Your Own Replicator| volume=285|date=August 2001| pages=38–39| first=Moshe| last= Sipper|author2=James A. Reggia }} Several other variations on this anecdotal response also exist.&lt;/ref&gt; Several other variations on this anecdotal response also exist. [[Samuel Butler (novelist)|Samuel Butler]] proposed in his 1872 novel ''[[Erewhon]]'' that machines were already capable of reproducing themselves but it was man who made them do so,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.MolecularAssembler.com/KSRM/1.htm#p5 |title=1 |publisher=Molecularassembler.com |date=2005-08-01 |accessdate=2009-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;  and added that ''"machines which reproduce machinery do not reproduce machines after their own kind"''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Samuel Butler |url=http://www.nzetc.org/tm/scholarly/tei-ButErew.html |title=Erewhon, Chapter 24, The book Of the Machines |publisher=Nzetc.org |accessdate=2009-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[George Eliot|George Eliot's]] 1879 book ''[[Impressions of Theophrastus Such]]'', a series of essays that she wrote in the character of a fictional scholar named Theophrastus, the essay "Shadows of the Coming Race" speculated about self-replicating machines, with Theophrastus asking "how do I know that they may not be ultimately made to carry, or may not in themselves evolve, conditions of self-supply, self-repair, and reproduction".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=George Eliot |url=http://www.online-literature.com/george_eliot/theophrastus-such/17/ |title=Impressions of Theophrastus Such, Chapter 17, Shadows of the Coming Race |publisher=online-literature.com |accessdate=2017-08-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1802 [[William Paley]] formulated the first known [[teleological argument]] depicting machines producing other machines,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.MolecularAssembler.com/KSRM/1.htm#p11 |title=1 |publisher=Molecularassembler.com |date=2005-08-01 |accessdate=2009-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; suggesting that the [[watchmaker argument|question of who originally made a watch]] was rendered moot if it were demonstrated that the watch was able to manufacture a copy of itself.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| first=William| last= Paley| title= Natural Theology: or Evidences of the Existence and Attributes of the Deity, Collected from the Appearances of Nature| chapter=Chapter i, Section 1| publisher= E. Goodale| year= 1802| isbn=0-576-29166-8}}; [http://www.hti.umich.edu/cgi/p/pd-modeng/pd-modeng-idx?type=HTML&amp;rgn=TEI.2&amp;byte=53049319 (12th Edition, 1809)]{{dead link|date=December 2017 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }} See also: {{cite book| editor=Michael Ruse| title=Philosophy of Biology| year=1998| pages=36–40}}; {{cite journal| first=Richard| last= Lenski| title=Twice as Natural| journal=Nature| volume= 414|date=15 November 2001| page=255| doi=10.1038/35104715| pmid=11713507| issue=6861}}&lt;/ref&gt; Scientific study of self-reproducing machines was anticipated by [[John Bernal]] as early as 1929&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.cscs.umich.edu/~crshalizi/Bernal/| last=Bernal| first= John Desmond| title=The World, the Flesh and the Devil: An Enquiry into the Future of the Three Enemies of the Rational Soul| year=1929}}&lt;/ref&gt; and by mathematicians such as [[Stephen Kleene]] who began developing [[recursion theory]] in the 1930s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.MolecularAssembler.com/KSRM/1.htm#p14 |title=1 |publisher=Molecularassembler.com |date=2005-08-01 |accessdate=2009-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; Much of this latter work was motivated by interest in information processing and algorithms rather than physical implementation of such a system, however. In the course of the 1950s, suggestions of several increasingly simple mechanical systems capable of self-reproduction were made—notably by [[Lionel Penrose]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Wolfram|first=Stephen|title=A New Kind of Science|publisher=Wolfram Media, Inc.|year=2002|page=1179|isbn=1-57955-008-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===von Neumann's kinematic model===

A detailed conceptual proposal for a physical non-biological self-replicating system was first put forward by mathematician [[John von Neumann]] in lectures delivered in 1948 and 1949, when he proposed a [[kinematic]] self-reproducing automaton model as a [[thought experiment]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| last=von Neumann| first=John| year=1966| title=The Theory of Self-reproducing Automata| editor= A. Burks| publisher=Univ. of Illinois Press| location= Urbana, IL| isbn=0-598-37798-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.MolecularAssembler.com/KSRM/2.1.htm |title=2.1 Von Neumann's Contributions |publisher=Molecularassembler.com |accessdate=2009-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; Von Neumann's concept of a physical self-replicating machine was dealt with only abstractly, with the hypothetical machine using a "sea" or stockroom of spare parts as its source of raw materials. The machine had a program stored on a memory tape that directed it to retrieve parts from this "sea" using a manipulator, assemble them into a duplicate of itself, and then copy the contents of its memory tape into the empty duplicate's. The machine was envisioned as consisting of as few as eight different types of components; four logic elements that send and receive stimuli and four mechanical elements used to provide a structural skeleton and mobility. While qualitatively sound, von Neumann was evidently dissatisfied with this model of a self-replicating machine due to the difficulty of analyzing it with mathematical rigor. He went on to instead develop an even more abstract model self-replicator based on [[cellular automata]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.MolecularAssembler.com/KSRM/2.1.3.htm |title=2.1.3 The Cellular Automaton (CA) Model of Machine Replication |publisher=Molecularassembler.com |accessdate=2009-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; His original kinematic concept remained obscure until it was popularized in a 1955 issue of ''[[Scientific American]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal| last=Kemeny| first=John G.| title=Man Viewed as a Machine| journal=Scientific American| volume=192|date=April 1955| issue=4| pages=58–67| doi=10.1038/scientificamerican0455-58| bibcode=1955SciAm.192d..58K}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Moore's artificial living plants===

In 1956 mathematician [[Edward F. Moore]] proposed the first known suggestion for a practical real-world self-replicating machine, also published in ''Scientific American''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal| journal=Scientific American| first=Edward F.| last=Moore|date=October 1956| volume=195| title=Artificial Living Plants| issue=4| pages=118–126| doi=10.1038/scientificamerican1056-118| bibcode=1956SciAm.195d.118M}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.MolecularAssembler.com/KSRM/3.1.htm |title=3.1 Moore Artificial Living Plants (1956) |publisher=Molecularassembler.com |accessdate=2009-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; Moore's "artificial living plants" were proposed as machines able to use air, water and soil as sources of raw materials and to draw its energy from sunlight via a [[solar cell|solar battery]] or a [[steam engine]]. He chose the seashore as an initial habitat for such machines, giving them easy access to the chemicals in seawater, and suggested that later generations of the machine could be designed to float freely on the ocean's surface as self-replicating factory barges or to be placed in barren desert terrain that was otherwise useless for industrial purposes. The self-replicators would be "harvested" for their component parts, to be used by humanity in other non-replicating machines.

===Dyson's replicating systems===

The next major development of the concept of self-replicating machines was a series of thought experiments proposed by physicist [[Freeman Dyson]] in his 1970 Vanuxem Lecture.&lt;ref&gt;Freeman J. Dyson, "The twenty-first century," Vanuxem Lecture delivered at Princeton University, 26 February 1970.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.MolecularAssembler.com/KSRM/3.6.htm |title=3.6 Dyson Terraforming Replicators (1970, 1979) |publisher=Molecularassembler.com |date=2005-08-01 |accessdate=2009-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; He proposed three large-scale applications of machine replicators. First was to send a self-replicating system to [[Saturn]]'s moon [[Enceladus (moon)|Enceladus]], which in addition to producing copies of itself would also be programmed to manufacture and launch [[solar sail]]-propelled cargo spacecraft. These spacecraft would carry blocks of Enceladean ice to [[Mars]], where they would be used to [[Terraforming of Mars|terraform the planet]]. His second proposal was a solar-powered factory system designed for a terrestrial desert environment, and his third was an "industrial development kit" based on this replicator that could be sold to developing countries to provide them with as much industrial capacity as desired. When Dyson revised and reprinted his lecture in 1979 he added proposals for a modified version of Moore's seagoing artificial living plants that was designed to distill and store fresh water for human use&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| title=Chapter 18: Thought Experiments| work=Disturbing the Universe| first=Freeman J.| last=Dyson| year=1979| publisher=Harper and Row| location=New York| pages=194–204}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the "[[Astrochicken]]."

===''Advanced Automation for Space Missions''===
[[File:Advanced Automation for Space Missions figure 5-19.jpg|thumb|right|An artist's conception of a "self-growing" robotic lunar factory]]

In 1980, inspired by a 1979 "New Directions Workshop" held at Wood's Hole, [[NASA]] conducted a joint summer study with [[ASEE]] entitled [[s:Advanced Automation for Space Missions|Advanced Automation for Space Missions]] to produce a detailed proposal for self-replicating factories to develop [[Moon|lunar]] resources without requiring additional launches or human workers on-site. The study was conducted at [[Santa Clara University]] and ran from June 23 to August 29, with the final report published in 1982.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| url=http://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Advanced_Automation_for_Space_Missions |editor=[[Robert Freitas]], William P. Gilbreath| title=Advanced Automation for Space Missions| year=1982| id=NASA Conference Publication CP-2255 (N83-15348)}}&lt;/ref&gt; The proposed system would have been capable of [[exponential growth|exponentially increasing]] productive capacity and the design could be modified to build self-replicating probes to explore the galaxy.

The reference design included small computer-controlled electric carts running on rails inside the factory, mobile "paving machines" that used large parabolic mirrors to focus sunlight on lunar [[regolith]] to melt and sinter it into a hard surface suitable for building on, and robotic front-end loaders for [[strip mining]]. Raw lunar regolith would be refined by a variety of techniques, primarily [[hydrofluoric acid]] [[Leaching (metallurgy)|leaching]]. Large transports with a variety of manipulator arms and tools were proposed as the constructors that would put together new factories from parts and assemblies produced by its parent.

Power would be provided by a "canopy" of solar cells supported on pillars. The other machinery would be placed under the canopy.

A "[[casting]] [[robot]]" would use sculpting tools and templates to make [[plaster]] [[molding (process)|molds]]. Plaster was selected because the molds are easy to make, can make precise parts with good surface finishes, and the plaster can be easily recycled afterward using an oven to bake the water back out. The robot would then cast most of the parts either from nonconductive molten rock ([[basalt]]) or purified metals. A carbon dioxide [[laser cutting]] and welding system was also included.

A more speculative, more complex microchip fabricator was specified to produce the computer and electronic systems, but the designers also said that it might prove practical to ship the chips from Earth as if they were "vitamins."

A 2004 study supported by NASA's Institute for Advanced Concepts took this idea further.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.niac.usra.edu/studies/883Toth-Fejel.html|title=Modeling Kinematic Cellular Automata: An Approach to Self-Replication|last=Toth-Fejel|first=Tihamer|date=|year=2004|website=|publisher=NASA Institute for Advanced Concepts|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some experts are beginning to consider self-replicating machines for [[asteroid mining]].

Much of the design study was concerned with a simple, flexible chemical system for processing the ores, and the differences between the ratio of elements needed by the replicator, and the ratios available in lunar [[regolith]]. The element that most limited the growth rate was [[chlorine]], needed to process regolith for [[aluminium]]. Chlorine is very rare in lunar regolith.

===Lackner-Wendt Auxon replicators===

In 1995, inspired by Dyson's 1970 suggestion of seeding uninhabited deserts on Earth with self-replicating machines for industrial development, [[Klaus Lackner]] and Christopher Wendt developed a more detailed outline for such a system.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal| last=Lackner| first=Klaus S.|author2=Christopher H. Wendt | title=Exponential growth of large self-replicating machine systems| journal=Mathl. Comput. Modelling| volume=21| year=1995| issue=10| pages=55–81| doi=10.1016/0895-7177(95)00071-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Lackner, Klaus S., and Wendt, Christopher H., "Self-reproducing machine systems for global scale projects," Document LA-UR-93-2886, 4th International Conference and Exposition on Engineering, Construction and Operations in Space/Conference and Exposition/Demonstrations on Robotic for Challenging Environments, Albuquerque, New Mexico, 26 February – 3 March 1994&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.MolecularAssembler.com/KSRM/3.15.htm |title=3.15 |publisher=Molecularassembler.com |date=2005-08-01 |accessdate=2009-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; They proposed a colony of cooperating mobile robots 10–30&amp;nbsp;cm in size running on a grid of electrified ceramic tracks around stationary manufacturing equipment and fields of solar cells. Their proposal didn't include a complete analysis of the system's material requirements, but described a novel method for extracting the ten most common chemical elements found in raw desert topsoil (Na, Fe, Mg, Si, Ca, Ti, Al, C, O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;) using a high-temperature carbothermic process. This proposal was popularized in [[Discover Magazine]], featuring solar-powered desalination equipment used to irrigate the desert in which the system was based.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal| journal=Discover|date=October 1995| first=Thomas| last=Bass| title=Robot, build thyself| pages=64–72}}&lt;/ref&gt; They named their machines "Auxons", from the [[Greek language|Greek]] word ''auxein'' which means "to grow."

==Recent work==

===Self-replicating rapid prototypers===
[[File:Reprap Darwin.jpg|thumb|right|RepRap 1.0 "Darwin" prototype]]

Early experimentation with [[rapid prototyping]] in 1997-2000 was not expressly oriented toward reproducing rapid prototyping systems themselves, but rather extended simulated "[[evolutionary robotics]]" techniques into the physical world. Later developments in rapid prototyping have given the process the ability to produce a wide variety of electronic and mechanical components, making this a rapidly developing frontier in self-replicating system research.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.MolecularAssembler.com/KSRM/3.20.htm |title=Freitas 2004, pp. 64-67 |publisher=Molecularassembler.com |date=2005-08-01 |accessdate=2009-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1998 Chris Phoenix informally outlined a design for a hydraulically powered replicator a few cubic feet in volume that used ultraviolet light to cure soft plastic feedstock and a fluidic logic control system, but didn't address most of the details of assembly procedures, error rates, or machining tolerances.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite newsgroup| author=Christopher J. Phoenix| newsgroup=sci.nanotech| title=Partial design for macro-scale machining self-replicator| date=March 21, 1998| url=http://groups.google.com/groups?hl=en&amp;selm=6f0nui%248ih%241%40news.nanospace.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.MolecularAssembler.com/KSRM/3.20.htm#p8 |title=3.20 |publisher=Molecularassembler.com |date=2005-08-01 |accessdate=2009-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:First replication.jpg|300px|right|thumb|All of the plastic parts for the machine on the right were produced by the almost identical machine on the left. (Adrian Bowyer (left) and Vik Olliver(right) are members of the RepRap project.)]]

In 2005, [[Adrian Bowyer]] of the [[University of Bath]] started the [[RepRap Project]] to develop a [[rapid prototyping]] machine which would be able to manufacture some or most of its own components, making such machines cheap enough for people to buy and use in their homes. The project is releasing its designs and control programs under the [[GNU GPL]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://staff.bath.ac.uk/ensab/replicator/| title=WebHome| accessdate=2007-02-18| deadurl=yes| archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070112200308/http://staff.bath.ac.uk/ensab/replicator/| archivedate=2007-01-12| df=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The RepRap approach uses [[fused deposition modeling]] to manufacture plastic components, possibly incorporating conductive pathways for circuitry. Other components, such as steel rods, nuts and bolts, motors and separate electronic components, would be supplied externally. In 2006 the project produced a basic functional prototype and in May 2008 the machine succeeded in producing all of the plastic parts required to make a 'child' machine.

Some researchers have proposed a [[microfactory]] of specialized machines that support recursion—nearly all of the parts of all of the machines in the factory can be manufactured by the factory.&lt;ref&gt;
James Jones.
[http://cubespawn.com/ CubeSpawn].
2009.
&lt;/ref&gt;

===NIAC studies on self-replicating systems===

In the spirit of the 1980 "Advanced Automation for Space Missions" study, the [[NASA Institute for Advanced Concepts]] began several studies of self-replicating system design in 2002 and 2003. Four phase I grants were awarded:

*[[Hod Lipson]] ([[Cornell University]]), "Autonomous Self-Extending Machines for Accelerating Space Exploration"&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.niac.usra.edu/files/studies/final_report/737Lipson.pdf| title=Autonomous Self-Extending Machines for Accelerating Space Exploration| first=Hod| last= Lipson|author2=Evan Malone | accessdate=2007-01-04| format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Gregory Chirikjian]] ([[Johns Hopkins University]]), "Architecture for Unmanned Self-Replicating Lunar Factories"&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.niac.usra.edu/files/studies/final_report/880Chirikjian.pdf| format=PDF| title=An Architecture for Self-Replicating Lunar Factories| first=Gregory S.| last= Chirikjian|date=April 26, 2004| accessdate=2007-01-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Paul Todd (biophysicist)|Paul Todd]] (Space Hardware Optimization Technology Inc.), "Robotic Lunar Ecopoiesis"&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| last= Todd| first= Paul| title=Final Progress Report on Robotic Lunar Ecopoiesis Test Bed
| date=30 April 2004| accessdate=2007-01-04| url=http://www.niac.usra.edu/files/studies/final_report/884Todd.pdf| format=PDF}} (phase I report)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.niac.usra.edu/files/studies/final_report/918Todd.pdf| title=Robotic Lunar Ecopoiesis Test Bed| date=July 6, 2006| accessdate=2007-01-04| first=Paul| last=Todd| format=PDF}} (phase II report)&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Tihamer Toth-Fejel]] ([[General Dynamics]]), "Modeling Kinematic Cellular Automata: An Approach to Self-Replication"&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.niac.usra.edu/files/studies/final_report/883Toth-Fejel.pdf | title=Modeling Kinematic Cellular Automata| first= Tihamer| last= Toth-Fejel |author2=Robert Freitas |author3=Matt Moses|date=April 30, 2004| format=PDF| accessdate=2007-01-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.MolecularAssembler.com/KSRM/3.25.4.htm |title=3.25.4 Toth-Fejel Kinematic Cellular Automata (2003-2004) |publisher=Molecularassembler.com |accessdate=2009-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; The study concluded that complexity of the development was equal to that of a Pentium 4, and promoted a design based on cellular automata.

===Bootstrapping Self-Replicating Factories in Space===

In 2012, NASA researchers Metzger, Muscatello, Mueller, and Mantovani argued for a bootstrapping approach to start self-replicating factories in space.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last=Metzger | first=Philip | last2=Muscatello | first2=Anthony | last3=Mueller | first3=Robert | last4=Mantovani | first4=James | title=Affordable, Rapid Bootstrapping of the Space Industry and Solar System Civilization | journal=Journal of Aerospace Engineering | volume=26 | issue=1 | pages=18–29 | publisher=American Society of Civil Engineers | date= January 2013 | language=English | url=http://ascelibrary.org/doi/abs/10.1061/(ASCE)AS.1943-5525.0000236 | doi=10.1061/(ASCE)AS.1943-5525.0000236 | access-date=2016-09-24| arxiv=1612.03238 }}&lt;/ref&gt; They developed this concept on the basis of [[In situ resource utilization|In Situ Resource Utilization (ISRU)]] technologies that NASA has been developing to "live off the land" on the Moon or Mars. Their modeling showed that in just 20 to 40 years this industry could become self-sufficient then grow to large size, enabling greater exploration in space as well as providing benefits back to Earth. In 2014, [[Thomas Kalil]] of the White House [[Office of Science and Technology Policy]] published on the White House blog an interview with Metzger on bootstrapping solar system civilization through self-replicating space industry.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.whitehouse.gov/blog/2014/10/14/bootstrapping-solar-system-civilization |title=Bootstrapping a Solar System Civilization |publisher=The White House |date=2014-10-14 |accessdate=2016-12-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; Kalil requested the public submit ideas for how "the Administration, the private sector, philanthropists, the research community, and storytellers can further these goals." Kalil connected this concept to what former NASA Chief technologist [[Mason Peck]] has dubbed "Massless Exploration", the ability to make everything in space so that you do not need to launch it from Earth. Peck has said, "...all the mass we need to explore the solar system is already in space. It's just in the wrong shape."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pri.org/stories/2015-01-05/exciting-new-ideas-space-technology-are-getting-short-changed-congress |title=Exciting new ideas in space technology are getting short-changed by Congress |publisher=PRI.org |date=2015-01-15 |accessdate=2016-12-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2016, Metzger argued that fully self-replicating industry can be started over several decades by astronauts at a lunar outpost for a total cost (outpost plus starting the industry) of about a third of the space budgets of the [[International Space Station]] partner nations, and that this industry would solve Earth's energy and environmental problems in addition to providing massless exploration.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last=Metzger | first=Philip | title=Space Development and Space Science Together, an Historic Opportunity | journal=Space Policy | volume=37 | issue=2 | pages=77–91 | publisher=Elsevier Ltd. | date= August 2016 | language=English | url=http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0265964616300625 | doi=10.1016/j.spacepol.2016.08.004 | access-date=2016-12-09 | arxiv=1609.00737}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Cornell University's self-assembler===

In 2005, a team of researchers at [[Cornell University]], including [[Hod Lipson]], implemented a self-assembling machine. The machine is composed of a tower of four articulated [[cube]]s, known as ''molecubes'', which can revolve about a [[triagonal]]. This enables the tower to function as a [[robotic arm]], collecting nearby molecubes and assembling them into a copy of itself. The arm is directed by a [[computer program]], which is contained within each molecube, analogous to how each animal [[cell (biology)|cell]] contains an entire copy of its [[DNA]]. However, the machine cannot manufacture individual molecubes, nor do they occur naturally, so its status as a self-replicator is debatable.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.physorg.com/news4055.html |title=Researchers build a robot that can reproduce |publisher=Physorg.com |date=2005-05-11 |accessdate=2010-06-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== New York University artificial DNA tile motifs ===

In 2011, a team of scientists at [[New York University]] created a structure called 'BTX' (bent triple helix) based around three double helix molecules, each made from a short strand of DNA.  Treating each group of three double-helices as a code letter, they can (in principle) build up self-replicating structures that encode large quantities of information.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2011/10/111012132651.htm |title=Self-Replication Process Holds Promise for Production of New Materials| publisher=Science Daily |accessdate=2011-10-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v478/n7368/full/nature10500.html |title=Self-replication of information-bearing nanoscale patterns|journal=Nature|accessdate=2011-10-13|volume=478|doi=10.1038/nature10500|pages=225–228|bibcode=2011Natur.478..225W}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Self-replication of magnetic polymers ===

In 2001 Jarle Breivik at [[University of Oslo]] created a system of magnetic building blocks, which in response to temperature fluctuations, spontaneously form self-replicating polymers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mdpi.com/1099-4300/3/4/273 |title=Self-Organization of Template-Replicating Polymers and the Spontaneous Rise of Genetic Information| publisher=Entroy |accessdate=2015-01-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Self-replication of neural circuits ===

In 1968 [[Zellig Harris]] wrote that "the metalanguage is in the language,"&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|title=Mathematical Structures of Language|page=17|last=Harris|first=Zellig|year=1968|publisher=John Wiley and Son|location= New York, NY}}&lt;/ref&gt; suggesting that self-replication is part of language. In 1977 [[Niklaus Wirth]] formalized this proposition by publishing a self-replicating [[deterministic context-free grammar]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Wirth|first1=Niklaus|title= What can we do about the unnecessary diversity of notation for syntactic definitions?|journal=Commun. ACM|volume=20|pages=822–823|doi=10.1145/359863.359883}}&lt;/ref&gt; Adding to it probabilities, [[Bertrand du Castel]] published in 2015 a self-replicating [[stochastic grammar]] and presented a mapping of that grammar to [[neural networks]], thereby presenting a [[Conceptual model|model]] for a self-replicating neural circuit.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=du Castel|first1=Bertrand|title=Pattern Activation/Recognition Theory of Mind|journal=Frontiers in Computational Neuroscience|volume=9|issue=90|publisher=EPFL|location=Lausanne|date = 15 July 2015|url=http://journal.frontiersin.org/article/10.3389/fncom.2015.00090/full|doi=10.3389/fncom.2015.00090|ref=neuroscience}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Partial construction==
Partial construction is the concept that the constructor creates a partially constructed (rather than fully formed) offspring, which is then left to complete its own construction.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|journal=Automata 2008| title=Signal Crossing Solutions in von Neumann Self-replicating Cellular Automata| year=2008| first=William R.| last=Buckley}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|journal=Biological Theory| title=Computational Ontogeny| volume=3| issue=1| year=2008| first=William R.| last=Buckley|doi=10.1162/biot.2008.3.1.3|page=3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The von Neumann model of self-replication envisages that the mother automaton should construct all portions of daughter automatons, without exception and prior to the initiation of such daughters. Partial construction alters the construction relationship between mother and daughter automatons, such that the mother constructs but a portion of the daughter, and upon initiating this portion of the daughter, thereafter retracts from imparting further influence upon the daughter. Instead, the daughter automaton is left to complete its own development. This is to say, means exist by which automatons may develop via the mechanism of a zygote.

==Self-replicating spacecraft==
{{Main article|Self-replicating spacecraft}}

The idea of an automated spacecraft capable of constructing copies of itself was first proposed in scientific literature in 1974 by [[Michael A. Arbib]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.MolecularAssembler.com/KSRM/3.11.htm#p1 |title=3.11 |publisher=Molecularassembler.com |date=2005-08-01 |accessdate=2009-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| first=Michael A.| last=Arbib| title=The Likelihood of the Evolution of Communicating Intelligences on Other Planets| work= Interstellar Communication: Scientific Perspectives| editor=Cyril Ponnamperuma, A. G. W. Cameron| location=Boston| publisher=Houghton Mifflin Company| year=1974| pages=59–78}}&lt;/ref&gt; but the concept had appeared earlier in [[science fiction]] such as the 1967 novel ''[[Berserker (Saberhagen)|Berserker]]'' by [[Fred Saberhagen]] or the 1950 novellette trilogy ''[[The Voyage of the Space Beagle]]'' by [[A. E. van Vogt]]. The first quantitative engineering analysis of a self-replicating spacecraft was published in 1980 by [[Robert Freitas]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal| first=Robert A., Jr.| last=Freitas| title=A Self-Reproducing Interstellar Probe| journal=[[Journal of the British Interplanetary Society]]| volume=33|date=July 1980| pages=251–264| url=http://www.rfreitas.com/Astro/ReproJBISJuly1980.htm | accessdate = 2008-10-01|bibcode = 1980JBIS...33..251F }}&lt;/ref&gt; in which the non-replicating [[Project Daedalus]] design was modified to include all subsystems necessary for self-replication. The design's strategy was to use the probe to deliver a "seed" factory with a mass of about 443 tons to a distant site, have the seed factory replicate many copies of itself there to increase its total manufacturing capacity, and then use the resulting automated industrial complex to construct more probes with a single seed factory on board each.

==Other references==

* A number of patents have been granted for self-replicating machine concepts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.MolecularAssembler.com/KSRM/3.16.htm |title=3.16 The Collins Patents on Reproductive Mechanics (1997-1998) |publisher=Molecularassembler.com |date=2005-08-01 |accessdate=2009-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; The most directly relevant include {{US patent|4734856}} "Autogeneric system" Inventor: Davis; Dannie E. (Elmore, AL) (March 1988), {{US patent|5659477}} "Self reproducing fundamental fabricating machines (F-Units)" Inventor: Collins; Charles M. (Burke, VA) (August 1997), {{US patent|5764518}} " Self reproducing fundamental fabricating machine system" Inventor: Collins; Charles M. (Burke, VA)(June 1998); Collins' PCT:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=WIPO |url=http://www.wipo.int/pctdb/en/wo.jsp?IA=WO1996020453&amp;DISPLAY=STATUS |title=(WO/1996/020453) SELF REPRODUCING FUNDAMENTAL FABRICATING MACHINES (F-UNITS) |publisher=Wipo.int |accessdate=2009-09-16 }}{{dead link|date=January 2018 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;  and {{US patent|6510359}} "Method and system for self-replicating manufacturing stations" Inventors: Merkle; Ralph C. (Sunnyvale, CA), Parker; Eric G. (Wylie, TX), Skidmore; George D. (Plano, TX) (January 2003).
*Macroscopic replicators are mentioned briefly in the fourth chapter of [[K. Eric Drexler|K. Eric Drexler's]] 1986 book ''[[Engines of Creation]]''.&lt;ref name="EoC"/&gt;
* In 1995, [[Nick Szabo]] proposed a challenge to build a macroscale replicator from [[Lego]] robot kits and similar basic parts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.lucifer.com/~sean/N-FX/macro.html| archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20060307220916/http://www.lucifer.com/~sean/N-FX/macro.html| archivedate=2006-03-07| title=Macroscale Replicator| first=Nick| last=Szabo| accessdate=2007-03-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; Szabo wrote that this approach was easier than previous proposals for macroscale replicators, but successfully predicted that even this method would not lead to a macroscale replicator within ten years.
* In 2004, [[Robert Freitas]] and [[Ralph Merkle]] published the first comprehensive review of the field of self-replication (from which much of the material in this article is derived, with permission of the authors), in their book ''[[Kinematic Self-Replicating Machines (book)|Kinematic Self-Replicating Machines]]'', which includes 3000+ literature references.&lt;ref name="Freitas 2004"/&gt; This book included a new molecular assembler design,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.MolecularAssembler.com/KSRM/4.11.3.htm |title=4.11.3 Merkle-Freitas Hydrocarbon Molecular Assembler (2000-2003) |publisher=Molecularassembler.com |date=2005-08-01 |accessdate=2009-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; a primer on the mathematics of replication,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.MolecularAssembler.com/KSRM/5.9.htm |title=5.9 Brief Mathematical Primer on Self-Replicating Systems |publisher=Molecularassembler.com |date=2005-08-01 |accessdate=2009-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the first comprehensive analysis of the entire replicator design space.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.MolecularAssembler.com/KSRM/5.1.9.htm |title=5.1.9 Freitas-Merkle Map of the Kinematic Replicator Design Space (2003-2004) |publisher=Molecularassembler.com |date=2005-08-01 |accessdate=2009-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In 2006, the strategy video game Sword of the Stars included an enemy of the Unknown Menace type called Von Neumann, which gradually replicated and spread throughout the galaxy once encountered.

== Prospects for implementation ==
As the use of industrial automation has expanded over time, some factories have begun to approach a semblance of self-sufficiency that is suggestive of self-replicating machines.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.MolecularAssembler.com/KSRM/3.7.htm |title=3.7 Self-Replicating Automated Industrial Factory (1973-present) |publisher=Molecularassembler.com |date=2005-08-01 |accessdate=2009-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, such factories are unlikely to achieve "full closure"&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.MolecularAssembler.com/KSRM/5.6.htm |title=5.6 Closure Theory and Closure Engineering |publisher=Molecularassembler.com |date=2005-08-01 |accessdate=2009-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; until the cost and flexibility of automated machinery comes close to that of human labour and the manufacture of spare parts and other components locally becomes more economical than transporting them from elsewhere. As [[Samuel Butler (novelist)|Samuel Butler]] has pointed out in [[Erewhon]], replication of partially closed universal machine tool factories is already possible. Since safety is a primary goal of all legislative consideration of regulation of such development, future development efforts may be limited to systems which lack either control, matter, or energy closure. Fully capable machine replicators are most useful for developing resources in dangerous environments which are not easily reached by existing transportation systems (such as [[outer space]]).

An artificial replicator can be considered to be a form of [[artificial life]]. Depending on its design, it might be subject to [[evolution]] over an extended period of time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.MolecularAssembler.com/KSRM/5.1.9.L.htm |title=5.1.9.L Evolvability |publisher=Molecularassembler.com |date=2005-08-01 |accessdate=2009-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, with robust [[error correction]], and the possibility of external intervention, the common [[science fiction]] scenario of robotic life run amok will remain extremely unlikely for the foreseeable future.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.MolecularAssembler.com/KSRM/5.11.htm |title=5.11 Replicators and Public Safety |publisher=Molecularassembler.com |accessdate=2009-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Grey goo|Grey goo scenario]]
* [[Self-reconfiguring modular robot]]
* [[AI takeover]]
* [[3D printing]]
* [[Computer virus]]
* [[Computer worm]]
* [[Ecophagy]]
* [[Existential risk from advanced artificial intelligence]]
* [[Astrochicken]]
* [[Lights out (manufacturing)]]
* [[Nanorobotics]]
* [[Spiegelman's Monster]]
* [[Self-replicating machines in fiction]]
* [[Self-replicating spacecraft]]
* [[RepRap project]]

== References ==
{{reflist|30em}}

== Bibliography ==
* {{Colvin1947}}
* M. Sipper, [https://drive.google.com/file/d/0B6G3tbmMcpR4MkpqY3EyN3k0djQ/view?usp=sharing Fifty years of research on self-replication: An overview], Artificial Life, vol. 4, no. 3, pp. 237-257, Summer 1998.  
===Other references===
* [[Freeman Dyson]] expanded upon Neumann's automata theories, and advanced a biotechnology-inspired theory. See [[Astrochicken]].
*The first technical design study of a self-replicating interstellar probe was published in a [http://www.rfreitas.com/Astro/ReproJBISJuly1980.htm 1980 paper] by [[Robert Freitas]]
*Clanking replicators are also mentioned briefly in the [http://www.foresight.org/EOC/EOC_Chapter_4.html#section01of03 fourth chapter] of [[K. Eric Drexler]]'s 1986 book ''[[Engines of Creation]]''.
*Article about a proposed clanking replicator system to be used for developing Earthly deserts in the October 1995 [[Discover Magazine]], featuring forests of solar panels that powered desalination equipment to irrigate the land.
* In 1995, [[Nick Szabo]] [https://web.archive.org/web/20060307220916/http://www.lucifer.com/~sean/N-FX/macro.html proposed] a challenge to build a macroscale replicator from Lego(tm) robot kits and similar basic parts.  Szabo wrote that this approach was easier than previous proposals for macroscale replicators, but successfully predicted that even this method would not lead to a macroscale replicator within ten years.
*In 1998, [[Chris Phoenix (nanotechnologist)|Chris Phoenix]] [https://groups.google.com/groups?hl=en&amp;selm=6f0nui%248ih%241%40news.nanospace.com suggested] a general idea for a macroscale replicator on the sci.nanotech [[usenet|newsgroup]], operating in a pool of [[ultraviolet]]-cured liquid [[plastic]], selectively solidifying the plastic to form solid parts. Computation could be done by [[fluidic logic]]. Power for the process could be supplied by a pressurized source of the liquid.
*In 2001, [[Peter Ward (paleontologist)|Peter Ward]] mentioned an escaped clanking replicator destroying the human race in his book ''[[Future Evolution]]''.
*In 2004, General Dynamics completed a [http://www.niac.usra.edu/files/studies/final_report/883Toth-Fejel.pdf study] for NASA's Institute for Advanced Concepts.  It concluded that complexity of the development was equal to that of a Pentium 4, and promoted a design based on cellular automata.
*In 2004, Robert Freitas and [[Ralph Merkle]] published the first comprehensive review of the field of self-replication, in their book [http://www.MolecularAssembler.com/KSRM.htm Kinematic Self-Replicating Machines], which includes 3000+ literature references.
*In 2005, [[Adrian Bowyer]] of the [[University of Bath]] started the [[RepRap]] project to develop a [[rapid prototyping]] machine that would be able to replicate itself, making such machines cheap enough for people to buy and use in their homes.  The project is releasing material under the [[GNU GPL]]. [https://web.archive.org/web/20070112200308/http://staff.bath.ac.uk/ensab/replicator/]
*In 2015, advances in [[graphene]] and [[silicene]] suggested that it could form the basis for a neural network with densities comparable to the human brain if integrated with [[silicon carbide]] based nanoscale CPUs containing [[memristors]].
The power source might be [[sun|solar]] or possibly [[radioisotope]] based given that new liquid based compounds can generate substantial power from radioactive decay.

{{Molecular nanotechnology footer}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Self-Replicating Machine}}
[[Category:Self-replicating machines| ]]
[[Category:Artificial life]]
[[Category:Robotic concepts]]
[[Category:Self-organization]]
[[Category:Reproduction]]
[[Category:Machines]]
[[Category:Thought experiments]]</text>
      <sha1>h9q5r9lfs77z68xhp6xupp4xs3o4t0n</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Veikko Aaltonen</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7028277</id>
    <revision>
      <id>831503681</id>
      <parentid>768538616</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-03-20T22:38:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Onel5969</username>
        <id>10951369</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Disambiguating links to [[La Vie de Bohème (disambiguation)]] (link changed to [[La Vie de Bohème (1992 film)]]) using [[User:Qwertyytrewqqwerty/DisamAssist|DisamAssist]].</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="4746">{{BLP sources|date=February 2016}}
{{Infobox person
| name                      = Veikko Aaltonen
| image                     = Veikko Aaltonen.jpg
| caption                   = Veikko Aaltonen in 2013.
| birth_name                = 
| birth_date                = {{birth date and age|1955|12|1|df=yes}}
| birth_place               = [[Sääksmäki]], [[Finland]]
| death_date                = &lt;!-- {{Death date and age|YYYY|MM|DD|YYYY|MM|DD}} (death date then birth date) --&gt;
| monuments                 = 
| residence                 = 
| nationality               = Finnish
| ethnicity                 = &lt;!-- Ethnicity should be supported with a citation from a reliable source --&gt;
| citizenship               = 
| education                 = 
| occupation                = director, editor, sound editor, production manager, film and television writer and actor
| known_for                 = 
| notable_works             = 
| style                     = 
| influences                = 
| influenced                = 
| home_town                 = 
| salary                    = 
| net_worth                 = &lt;!-- Net worth should be supported with a citation from a reliable source --&gt;
| height                    = &lt;!-- {{height|m=}} --&gt;
| weight                    = &lt;!-- {{convert|weight in kg|kg|lb}} --&gt;
| television                = 
| spouse                    = 
| partner                   = 
| children                  = 
| parents                   = 
| relatives                 = 
| awards                    = 
| website                   = &lt;!-- {{URL|www.example.com}} --&gt;
| box_width                 = 
}}
'''Veikko Aaltonen''' (born 1 December 1955 in [[Sääksmäki]], [[Finland]]) is a [[Finland|Finnish]] [[Film director|director]], [[editing|editor]], [[Sound editor (filmmaking)|sound editor]], production manager and [[film]] and [[television]] [[writer]] and [[actor]].

Aaltonen began his career in the mid-1970s working as a sound editor on various films. Early in his career he worked with [[Rauni Mollberg]] as co-writer on two of his films, ''Milka'' (1980) and ''[[The Unknown Soldier (1985 film)|The Unknown Soldier]]'' (1985).

In 1987 Aaltonen directed his first feature film, ''Tilinteko'', which he co-wrote with [[Aki Kaurismäki]], who also produced the film. Five years later he directed a film that has been considered his primary breakthrough, ''The Prodigal Son'' (1992).

Aaltonen has also made documentaries and directed TV series.

== Partial filmography ==
* ''[[The Worthless (film)|The Worthless]]'' (''Arvottomat'', 1982) – actor
* ''[[Crime and Punishment (1983 film)|Crime and Punishment]]'' (''Rikos ja rangaistus'', 1983) – editor
* ''[[The Unknown Soldier (1985 film)|The Unknown Soldier]]'' (''Tuntematon sotilas'', 1985) – co-writer
* ''[[La Vie de Bohème (1992 film)|La Vie de Bohème]]'' (1992) – editor
* ''[[Our Father...]]'' (''Isä meidän'', 1993) – director, writer, editor
* ''[[Merisairas|Seasick]]'' (1996) – director, co-editor
* ''[[Kiss Me in the Rain]]'' (''Rakkaudella, Maire'', 1999) – director, editor
* ''Maa'' (2001) – director, editor, writer&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://yle.fi/vintti/yle.fi/tv1/juttuarkisto/dokumentit/aaltosen-dokumentti-maa.html |title=Aaltosen dokumentti: Maa |publisher=[[Yle TV1]] |language=Finnish |date=2010-06-21 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''Työväenluokka'' (2004) – director, writer, editor&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://yle.fi/vintti/yle.fi/tv1/juttuarkisto/elokuvat/veikko-aaltonen-tyovaenluokka.html |title=Veikko Aaltonen: Työväenluokka |publisher=Yle TV1 |language=Finnish |date=2010-04-28 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''Paimenet'' (2004) – director, writer&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.valomerkki.fi/kirkko-ja-kaupunki/kirkko-ja-kaupunki-arkisto/4072 |title=Veikko Aaltoselle ja Klaus Härölle kirkon kulttuuripalkinto |website=Kirkko ja kaupunki |publisher=Finnish Lutheran Parish of Helsinki |language=Finnish |date=2006-12-04 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''[[Trench Road]]'' (''Juoksuhaudantie'', 2004) – director, writer
* ''Uudisraivaaja'' (2005) – director
* ''Sydänjää'' (2007) – director
* ''Harvoin tarjolla'' (2008) – director
* ''Helppo elämä'' (television drama series, 2009–2011) – director
* ''Kansan mies'' (television drama series, 2013– ) – director

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* {{IMDb name|0007399|Veikko Aaltonen}}
* [https://www.nytimes.com/movies/person/78895/Veikko-Aaltonen/filmography Veikko Aaltonen: Filmography], ''[[The New York Times]]''

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Aaltonen, Veikko}}
[[Category:1955 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:People from Valkeakoski]]
[[Category:Finnish film directors]]
[[Category:Finnish film producers]]


{{Finland-film-director-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>k12yzu8ms2yuq0suay4dmvx1nv7l2is</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
