<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.33.0-wmf.4</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Art media</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>41096877</id>
    <redirect title="List of art media" />
    <revision>
      <id>792196284</id>
      <parentid>745489986</parentid>
      <timestamp>2017-07-25T02:08:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Xqbot</username>
        <id>8066546</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Bot: Fixing double redirect to [[List of art media]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="105">#REDIRECT [[List of art media]]
[[Category:Art media| 01]]
[[Category:Art materials]]
[[Category:Arts|M]]</text>
      <sha1>ryg2sgzvykk3gd2ic9zzysgwfqad0ea</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Bill Henson</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2456307</id>
    <revision>
      <id>867643747</id>
      <parentid>863459956</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-11-07T02:10:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rescuing 1 sources and tagging 0 as dead. #IABot (v2.0beta9)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="26964">{{for|the American animator|Bill "Tex" Henson}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2011}}
{{Use Australian English|date=October 2011}}
{{Infobox artist
| name          = Bill Henson
| image         = 
| imagesize     = 
| caption       = Bill Henson before his opening night at his exhibition.
| birth_name     = 
| website        = {{URL|www.billhenson.com}}
| birth_date     = {{birth date and age|df=yes|1955|10|7|}}
| birth_place    = [[Melbourne]], [[Australia]]
| death_date     = 
| death_place    = 
| nationality   = [[Australia]]n
| field         = [[Photography]]
| training      = 
| movement      = 
| works         = 
| patrons       =

| awards        = 
}}
'''Bill Henson''' (born 7 October 1955)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ngv.vic.gov.au/col/artist/2363 NGV]. Retrieved 8 February 2014&lt;/ref&gt; is an [[Australian]] contemporary art photographer.

==Art==
Henson has exhibited nationally and internationally in galleries such as the [[Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum]] in New York, the [[Venice Biennale]], the [[National Gallery of Victoria]] in Melbourne, Australia, the [[Art Gallery of New South Wales]] in Sydney, Australia and the [[Bibliothèque Nationale]] in Paris. His current practice involves holding one exhibition in Australia every two years, and up to three overseas exhibitions each year.

The use of [[chiaroscuro]]&lt;ref&gt;"What becomes apparent when you see Henson’s work in person is the importance of the almost pitch-black darkness that, in whatever formal context he has devised over the years, always cloaks his forlorn, defiantly unneedy subjects, giving their run-down urban environments the look of remote desert outposts. It’s a black that seems both to be caked on the surface of the photographs, like tar or centuries of soot, and to recede infinitely into the background. It looks as solid as lead, a physical threat to the teens it blankets, and at the same time it’s as if the blackness were exuded by their bodies, forming a kind of paranormal manifestation of some feeling too intense and guarded to register in any other fashion. In its own peculiar way Henson’s black is as unique an achievement as, say, Robert Ryman’s white." Dennis Cooper (2002) The Photography of Bill Henson: Naked Youth, ''Artforum International'', No. 6, p.94-97&lt;/ref&gt; is common throughout his works, through underexposure and adjustment in printing. His photographs' use of [[bokeh]] is intended to give them a [[painterly]] atmosphere. The work is often presented as [[diptych]]s, [[triptych]]s and in other groupings, and the exhibitions are specifically curated by Henson to reflect a sense of musicality.&lt;ref&gt;"As the new Biss recording of Mozart's K364 ''Sinfonia Concertante'', the ''Andante'' movement only, repeats itself endlessly on my stereo, the sound of Richard Tognetti and the ACO orchestra at their absolute greatest washes over me like a tsunami, while my head is also spinning with the staggering beauty of a single gesture made by a woman riding the escalator at the Westfield Doncaster shopping centre, and with just how Tognetti's violin sounds like she looked. Well, there you have it. I call it millennial slippage. You might call it madness..." Henson in interview with Amanda Smith, Artworks Broadcast:Sunday 15 August 2010 11:05AM, Australian Broadcasting Commission transcript, http://www.abc.net.au/radionational/programs/artworks/artworks-feature-bill-henson/3020240 Downloaded 26 May 2012&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Capon, E., Malouf, D. &amp; Annear, J., in ''Mnemosyne'', Art Gallery of New South Wales, Scalo, (2205) 8-9, 12, 35.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;see discussion of the ''Luminous'' concert (2005) performed by the Australian Chamber Orchestra to a screening of Henson imagery in Stevens, Meghan (2009).''Music and Image in Concert''. Australia: Music and Image in Concert&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Smee, S., Touch of Innocence, Weekend Australian [newspaper]. 22–23 January 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;

Duality is a recurring theme of Henson's work, often in combination with adolescent subjects.&lt;ref&gt;"And this sexiness that is there and emphasised is crucial to the austere pessimism of these works. But to see it as the point of the photographs, arraigning Henson as a purveyor of kiddie porn to the elite, is, putting it charitably, to miss the point. It’s like reading him as a centrefold photographer for whom the background is just backdrop. Or thinking the clothed figure in Titian’s ''Allegory of Vice and Virtue'' represents the good girl. What Henson is actually giving us is a series of shattered paysages moralisés, where the innocent sexiness of the bodies is posed against a landscape they are not part of — the majestic, insensible alps (alps that bring to mind the poignancy, which had never struckeme before of Robbe-Grillet’s statement about how Mt Blanc had not been waiting since the Permian Age to be a symbol for Shelley). Henson’s alps appear like a scroll rolled back, to reveal a ''[[Ethics (Spinoza)|deus sive natura]]'' it is sentimental to even describe as pitiless. These alps tower over the figures but the environment they are posed in seems just as alien. There is no back to nature primitivism about these figures. They are bruised and wounded and helpless — the flowers about to be consumed in the furnace." John Forbes (1993) 'Bill Henson'. In Henson, Bill &amp; Annear, Judy &amp; Art Gallery of New South Wales &amp; National Gallery of Victoria (2005).  ''Mnemosyne''. Scalo in association with Art Gallery of New South Wales, Zurich&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Crawford"&gt;{{cite journal | last = Crawford | first = A | year = 2003 | title = Bill Henson: Lux et Nox | journal = Art Monthly Australia | volume = 164 | issue = October }}&lt;/ref&gt; He frequently employs a flattened perspective through the use of telephoto lenses. His works are often in the form of staged tableaux&lt;ref&gt;DARIA, Ioan (2009) The Photographic Treatment of Emotion in Front of a Stage. Bill Henson: The Opera Project. ''EKPHRASIS: IMAGES, CINEMA, THEATRE, MEDIA,'' 1/2009 Integrating Methodologies in Visual Culture Research, The Faculty of Theater and Television, Babeș-Bolyai University, Cluj. Online http://ekphrasis.accentpublisher.ro/files/magazines_content/47/0.pdf accessed 27 May 2012&lt;/ref&gt; in which faces of the subjects are often blurred or partly shadowed and do not directly face the viewer.&lt;ref&gt;"Henson's images brood and turn in on themselves rather than present themselves explicitly to the audience." Burke, Janine and Henson, Bill. Art for the End of the World. ''Meanjin'', Vol. 40, No. 3, Oct 1981: 375-388.&lt;/ref&gt;

Henson states that he is not interested in a political or sociological agenda.&lt;ref&gt;"I don’t use soap boxes. I don’t have much to say about whether or not people have lost the plot now. No." Henson, Bill &amp; Mirlesse, Sabine (2015) ''Dreamscapes and Sensory Experience: An Interview with Bill Henson By Sabine Mirlesse, June 15, 2015.'' American Suburb X website [http://www.americansuburbx.com/2015/06/bill-henson-interview-2015.html?mc_cid=265691eea3&amp;mc_eid=c414479e1c] Accessed 20 June 2015&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;"I'm not here today to talk about the downfall of Kevin Rudd or the prospects for some Elizabethan renaissance of the arts if Julia Gillard is elected...". Henson in interview with Amanda Smith, Artworks Broadcast:Sunday 15 August 2010 11:05AM, Australian Broadcasting Commission transcript, http://www.abc.net.au/radionational/programs/artworks/artworks-feature-bill-henson/3020240 Downloaded 26 May 2012&lt;/ref&gt;

==Life and influences==
Raised in the Eastern suburbs of Melbourne, Henson studied Visual Arts and Design 1974–1975 at [[Victoria College, Melbourne|Prahran College of Advanced Education]] where [[Athol Shmith]] was head of the Photography program and [[John Cato]] and [[Paul Cox (director)|Paul Cox]] were lecturers. He did not complete the diploma, but the nineteen-year-old Henson's work was promoted by Shmith to [[Jennie Boddington]],&lt;ref&gt;"It is remarkable that, so young, his armoury of technical skill is so narrowly focused and accurately directed to serve his needs. He does his own colour processing in his bedroom[...]. He has referred to a ‘certain morbidity’ in his work. Well, that is an element of life too. The young ballerinas seem to be under a spell, in thrall. At one and the same time he is tender artist and tyrant.  The delicacy and control of colour in these shades will excite wonderment and pleasure, where a hint of coral light imbues the lobe of an ear, or minuscule catchlight alights with barest touch on the tip of eyelashes or edges the profiled iris of her eye. At times he teases with only a suggestion of vaporous form, but the presence breathes within the frame. Do we not grieve for mortality when we perceive (for there is a tactile as well as a visual understanding here) the wisp of hair on the nape of her neck? There is something in the order of mystery. Enter the trance." Jennie Boddington (1975), ''Of Tender Years'' Published Photography Gallery room brochure, National Gallery of Victoria. Melbourne&lt;/ref&gt;   inaugural Curator of Photography at the [[National Gallery of Victoria]]&lt;ref&gt;Boddington, J., Henson, B., (July 1975) exhibition catalogue. Melbourne:National Gallery of Victoria&lt;/ref&gt; with the result that Henson's first solo show was exhibited there in 1975.&lt;ref&gt;Smee, Sebastian. Bill Henson. Art and Australia Vol.42, No.3, Autumn 2005, p. 396 – 405&lt;/ref&gt;

From his period as a student until its closure in 1980, he worked at The Bookshop of Margareta Webber&lt;ref&gt;Henson, Bill, (1980) ''The bookshop of Margareta Webber'' : 1 map ; 46 x 60 cm. (Not drawn to scale). State Library of Victoria collection. Melbourne: Webbers Booksellers http://trove.nla.gov.au/work/7648003&lt;/ref&gt; 343 Little Collins Street Melbourne, which specialised in luxurious books on ballet, dance and the visual arts. Leaving the bookshop, he traveled and photographed in Eastern Europe.&lt;ref&gt;'The first city I wanted to see was Dresden.' Henson quoted by Smee, Sebastian. Bill Henson. ''Art and Australia'' Vol.42, No.3, Autumn 2005, p. 396 – 405&lt;/ref&gt; He taught briefly at the [[Victorian College of the Arts]] in Melbourne. Henson's long-term relationship with Luminist Melbourne painter [[Louise Hearman]], whom he met in 1981 at the Victorian College of Arts, has been noted&lt;ref&gt;Coslovich, Gabriella (2008) Seeing in the dark: Louise Hearman remains enthralled by the richness of oil paint. ''The Age'' [newspaper] 18 October 2008. Online article http://www.theage.com.au/news/entertainment/arts/seeing-in-the-dark/2008/10/16/1223750228676.html accessed 26 May 2012&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;"...the foreboding tension of her surfaces, a quality more in common with artists such as Dale Frank and Bill Henson." Collection notes Art Gallery of New South Wales © Art Gallery of New South Wales Contemporary Collection Handbook, 2006, online http://www.artgallery.nsw.gov.au/work/502.1995/ accessed 26 May 2012&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Gregg, Simon (2011) ''New Romantics: Darkness and Light in Australian Art''. Melbourne: Australian Scholarly Publishing Pty, Limited&lt;/ref&gt; as mutually influential on their art. Hearman won the 2014 [[Doug Moran National Portrait Prize|Moran portrait prize]], Australia's richest at $A150,000, with her double portrait of Bill Henson.&lt;ref&gt;'The co-judge of the prize, former Art Gallery of NSW director Edmund Capon, said Henson and Hearman had lived together for decades.   But Hearman was coy on the subject. "Well, why don’t we just leave that open?" she said.  Capon is a long-term friend of Henson and Hearman, and curated Henson’s 2005 exhibition at the AGNSW.' [http://www.heraldsun.com.au/entertainment/arts/paintings-of-bill-henson-wins-150000-doug-moran-portrait-prize/story-fni0fcgk-1227105829260 Elizabeth Fortescue, "Paintings of Bill Henson wins $150,000 Doug Moran Portrait Prize". HERALD SUN 28 October 2014]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Controversies==

===Images seized===
On 22 May 2008, the opening night of Bill Henson's 2007–2008 exhibition at the [[Roslyn Oxley9 Gallery]] in [[Paddington, New South Wales|Paddington]], Sydney, was canceled after eight individual complaints were made to Police voicing concerns about an email invitation from the Gallery to a "Private View" that depicted photographs of a nude 13-year-old girl. [[Hetty Johnston]], a [[child protection]] advocate also lodged a complaint with the New South Wales police.&lt;ref name="Tovey"&gt;{{cite news | last = Tovey | first = Josephine |author2=Kennedy, Les |author3=Welch, Dylan | date = 24 May 2008| title = Art obscenity charges | work = [[The Sydney Morning Herald]] | url = http://www.smh.com.au/news/arts/henson-finds-support-over-photos/2008/05/23/1211183097197.html | accessdate = 2008-05-28 | archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20080713043449/http://www.smh.com.au/news/arts/henson-finds-support-over-photos/2008/05/23/1211183097197.html| archivedate= 13 July 2008 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Gallery"&gt;{{cite news |title=Gallery: Nude children exhibit shut |work=[[News.com.au]] |url=http://www.news.com.au/gallery/0,22056,5031912-5010140,00.html |accessdate=2008-05-28 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080525213842/http://www.news.com.au/gallery/0%2C22056%2C5031912-5010140%2C00.html |archivedate=25 May 2008 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;
On the same day a ''[[Sydney Morning Herald]]'' columnist, [[Miranda Devine]], had also written a scathing article in response to viewing the email invitation,&lt;ref name="Devine"&gt;{{cite news | last = Devine | first = Miranda | date = 22 May 2008 | title = Moral backlash over sexing up of our children | work = [[The Sydney Morning Herald]] | url = http://www.smh.com.au/articles/2008/05/21/1211182891875.html?page=3 | accessdate = 2008-06-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; which precipitated heated talk-back and media discussion throughout the day. In the process of removing the images from the Gallery, Police found more photographs of naked children on exhibition among various [[large format]] photographs of nonfigurative subjects, which they later sought to examine for the purposes of determining their legal status under the NSW Crimes Act and child protection legislation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aifs.gov.au/nch/resources/legislation/legislation.html |title=Australian child protection legislation- National Child Protection Clearinghouse |accessdate=2009-07-11 |deadurl=bot: unknown |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090711023525/http://www.aifs.gov.au/nch/resources/legislation/legislation.html |archivedate=11 July 2009 |df=dmy }}. aifs.gov.au&lt;/ref&gt; Following discussions with the Gallery and a decision by Henson, the Gallery canceled the opening and postponed the show.&lt;ref&gt;Roslyn Oxley Gallery, 'Media Statement', 23/5/08&lt;/ref&gt;

It was announced on 23 May that a number of the images in the exhibition had been seized by police local Area Commander Alan Sicard, with the intention of charging Bill Henson, the Gallery, or both with "publishing an indecent article" under the Crimes Act.&lt;ref name="Kennedy"&gt;{{cite news | last = Kennedy | first = Les | date = 23 May 2008| title = Henson show charges | work = [[The Sydney Morning Herald]] | url = http://www.smh.com.au/news/arts/henson-show-charges/2008/05/23/1211183060208.html | accessdate = 2008-05-28 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The seized images were also removed from the Roslyn Oxley9 Gallery website, where the remainder of the series can now be viewed online.&lt;ref name="roslynoxley9"&gt;{{cite web | title = Bill Henson, 2008 | work = Roslyn Oxley9 Gallery | url = http://www.roslynoxley9.com.au/artists/18/Bill_Henson/1098/ | accessdate = 2008-05-28 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The situation provoked a national debate on censorship. In a televised interview, Prime Minister [[Kevin Rudd]] stated that he found the images "absolutely revolting"&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.smh.com.au/articles/2008/05/23/1211183044543.html Rudd revolted – Arts – Entertainment]. smh.com.au (2008-05-23). Retrieved on 2012-05-24.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theage.com.au/news/national/henson-still-revolting-pm/2008/05/28/1211654079734.html Rudd stands by criticism of Henson images – National]. theage.com.au (2008-05-28). Retrieved on 2012-05-24.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.ninemsn.com.au/article.aspx?id=567968 Rudd 'revolted' at art of naked children] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20081208165310/http://news.ninemsn.com.au/article.aspx?id=567968 |date=8 December 2008 }}. News.ninemsn.com.au (2008-05-23). Retrieved on 2012-05-24.&lt;/ref&gt; and that they had "no artistic merit".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theaustralian.news.com.au/story/0,25197,23745396-2702,00.html PM says Henson photos have no artistic merit | The Australian] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20091019041841/http://www.theaustralian.news.com.au/story/0,25197,23745396-2702,00.html |date=19 October 2009 }}. Theaustralian.news.com.au (2012-02-17). Retrieved on 2012-05-24.&lt;/ref&gt; These views swiftly drew censure from members of the 'creative stream' who attended the recent [[Australia 2020 Summit|2020 Summit]] convened by Rudd, led by actress [[Cate Blanchett]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.canberratimes.com.au/news/local/news/general/blanchett-joins-chorus-against-henson-attack/778095.aspx? |title=Blanchett joins chorus against Henson attack |accessdate=2010-09-04 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100904163257/http://www.canberratimes.com.au/news/local/news/general/blanchett-joins-chorus-against-henson-attack/778095.aspx |archivedate=4 September 2010 |df=dmy }}. The Canberra Times (2008-05-28)&lt;/ref&gt;

On 5 June 2008 the former director of the National Gallery of Australia, Betty Churcher, said it was "not surprising" that the New South Wales Department of Public Prosecutions (DPP) would announce its official recommendation that no charges be laid regarding the Sydney Roslyn Oxley9 gallery's collection of photographs by artist Bill Henson. Ms Churcher said it would have been ridiculous to drag the case through the courts:&lt;ref&gt;[http://au.news.yahoo.com/080606/21/175vw.html 'Not surprising' no charges laid over NGA Henson collection] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080610145101/http://au.news.yahoo.com/080606/21/175vw.html |date=10 June 2008 }} Retrieved on 2008-06-06.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://au.news.yahoo.com/080606/21/1761j.html No case against Henson: prosecutors] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080609050237/http://au.news.yahoo.com/080606/21/1761j.html |date=9 June 2008 }} Retrieved on 2008-06-06.&lt;/ref&gt; {{quote|''I'm very pleased that the public prosecutor has decided that it's likely to end the debacle because they always do, as soon as you take art into court it never works ... The court is not the place to decide matters of art.''}}

On 6 June 2008 it was reported in ''[[The Age]]'' that police would not prosecute Bill Henson over his photographs of naked teenagers, after they were declared "mild and justified" and given a PG rating&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theage.com.au/national/no-charges-for-henson-20080606-2mnv.html No charges for Henson]. theage.com.au (2008-06-06)&lt;/ref&gt; by the [[Australian Classification Board]], suggesting viewing by children under the age of 16 is suitable with parental guidance.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theage.com.au/national/no-charges-for-henson-20080606-2mnv.html 'No charges for Henson] Retrieved on 2008-06-06.&lt;/ref&gt;

Australian scholar [[Niall Lucy]] criticized Devine's response to Henson's art in his 2010 book ''Pomo Oz: Fear and Loathing Down Under''.&lt;ref&gt;Niall Lucy, ''Pomo Oz: Fear and Loathing Downunder'' (Fremantle: Fremantle Press, 2011).&lt;/ref&gt; [[David Marr (journalist)|David Marr]]'s book about the 2008 incident ''The Henson case'' was listed for the 2009 [[Victorian Premier's Literary Award]] and the 2009 [[Prime Minister's Literary Awards]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Marr|first=David|title=The Henson case|year=2008|publisher=Text Publishing|location=Melbourne, Victoria|isbn=978-1-921520-03-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Selection of models===
On 4 October 2008, Henson became the center of controversy again after it was revealed in extracts of ''The Henson case''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.textpublishing.com.au/books-and-authors/book/the-henson-case |title=The Henson Case |publisher=Text Publishing }}&lt;/ref&gt; that in 2007 he visited St Kilda Park Primary School to pick out potential models for his artwork.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | first= | last= | title=Henson 'scouted school for child models' | date=4 October 2008 | publisher=The Age | url =http://news.theage.com.au/national/henson-scouted-school-for-child-models-20081004-4tnh.html | work = | pages = | accessdate = 2008-10-05 | archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20081005154904/http://news.theage.com.au/national/henson-scouted-school-for-child-models-20081004-4tnh.html| archivedate= 5 October 2008 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | first= | last= | title=Parents Back School in Henson Row | date=4 October 2008 | publisher=The Sydney Morning Herald | url =http://www.smh.com.au/news/entertainment/arts/parents-back-school-in-henson-row/2008/10/06/1223145239295.html | work = | pages = | accessdate = 2008-10-06 | archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20081008014222/http://www.smh.com.au/news/entertainment/arts/parents-back-school-in-henson-row/2008/10/06/1223145239295.html| archivedate= 8 October 2008 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | first= | last= | title=Gillard attacks artist's search for models | date=4 October 2008 | publisher=The Sydney Morning Herald | url =http://www.smh.com.au/news/entertainment/arts/gillard-attacks-artists-search-for-models/2008/10/05/1223145173695.html | work = | pages = | accessdate = 2008-10-06 | archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20081008014208/http://www.smh.com.au/news/entertainment/arts/gillard-attacks-artists-search-for-models/2008/10/05/1223145173695.html| archivedate= 8 October 2008 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; Henson was allowed entry into the school and escorted by principal Sue Knight around the school grounds and picked two children he thought would be suitable – one child, a boy, was later photographed after his parents were approached by the school on behalf of the artist.{{fact|date=October 2018}}

An investigation into the matter was launched by the [[Department of Education and Early Childhood Development (Victoria)|Department of Education]] on 6 October 2008. The investigation found that the principal had complied with departmental policy, and had no case to answer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.theage.com.au/national/principal-in-clear-over-henson-20081107-5k8j.html |location=Melbourne |work=The Age |title=Principal in clear over Henson |first1=Farrah |last1=Tomazin |first2=Bridie |last2=Smith |date=8 November 2008 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20091017105111/http://www.theage.com.au/national/principal-in-clear-over-henson-20081107-5k8j.html |archivedate=17 October 2009 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Exhibitions (selected)==
A few of his exhibitions:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | date = 22 May 2008  | title = Bill Henson career biography | work = [[The Daily Telegraph (Sydney)|The Daily Telegraph]] | url = http://www.news.com.au/dailytelegraph/story/0,22049,23741573-5001021,00.html | accessdate = 2008-05-28 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Christophe Guye Galerie, [https://christopheguye.com/artists/bill-henson/biography Bill Henson (Biography)]&lt;/ref&gt;

'''1975'''
* ''Bill Henson'', National Gallery of Victoria, Melbourne&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.ngv.vic.gov.au/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/MR-Bill-Henson_Final.pdf|title=NGV Festival of Photography (Bill Henson)|publisher=NGV International|format=pdf|access-date=10 October 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
'''1981'''
* ''Bill Henson Photographs'', Photographers' Gallery, London
'''1985'''
* ''Bill Henson, Untitled 1983/84'', Pinacotheca, Melbourne, Australia, July
'''1989'''
* ''Bill Henson Fotografien'', Museum Moderner Kunst, Palais Liechtenstein, Wien
'''1990'''
* ''Bill Henson Photographs'', Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris
'''1993'''
* ''Bill Henson'', Tel Aviv Museum of Art
'''1998'''
* ''Bill Henson'', ACP Galerie Peter Schuengel, Salzburg
'''2004'''
* ''Presence 3: Bill Henson'', The Speed Art Museum, Kentucky
'''2006'''
* ''Bill Henson'', Institute of Modern Art, Brisbane
'''2008'''
* ''Bill Henson'', Robert Miller Gallery, New York, United States&lt;ref name=robertmilgal&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.robertmillergallery.com/past|title=Past Exhibition|website=Robert Miller Gallery|access-date=10 October 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''Bill Henson'', Roslyn Oxley9 Gallery, Sydney, Australia&lt;ref name=roslox9/&gt;
'''2010'''
* ''Bill Henson'', Roslyn Oxley9 Gallery, Sydney, Australia&lt;ref name=roslox9/&gt;
'''2011'''
* ''Bill Henson'', Tolarno Galleries, Melbourne, Australia
'''2012'''
* ''Diane Arbus, Bill Henson, Robert Mapplethorpe'', Robert Miller Gallery, New York, United States&lt;ref name=robertmilgal/&gt;
* ''Bill Henson'', Roslyn Oxley9 Gallery, Sydney, Travelled over Australia&lt;ref name=roslox9&gt;{{cite web| url = http://www.roslynoxley9.com.au/artists/18/Bill_Henson/profile/| title= Bill Henson Public Collections| website=Roslyn Oxley9 Gallery|access-date=10 October 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
'''2013'''
* ''Cloud Landscapes'', Art Gallery of New South Wales, Sydney
* ''The Youth Code!'', [[Christophe Guye Galerie]], Zurich, Switzerland&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= https://christopheguye.com/exhibitions/the-youth-code/introduction|title=The Youth Code|website=Christophe Guye Galerie|access-date=10 October 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Books==
Major monographs on the artist's work:
* Bill Henson ; edited by Martin Jaeggi and Walter Keller (2002). ''Lux et Nox'' Zurich, Switzerland : Scalo;  2nd ed. London:Thames &amp; Hudson (2009)
* Henson, Bill, (2005) ''Mnemosyne''. Zurich : Scalo in association with Art Gallery of New South Wales.

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[https://christopheguye.com/artists/bill-henson/selected-works Gallery] at Christophe Guye Galerie
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20071011114855/http://www.nypress.com/18/27/books/travisjeppesen.cfm Bill Henson's ''Mnemosyne''] by [[Travis Jeppesen]] 
* {{cite web|publisher=[[Victoria and Albert Museum]] |url=http://www.vam.ac.uk/collections/photography/past_exhns/twilight/henson/index.html |title=Bill Henson photographs taken at twilight |work=Photography |accessdate=2007-08-25 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070926222906/http://www.vam.ac.uk/collections/photography/past_exhns/twilight/henson/index.html |archivedate=26 September 2007 |deadurl=unfit }} 
*[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=re28HkN39MQ Leo Scofield Interviews Bill Henson]
*[http://metapsychology.mentalhelp.net/poc/view_doc.php?type=book&amp;id=2782&amp;cn=166 Review of Bill Henson's ''Mnemosyne'' by Christian Perring]

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Henson, Bill}}
[[Category:1955 births]]
[[Category:Australian photographers]]
[[Category:Photographers from Melbourne]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Censorship in the arts]]
[[Category:RMIT University alumni]]
[[Category:Victorian College of the Arts alumni]]
[[Category:Australian contemporary artists]]</text>
      <sha1>e5g2k6c3hrhjwlj27vjvsjrvnkdqxee</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Dorota Nieznalska</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>27423862</id>
    <revision>
      <id>857089764</id>
      <parentid>857089745</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-08-29T14:05:33Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>180.94.140.233</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="13505">'''Dorota Alicja Nieznalska''' (born September 19, 1973) is a [[Poland|Polish]] [[Visual arts|visual artist]] and [[Sculpture|sculptor]].

Nieznalska's controversial installation ''Pasja'' (2002), which included the placement of an image of the [[penis]] upon a metal [[Greek cross]], resulted in a notable scandal, as the display was condemned as immoral and [[blasphemous]] by Polish [[Conservatism|conservative]] [[Roman Catholicism|Catholics]]. The group exhibition at which the installation was presented was closed down by the authorities, while Nieznalska herself faced legal charges on account of an alleged violation of a provision of the Polish criminal code prohibiting blasphemy.

The sculptor was successful in fighting off the blasphemy conviction following the favorable ruling of an [[appeals court]] in 2009.

== Early life ==

Dorota Alicja Nieznalska was born to a devout family in [[Gdańsk]] in 1973.&lt;ref name="Baird 2005"&gt;Baird, Daniel (October 2005). [http://www.walrusmagazine.com/articles/2005.10-visual-art-jewish-polan/3/ "Between the Cross and the Jewish Graveyard".] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090109123459/http://www.walrusmagazine.com/articles/2005.10-visual-art-jewish-polan/3/ |date=January 9, 2009 }} ''[[The Walrus]]''. Retrieved 20 May 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Raised in the Gdańsk-[[Gdynia]]&amp;ndash;[[Sopot]] [[Tricity, Poland|Tricity]] area, Nieznalska was educated at an art high school in [[Gdynia Orłowo]].&lt;ref name = "WV: Arts and the Church"&gt;(24 July 2003). [http://www.warsawvoice.pl/WVpage/pages/article.php/3040/article "Art vs. The Church".] ''[[The Warsaw Voice]]''. Retrieved 20 May 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = "Official biography"&gt;[http://www.nieznalska.com/bioen.html Official biography at ''http://www.nieznalska.com''.] Retrieved 20 May 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Nieznalska enrolled at [[Gdańsk]]'s Academy of Fine Arts as a student of sculpture in 1993, a year after making her first solo exhibition in her native city.&lt;ref name="Official biography"/&gt; Nieznalska's fine arts instructors were the Professors [[Franciszek Duszeńko]] and [[Grzegorz Klaman]].&lt;ref name = "Sinkiewicz December 2006"&gt;Sienkiewicz, Karol (December 2006). [http://www.culture.pl/en/culture/artykuly/os_nieznalska_dorota "Dorota Nieznalska".] ''Polish Culture''. Retrieved 20 May 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Nieznalska graduated from the academy in 1999 and exhibited a number of student works (''Insemination'', 1997; ''The Pleasure Principle'', 1998; ''Absolution'', 1999) in the 1990s.&lt;ref name = "Official biography"/&gt;&lt;ref name = "Kowalczyk 70"&gt;{{cite book|last=Kowalczyk|first=Izabela|title=Niebezpieczne związki sztuki z ciałem|publisher=Galeria Miejska Arsenał|year=2002|page=70|language=pl}}&lt;/ref&gt; She subsequently participating in three major exhibitions in Gdańsk, [[Warsaw]], and [[Białystok]] in 2000 and 2001.&lt;ref name = "Official biography"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Pasja"&gt;Taraszkiewicz-Zwolicka, Małgorzata. [http://www.alternatywa.com/artysci.html "Pasja".] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100524104543/http://www.alternatywa.com/artysci.html |date=May 24, 2010 }} Alternatywa.com. Retrieved 20 May 2010. {{pl icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==''Pasja'' (2002)==
[[Blasphemy]] charges were levelled against Nieznalska after an exhibition featuring the 2002 work ''Pasja'' (''"Passion"''), an artistic installation concerned with the themes of [[masculinity]] and [[suffering]].&lt;ref name = "Sinkiewicz December 2006"/&gt;&lt;ref name = "Feminist Revolt"&gt;Leskowicz, Pawel. [http://www.lilithgallery.com/feminist/Feminist_Revolt_Poland.html "Feminist Revolt: Censorship of Women’s Art in Poland".] The Lilith Gallery of Toronto. Retrieved 20 May 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = "HF March 2010"/&gt; The installation was displayed at the experimental Gdańsk, [[Wyspa Gallery]], an institution associated with the academy, and consisted of two elements: a large [[Greek cross]] made of metal was suspended from the ceiling of the gallery, and covered; its center was filled in with an image of a man's [[hips]], [[thighs]], and [[penis]].&lt;ref name = "Art Liberated"&gt;[http://www.artliberated.org/?id=20&amp;p=cases Dorota Nieznalska. ''Pasja'' (''Passion'') , 2002.] Artliberated.org Retrieved 20 May 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Behind the cross, the viewer's attention was drawn to a large video, its display projecting from an overhead angle the face and shoulders of a grimacing man in the act of [[Weight training|weight-lifting]].&lt;ref name = "Art Liberated"/&gt; The viewer's inability to behold the man's body, his other body parts being cut off from the screen, concocted an effect of ambiguity as to the activity of the man on the screen, suggesting that the man's feeling of torment could have been the effect of other kinds of activity.&lt;ref name = "Art Liberated"/&gt; The installation would be described by some as depicting "the penis of [[Jesus Christ|Christ]]" in the ensuing controversy.&lt;ref name = "Baird 2005"/&gt;

==Legal charges of blasphemy==
Gdańsk activists of the [[right-wing]] [[League of Polish Families]] began a petition to the local authorities to open a legal case following the release of television footage of the exhibition.&lt;ref name = "Baird 2005"/&gt;&lt;ref name = "Jarecka Wyborcza 2009"&gt;Jarecka, Dorota (5 June 2009).[http://wyborcza.pl/1,75475,6689861,Nieznalska__katolicy__kulturysci.html "Nieznalska, katolicy, kulturyści".] ''[[Gazeta Wyborcza]]''. Retrieved 20 May 2010. {{pl icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = "Heuer 2003"&gt;Heuer, Megan (June–July 2003). [http://www.brooklynrail.org/2003/06/art/gender "Architectures of Gender: Contemporary Women’s Art in Poland".] ''[[The Brooklyn Rail]]''. Retrieved 20 May 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Complaints about ''Pasja'' led to Nieznalska's being summoned to report to the local police on 2 March 2002. The city's [[Rightism|rightist]] municipal councilors quickly closed the exhibition while the young artist, insisting that her intention was to focus on "the cult of the male body", became the defendant of a trial concerning Nieznalska's alleged violation of the [[criminal code]].&lt;ref name = "WV: Arts and the Church"/&gt; Nieznalska's upcoming exhibits in [[Słupsk]] and [[Ostrów Wielkopolski]] were cancelled after further intervention from the League of Polish Families.&lt;ref name = "Baird 2005"/&gt; Members of the [[Polish nationalism|nationalist]] youth group ''[[Młodzież Wszechpolska]]'' threatened to "hang such artists" and "shave their heads, like the [[Armia Krajowa|Home Army]] did with women who were in close relationships with [the] [[Nazi Germany|Germans]]"&lt;ref name = "Raster 2003"&gt;Szylak, Aneta &amp; Grzegorz Klaman (20 July 2003). [http://www.raster.art.pl/english/artykuly/nieznalska.htm "The Case of Dorota Nieznalska".] ''Raster''. Retrieved 20 May 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

At the conclusion of the first legal process in 2003, the court found Nieznalska guilty of "offending religious feelings", a violation of the ban on [[blasphemy]] within Article 196 of the [[criminal code]].&lt;ref name = "Feminist Revolt"/&gt; Judge [[Tomasz Zieliński]] denied that Nieznalska's work was entitled to any special constitutional protection as an object of art, stating that "the fact that a work is within the boundaries of art has no significance for whether it can offend the feelings of other people."&lt;ref name = "Levine 66-67"&gt;{{cite book|last=Levine|first=Caroline|title=Provoking Democracy: Why We Need the Arts|publisher=Wiley-Blackwell|year=2007|pages=66–67|isbn=1-4051-5926-X}}&lt;/ref&gt; The court ordered Nieznalska to perform six months of unpaid [[community service]].&lt;ref name = "Levine 66-67"/&gt; The trial prosecutor had originally demanded a fine of 2000 ''[[złoty]]'', but the court decided to increase the penalty.&lt;ref name = "WV: Arts and the Church"/&gt; Judge Zieliński additionally forbade Nieznalska from traveling out of the country.&lt;ref name = "Levine 66-67"/&gt; The local deputies of the League of Polish Families present during the sentencing clapped to express their approval.&lt;ref name = "WV: Arts and the Church"/&gt;

Controversy surrounding Nieznalska's installation, already boiling during the initial trial, persisted well into the appeals process. An unsigned [[editorial]] in Poland's [[English language|Anglophone]] monthly ''[[The Warsaw Voice]]'', summing up the court case shortly after the initial verdict as a battle between the [[Leftism|left]] and [[Rightism|right]] - albeit "the first of its kind" for modern Poland - treated Nieznalska as "a tasteless provocateur, covering up her lack of genuine talent with shock tactics" and cited the opinion of [[Franciszek Starowieyski]], "one of the best-known Polish sculptors, himself rather partial to unconventional works", who "said before the beginning of the lawsuit that the one to blame was not the novice artist but the curator of the Gdańsk gallery. According to Starowieyski, Nieznalska's installation was of such a low artistic standard that it should never have been exhibited. Many other known artists, while not approving of the sentence, agreed that if not for the scandal, Nieznalska's work would have stood little chance of making it into reputable galleries."&lt;ref name = "WV: Arts and the Church"/&gt; The former [[President of Poland|president]] [[Lech Wałęsa]] spoke out against Nieznalska and supported a [[Hardline|hard line]], maintaining that the artist's sentence was insufficiently severe.&lt;ref name = "Baird 2005"/&gt; The fine arts professors supporting the Wyspa exhibitions decided to atone for the mistake by closing the gallery.&lt;ref name = "Raster 2003"/&gt;

The more [[Liberalism|liberal]] sections of Polish society stood up in support of the sculptor's right to free artistic expression. A letter of protest signed about 1500 artists, professionals, and other concerned citizens argued for "civic freedoms" and art as "one sphere" of "freedom, incorrectness, difference."&lt;ref name = "Levine 66-67"/&gt; An [[Opinion journalism|opinion piece]] by [[Andrzej Osęka]] for the liberal daily ''[[Gazeta Wyborcza]]'' compared the Nieznalska case to the 2005 [[Jyllands-Posten controversy|''Jyllands-Posten'' controversy]] in Denmark, noting that whereas the Danish newspaper suffered no legal consequences on account of its publication of a cartoon deliberately offensive to the [[Islam|Muslim faith]] in spite of loud outcries from Muslim communities around the world, Nieznalska's case had resulted in a campaign of legal intimidation because of poor legislation and the judges' deference to the politicians.&lt;ref name = "Osęka Wyborcza 2005"&gt;Osęka, Andrzej (12 February 2005). [http://wyborcza.pl/2029020,75515,3034342.html "Bojaźliwi bluźniercy".] ''[[Gazeta Wyborcza]]''. Retrieved 20 May 2010. {{pl icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Adam Mickiewicz University]] [[art historian]] [[Pawel Leszkowicz]] compared Nieznalska to [[Alicja Zebrowska]] and [[Katarzyna Kozyra]], two other female artists attacked for immoral works in the 1990s.&lt;ref name = "Feminist Revolt"/&gt;

Two former Wyspa staff - curator [[Aneta Szylak]] and director Grzegorz Klaman, Nieznalska's former instructor - wrote that while "[s]ince the times of [[Plato]], the academy [had been] a place for intellectual and artistic discourse", the principle "was broken when the gallery closed... Because she had the courage to show 'Pasja', Nieznalska had her scholarships and subsidies cut off; she has been stigmatized and censored... A spectacular political sham is [the League of Polish Families'] typical marketing strategy, and the judge acted just like they wanted him to."&lt;ref name = "Raster 2003"/&gt;

Nieznalska was acquitted after an arduous process and multiple appeals in June 2009.&lt;ref name = "Jarecka Wyborcza 2009"/&gt;&lt;ref name = "Sinkiewicz December 2009"&gt;Sienkiewicz, Karol (December 2009). [http://www.culture.pl/en/culture/artykuly/es_sienkiewicz_podsumowanie_roku_2009 "Visual Arts - Summary of 2009".] ''Polish Culture''. Retrieved 20 May 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Gazeta Wyborcza'' hailed the decision as "a toast to freedom."&lt;ref name = "Jarecka Wyborcza 2009"/&gt;

The [[European Humanist Federation]] has alleged that Polish prosecutors have been trying to revive the case in 2010.&lt;ref name = "HF March 2010"&gt;(March 2010). [http://www.humanistfederation.eu/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=280 "The Case of Dorota Nieznalska".] The [[European Humanist Federation]]. Retrieved 20 May 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Polish reports denied that Nieznalska would be subjected to a third trial, emphasizing the acquittal as binding.&lt;ref name = "Trojmiasto March 2010"&gt;Szaro, Grzegorz (11 March 2010). [http://trojmiasto.gazeta.pl/trojmiasto/1,35636,7649764,Nieznalska_uniewinniona__procesu_nie_bedzie.html "Nieznalska uniewinniona, procesu nie będzie".] ''Wiadomości Trójmiasto''. Gazeta.pl. Retrieved 20 May 2010. {{pl icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
Official websites:
* [http://www.nieznalska.com http://www.nieznalska.com]
* [http://nieznalska.art.pl http://nieznalska.art.pl]
The blasphemy case:
* [http://www.mitpressjournals.org/doi/abs/10.1162/dram.2007.51.2.176?journalCode=dram "The Anatomy of Blasphemy: Passion and the Trial of Dorota Nieznalska"]: ''[[The Drama Review]]'' article on the Nieznalska blasphemy trial by Magda Romanska (2007).

{{Authority control}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Nieznalska, Dorota Alicja}}
[[Category:1973 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Censorship in the arts]]
[[Category:People from Gdynia]]
[[Category:People prosecuted for blasphemy]]
[[Category:Polish artists]]
[[Category:Polish sculptors]]
[[Category:Polish women artists]]
[[Category:Polish atheists]]</text>
      <sha1>5a2zs13or6foc80snxwflonp0inr2o0</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Dream art</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>885257</id>
    <revision>
      <id>849831616</id>
      <parentid>839915558</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-07-11T17:17:41Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Filedelinkerbot</username>
        <id>20611691</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bot: Removing [[c:File:The Sleep of Reason Produces Monsters (Reminiscence).jpg]] , deleted by [[:C:User:Jcb|Jcb]] (Copyright violation; see [[Commons:COM:Licensing|Commons:Licensing]] -).</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="11392">{{unfocused|date=October 2017}}
{{Refimprove|date=August 2010}}
[[Image:Pierre-Cécile Puvis de Chavannes 003.jpg|thumb|250px|right|Pierre-Cécile Puvis de Chavannes: ''The Dream'', 1883]]
'''Dream art''' is any form of [[art]] directly based on material from [[dream]]s, or which employs dream-like imagery.

==History==
References to dreams ''in'' art are as old as literature itself: the story of [[Gilgamesh]], the [[Bible]], and the [[Iliad]] all describe dreams of major characters and the meanings thereof. However, dreams ''as'' art, without a "real" frame story, appear to be a later development—though there is no way to know whether many premodern works were dream-based.

In European literature, the [[Romanticism|Romantic]] movement emphasized the value of emotion and irrational inspiration. "Visions", whether from dreams or intoxication, served as raw material and were taken to represent the artist's highest creative potential.

In the late 19th and early 20th centuries, [[Symbolism (arts)|Symbolism]] and [[Expressionism]] introduced dream imagery into visual art. Expressionism was also a literary movement, and included the later work of the playwright [[August Strindberg]], who coined the term "dream play" for a style of narrative that did not distinguish between fantasy and reality.

At the same time, discussion of dreams reached a new level of public awareness in the Western world due to the work of [[Sigmund Freud]], who introduced the notion of the [[subconscious]] mind as a field of scientific inquiry. Freud greatly influenced the 20th-century [[Surrealist]]s, who combined the visionary impulses of Romantics and Expressionists with a focus on the unconscious as a creative tool, and an assumption that apparently irrational content could contain significant meaning, perhaps more so than rational content.

The invention of film and [[animation]] brought new possibilities for vivid depiction of nonrealistic events, but films consisting ''entirely'' of dream imagery have remained an avant-garde rarity. [[Comic book]]s and [[comic strip]]s have explored dreams somewhat more often, starting with [[Winsor McCay]]'s popular newspaper strips; the trend toward confessional works in [[alternative comics]] of the 1980s saw a proliferation of artists drawing their own dreams.

In the collection, [https://www.amazon.com/dp/0982869509 The Committee of Sleep], Harvard psychologist [[Deirdre Barrett]] identifies modern dream-inspired art such as paintings including Jasper Johns's ''Flag'', much of the work of Jim Dine and Salvador Dalí, novels ranging from "Sophie's Choice" to works by Anne Rice and Stephen King and films including Robert Altman's ''Three Women'', John Sayles ''Brother from Another Planet'' and Ingmar Bergman's ''Wild Strawberries''. That book also describes how Paul McCartney's ''Yesterday'' was heard by him in a dream and Most of Billy Joel's and Ladysmith Black Mambazo's music has originated in dreams.

Dream material continues to be used by a wide range of contemporary artists for various purposes. This practice is considered by some to be of psychological value for the artist—independent of the artistic value of the results—as part of the discipline of "dream work".

The international [[Association for the Study of Dreams]][http://www.asdreams.org] holds an annual juried show of visual dream art.

==Notable works directly based on dreams==
{{Unreferenced section|date=March 2009}}

===[[Visual art]]===
* Many works by [[William Blake]] (1757–1827)
* Many works by [[Salvador Dalí]] (1904–1989)
* Many works by [[Man Ray]]
* Many works by [[Max Magnus Norman]]
* Many works by [[Elle Nicolai]]
* Many works by [[Odilon Redon]] (1840–1916)
* Many works by [[Jonathan Borofsky]] (born 1942)
* Many works by [[Jim Shaw (artist)|Jim Shaw]] (born 1952)
* Many works by David Reisman (born 1958)[http://www.news-gazette.com/reprintreqs/reisman/reisman.html]
* Many works by Jane Gifford (www.janegifford.co.uk)
* The works of Alan Sweeney [http://www.alansweeney.com/]
* Online illustrated daily dreams of Robin Whitmore [http://robinwhitmoredreamdiary.blogspot.com/]
* Many works by Kevin Coffee [http://www.coffeespill.com/]
* Many works by Carl Linkhart [https://web.archive.org/web/20111202065909/http://home.earthlink.net/~carllinkhart/index.html]
* Alfredo Arcia's art [http://dart.fine-art.com/squery.asp?BSearch=Arcia&amp;BSearchType=name]
* Sheila Heldebrand Toth's collages [https://web.archive.org/web/20100820173327/http://sstoth0.tripod.com/dreamimages/id38.html]
* Art presented on exhibitions of the International Association for the Study of Dreams [http://www.asdreams.org/subidxshowart.htm]

===[[Literature]]===
* "[[Kubla Khan]]" (1816) by [[Samuel Taylor Coleridge]] (possibly based on a dream provoked by [[opium]])
* ''[[Frankenstein]]'' (1818) by [[Mary Shelley]]
* ''[[The Strange Case of Dr. Jekyll and Mr. Hyde]]'' (1886) by [[Robert Louis Stevenson]]
* ''[[The Dream-Quest of Unknown Kadath]]'' (1927) and other works by [[H.P. Lovecraft]]
* ''[[The Art of Dreaming]]'' (1993) {{ISBN|0-06-092554-X}} [[Carlos Castaneda]]
* ''The Facts of Winter'' (2005) by [[Paul LaFarge]]
* Most of [[Clive Barker]]'s work
*  [[Dracula]] Bram Stoker claimed was inspired by a nightmare he had experienced

===[[Film]]===
{{main|Oneiric (film theory)}}
* Several films of [[Andrei Tarkovsky]], most notably ''[[The Mirror (1975 film)|The Mirror]]''
* The major films of [[Sergei Parajanov]], most notably ''[[The Color of Pomegranates|Sayat Nova]]'' and ''[[Shadows of Forgotten Ancestors]]''
* Much of the filmography of [[David Lynch]] (e.g. ''[[Eraserhead]]'', ''[[Blue Velvet (film)|Blue Velvet]]'', ''[[Mulholland Drive (film)|Mulholland Drive]]'', etc.)
* ''[[The Brother from Another Planet]]'' by [[John Sayles]]
* ''[[Dreams (1990 film)|Dreams]]'' (1990) by [[Akira Kurosawa]]
* Many works of [[Federico Fellini]] (1920–1993)
* ''[[Meshes of the Afternoon]]'' (1943), ''[[At Land]]'' (1944), and ''[[Ritual in Transfigured Time]]'' (1946) by [[Maya Deren]].
* ''[[3 Women]]'' (1977) by [[Robert Altman]]
* ''[[Waking Life]]'' (2001) by [[Richard Linklater]]
* ''[[Eternal Sunshine of the Spotless Mind]]'' (2004) and ''[[Science of Sleep]]'' (2006) by [[Michel Gondry]]
* ''The works of [[Luis Buñuel]]
* ''[[Paprika (2006 film)|Paprika]]'' (2006) by [[Satoshi Kon]]
* ''[[Eyes Wide Shut]]'' (1999) by [[Stanley Kubrick]]
* [[Inception]] (2010) directed by [[Christopher Nolan]]

===[[Comics]]===
* Many short works of [[Julie Doucet]]
* Many short works of [[David B.]]
* ''Jim'' by [[Jim Woodring]]
* ''Psychonaut'' by [[Aleksandar Zograf]]
* ''Rare Bit Fiends'' by [[Rick Veitch]]
* ''[[Slow Wave]]'' by [[Jesse Reklaw]]

===[[Music]]===
* ''[[Devil's Trill Sonata]]'' by [[Giuseppe Tartini]]
* ''[[La Villa Strangiato]]'' by [[Rush (band)|Rush]]
* ''[[Selected Ambient Works Volume II]]'' by [[Aphex Twin]]
* ''[[Yesterday (Beatles song)|Yesterday]]'' by [[Paul McCartney]]
* ''[[El Cielo (album)|El Cielo]]'' by [[Dredg]]
* ''[[Inside a Dream (song)|Inside a Dream]]'' by [[Jane Wiedlin]]
* ''[[Isn't Anything]] and [[Loveless (My Bloody Valentine album)|Loveless]]'' by [[My Bloody Valentine (band)|My Bloody Valentine]]
* ''[[And the Glass-Handed Kites]]'' and other works of [[Mew (band)|Mew]]
* ''[[If I Needed You]]'' by [[Townes Van Zandt]]
* ''[[The Pros and Cons of Hitch Hiking]]'' by [[Roger Waters]]
* ''Lucid Dreams'' by [[Celia Green]]
* ''Micro Cuts'' by [[Muse (band)|Muse]]
* ''[[My Fruit Psychobells...A Seed Combustible]], [[Bath (album)|Bath]],  [[Leaving Your Body Map]], and [[Part the Second]]'' by [[maudlin of the Well]]
*'' Dimethyltryptamine by [[Jay Electronica]] 
* ''[[Until the Quiet Comes]]'' by [[Flying Lotus]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Lawler |first=Karen |date=October 5, 2012 |url=http://www.state.ie/album-reviews/flying-lotus-until-the-quiet-comes |title=Flying Lotus – Until The Quiet Comes |journal=[[State (magazine)|State]] |location=County Kildare |accessdate=2012-10-05 |archiveurl=https://www.webcitation.org/6BYeQ6Y1i?url=http://www.state.ie/album-reviews/flying-lotus-until-the-quiet-comes |archivedate=2012-10-20 |deadurl=no |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Works intended to resemble dreams, but not directly based on them==

===[[Novel]]s===
* ''[[Alice's Adventures in Wonderland]]'' by [[Lewis Carroll]] (1865)
* ''The Nightmare has Triplets'' trilogy by [[James Branch Cabell]]
** ''Smirt: An Urbane Nightmare'' (1934)
** ''Smith: A Sylvan Interlude'' (1934)
** ''Smire: An Acceptance in the Third Person'' (1937)
* ''The Coma'' by [[Alex Garland]]
* "[[Darkness at Noon]]" by Arther Koestler
* Most of the works of [[Franz Kafka]]
* ''[[Finnegans Wake]]'' by [[James Joyce]]

===[[Drama]]===
* ''A Dream Play'' (1901) and other plays by [[August Strindberg]] during his Symbolist and Expressionist periods
* ''Copacabana'' by Barry Manilow (born 1947)

===[[Film]]===
* ''[[Un chien andalou]]'' (1927) by [[Luis Buñuel]] and [[Salvador Dalí]] (actually started when Buñuel and Dalí discussed their dreams, then decided to start with two of them and make a film)
* Many films by [[Maya Deren]] (1917–1961)
* Many films by [[David Lynch]], especially ''[[Eraserhead]]'' and ''[[Mulholland Drive (film)|Mulholland Drive]]'', contain dreamlike elements.
* Dream scenes are popular in many [[horror movie]]s, notably the ''[[Nightmare on Elm Street]]'' series
* ''[[The Trial (1962 film)|The Trial]]'' by [[Orson Welles]] (based on the novel by [[Franz Kafka]])
* ''[[Eternal Sunshine of the Spotless Mind]]'' features around witnessing the effects of having one's memory erased through dreaming.
* ''[[The Science of Sleep]]'' (2006) by [[Michel Gondry]]
* ''[[The Cell]]'' (2000) by [[Tarsem Singh]] contains vivid and surreal imagery to convey the mind-world of a serial killer.
* ''[[The Good Night]]'' (2007) by [[Jake Paltrow]]
* The animated science fiction film ''[[Paprika (2006 film)|Paprika]]'' (2006) by [[Satoshi Kon]] features intense dream imagery.
* ''[[Inception]]'' (2010) by [[Christopher Nolan]] contains extravagant sequences inside the dreams of people through "dream sharing". There are many sequences in 'reality' that also feature very dream-like imagery, questioning the main protagonist's state of consciousness.

===[[Comics]]===
* ''[[Dreams of a Rarebit Fiend]]'' (1904–1921) and ''[[Little Nemo]]'' (1905–1913) by [[Winsor McCay]] (also his animated films)
* [[The Sandman (DC Comics/Vertigo)]] by Neil Gaiman
* Many works of [[Milo Manara]]

==See also==
* [[Fantastic art]]
* [[Dream pop]]
* [[Shoegaze]]
* [[Psychedelic art]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Further reading==
* Dieterle, Bernard and [[ManfredEngel|Engel, Manfred]] (eds.). ''The Dream and the Enlightenment / Le Rêve et les Lumières.'' Paris: Honoré Champion 2003, {{ISBN|2-7453-0672-3}}.
* Dieterle, Bernard and [[ManfredEngel|Engel, Manfred]] (eds.). ''Writing the Dream / Écrire le rêve'' (= Cultural Dream Studies 1). Würzburg: Königshausen &amp; Neumann 2017, {{ISBN|978-3-8260-6120-2}}.

==External links==
* [http://www.ondreaming.org Dreams: Artwork of the Collective Unconscious] (1998) by Gail Bixler-Thomas
* ''[http://www.doctorhugo.org/dreamz/ Fuzzy Dreamz]'' (1996) by [[Dr. Hugo Heyrman]] &amp;mdash;an online art project of short films, forming a [[psychogeography]] of dreams.

[[Category:Art genres]]
[[Category:Dream|Art]]</text>
      <sha1>fjhs16ow4498jbwewzcfnttgk65qimd</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Engraving</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>60125</id>
    <revision>
      <id>866112917</id>
      <parentid>863798541</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-10-28T09:46:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Xezbeth</username>
        <id>86247</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>hatnote</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="32041">{{for|the music album by Forest Swords|Engravings (album)}}
{{redirect|Engrave|the album by Amulet|Engrave (album)}}
{{redirect|Graven|the surname|Graven (surname)|the street in Aarhus, Denmark|Graven, Aarhus}}
{{More footnotes|date=March 2017}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=April 2012}}

[[Image:Dürer-Hieronymus-im-Gehäus.jpg|thumb|''[[Saint Jerome in His Study (Dürer)|St. Jerome in His Study]]'' (1514), an engraving by [[Northern Renaissance]] master [[Albrecht Dürer]]]]
[[File:Engraving.jpg|thumb|Artist and engraver [[Chaim Goldberg]] at work]]

'''Engraving''' is the practice of incising a design onto a hard, usually flat surface by cutting grooves into it with a [[Burin (engraving)|burin]]. The result may be a decorated object in itself, as when silver, gold, steel, or [[Glass engraving|glass]] are engraved, or may provide an [[Intaglio (printmaking)|intaglio]] printing plate, of copper or another metal, for printing images on paper as prints or illustrations; these images are also called "engravings". Engraving is one of the oldest and most important techniques in [[printmaking]]. [[Wood engraving]] is a form of [[relief printing]] and is not covered in this article.

Engraving was a historically important method of producing images on paper in artistic [[printmaking]], in [[mapmaking]], and also for commercial reproductions and illustrations for books and magazines. It has long been replaced by various [[photographic]] processes in its commercial applications and, partly because of the difficulty of learning the technique, is much less common in printmaking, where it has been largely replaced by [[etching]] and other techniques.

"Engraving" is also loosely but incorrectly used for any old black and white print; it requires a degree of expertise to distinguish engravings from prints using other techniques such as [[etching]] in particular, but also [[mezzotint]] and other techniques. Many [[old master print]]s also combine techniques on the same plate, further confusing matters.  [[Line engraving]] and [[steel engraving]] cover use for reproductive prints, illustrations in books and magazines, and similar uses, mostly in the 19th century, and often not actually using engraving.

Traditional engraving, by [[Burin (engraving)|burin]] or with the use of machines, continues to be practised by [[goldsmith]]s, glass engravers, [[Gunsmith#Gun Engraver|gunsmiths]] and others, while modern industrial techniques such as [[photoengraving]] and [[laser engraving]] have many important applications. [[Engraved gem]]s were an important art in the ancient world, revived at the Renaissance, although the term traditionally covers [[relief]] as well as intaglio carvings, and is essentially a branch of sculpture rather than engraving, as drills were the usual tools.

==Terms==
[[Image:gravers.jpg|thumb|left|An assortment of hand engraving tools]]

Other terms often used for printed engravings are '''copper engraving''', '''copper-plate engraving''' or ''[[line engraving]]''. [[Steel engraving]] is the same technique, on steel or steel-faced plates, and was mostly used for banknotes, illustrations for books, magazines and reproductive prints, [[letterhead]]s and similar uses from about 1790 to the early 20th century, when the technique became less popular, except for banknotes and other forms of [[security printing]]. Especially in the past, "engraving" was often used very loosely to cover several printmaking techniques, so that many so-called engravings were in fact produced by totally different techniques, such as etching or [[mezzotint]]. "Hand engraving" is a term sometimes used for engraving objects other than printing plates, to inscribe or decorate jewellery, firearms, trophies, knives and other fine metal goods. Traditional engravings in printmaking are also "hand engraved", using just the same techniques to make the lines in the plate.

==Process==
{{references|section|date=October 2016}}
[[Image:Louis George Gravur 1.jpg|thumb|right|At an engravers workshop: Miniature engraving on a ''[[Louis George]]'' watch movement: Smallest engraving of the royal [[Prussia]]n eagle on a watch movement. It takes about 100 passes to create the figure.]]
{{double image|right|Norblin Ecce Homo 02.jpg|205|Norblin Ecce Homo 01.jpg|200|''Ecce Homo'' by [[Jean-Pierre Norblin de La Gourdaine|Jan Norblin]], original print (left) and copper [[etching]] plate (right) with composition reversed ([[National Museum, Warsaw|National Museum]] in [[Warsaw]]).}}

Each graver is different and has its own use. '''Engravers''' use a hardened steel tool called a burin, or graver, to cut the design into the surface, most traditionally a copper plate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://expositions.bnf.fr/bosse/grand/214.htm|title=Abraham Bosse|year=1645|publisher=Bibliothèque nationale de France|accessdate=15 July 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, modern hand engraving artists use burins or gravers to cut a variety of metals such as silver, nickel, steel, brass, gold, titanium, and more, in applications from weaponry to jewellery to motorcycles to found objects. Modern professional engravers can engrave with a resolution of up to 40 lines per mm in high grade work creating game scenes and scrollwork. [[Die (manufacturing)|Dies]] used in mass production of molded parts are sometimes hand engraved to add special touches or certain information such as part numbers.

In addition to hand engraving, there are engraving machines that require less human finesse and are not directly controlled by hand. They are usually used for lettering, using a [[pantograph]]ic system. There are versions for the insides of rings and also the outsides of larger pieces. Such machines are commonly used for inscriptions on rings, lockets and presentation pieces.

===Tools and gravers or burins===
Gravers come in a variety of shapes and sizes that yield different line types. The burin produces a unique and recognizable quality of line that is characterized by its steady, deliberate appearance and clean edges. The angle tint tool has a slightly curved tip that is commonly used in printmaking. Florentine liners are flat-bottomed tools with multiple lines incised into them, used to do fill work on larger areas or to create uniform shade lines that are fast to execute. Ring gravers are made with particular shapes that are used by jewelry engravers in order to cut inscriptions inside rings. Flat gravers are used for fill work on letters, as well as "wriggle" cuts on most musical instrument engraving work, remove background, or create bright cuts. Knife gravers are for line engraving and very deep cuts. Round gravers, and flat gravers with a radius, are commonly used on silver to create bright cuts (also called '''bright-cut engraving'''), as well as other hard-to-cut metals such as nickel and steel. Square or V-point gravers are typically square or elongated diamond-shaped and used for cutting straight lines. V-point can be anywhere from 60 to 130 [[Degree (angle)|degrees]], depending on purpose and effect. These gravers have very small cutting points. Other tools such as [[mezzotint]] rockers, roulets and burnishers are used for texturing effects. Burnishing tools can also be used for certain stone setting techniques.

Musical instrument engraving on American-made brass instruments flourished in the 1920s and utilizes a specialized engraving technique where a flat graver is "walked" across the surface of the instrument to make zig-zag lines and patterns. The method for "walking" the graver may also be referred to as "wriggle" or "wiggle" cuts. This technique is necessary due to the thinness of metal used to make musical instruments versus firearms or jewelry. Wriggle cuts are commonly found on silver Western jewelry and other Western metal work.

===Tool geometry===
[[File:2008-engraving.jpg|right|thumb|Stone engraving]]
Tool geometry is extremely important for accuracy in hand engraving. When sharpened for most applications, a graver has a "face", which is the top of the graver, and a "heel", which is the bottom of the graver; not all tools or application require a heel. These two surfaces meet to form a point that cuts the metal. The geometry and length of the heel helps to guide the graver smoothly as it cuts the surface of the metal. When the tool's point breaks or chips, even on a microscopic level, the graver can become hard to control and produces unexpected results. Modern innovations have brought about new types of carbide that resist chipping and breakage, which hold a very sharp point longer between resharpening than traditional metal tools.

===Tool sharpening===
Sharpening a graver or burin requires either a [[sharpening stone]] or wheel. Harder carbide and steel gravers require diamond-grade sharpening wheels; these gravers can be polished to a mirror finish using a ceramic or cast iron lap, which is essential in creating bright cuts. Several low-speed, reversible sharpening system made specifically for hand engravers are available that reduce sharpening time. Fixtures that secure the tool in place at certain angles and geometries are also available to take the guesswork from sharpening to produce accurate points. Very few master engravers exist today who rely solely on "feel" and muscle memory to sharpen tools. These master engravers typically worked for many years as an apprentice, most often learning techniques decades before modern machinery was available for hand engravers. These engravers typically trained in such countries as Italy and Belgium, where hand engraving has a rich and long heritage of masters.

===Artwork design===
Design or artwork is generally prepared in advance, although some professional and highly experienced hand engravers are able to draw out minimal outlines either on paper or directly on the metal surface just prior to engraving. The work to be engraved may be lightly scribed on the surface with a sharp point, laser marked, drawn with a fine permanent marker (removable with acetone) or pencil, transferred using various chemicals in conjunction with inkjet or laser printouts, or [[Stipple engraving|stippled]]. Engraving artists may rely on hand drawing skills, copyright-free designs and images, computer-generated artwork, or common design elements when creating artwork.

===Handpieces===
Originally, handpieces varied little in design as the common use was to push with the handle placed firmly in the center of the palm. With modern pneumatic engraving systems, handpieces are designed and created in a variety of shapes and power ranges. Handpieces are made using various methods and materials. Knobs may be handmade from wood, molded and engineered from plastic, or machine-made from brass, steel, or other metals. The most widely known hand engraving tool maker, GRS Tools in Kansas is an American-owned and operated company that manufacture handpieces as well as many other tools for various applications in metal engraving.

===Cutting the surface===
[[Image:Louis George Meistergraveurin 2.jpg|thumb|left|Master engraver ennobling a watch movement. Top level engravers work under a [[stereo microscope]]. ]]

The actual engraving is traditionally done by a combination of pressure and manipulating the work-piece. The traditional "hand push" process is still practiced today, but modern technology has brought various mechanically assisted engraving systems. Most pneumatic engraving systems require an air source that drives air through a hose into a handpiece, which resembles a traditional engraving handle in many cases, that powers a mechanism (usually a piston). The air is actuated by either a foot control (like a gas pedal or sewing machine) or newer palm / hand control. This mechanism replaces either the "hand push" effort or the effects of a hammer. The internal mechanisms move at speeds up to 15,000 strokes per minute, thereby greatly reducing the effort needed in traditional hand engraving. These types of pneumatic systems are used for power assistance only and do not guide or control the engraving artist. One of the major benefits of using a pneumatic system for hand engraving is the reduction of fatigue and decrease in time spent working.

Hand engraving artists today employ a combination of hand push, pneumatic, rotary, or hammer and chisel methods. Hand push is still commonly used by modern hand engraving artists who create "bulino" style work, which is highly detailed and delicate, fine work; a great majority, if not all, traditional printmakers today rely solely upon hand push methods. Pneumatic systems greatly reduce the effort required for removing large amounts of metal, such as in deep relief engraving or Western bright cut techniques.

===Finishing===
Finishing the work is often necessary when working in metal that may rust or where a colored finish is desirable, such as a firearm. A variety of spray lacquers and finishing techniques exist to seal and protect the work from exposure to the elements and time. Finishing also may include lightly sanding the surface to remove small chips of metal called "burrs" that are very sharp and unsightly. Some engravers prefer high contrast to the work or design, using black paints or inks to darken removed (and lower) areas of exposed metal. The excess paint or ink is wiped away and allowed to dry before lacquering or sealing, which may or may not be desired by the artist.

===Modern hand engraving===
[[File:Hand engraving tool.jpg|thumb|Hand Engraving Tool Example]]

Because of the high level of microscopic detail that can be achieved by a master engraver, [[counterfeit]]ing of engraved designs is well-nigh impossible, and modern [[banknote]]s are almost always engraved, as are plates for printing money, checks, bonds and other security-sensitive papers. The engraving is so fine that a normal printer cannot recreate the detail of hand engraved images, nor can it be scanned. In the [[Bureau of Engraving and Printing]], more than one hand engraver will work on the same plate, making it nearly impossible for one person to duplicate all the engraving on a particular banknote or document.

The modern discipline of hand engraving, as it is called in a [[metalworking]] context, survives largely in a few specialized fields. The highest levels of the art are found on firearms and other metal weaponry, jewellery, and musical instruments.

In most commercial markets today, hand engraving has been replaced with milling using CNC engraving or [[milling machine]]s. Still, there are certain applications where use of hand engraving tools cannot be replaced.

===Machine engraving===
[[File:1847Colt Walker.jpg|thumb|1847 Colt Walker pistol with roll engraved cylinder]]
In some instances, images or designs can be transferred to metal surfaces via mechanical process. One such process is roll stamping or roller-die engraving. In this process, a hardened image die is pressed against the destination surface using extreme pressure to impart the image. In the 1800s [[pistol cylinder]]s were often decorated via this process to impart a continuous scene around its surface.

===Computer-aided machine engraving===
[[Image:Engraving on Corian.jpg|thumb|left|Computerized engraving on [[Corian]].]]
Engraving machines such as the K500 (packaging) or K6 (publication) by Hell Gravure Systems use a diamond stylus to cut cells. Each cell creates one printing dot later in the process. A K6 can have up to 18 engraving heads each cutting 8.000 cells per second to an accuracy of .1&amp;nbsp;µm and below. They are fully computer-controlled and the whole process of cylinder-making is fully automated.

It is now common place for retail stores (mostly jewellery, silverware or award stores) to have a small computer controlled engrave on site. This enables them to personalise the products they sell. Retail engraving machines tend to be focused around ease of use for the operator and the ability to do a wide variety of items including flat metal plates, jewelry of different shapes and sizes, as well as cylindrical items such as mugs and tankards. They will typically be equipped with a computer dedicated to graphic design that will enable the operator to easily design a text or picture graphic which the software will translate into digital signals telling the engraver machine what to do. Unlike industrial engravers, retail machines are smaller and only use one diamond head. This is interchangeable so the operator can use differently shaped diamonds for different finishing effects. They will typically be able to do a variety of metals and plastics. Glass and crystal engraving is possible, but the brittle nature of the material makes the process more time consuming.

Retail engravers mainly use two different processes. The first and most common 'Diamond Drag' pushes the diamond cutter through the surface of the material and then pulls to create scratches. These direction and depth are controlled by the computer input. The second is 'Spindle Cutter'. This is similar to Diamond Drag, but the engraving head is shaped in a flat V shape, with a small diamond and the base. The machine uses an electronic spindle to quickly rotate the head as it pushes it into the material, then pulls it along whilst it continues to spin. This creates a much bolder impression than diamond drag. It is used mainly for brass plaques and pet tags.

With state-of-the-art machinery it is easy to have a simple, single item complete in under ten minutes.
The engraving process with diamonds is state-of-the-art since the 1960s.

Today laser engraving machines are in development but still mechanical cutting has proven its strength in economical terms and quality. More than 4,000 engravers make approx. 8 Mio printing cylinders worldwide per year.

==History==
''For the printing process, see [[intaglio (printmaking)]]. For the Western art history of engraved prints, see [[old master print]] and [[line engraving]]''

The first evidence for humans engraving patterns is a chiselled shell, dating back between 540,000 and 430,000 years, from Trinil, in Java, Indonesia, where the first Homo erectus was discovered.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.australiangeographic.com.au/news/2014/12/worlds-oldest-engraving-discovered/ World's oldest engraving discovered], Australian Geographic, 4 December 2014&lt;/ref&gt; Hatched banding upon ostrich eggshells used as water containers found in South Africa in the [[Diepkloof Rock Shelter]] and dated to the [[Middle Stone Age]] around 60,000 BC are the next documented case of human engraving.&lt;ref name="Texier"&gt;Texier PJ, Porraz G, Parkington J, Rigaud JP, Poggenpoel C, Miller C, Tribolo C, Cartwright C, Coudenneau A, Klein R, Steele T, Verna C. (2010). "A Howiesons Poort tradition of engraving ostrich eggshell containers dated to 60,000 years ago at Diepkloof Rock Shelter, South Africa". ''Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences USA''. {{doi|10.1073/pnas.0913047107}} {{PMID|20194764}}&lt;/ref&gt; Engraving on bone and ivory is an important technique for the [[Art of the Upper Paleolithic]], and larger engraved [[petroglyph]]s on rocks are found from many prehistoric periods and cultures around the world.

In [[Ancient history|antiquity]], the only engraving on metal that could be carried out is the shallow grooves found in some jewellery after the beginning of the 1st Millennium B.C. The majority of so-called engraved designs on ancient gold rings or other items were produced by [[chasing (metalworking)|chasing]] or sometimes a combination of [[lost-wax casting]] and chasing. [[Engraved gem]] is a term for any carved or engraved semi-precious stone; this was an important small-scale art form in the ancient world, and remained popular until the 19th century.
[[File:Battle of Engravers by George Cruikshank 1828.jpg|thumb|left|250px|''Battle of Engravers'', [[satire|satirical]] [[etching]] by [[George Cruikshank]], showing hypothetical battle between the engravers, including [[William Hogarth]], [[Antoine Masson]], [[William Woollett]], [[Jean-Joseph Balechou]], [[Albrecht Dürer]] and [[Marcantonio Raimondi]].]]
However the use of [[glass engraving]], usually using a wheel, to cut decorative scenes or figures into glass vessels, in imitation of [[hardstone carving]]s, appears as early as the first century AD,&lt;ref name="Caron"&gt;Caron, B., A Roman Figure-Engraved Glass Bowl. Metropolitan Museum Journal, 1993. 28: p. 47–55.&lt;/ref&gt; continuing into the fourth century CE at urban centers such as Cologne and Rome,&lt;ref name="Fleming"&gt;Fleming, S.J., Roman Glass; reflections on cultural change. 1999, Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Museum of Archaeology and Anthropology.&lt;/ref&gt; and appears to have ceased sometime in the fifth century. Decoration was first based on Greek mythology, before hunting and circus scenes became popular, as well as imagery drawn from the Old and New Testament.&lt;ref name="Fleming" /&gt; It appears to have been used to mimic the appearance of precious metal wares during the same period, including the application of gold leaf, and could be cut free-hand or with lathes. As many as twenty separate stylistic workshops have been identified, and it seems likely that the engraver and vessel producer were separate craftsmen.&lt;ref name="Caron" /&gt;

In the European Middle Ages goldsmiths used engraving to decorate and inscribe metalwork. It is thought that they began to print impressions of their designs to record them. From this grew the engraving of copper printing plates to produce artistic images on paper, known as [[old master print]]s, in Germany in the 1430s. Italy soon followed. Many early engravers came from a goldsmithing background. The first and greatest period of the engraving was from about 1470 to 1530, with such masters as [[Martin Schongauer]], [[Albrecht Dürer]], and [[Lucas van Leiden]].

[[File:Rembrandt - self portrait etching.jpg|thumb|right|Modern impression of Rembrandt's 1639 self-portrait, with the engraving plate.]]
Thereafter engraving tended to lose ground to [[etching]], which was a much easier technique for the artist to learn. But many prints combined the two techniques: although [[Rembrandt]]'s prints are generally all called etchings for convenience, many of them have some burin or drypoint work, and some have nothing else. By the nineteenth century, most engraving was for commercial illustration.

Before the advent of photography, engraving was used to reproduce other forms of art, for example paintings. Engravings continued to be common in newspapers and many books into the early 20th century, as they were cheaper to use in printing than photographic images.

Many classic postage stamps were engraved, although the practice is now mostly confined to particular countries, or used when a more "elegant" design is desired and a limited color range is acceptable.

[[File:Buffalo nickles.jpg|thumb|right|[[Buffalo nickel]]s, coins customised with engraving tools]] 
Modifying the [[relief]] designs on coins is a craft dating back to the 18th century and today modified coins are known colloquially as [[hobo nickel]]s. In the United States, especially during the [[Great Depression]], coin engraving on the large-faced [[Buffalo nickel|Indian Head nickel]] became a way to help make ends meet. The craft continues today, and with modern equipment often produces stunning miniuture sculptural artworks and floral scrollwork.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thisiscolossal.com/2016/10/shaun-hughes-engraving/ Elaborate Floral Scrollwork Engraved on Coins] by Shaun Hughes embellishing existing coin faces with different styles of floral scrollwork (2016).  Retrieved May 27 2018&lt;/ref&gt;

During the mid-20th century, a renaissance in hand-engraving began to take place. With the inventions of pneumatic hand-engraving systems that aided hand-engravers, the art and techniques of hand-engraving became more accessible. 

===Music engraving===
{{main|Music engraving}}
The first music printed from engraved plates dates from 1446 and most printed music was produced through engraving from roughly 1700–1860. From 1860–1990 most printed music was produced through a combination of engraved master plates reproduced through offset lithography.

The first comprehensive account is given by Mme Delusse in her article "Gravure en lettres, en géographie et en musique" in [[Diderot]]'s Encyclopedia. The technique involved a five-pointed raster to score staff lines, various punches in the shapes of notes and standard musical symbols, and various burins and scorers for lines and slurs. For correction, the plate was held on a bench by callipers, hit with a dot punch on the opposite side, and burnished to remove any signs of the defective work. The process involved intensive pre-planning of the layout, and many manuscript scores with engraver's planning marks survive from the 18th and 19th centuries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Poole|first=H. Edmund|title=Music Printing and Publishing|year=1980|publisher=Norton|location=New York|pages=40–54}}&lt;/ref&gt;

By 1837 [[pewter]] had replaced copper as a medium, and Berthiaud gives an account with an entire chapter devoted to music (''Novel manuel complet de l'imprimeur en taille douce'', 1837). Printing from such plates required a separate inking to be carried out cold, and the printing press used less pressure. Generally, four pages of music were engraved on a single plate. Because music engraving houses trained engravers through years of apprenticeship, very little is known about the practice. Fewer than one dozen sets of tools survive in libraries and museums.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Gamble|first=William|title=Music Engraving and Printing: Historical and Technical Treatise|year=1923|publisher=Pitman|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; By 1900 music engravers were established in several hundred cities in the world, but the art of storing plates was usually concentrated with publishers. Extensive bombing of Leipzig in 1944, the home of most German engraving and printing firms, destroyed roughly half the world's engraved music plates.

==Applications today==
[[File:Ars moriendi (Meister E.S.), L.181.png|thumb|[[Ars moriendi]] engraving by Master ES, circa 1450]]

Examples of contemporary uses for engraving include creating text on jewellery, such as pendants or on the inside of [[engagement ring|engagement]]- and [[wedding ring]]s to include text such as the name of the partner, or adding a winner's name to a sports trophy.  Another application of modern engraving is found in the [[printing]] industry. There, every day thousands of pages are mechanically engraved onto [[rotogravure]] cylinders, typically a steel base with a copper layer of about 0.1&amp;nbsp;mm in which the image is transferred. After engraving the image is protected with an approximately 6&amp;nbsp;µm chrome layer. Using this process the image will survive for over a million copies in high speed [[printing press]]es.  Engraving machines such as GUN BOW (one of the leading engraving brands) are the best examples of hand engraving tools, although this type of machine is typically not used for fine hand engraving.
Some schools throughout the world are renowned for their teaching of engraving, like the [[École Estienne]] in Paris.

==Creating tone==
[[Image:Claude Mellan - Face of Christ - WGA14764.jpg|thumb|''Sudarium of Saint Veronica'' by [[Claude Mellan]] (1649), a famous showpiece where the image is formed by a single continuous line, starting on the tip of Christ's nose.]]

In traditional engraving, which is a purely linear medium, the impression of [[half-tone]]s was created by making many very thin parallel lines, a technique called [[hatching]]. When two sets of parallel-line ''hatchings'' intersected each other for higher density, the resulting pattern was known as ''cross-hatching''. Patterns of dots were also used in a technique called [[stippling]], first used around 1505 by [[Giulio Campagnola]]. [[Claude Mellan]] was one of many 17th-century engravers with a very well-developed technique of using parallel lines of varying thickness (known as the "swelling line") to give subtle effects of tone (as was [[Hendrick Goltzius|Goltzius]]) – see picture below. One famous example is his ''[[Veil of Veronica|Sudarium of Saint Veronica]]'' (1649), an engraving of the face of Jesus made from a single spiraling line that starts at the tip of Jesus's nose.

==Biblical references==
The earliest allusion to engraving in the Bible may be the reference to [[Judah (Biblical figure)|Judah]]'s seal ring (Ge 38:18), followed by (Ex 39.30). Engraving was commonly done with pointed tools of iron or even with diamond points. (Jer 17:1).

Each of the two onyx stones on the shoulder-pieces of the high priest’s [[ephod]] was engraved with the names of six different tribes of [[Israel]], and each of the 12 precious stones that adorned his breastpiece was engraved with the name of one of the tribes. The holy sign of dedication, the shining gold plate on the high priest's turban, was engraved with the words: "Holiness belongs to [[Adonai]]." [[Bezalel]], along with Oholiab, was qualified to do this specialized engraving work as well as to train others.—Ex 35:30–35; 28:9–12; 39:6–14, 30.

==Noted engravers==
{{see also|List of printmakers}}
&lt;!-- IT SAYS "NOTED"! That's a polite way of saying VERY FAMOUS --&gt;
[[File:WIERIX, Hieronymus St Michael Slaying the Dragon 1584.jpg|thumb|''St Michael Slaying the Dragon'', 1584, [[Hieronymus Wierix]]]]
Prints:
* [[Jacopo de' Barbari]] (active 1500–1515)
* [[William Blake]] (1757–1827)
* [[Theodore de Bry]] (1528–1598)
* [[Giulio Campagnola]] (active c.1505–1515)
* [[Paul Gustave Doré]] (1832–1883)
* [[Albrecht Dürer]] (1471–1528)
* [[Maso Finiguerra]] (1426–1464)
* [[Hendrick Goltzius]] (c.1558–1617)
* [[Francisco de Goya]] (1746–1828)
* [[William Hamlin]] (1772–1869)
* [[Stanley William Hayter]] (1901–1988)
* [[William Hogarth]] (1697–1764)
* [[Mauricio Lasansky]] (1914–2012)
* [[Lucas van Leyden]] (1494–1533)
* [[Andrea Mantegna]] (c.1431–1506)
* [[Master ES]] (active c.1450–1470)
* [[Israhel van Meckenem]] (c.1445–1501)
* [[Claude Mellan]] (1598–1688)
* [[Matthäus Merian]] (1593–1650)
* [[Willem Panneels]] (c.1600–c.1634)
* [[Alardo de Popma]], (1617–1641)
* [[José Guadalupe Posada]] (1852–1913)
* [[Giovanni Battista Piranesi]] (1720-1778)
* [[Paulus Pontius]] (1603 – 1658)
* [[Jan Saenredam]] (1565–1607)
* [[Nikolaos Ventouras]] (1899–1990)
* [[Georg Matthäus Vischer]] (1628–1696)
* [[Lucas Vorsterman]] (1595–1675)
* [[Anthonie Wierix]] (1552–1624)
* [[Hieronymus Wierix]] (1553–1619)

[[File:Paul Gustave Louis Christophe Doré III.jpg|thumb|Don Quixote engraving by [[Paul Gustave Doré]]]]

Of [[Gemstone|gem]]s:
*Pyrgoteles, [[Alexander the Great|Alexander]]'s gem-engraver
*Theodorus of Samos, [[Polycrates]]' gem-engraver

Of guns:
* [[Malcolm Appleby]]
* [[Geoffroy Gournet]]

Of coins:
* [[Thomas Hugh Paget]]
* [[Leonard Charles Wyon]]
* [[William Wyon]]

Of postage stamps:
* [[Czesław Słania]]
* [[Leonard Charles Wyon]]
* [[William Wyon]]

Of pins:
* [[Godfrey Lundberg]] (1879–1933)

==See also==
* [[Drypoint]]
* [[Laser engraving]]
* [[List of stationery topics]]
* [[Mezzotint]]
* [[Louis Daniel Nimschke]]
* [[Photogravure]]
* [[Toreutics]]

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Engraving}}
{{commons category|Engraved illustrations}}
*[http://libmma.contentdm.oclc.org/cdm/compoundobject/collection/p15324coll10/id/94303/rec/1 Prints &amp; People: A Social History of Printed Pictures], an exhibition catalog from The Metropolitan Museum of Art (fully available online as PDF), which contains material on engraving
* [http://www.metmuseum.org/toah/hd/engr/hd_engr.htm Engraving from The Metropolitan Museum of Art Timeline of Art History]
* [http://engravershive.com Engravers Hive]

{{Jewellery}}

[[Category:Engraving| ]]
[[Category:Jewellery making]]
[[Category:Metalworking]]
[[Category:Printmaking]]
[[Category:Artistic techniques]]</text>
      <sha1>lk4go3gcnvrysm6otj17dgy1suag5tm</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Excessivism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>13461083</id>
    <revision>
      <id>866212051</id>
      <parentid>850606015</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-10-29T00:24:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Cobrahman</username>
        <id>27328543</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Bibliography */ a new article</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="10945">{{multiple issues|
{{news release|1=article|date=December 2016}}
{{original research|date=December 2016}}
{{third-party|date=December 2016}}
}}
'''Excessivism'''  is an art movement which was introduced in 2015 by [[Americans|American]] [[artist]] and [[curator]] [[Kaloust Guedel]] with an exhibition titled ''Excessivist Initiative''.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{cite web|title = Contemporary Art Exhibits at LA Artcore|url = http://www.laartcore.org/New_Website/exhibitions.html|website = www.laartcore.org|accessdate = 2015-10-12|archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20151029101334/http://www.laartcore.org/New_Website/exhibitions.html|archive-date = 2015-10-29|dead-url = yes|df = }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{cite web|title = Kavi Gupta Gallery : News : Roxy Paine - Excessivism, LA Artcore, Los Angeles|url = http://kavigupta.com/news/289|website = kavigupta.com|accessdate = 2015-10-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title = The "EXCESSIVIST INITIATIVE" An Art Exhibition October 2 Through October 29 {{!}} PRLog|url = http://www.prlog.org/12492706-the-excessivist-initiative-an-art-exhibition-october-2-through-october-29.html|website = www.prlog.org|accessdate = 2015-10-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title = Garboushian Gallery Premiers ‘1915’ Exhibit|url = http://asbarez.com/136065/garboushian-gallery-premiers-1915-exhibit/|website = Asbarez.com|accessdate = 2015-10-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = https://www.huffingtonpost.com/shana-nys-dambrot/the-excessivist-initiativ_b_8180840.html |title=Excessivism: Irony, Imbalance and a New Rococo |website = The Huffington Post|date=2015-09-23|accessdate = 2015-10-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; A preview of the exhibition&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{cite web|title = Excessivism: Irony, Imbalance and a New Rococo|url = http://www.huffingtonpost.com/shana-nys-dambrot/the-excessivist-initiativ_b_8180840.html|website = The Huffington Post|accessdate = 2015-10-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; written by art critic and curator Shana Nys Dambrot, titled "Excessivism: Irony, Imbalance and a New Rococo" was published in the ''[[The Huffington Post|Huffington Post]]''.&lt;ref name=":1"/&gt; Its early adopters go back to late 20th century.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title = Early adopters|url = http://www.zadikzadikian.com/resume/|website = Zadik Zadikian|accessdate = 2015-10-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title = Where Stands Postmodern American Poetry: Is Paul Hoover's Anthology the Final Word?|url = http://www.huffingtonpost.com/anis-shivani/where-stands-postmodern-a_b_7641644.html|website = The Huffington Post|accessdate = 2015-10-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Concept==
Excessivism is a reflection, examination, or investigation of every aspect of life in excessive state with particular consideration to the areas that have real and consequential effect on the members of the society.  Subject areas are, but not limited to, economics, politics and psychology. In the area of economics it is a commentary on [[economic materialism]]. It reflects, examines and investigates the excessive desire to acquire material goods beyond one's needs and often means.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; Excessivism depicts the excessive use of resources in an exaggerated way, by means of two- or three-dimensional visual creations, written or spoken words, or in any other manner. It aims at a reflection, examination, or investigation of the capitalist system, devoid of aesthetic, legal, commercial, ethical, moral, racial, or religious considerations.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

The goal of the capitalist system is to deliver profit for private investors, or corporations (without consideration of consequences including human and environmental), as contrasted to cooperatively or state-owned means of wealth. Said structure provides incomparable contribution to economic growth, employment and prosperity. According to [[determinism]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = The Southern Cone Model: The Political Economy of Regional Capitalist Development in Latin America|url = https://books.google.com/books?id=w0N-AgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA24&amp;dq=excessive+economic+determinism&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;q=excessive%2520economic%2520determinism&amp;f=false|publisher = Routledge|date = 2004-08-02|isbn = 9781134327089|first = Nicola|last = Phillips}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Charting a New Course: The Politics of Globalization and Social Transformation|url = https://books.google.com/books?id=5CEGwRutaEEC|publisher = Rowman &amp; Littlefield|date = 2001-01-01|isbn = 9780742508934|first = Fernando Henrique|last = Cardoso|first2 = Mauricio Augusto|last2 = Font}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Crafting Qualitative Research: Working in the Postpositivist Traditions|url = https://books.google.com/books?id=KtDKBgAAQBAJ|publisher = Routledge|date = 2015-02-24|isbn = 9781317473695|first = Pushkala|last = Prasad}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = The Elgar Companion to Radical Political Economy|url = https://books.google.com/books?id=lc6b1Q1Kf1YC|publisher = Edward Elgar Publishing|date = 1994-01-01|isbn = 9781843768647|first = Philip|last = Arestis|first2 = Malcolm C.|last2 = Sawyer}}&lt;/ref&gt; freedom of choice is illusory and society is positioned to function as a reliable producer of excess, the lubricant of the capitalist engine.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

== History ==
The inaugural exhibition of Excessivism took place in LA Artcore Brewery Annex gallery with the title "Excessivist Initiative".&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; And the Excessivism Manifesto was published in [[Downtown News]] weekly in September 2015.&lt;ref&gt;[[Downtown News]], Excessivism Manifesto, September 28, 2015 page 10&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite paper|url=http://www.survivorlibrary.com/library/architect_and_engineer_of_california_vol_22_1910.pdf |title=The Architect and Engineer of California Volume 22 |publisher=The Architect and Engineer Co. |date=August 1910 |accessdate=2017-06-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to an art critic Shana Nys Dambrot the idea was conceived in the studio of the founder based on his personal realizations of his relationship as a consumer with the capitalist environment.&lt;ref name=":1"/&gt;  Excessivism was introduced to the Los Angeles art scene in November 2014 in the Red Pipe gallery in an  exhibition titled ''Excess The New Norm''. It was curated by art critic, publisher and curator Mat Gleason.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Red Pipe Gallery: Kaloust Guedel: Excess The New Norm|url=http://www.artslant.com/la/events/show/353832-excess-the-new-norm|publisher=ArtSlant|accessdate=14 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The artists included in the inaugural exhibition were Brett Baker, Christophe Baudson, Andrew Dadson, [[Ian Davenport]], Jonas Etter, [[Kaloust Guedel]], Don Harger, Zhu Jinshi, Fabian Marcacio, [[Roxy Paine]], Scott Richter, Samvel Saghatelian, Elizabeth Sheppell, Michael Toenges, Michael Villarreal, Danh Vō, Cullen Washington jr., Brigid Watson, Leslie Wayne, [[Ai Weiwei]] and Zadik Zadikian.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":3"&gt;{{cite web|title = The "Excessivist Initiative" an Art Exhibition|url = http://www.prweb.com/releases/2015/09/prweb12967200.htm|website = PRWeb|accessdate = 2015-10-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Bibliography==

*Art &amp; Museum, Pg. 48, Autumn 2017 &lt;ref&gt;https://issuu.com/familyofficeelitemagazine/docs/art-museum-autumn-17-single&lt;/ref&gt;
*Vogue, This Parsons x Kering Empowering Imagination Finalist Is Tackling the Excesses of Overconsumption Head On, May 8 2017, by Nicole Phelps&lt;ref&gt; https://www.vogue.com/article/parsons-kering-overconsumption-ji-won-choi&lt;/ref&gt;
 
*Diversions LA,  February 8, 2017, by Genie Davis &lt;ref&gt;http://diversionsla.com/excessivism-creating-beyond-boundaries/&lt;/ref&gt;
*Artcopyblog, KALOUST GUEDEL’S EXCESSIVISM AND THE RISE OF DONALD TRUMP, by Brenda Haroutunian, JUNE 26, 2016&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Brenda Haroutunian |url=http://www.artcopyblog.com/kaloust-guedels-excessivism-speaks-to-trumps-popularity/ |title=Kaloust Guedel'S Excessivism And Trump'S Rise To Power |publisher=Artcopyblog.com |date=2016-06-26 |accessdate=2017-06-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*WideWalls Magazine, Excessivism - A Phenomenon Every Art Collector Should Know, by Angie Kordic, January 2016&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Angie Kordic |url=http://www.widewalls.ch/excessivism-art-movement |title=Excessivism – A Phenomenon Every Art Collector Should Know &amp;#124; WideWalls |publisher=Widewalls.ch |accessdate=2017-06-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Asbarez, (Armenian), by Ani Tadevosyan, January 13, 2016&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=armenianeditor |url=http://asbarez.com/arm/243919/%D5%86%D5%B8%D6%80-%D5%88%D6%82%D5%B2%D5%B2%D5%B8%D6%82%D5%A9%D5%AB%D6%82%D5%B6-%D4%B1%D6%80%D5%B8%D6%82%D5%A5%D5%BD%D5%BF%D5%B8%D6%82%D5%B4%D5%9D-%D5%8A%D5%A1%D6%80%D5%BF%D5%A1%D5%A4%D6%80%D5%B8/ |title=Նոր Ուղղութիւն Արուեստում՝ Պարտադրում Է Ժամանակակից Մարդը &amp;#124; Asbarez - Armenian |publisher=Asbarez |date=2016-01-13 |accessdate=2017-06-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Gallereo Magazine, The Newest Art Movement You've Never Heard of, Nov. 20, 2015&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.gallereo.com/blog-the-newest-art-movement-you-ve-never-heard-of-post-1851-55.html |title=The Newest Art Movement You've Never Heard Of |publisher=Gallereo.com |date=2015-11-20 |accessdate=2017-06-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*CaliforniaNewswire, New Art Movement, Excessivism, is a Commentary on Economic Materialism, Nov. 02, 2015&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Christopher Simmons |url=http://californianewswire.com/2015/11/02/new-art-movement-excessivism-is-a-commentary-on-economic-materialism-CNW30668_104216.php |title=New Art Movement, Excessivism, is a Commentary on Economic Materialism |publisher=California Newswire |date=2015-11-02 |accessdate=2017-06-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Miami Herald, Excessivism is Best Kept Secret in the Art World, Nov. 02, 2015&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://markets.financialcontent.com/mi.miamiherald/news/read/30936374 |title=Excessivism is Best Kept Secret in the Art World &amp;#124; Financial Content &amp;#124; ${sectionParameter |publisher=Markets.financialcontent.com |date=2015-11-02 |accessdate=2017-06-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Downtown News, Excessivism Manifesto, September 28, 2015, page 10
*Reuters, Why Donald Trump's Bid for Presidency Related to New Art Movement is Essential? Artist Kaloust Guedel Explains, Dec. 14, 2015&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.reuters.com/article/kaloustguedel-idUSnPn532Lx7+84+PRN20151214 ]{{dead link|date=June 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*"Excessivism: Irony, Imbalance and a New Rococo". The Huffington Post. Retrieved 2015-10-12.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Shana Nys Dambrot |url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/shana-nys-dambrot/the-excessivist-initiativ_b_8180840.html |title=Excessivism: Irony, Imbalance and a New Rococo &amp;#124; HuffPost |publisher=Huffingtonpost.com |date=2015-09-23 |accessdate=2017-06-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
*[http://www.excessivism.com/ Official website]

{{Westernart}}

[[Category:Contemporary art movements]]
[[Category:Postmodern art]]
[[Category:Postmodernism]]
[[Category:Art movements]]
[[Category:Contemporary art]]
[[Category:Art genres]]
[[Category:Remodernism]]
[[Category:Theories of aesthetics]]
[[Category:21st century in art]]</text>
      <sha1>jahsln6x1umd4dym1ri5bdfyzi6ibai</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Hierarchy of genres</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>385946</id>
    <revision>
      <id>857849062</id>
      <parentid>851960312</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-09-03T12:28:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Citizen Canine</username>
        <id>33426808</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[MOS:CENTURY]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="24330">[[File:CARRACCI, Annibale - An allegory of Truth and Time (1584-5).JPG|thumb|[[Annibale Carracci]], Allegory of Truth and Time (1584–5), an allegorical [[history painting]] relying very little upon realism.]]
[[File:Retrato del Papa Inocencio X. Roma, by Diego Velázquez.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Diego Velázquez|Velázquez]], [[portrait painting]] of ''[[Pope Innocent X]]'', c. 1650]]
[[Image:Adriaen van Ostade 010.jpg|thumb|A [[genre painting]]. [[Adriaen van Ostade]], ''Fishmonger'', 1660–1670, oil on oak, 29 × 26.5 cm, [[Museum of Fine Arts (Budapest)|Museum of Fine Arts]], Budapest.]]
[[Image:Themistokles von Eckenbrecher Utsikt over Lærdalsøren.jpeg|thumb|A [[landscape art|landscape]]. Themistokles von Eckenbrecher, ''View of Laerdalsoren, on the [[Sognefjord]]'', oil on canvas, 1901.]]
[[File:Snyders Dogs fighting.jpg|thumb|[[Frans Snyders]], ''Dogs Fighting'']]
[[Image:Heinrich Uhl Stillleben.jpg|thumb|A [[still life]]. [[Heinrich Uhl]], ''Still life with Jewelry Box, Opera Glasses, Gloves, and Bouquet of Flowers'', oil on canvas, 50 x 60 cm.]]
[[File:Bruegel, Pieter de Oude - De val van icarus - hi res.jpg|thumb|''[[Landscape with the Fall of Icarus]]'', after [[Pieter Bruegel the Elder|Pieter Bruegel]], an original treatment of a history subject dominated by a genre figure.]]
[[File:Pythagoras advocating vegetarianism (1618-20); Peter Paul Rubens.jpg|thumb|''[[Pythagoras]] Advocating Vegetarianism'' (1618–30), by [[Peter Paul Rubens]] (figures) and [[Frans Snyders]] (still life), mixing history painting and still life in a way typical of [[Flemish Baroque painting]].]]
[[File:Burial of Phocion.jpg|thumb|The ''Burial of [[Phocion]]'' by [[Poussin]], 1648; a couple of small figures upgrade a landscape into a history painting]]
[[File:Paulus Potter - Young Bull.JPG|thumb|[[Paulus Potter]], ''[[The Bull (painting)|The Bull]]'' (1647); 3.4 metres wide. An unusually monumental animal painting that challenges the hierarchy of genres by its size; in the 19th century such works would become common.]]
[[File:Wright of Derby, The Orrery.jpg|thumb|[[Joseph Wright of Derby]], ''[[A Philosopher Lecturing on the Orrery]]'', 1766, a [[Conversation piece (paintings)|conversation piece]] with no portraits and with the full seriousness of the history painting.]]
[[File:David Wilkie Chelsea Pensioners Reading the Waterloo Dispatch.jpg|thumb|[[David Wilkie (artist)|Sir David Wilkie]], ''[[The Chelsea Pensioners reading the Waterloo Dispatch]]'', 1822.  Genre or history painting?  The types have merged, in a way typical of the 19th century.]]

A '''hierarchy of genres''' is any formalization which ranks different  [[genre]]s in an art form in terms of their prestige and cultural value.

In literature, the [[Epic poetry|epic]] was considered the highest form, for the reason expressed by [[Samuel Johnson]] in his ''Life of [[John Milton]]'': "By the general consent of criticks, the first praise of genius is due to the writer of an epick poem, as it requires an assemblage of all the powers which are singly sufficient for other compositions."  Below that came [[lyric poetry]], and comic poetry, with a similar ranking for [[drama]]. The [[novel]] took a long time to establish a firm place in the hierarchy, doing so only as belief in any systematic hierarchy of forms expired in the 19th century.

In music, settings of words were accorded a higher status than merely instrumental works, at least until the [[Baroque]] period, and [[opera]] retained a superior status for much longer.  The status of works also varies with the number of players and singers involved, with those for large forces, which are certainly more difficult to write and more expensive to perform, given higher status. Any element of comedy reduced the status of a work, though, as in other art forms, often increasing its popularity.

The hierarchies in figurative art are those initially formulated for painting in 16th-century Italy, which held sway with little alteration until the early 19th century.  These were formalized and promoted by the [[Academy|academies]] in Europe between the 17th century and the modern era, of which the most influential became the French [[Académie de peinture et de sculpture]], which held a central role in [[Academic art]].  The fully developed hierarchy distinguished between:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Belton|first1=Dr. Robert J.|title=Art History: A Preliminary Handbook|chapter=The Elements of Art|date=1996|chapter-url=http://fccs.ok.ubc.ca/about/links/resources/arthistory/elements.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*[[History painting]], including historically important, religious, mythological, or allegorical subjects
*[[Portrait painting]]
*[[Genre works|Genre painting]] or scenes of everyday life
*[[landscape art|Landscape]] and cityscape art (landscapists were called "common [[infantry|footmen]] in the Army of Art" by the Dutch theorist [[Samuel van Hoogstraten]])
*[[Animal painting]]
*[[Still life]]

The hierarchy was based on a distinction between art that made an intellectual effort to "render visible the universal essence of things" (''imitare'' in Italian) and that which merely consisted of "mechanical copying of particular appearances" (''ritrarre'').&lt;ref&gt;Bass, 36 [https://books.google.com/books?id=6TSDvkud168C&amp;pg=PA36&amp;dq=Hierarchy+of+genres+painting&amp;lr=&amp;as_brr=3#v=onepage&amp;q=Hierarchy%20of%20genres%20painting&amp;f=false Google books]&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Idealism]] was privileged over [[Philosophical realism|realism]] in line with [[Renaissance Neo-Platonist]] philosophy.

The term is mostly used within the field of painting, and from the [[High Renaissance]] onwards, by which time painting had asserted itself as the highest form of art.  This had not been the case in [[Medieval art]] and the art-commissioning sectors of society took a considerable period to fully accept this view.  The [[Raphael Cartoons]] are a clear example of the continuing status of [[tapestry]], the most expensive form of art in the 16th century.  In the Early Medieval period lavish pieces of metalwork had typically been the most highly regarded, and valuable materials remained an important ingredient in the appreciation of art until at least the 17th century.  Until the 19th century the most extravagant [[objets d'art]] remained more expensive, both new and on the art market, than all but a few paintings.  Classical writings which valued the supreme skills of individual artists were influential, as well as developments in art which allowed the Renaissance artist to demonstrate their skill and invention to a greater degree than was usually possible in the Middle Ages.

==Renaissance art==
The hierarchy grew out of the struggle  to gain acceptance of painting as one of the [[Liberal arts]], and then controversies to establish an equal or superior status within them with [[architecture]] and [[sculpture]].  These matters were considered of great importance by artist-theorists such as [[Leon Battista Alberti]], [[Leonardo da Vinci]], and [[Giorgio Vasari]].  Against the sculptors, Leonardo argued that the intellectual effort necessary to create an illusion of three-dimensionality made the painters' art superior to that of the sculptor, who could do so merely by recording appearances.&lt;ref&gt;Blunt, 28, 53-4&lt;/ref&gt;  In his ''[[De Pictura]]'' ("About Painting") of 1441, Alberti argued that multi-figure history painting was the noblest form of art, as being the most difficult, which required mastery of all the others, because it was a visual form of history, and because it had the greatest potential to move the viewer.  He placed emphasis on the ability to depict the interactions between the figures by gesture and expression.&lt;ref&gt;Blunt, 11-12,&lt;/ref&gt;

Theorists of the Early and High Renaissance accepted the importance of representing nature closely, at least until the later writings of [[Michelangelo]], who was strongly influenced by [[neoplatonism]].&lt;ref&gt;Blunt, 61, 65-74&lt;/ref&gt;  By the time of [[Mannerist]] theorists such as [[Gian Paolo Lomazzo]] and [[Federico Zuccari]] (both also painters) this was far less of a priority.  Both emphasized beauty as "something which was directly infused into the mind of man from the mind of God, and existed there independent of any sense-impressions", a view bound to further reduce the status of works depending on realism.&lt;ref&gt;Blunt, 140-141 (quote, 141)&lt;/ref&gt;  In practice the hierarchy represented little break with either medieval and classical thought, except to place secular history painting in the same class as religious art, and to distinguish (not always clearly) between static iconic religious subjects and narrative figure scenes, giving the latter a higher status.  Ideas of [[decorum]] also fed into the hierarchy; comic, sordid or merely frivolous subjects or treatment ranked lower than elevated and moral ones.{{Citation needed|date = May 2018}}

During the Renaissance landscape, genre scenes and still lifes hardly existed as established genres, so discussion of the status or importance of different types of painting was mainly concerned with history subjects as against portraits, initially small and unpretentious, and iconic portrait-type religious and mythological subjects.  For most artists some commitment to realism was necessary in a portrait; few could take the high-handed approach of Michelangelo, who largely ignored the actual appearance of the [[Medici]] in his [[Medici Chapel]] sculptures, supposedly saying that in a thousand years no one would know the difference (a retort [[Thomas Gainsborough|Gainsborough]] is also said to have used, with a shorter timeframe).&lt;ref&gt;Campbell, 1-2&lt;/ref&gt;  

Many portraits were extremely flattering, which could be justified by an appeal to idealism as well as the sitter's vanity; the theorist [[Giovanni Battista Armenini|Armenini]]&lt;ref&gt;Giovanni Battista Armenini (1533-1609) ''De vera precetti della pittura'' (1587), " On the True Precepts of the Art of Painting".&lt;/ref&gt; claimed in 1587 that "portraits by excellent artists are considered to be painted with better style [''maniera''] and greater perfection than others, but more often than not they are less good likenesses".&lt;ref&gt;Campbell, 23-24 (quote)&lt;/ref&gt;  On the other hand, numbers of courtly sitters and their parents, suitors or courtiers complained that painters entirely failed to do justice to the reality of the sitter.&lt;ref&gt;Campbell, 38-9&lt;/ref&gt;

The question of decorum in religious art became the focus of intense effort by the Catholic Church after the [[Art in Roman Catholicism#Council of Trent|decrees on art of the Council of Trent]] of 1563.  Paintings depicting biblical events as if they were occurring in the households of wealthy contemporary Italians were attacked, and soon ceased.  Until the challenge of [[Caravaggio]] at the end of the century, religious art became thoroughly ideal.{{Citation needed|date = May 2018}}

==17th and 18th century art==
The new genres of landscape, genre painting, animal painting and still life came into their own in the 17th century, with the virtual cessation of religious painting in Protestant countries, and the expansion of picture buying to the prosperous middle class.  Although similar developments occurred in all advanced European countries, they were most evident in the enormously productive schools of [[Dutch Golden Age painting]] and [[Flemish Baroque painting]].  However no theorists emerged to champion the new genres, and the relatively small amount of Dutch theoretical writing, by [[Karel van Mander]], [[Samuel Dirksz van Hoogstraten]],&lt;ref&gt;''Inleyding tot de Hooge Schoole der Schilderkonst'' ( Rotterdam 1678), "Introduction to the Academy of Painting".&lt;/ref&gt; [[Gerard de Lairesse]] and others, was mostly content to rehash Italian views, so that their writings can seem oddly at variance with the Dutch art actually being produced in their day.&lt;ref&gt;Fuchs, 103-104&lt;/ref&gt;

The hierarchy was mostly accepted by artists, and even genre specialists such as [[Jan Steen]], [[Karel Dujardin]] and [[Vermeer]] produced a few history paintings, which were better paid when commissions could be obtained, but in general far harder to sell.  The unhappy history of [[Rembrandt]]'s last history commission, ''[[The Conspiracy of Claudius Civilis]]'' (1661) illustrates both his commitment to the form and the difficulties he had in finding an audience.&lt;ref&gt;Fuchs, 69-77&lt;/ref&gt;  In Flanders, as well as great quantities of pure genre works, there was a trend towards history paintings with a major genre element, whether animals, landscape or still life.  Often the different elements were painted by different artists; [[Rubens]] and [[Frans Snyders]] often co-operated in this way.

The size of paintings, and very often the prices they realized, increasingly tended to reflect their position in the hierarchy in this period. Until the Romantic period the price and saleability of what were essentially landscapes could be increased by adding small mythological or religious figures, creating a ''landscape with...'', a practice that went back to the beginnings of landscape painting in the Flemish [[world landscape]]s of [[Joachim Patinir]] in the early 16th century. [[Flemish Baroque painting]] was the last school to often paint the lowest genres at a large size, but usually combined with figure subjects.

An influential formulation of 1667 by [[André Félibien]], a historiographer, architect and theoretician of French classicism became the classic statement of the theory for the 18th century:&lt;blockquote&gt;Celui qui fait parfaitement des païsages est au-dessus d'un autre qui ne fait que des fruits, des fleurs ou des coquilles. Celui qui peint des animaux vivants est plus estimable que ceux qui ne représentent que des choses mortes &amp; sans mouvement ; &amp; comme la figure de l'homme est le plus parfait ouvrage de Dieu sur la Terre, il est certain aussi que celui qui se rend l'imitateur de Dieu en peignant des figures humaines, est beaucoup plus excellent que tous les autres ... un Peintre qui ne fait que des portraits, n'a pas encore cette haute perfection de l'Art, &amp; ne peut prétendre à l'honneur que reçoivent les plus sçavans. Il faut pour cela passer d'une seule figure à la représentation de plusieurs ensemble ; il faut traiter l'histoire &amp; la fable ; il faut représenter de grandes actions comme les historiens, ou des sujets agréables comme les Poëtes ; &amp; montant encore plus haut, il faut par des compositions allégoriques, sçavoir couvrir sous le voile de la fable les vertus des grands hommes, &amp; les mystères les plus relevez.&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=jl8IAeoj-7IC&amp;lpg=PA96&amp;dq=Hierarchy%20of%20genres%20painting&amp;lr=&amp;as_brr=3&amp;pg=PA97#v=onepage&amp;q=Hierarchy%20of%20genres%20painting&amp;f=false Books.google.co.uk], translation&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;He who produces perfect landscapes is above another who only produces fruit, flowers or seashells. He who paints living animals is more estimable than those who only represent dead things without movement, and as man is the most perfect work of God on the earth, it is also certain that he who becomes an imitator of God in representing human figures, is much more excellent than all the others ... a painter who only does portraits still does not have the highest perfection of his art, and cannot expect the honour due to the most skilled.  For that he must pass from representing a single figure to several together; history and myth must be depicted; great events must be represented as by historians, or like the poets, subjects that will please, and climbing still higher, he must have the skill to cover under the veil of myth the virtues of great men in allegories, and the mysteries they reveal".&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Allegorical painting was raised above other types of [[history painting]]; together they were the ''grand genre'', including paintings with religious, mythological, historical, literary, or allegorical subjects—they embodied some interpretation of life or conveyed a moral or intellectual message. The gods and goddesses from the ancient mythologies represented different aspects of the human psyche, figures from religions represented different ideas, and history, like the other sources, represented a dialectic or play of ideas. Subjects with several figures ranked higher than single figures. For a long time, especially during the [[French Revolution]], history painting often focused on depiction of the heroic male nude; though this waned in the 19th century.

After history painting came, in order of decreasing worth: [[Portrait painting|portraits]], scenes of everyday life (called ''scènes de genre'', or "[[Genre works|genre painting]]", and also ''petit genre'' to contrast it with the ''grande genre''), [[Landscape art|landscapes]], animal painting, and finally [[still life]]s. In his formulation, such paintings were inferior because they were merely reportorial pictures without moral force or artistic imagination. Genre paintings—neither ideal in style, nor elevated in subject—were admired for their skill, ingenuity, and even humour, but never confused with high art. 

The hierarchy of genres also had a corresponding hierarchy of formats: large format for history paintings, small format for still lifes.  This had occasionally been breached in the past, especially in large Flemish works, and the monumental ''[[The Young Bull]]'' of the Dutch artist [[Paulus Potter]], as well as the larger of the two ''[[Butchers' Shop]]'' canvases of [[Annibale Carracci]].  But for the most part the relative prices obtainable for the different genres ensured the hierarchy of size also; it would not have been economic to paint a very large subject from the lower genres, except for commissioned group portraits.  Rubens' largest landscapes were painted for his own houses.

The use of the pictorial elements of painting such as line and color to convey an ultimate unifying theme or idea was regarded as the highest expression of art, and an idealism was adopted in art, whereby forms seen in nature would be generalized, and in turn subordinated to the unity of the artwork. It aimed at universal truth through the imitation of nature. Later  dissenting theorists, such as [[Gotthold Ephraim Lessing]], held that this focus on [[allegory]] was faulty and based on a wrong analogy between the plastic arts and poetry rooted in the [[Horace|Horatian]] dictum [[ut pictura poesis]] ("as is painting so is poetry").

The British painter [[Sir Joshua Reynolds]] in his ''Discourses'' of the 1770s and 1780s, reiterated the argument for still life to the lowest position in the hierarchy of genres on the grounds that it interfered with the painter's access to central forms, those products of the mind's generalising powers. At the summit reigned history painting, centred on the human body: familiarity with the forms of the body permitted the mind of the painter, by comparing innumerable instances of the human form, to abstract from it those typical or central features that represented the body's essence or ideal.

Though Reynolds agreed with Félibien about the natural order of the genres, he held that an important work from any genre of painting could be produced under the hand of genius: "Whether it is the human figure, an animal, or even inanimate objects, there is nothing, however unpromising in appearance, but may be raised into dignity, convey sentiment, and produce emotion, in the hands of a painter of genius. What was said of [[Virgil]], that he threw even the dung about the ground with an air of dignity, may be applied to [[Titian]]; whatever he touched, however naturally mean, and habitually familiar, by a kind of magic he invested with grandeur and importance."

Though European academies usually strictly insisted on this hierarchy, over their reign, many artists were able to invent new genres which raised the lower subjects to the importance of history painting. Reynolds himself achieved this by inventing the portraiture style that was called the [[Grand Manner]], where he flattered his sitters by likening them to mythological characters. [[Jean-Antoine Watteau]] invented a genre that was called [[fêtes galantes]], where he would show scenes of courtly amusements taking place in Arcadian setting; these often had a poetic and allegorical quality which were considered to ennoble them. 

[[Claude Lorrain]] practised a genre called the [[ideal landscape]], where a composition would be loosely based on nature and dotted with classical ruins as a  setting for a biblical or historical theme. It artfully combined landscape and history painting, thereby legitimising the former. It is synonymous with the term ''historical landscape'' which received official recognition in the Académie française when a [[Prix de Rome]] for the genre was established in 1817. Finally, [[Jean-Baptiste-Siméon Chardin]] was able to create still life paintings that were considered to have the charm and beauty as to be placed alongside the best allegorical subjects. However, aware of this hierarchy, Chardin began including figures in his work in about 1730, mainly women and children.

==19th century==
[[Romanticism]] greatly increased the status of landscape painting, beginning in [[British art]] and more gradually that of genre painting, which began to influence history painting in the anecdotal treatments of the [[Style Troubadour]] in France and equivalent trends elsewhere. Landscapes grew in size to reflect their new importance, often matching history paintings, especially in the American [[Hudson River School]] and Russian painting. Animal paintings also increased in size and dignity, but the full-length portrait, even of royalty, became mostly reserved for large public buildings.

Until the middle of the 19th century, [[women artists|women]] were largely unable to paint history paintings as they were not allowed to participate in the final process of artistic training—that of life drawing, in order to protect their modesty. They could work from reliefs, prints, casts and from the Old Masters, but not from the nude model. Instead they were encouraged to participate in the lower painting forms such as portraiture, landscape and genre. These were considered more feminine in that they appealed to the eye rather than the mind.

Toward the end of the 19th century, painters and critics began to rebel against the many rules of the Académie française, including the status accorded to [[history painting]], which was beginning to be bought mainly by public bodies of one sort or another, as private buyers preferred subjects from lower down the hierarchy.  In Britain the [[Pre-Raphaelite]] movement tried to revitalize the history painting, with mixed success; other movements made similar efforts.  Many Pre-Raphaelites ended their careers mainly painting other subjects.  New artistic movements included the [[Realism (visual arts)|Realists]] and [[Impressionism|Impressionists]], which each sought to depict the present moment and daily life as observed by the eye, and unattatched from historical significance; the Realists often choosing genre painting and still life, while the Impressionists would most often focus on landscapes.

==Notes==
{{reflist|30em}}

==References==
*Bass, Laura L.,''The Drama of the Portrait: Theater and Visual Culture in Early Modern Spain'', Penn State Press, 2008, {{ISBN|0-271-03304-5}}, {{ISBN|978-0-271-03304-4}}
*[[Anthony Blunt|Blunt Anthony]], ''Artistic Theory in Italy, 1450-1660'', 1940 (refs to 1985 edn), [[OUP]], {{ISBN|0-19-881050-4}}
*Campbell, Lorne, ''Renaissance Portraits, European Portrait-Painting in the 14th, 15th and 16th Centuries'', Yale, {{ISBN|0-300-04675-8}}
*Fuchs, RH; ''Dutch painting''; 1978, Thames and Hudson, London, {{ISBN|0-500-20167-6}}
* Lee, Rensselaer W., ''Ut Pictura Poesis, The Humanistic Theory of Painting'', Norton Simon, New York, 1967. [http://www.noteaccess.com/Texts/Lee/ Rensselaer W. Lee, ''Ut Pictura Poesis'' Online text of book]
*[[Gerald Reitlinger|Reitlinger, Gerald]]; ''The Economics of Taste, Vol I: The Rise and Fall of Picture Prices 1760-1960, Barrie and Rockliffe, London, 1961

{{DEFAULTSORT:Hierarchy Of Genres}}
[[Category:Art genres]]
[[Category:Art history]]
[[Category:Painting]]
[[Category:Visual arts theory]]</text>
      <sha1>2ifjvwxdpc60l1v2a4h1r70gl5efomj</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Irrealism (the arts)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>15125</id>
    <revision>
      <id>867241398</id>
      <parentid>859734857</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-11-04T15:24:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Citation bot</username>
        <id>7903804</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Alter: isbn. Removed accessdate with no specified URL. Removed parameters. You can [[WP:UCB|use this bot]] yourself. [[WP:DBUG|Report bugs here]]. | [[WP:UCB|User-activated]]; [[Category:Critical theory]].</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="10622">'''Irrealism''' is a term that has been used by various writers in the fields of philosophy, literature, and art to denote specific modes of unreality and/or the problems in concretely defining reality.  While in philosophy the term specifically refers to a position put forward by the American philosopher [[Nelson Goodman]], in literature and art it refers to a variety of writers and movements.  If the term has nonetheless retained a certain consistency in its use across these fields and would-be movements, it perhaps reflects the word’s position in general English usage: though the standard dictionary definition of ''irreal'' gives it the same meaning as ''unreal'', ''irreal'' is very rarely used in comparison with ''unreal''.  Thus, it has generally been used to describe something which, while unreal, is so in a very specific or unusual fashion, usually one emphasizing not just the "not real," but some form of estrangement from our generally accepted sense of reality.

==Irrealism in Literature==

In literature, the term irrealism was first used extensively in the United States in the 1970s to describe the post-realist "new fiction" of writers such as [[Donald Barthelme]] or [[John Barth]].  More generally, it described the notion that all forms of writing could only "offer particular versions of reality rather than actual descriptions of it," and that a story need not offer a clear resolution at its end.  [[John Gardner (novelist)|John Gardner]], in ''The Art of Fiction'', cites in this context the work of Barthelme and its "seemingly limitless ability to manipulate [literary] techniques as modes of apprehension [which] apprehend nothing."&lt;ref&gt;(Gardner 1984)&lt;/ref&gt;   Though Barth, in a 1974 interview, stated, "irrealism—not antirealism or unrealism, but irrealism—is all that I would confidently predict is likely to characterize the prose fiction of the 1970s," &lt;ref&gt;(Bellamy 1974)&lt;/ref&gt; this did not prove to be the case.  Instead writing in the United States quickly returned to its realist orthodoxy and the term irrealism fell into disuse.

In recent years, however, the term has been revived in an attempt to describe and categorize, in literary and philosophical terms, how it is that the work of an irrealist writer differs from the work of writers in other, non-realistic genres (e.g., the fantasy of [[J.R.R. Tolkien]], the magical realism of [[Gabriel García Márquez]]) and what the significance of this difference is.  This can be seen in Dean Swinford's essay ''Defining irrealism: scientific development and allegorical possibility''.[http://cafeirreal.alicewhittenburg.com/review1a.htm]  Approaching the issue from a structuralist and narratological point of view, he has defined irrealism as a "peculiar mode of postmodern allegory" that has resulted from modernity’s fragmentation and dismantling of the well-ordered and coherent medieval system of symbol and allegory.  Thus a lion, when presented in a given context in medieval literature, could only be interpreted in a single, approved way.  Contemporary literary theory, however, denies the attribution of such fixed meanings.  According to Swinford, this change can be attributed in part to the fact that "science and technical culture have changed perceptions of the natural world, have significantly changed the natural world itself, thereby altering the vocabulary of symbols applicable to [[epistemological]] and allegorical attempts to understand it."  Thus irreal works such as [[Italo Calvino]]'s ''Cosmicomics'' and [[Jorge Luis Borges]]' ''Ficciones'' can be seen as an attempt to find a new allegorical language to explain our changed perceptions of the world that have been brought about by our scientific and technical culture, especially concepts such as quantum physics or the theory of relativity.  "The Irrealist work, then, operates within a given system," writes Swinford, "and attests to its plausibility, despite the fact that this system, and the world it represents, is often a mutation, an aberration."

The online journal ''[[The Cafe Irreal]]'' [http://www.cafeirreal.com/], on the other hand, has defined irrealism as being a type of existentialist literature in which the means are continually and absurdly rebelling against the ends that we have determined for them.&lt;ref&gt;Evans, G.S. and Alice Whittenburg, "After Kafka: Kafka Criticism and Scholarship as a Resource in an Attempt to Promulgate a New Literary Genre," ''Journal of the Kafka Society of America'', 31/32(1+2):18-26.&lt;/ref&gt; An example of this would be [[Franz Kafka]]'s story ''[[The Metamorphosis]]'', in which the salesman [[Gregor Samsa]]'s plans for supporting his family and rising up in rank by hard work and determination are suddenly thrown topsy-turvy by his sudden and inexplicable transformation into a man-sized insect.  Such fiction is said to emphasize the fact that human consciousness, being finite in nature, can never make complete sense of, or successfully order, a universe that is infinite in its aspects and possibilities.  Which is to say: as much as we might try to order our world with a certain set of norms and goals (which we consider our real world), the paradox of a finite consciousness in an infinite universe creates a zone of irreality ("that which is beyond the real") that offsets, opposes, or threatens the real world of the human subject.  Irrealist writing often highlights this irreality, and our strange fascination with it, by combining the unease we feel because the real world doesn't conform to our desires with the narrative quality of the dream state (where reality is constantly and inexplicably being undermined); it is thus said to communicate directly, "by feeling rather than articulation, the uncertainties inherent in human existence or, to put it another way... the irreconcilability between human aspiration and human reality." [http://cafeirreal.alicewhittenburg.com/what_is_irr.htm]  If the irreal story can be considered an allegory, then, it would be an allegory that is "so many pointers to an unknown meaning," in which the meaning is felt more than it is articulated or systematically analyzed.

==Irrealism in Art==

Various writers have addressed the question of Irrealism in Art.  Many salient observations on Irrealism in Art are found in Nelson Goodman's ''Languages of Art''.  Goodman himself produced some multimedia shows, one of which inspired by hockey and is entitled ''Hockey Seen: A Nightmare in Three Periods and Sudden Death''.

Garret [[Rowlan]], writing in ''[[The Cafe Irreal]]'', writes that the malaise present in the work of the Italian artist [[Giorgio de Chirico]], "which recalls Kafka, has to do with the sense of another world lurking, hovering like the long shadows that dominate de Chirico's paintings, which frequently depict a landscape at twilight's uncertain hour. Malaise and mystery are all by-products of the interaction of the real and the unreal, the rub and contact of two worlds caught on irrealism's shimmering surface." [http://cafeirreal.alicewhittenburg.com/review4a.htm]

The writer Dean Swinford, whose concept of irrealism was described at length in the section "Irrealism in Literature", wrote that the artist Remedios Varos, in her painting ''The Juggler'', "creates a personal allegorical system which relies on the predetermined symbols of Christian and classical iconography. But these are quickly refigured into a personal system informed by the scientific and organized like a machine...in the Irreal work, allegory operates according to an altered, but constant and orderly iconographic system."

Artist Tristan Tondino has made a number of claims about Irrealism.  Most of his claims are found in his paintings, many of which are [[Lettrist]] Abstractions. "There is no specific style to Irrealist Art.  It is the result of awareness that every human act is the result of the limitations of the world of the actor." &lt;ref&gt;Tondino 2003, ''Zot - Giving a Painter Crap...''&lt;/ref&gt;

In Australia, the art journal ''the art life'' has recently detected the presence of a "New Irrealism" among the painters of that country, which is described as being an "approach to painting that is decidedly low key, deploying its effects without histrionic showmanship, while creating an eerie other world of ghostly images and abstract washes." What exactly constituted the "old" irrealism, they do not say.

== Irrealist Art, Film and Music Edition ==

Irrealist Art Edition is a publishing company created in the 90s by contemporary plastic artist [[Frédéric Iriarte]]. Together with the Estonian poet, writer and art critic [[Ilmar Laaban]], they developed their concept of Irrealism through several essays, exhibitions, projects, manifest and a book, "Irréalisation". [http://www.iriarte.info/Irrealiste-Forlaget/EN/index.html Irrealist Art Edition] {{ISBN|91-630-2304-0}}

== Irrealism in music ==

Some [[hardcore punk|hardcore]] bands in [[Italy]] have claimed to be irrealist.{{Citation needed|date=December 2016}}

== See also ==
* [[Franz Kafka]]
* [[Nikolai Gogol]]
* [[René Magritte]]
* [[Kōbō Abe]]
* [[Giorgio de Chirico]]
* [[Magnus Mills]]
* [[Jorge Luis Borges]]
* [[Donald Barthelme]]
* [[John Barth]]
* [[Remedios Varo]]
* [[Frédéric Iriarte]]
* [[D. Harlan Wilson]]
* [[Max Blecher]]

== Footnotes ==
&lt;references/&gt;

== References ==
* {{cite book
 | last = Gardner
 | first = John
 | authorlink = 
 | editor = 
 | others = 
 | title = The Art of Fiction
 | origyear =  
 | month = 
 | edition = 
 | year = 1984
 | publisher = A. Knopf 
 | location = New York
 | language = 
 | isbn = 978-0-394-50469-8
 | doi =
 | pages = 
 | chapter = 
 | url = 
 | quote =
 }}
* {{cite book
 | last = Bellamy 
 | first = Joe David 
 | authorlink = 
 | editor = 
 | others = 
 | title = The New Fiction; Interviews with Innovative American Writers 
 | origyear = 
 | month = 
 | edition = 
 | year = 1974
 | publisher = University of Illinois Press 
 | location = Urbana 
 | language = 
 | isbn = 978-0-252-00430-8
 | doi =
 | pages = 
 | chapter = 
 | url = 
 | quote =
 }}
* Swinford, Dean, “Defining Irrealism: Scientific Development and Allegorical Possibility,” ''Journal of the Fantastic in the Arts'', 12.1 (2001): 77-89.
* Evans, G.S. and Alice Whittenburg, "After Kafka: Kafka Criticism and Scholarship as a Resource in an Attempt to Promulgate a New Literary Genre," ''Journal of the Kafka Society of America'', 31/32(1+2): 18-26.

[[Category:Critical theory]]
[[Category:Realism (art movement)]]
[[Category:Art movements]]
[[Category:Literary movements]]
[[Category:Philosophical movements]]</text>
      <sha1>2kly1nx1j055wmvvxlowffx1cti9e07</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>L'Origine du monde</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1405023</id>
    <revision>
      <id>865374659</id>
      <parentid>865372771</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-10-23T15:12:32Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Rrwagner59</username>
        <id>16779769</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>moved a thumbnail; linked Du Camp citation to source</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="25492">{{Infobox artwork
| image_file=Origin-of-the-World.jpg
| image_size = 300px
| title={{Lang|fr|L'Origine du monde}}
| artist=Gustave Courbet
| year=1866
| medium=Oil on canvas
| height_metric=46
| width_metric=55
| metric_unit=cm
| museum=Musée d'Orsay, Paris
}}
'''{{Lang|fr|L'Origine du monde}}''' ("The Origin of the World") is a picture painted in oil on canvas by the French artist [[Gustave Courbet]] in 1866. It is a close-up view of the [[genitals]] and [[abdomen]] of a naked woman, lying on a bed with legs spread. The framing of the nude body, with head, arms and lower legs outside of view, emphasizes the [[eroticism]] of the work.

== History ==
=== Identity of the model ===
[[File:The Origin of the World (upper section).jpg|thumb|Putative upper section of ''L'Origine du monde'']]
Art historians have speculated for years that Courbet's model for {{Lang|fr|L'Origine du monde}} was his favourite model, [[Joanna Hiffernan]], also known as ''Jo''. Her lover at the time was the American painter [[James Abbott McNeill Whistler|James Whistler]], a friend of Courbet.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.theguardian.com/artanddesign/2018/sep/25/joanna-hiffernan-courbet-nude-lorigine-du-monde |title=Who posed for the 'Mona Lisa of vaginas'? |last=Jones |first=Jonathan |author-link=Jonathan Jones (journalist) |date=25 September 2018 |website=The Guardian |access-date=2018-10-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Gustave Courbet - Jo, la belle Irlandaise (MET-Museum).jpg|thumb|''La belle Irlandaise (Portrait of Jo)'' by Courbet: Joanna Hiffernan, possible model for ''L'Origine du monde'']]
Hiffernan was the subject of a series of four portaits by Courbet entitled [[Jo, the Beautiful Irishwoman|''La belle Irlandaise (Portrait of Jo)'']] painted in 1865-66. The possibility that she was the model for {{Lang|fr|L'Origine du monde}}&lt;ref name=tele /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|first1=Benoit|last1=Noël|first2=Jean|last2=Hournon|title=Parisiana – La capitale des peintres au XIX&lt;sup&gt;ème&lt;/sup&gt; siècle|publisher=Les Presses Franciliennes|chapter=Gustave Courbet – L'Origine du Monde, 1866|page=37|isbn=9782952721400|language=French}}&lt;/ref&gt; or that she was having an affair with Courbet might explain Courbet's and Whistler's brutal separation a short while later.&lt;ref name=Kosinski&gt;Dorothy M. Kosinski, [https://www.jstor.org/pss/1483342 Gustave Courbet's ''The Sleepers.'' The Lesbian Image in Nineteenth Century French Art and Literature], Artibus et Historiae, Vol. 9, No. 18  (1988), p.187&lt;/ref&gt; In spite of Hiffernan's [[red hair]] contrasting with the darker pubic hair of {{Lang|fr|L'Origine du monde}}, the hypothesis that Hiffernan was the model continues. Redhead Jacky Colliss Harvey puts forward the idea that the woman's body-hair suggests a more obvious candidate might be the brunette painted with Hiffernan in Courbet's ''[[Le Sommeil]]''; and that the identification with Hiffernan has been greatly influenced by the eroticised and sexualised image of the female redhead.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = RED: A History of the Redhead|last = Colliss Harvey|first = Jacky|publisher = Black Dog &amp; Leventhal|year = 2015|isbn = 978-1-57912-996-5|location = New York|pages = 119-120}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Melle Queniaux opéra (ballet) par Nadar (1820-1910).jpg|thumb|left|Constance Quéniaux, possible model for ''L'Origine du monde'']]
In February 2013, ''[[Paris Match]]'' reported that Courbet expert Jean-Jacques Fernier had authenticated a painting of a young woman's head and shoulders as the upper section of {{Lang|fr|L'Origine du monde}} which according to some was severed from the original work. Fernier has stated that because of the conclusions reached after two years of analysis, the head will be added to the next edition of the Courbet [[catalogue raisonné]].&lt;ref name=tele&gt;[https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/france/9854914/Amateur-art-buff-finds-35-million-head-of-Courbet-masterpiece.html "Amateur art buff finds £35 million head of Courbet masterpiece"] by Henry Samuel, ''[[The Daily Telegraph]]'', 7 February 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|work=[[Paris Match]]|title=''L'Origine du monde'': Le secret de la femme cachée|url=http://www.parismatch.com/Culture-Match/Art/Actu/L-Origine-du-monde-de-Gustave-Courbet-Le-secret-de-la-femme-cachee-463132/|date=7 February 2013|language=French|access-date=2013-02-07|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130415141855/http://www.parismatch.com/Culture-Match/Art/Actu/L-Origine-du-monde-de-Gustave-Courbet-Le-secret-de-la-femme-cachee-463132/|archive-date=2013-04-15|dead-url=yes|df=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Musée d'Orsay]] has indicated that ''L'Origine du monde'' was not part of a larger work.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/culture/art/9860793/Has-the-head-of-The-Origin-of-the-World-been-found.html|title=Has the head of The Origin of the World been found? |work= The Telegraph|date=10 February 2013|accessdate=11 February 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[The Daily Telegraph]]'' reported that "experts at the [French] art research centre CARAA (Centre d'Analyses et de Recherche en Art et Archéologie) were able to align the two paintings via grooves made by the original wooden frame and lines in the canvas itself, whose grain matched."&lt;ref name=tele /&gt; According to CARAA, it performed pigment analyses which were identified as classical pigments of the 2nd half of the 19th century. No other conclusions were reported by the CARAA.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.caraa.fr/EN/detail-actu.php?actu=18 "Summary of analytical report – Painting on canvas, portrait of a woman"] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150217201825/http://www.caraa.fr/EN/detail-actu.php?actu=18 |date=2015-02-17 }}, Centre d'Analyses et de Recherche en Art et Archéologie, 7 February 2013&lt;/ref&gt; The claim reported by ''Paris Match'' was characterized as dubious by ''[[Le Monde]]'' art critic [[Philippe Dagen]], indicating differences in style, and that canvas-similarities could be caused by buying from the same shop.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/world/2013/0209/1224329840770.html|title=Art collector claims to have found top part of Courbet's ''Origin of the World''|work=[[The Irish Times]]|accessdate=11 February 2013|date=9 February 2013|author=Ruadhán Mac Cormaic}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Documentary evidence however links the painting with [[Constance Quéniaux]], a former dancer at the [[Paris Opera]] and a mistress of the Ottoman diplomat [[Halil Şerif Pasha]] (Khalil Bey) who commisioned the painting. According to the historian Claude Schopp and the head of the [[French National Library]]'s prints department, Sylvie Aubenas, the evidence is found in correspondence between [[Alexandre Dumas fils]] and [[George Sand]].&lt;ref name=guardian&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.theguardian.com/artanddesign/2018/sep/25/origin-of-gustave-courbet-scandalous-painting-revealed |title=Mystery solved? Identity of Courbet's 19th-century nude revealed |agency=[[Agence France-Presse]] |location=Paris |date=2018-09-25 |website=the Guardian |language=en |access-date=2018-09-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another potential model was [[Marie-Anne Detourbay]], who also was a mistress of Halil Şerif Pasha.&lt;ref name=guardian /&gt;

=== Owners ===
Halil Şerif Pasha (Khalil Bey) is believed to have commissioned the work shortly after he moved to Paris. [[Charles Augustin Sainte-Beuve]] introduced him to Courbet and he ordered a painting to add to his personal collection of erotic pictures, which already included {{Lang|fr|[[The Turkish Bath|Le Bain turc]]}} (''The Turkish Bath'') from [[Jean-Auguste-Dominique Ingres|Ingres]] and another painting by Courbet, ''[[Le Sommeil]]'' (''The Sleepers''), for which it is supposed that Hiffernan was one of the models.
[[File:Halil Sherif Pasha.jpg|thumbnail|left|Halil Şerif Pasha (Khalil Bey) commissioned the painting.]]
After Khalil Bey's finances were ruined by gambling, the painting subsequently passed through a series of private collections. It was first bought during the sale of the Khalil Bey collection in 1868, by antique dealer Antoine de la Narde. [[Edmond de Goncourt]] hit upon it in an antique shop in 1889, hidden behind a wooden pane decorated with the painting of a castle or a church in a snowy landscape. According to [[Robert Fernier]], who published two volumes of the Courbet catalogue raisonné and founded the [[Musée Courbet]], Hungarian collector Baron [[Ferenc Hatvany]] bought it at the [[Bernheim-Jeune]] gallery in 1910 and took it with him to Budapest. Towards the end of the [[Second World War]] the painting was looted by [[Red Army|Soviet troops]], but later ransomed by Hatvany. Hatvany left Hungary, which was on the brink of a Communist takeover, in 1947. He was allowed to take only one art work with him, and he took {{Lang|fr|L'Origine}} to Paris.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.artnews.com/2008/02/01/the-mysterious-journey-of-an-erotic-masterpiece/ "The Mysterious Journey of an Erotic Masterpiece"] by Konstantin Akinsha, ''[[ARTnews]]'', 1 February 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1955 {{Lang|fr|L'Origine du monde}} was sold at auction for 1.5 million francs, about 4,285 US dollars at the time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.measuringworth.com/datasets/exchangeglobal/result.php?year_source=1955&amp;year_result=1955&amp;countryE%5B%5D=France|title=Measuring Worth - Relative Worth Comparators and Data Sets|website=www.measuringworth.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Its new owner was the psychoanalyst [[Jacques Lacan]]. He and his wife, actress [[Sylvia Bataille]], installed it in their country house in [[Guitrancourt]]. Lacan asked [[André Masson]], his stepbrother, to build a double bottom frame and draw another picture thereon. Masson painted a surrealist, allusive version of {{Lang|fr|L'Origine du monde}}.&lt;ref&gt;''Lacan and the Matter of Origins'' by Shuli Barzilai, p. 8&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lacan.com/courbet.htm|title=courbet - origin of the world|website=www.lacan.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The New York public had the opportunity to view {{Lang|fr|L'Origine du monde}} in 1988 during the ''Courbet Reconsidered'' show at the [[Brooklyn Museum]]; the painting was also included in the exhibition ''Gustave Courbet'' at the [[Metropolitan Museum of Art]] in 2008. After Lacan died in 1981, the French Minister of Economy and Finances agreed to settle the family's [[inheritance tax]] bill through the transfer of the work ({{Lang|fr|[[Acceptance in lieu|"Dation en paiement"]]}} in French law) to the [[Musée d'Orsay]]; the transfer was finalized in 1995.

=== Provocative work ===
During the 19th century, the display of the nude body underwent a revolution whose main activists were Courbet and [[Édouard Manet|Manet]]. Courbet rejected academic painting and its smooth, idealised nudes, but he also directly recriminated the hypocritical social conventions of the [[Second French Empire|Second Empire]], where [[eroticism]] and even [[pornography]] were acceptable in [[mythology|mythological]] or [[oneiric]] paintings.

Courbet later insisted he never lied in his paintings, and his [[realism (arts)|realism]] pushed the limits of what was considered presentable. With {{Lang|fr|L'Origine du monde}}, he has made even more explicit the eroticism of Manet's ''[[Olympia (Manet)|Olympia]]''. [[Maxime Du Camp]], in a harsh tirade, reported his visit to the work's purchaser, and his sight of a painting "giving realism's last word".{{sfn|Du Camp|1878|p=190}}

[[File:Courbet-origine-monde.jpg|thumb|{{Lang|fr|L'Origine du monde}} in the {{Lang|fr|Musée d'Orsay}}]]
By the very nature of its realistic, graphic nudity, the painting still has the power to shock and triggers censorship.

Although moral standards and resulting taboos regarding the artistic display of nudity have changed since Courbet, owing especially to [[photography]] and [[film|cinema]], the painting remained provocative. Its arrival at the Musée d'Orsay caused high excitement. According to postcard sales, {{Lang|fr|L'Origine du monde}} is the second most popular painting in the Musée d'Orsay, after [[Pierre-Auguste Renoir|Renoir's]] ''[[Bal du moulin de la Galette]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.the-tls.co.uk/tls/reviews/arts_and_commentary/article759415.ece|title=The history of ''The Origin of the World''| location=London|work=The Times Literary Supplement|first=Mark|last=Hutchinson|date=8 August 2007}} {{Subscription required}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some critics maintain that the body depicted is not (as has been argued) a lively erotic portray of a female but of a corpse: "''L’Origine'' does not represent a full female body but rather a slice of one, cut off by the frame [...]. The pallidness of the skin and the mortuary gauze surrounding the body suggest death."{{sfn|Uparella|Jauregui|2018|p=95}}

== Influence ==
The explicitness of the picture may have served as an inspiration, albeit with a satirical twist, for [[Marcel Duchamp]]'s last major work, ''[[Étant donnés]]'' (1946–1966), a construction also featuring the image of a woman lying on her back with her legs spread.&lt;ref&gt;[http://toutfait.com/femalic-molds/ "Femalic Molds"], The Marcel Duchamp Studies Online Journal (toutfait.com), 1 April 2003/5 May 2016&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1989, French artist [[Orlan]] created the [[cibachrome]] ''L'origine de la guerre'' (''The Origin of War''), a male version of ''L'origine du monde'' showing a [[penile erection]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.loeildelaphotographie.com/2013/11/27/exhibition/23329/orlan-l-origine-de-la-guerre-orsay-masculin-masculin |title=ORLAN: L’origine de la Guerre |last= |first= |date= |website=The Eye of Photography |publisher= |access-date=2018-10-22 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In February 1994, the novel {{Lang|fr|Adorations perpétuelles}} (''Perpetual Adorations'') by {{Interlanguage link multi|Jacques Henric|fr}} reproduced {{Lang|fr|L'Origine du monde}} on its cover. Police visited several French bookshops to have them withdraw the book from their windows. A few proprietors maintained the book, but others complied, and some voluntarily removed it.{{Citation needed|date=October 2018}}

Brazilian artist [[Vik Muniz]] created two versions of the famous painting. "The first [1999] is a photograph made of dust or dirt, which plays with the common moralist association between female genitalia and filth. In the second piece [2013], Muniz remakes ''L’Origine'' from an assemblage of journal clippings that are reminiscent of the anatomic and artistic procedure of cutting that produced [...] the female body."{{sfn|Uparella|Jauregui|2018|pp=103-105}}

''Two Origins of the World'' (2000) by Mexican artist [[Enrique Chagoya]] "recycles ''L’Origine du monde'' as a spectral backdrop behind three solid black, blue and white squares of canvas in three of the corners of the painting. In the foreground of the bottom right corner, an indigenous man sits at a fourth canvas, this one on an easel, apparently 'interpreting' the Courbet painting."{{sfn|Uparella|Jauregui|2018|p=105}}

In 2002, American artist [[Jack Daws]] created an homage to the painting. Entitled ''Origins of the World'', it is a collection of various photographs of vulvas, taken from pornographic magazines, and framed in montage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.gregkucera.com/daws_sculpture.htm |title=Jack Daws Sculpture |website=Greg Kucera Gallery, Inc. |publisher= |access-date=2018-10-22 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The British artist [[Anish Kapoor]] created an installation in 2004 called ''L'Origine du monde'', which references Courbet's painting. The piece is in the [[21st Century Museum of Contemporary Art, Kanazawa]] in Japan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.kanazawa21.jp/data_list.php?g=97&amp;d=78&amp;lng=e|title=金沢21世紀美術館|website=金沢21世紀美術館}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The image is also referenced as inspiring [[Catherine Breillat]]'s filming of the female genitalia in her 2004 film {{Lang|fr|Anatomie de l'enfer}} (''[[Anatomy of Hell]]'').&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.arkepix.com/kinok/Catherine%20BREILLAT/breillat_interview.html "Catherine Breillat, cinéaste"] {{Webarchive|url=http://arquivo.pt/wayback/20091004064647/http://www.arkepix.com/kinok/Catherine%20BREILLAT/breillat_interview.html |date=2009-10-04 }}, interview by Laurent Devanne, [[Radio libertaire]] (1 February 2004)&lt;/ref&gt;

The Serbian [[performance art]]ist [[Tanja Ostojić]] parodied the work in a poster in 2005, informally called the "EU panties" poster. Like Courbet's painting, the poster proved controversial, and was ultimately removed from the art exhibition in which it was originally displayed.{{Citation needed|date=October 2018}}

On February 23, 2009 in [[Braga]], Portugal, [[Polícia de Segurança Pública|the police]] confiscated the book ''Pornocratie'' by Catherine Breillat, displayed in bookshops using {{Lang|fr|L'Origine du monde}} as its cover.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |url         = http://ultimahora.publico.clix.pt/noticia.aspx?id=1366440&amp;idCanal=62
 |title       = PSP apreende livros por considerar pornográfica capa com quadro de Courbet
 |accessdate  = 24 February 2009
 |author      = Lusa
 |authorlink  = Lusa news agency
 |date        = 23 February 2009
 |language    = Portuguese
 |deadurl     = yes
 |archiveurl  = http://arquivo.pt/wayback/20090525083907/http://ultimahora.publico.clix.pt/noticia.aspx?id%3D1366440%26idCanal%3D62
 |archivedate = 25 May 2009
 |df          = 
}}&lt;/ref&gt; A great deal of controversy was sparked by the police action. The reason given was the need to maintain public order. Also, the book title incorrectly hinted at pornographic content. Portuguese law forbids public displays of pornography.{{Citation needed|date=October 2018}}

In 2010, British composer [[Tony Hymas]] composed {{Lang|fr|De l'origine du monde}} a [[Suite (music)|musical suite]] dedicated to the picture as well as relations between Courbet and the [[Paris Commune]], based on texts by Courbet himself, [[Charles Baudelaire]] and [[Pierre Dupont]].{{Citation needed|date=February 2013}}

In February 2011, [[Facebook]] censored {{Lang|fr|L'Origine du monde}} after it was posted by Copenhagen-based artist Frode Steinicke, to illustrate his comments about a television program aired on DR2. Following the incident, many other Facebook users defiantly changed their profile pictures to the Courbet painting in an act of solidarity with Steinicke. Facebook, which originally disabled Steinicke's profile, finally re-enabled it without the {{Lang|fr|L'Origine du monde}} picture. As the case won media attention, Facebook deleted other pages about the painting.&lt;ref&gt;Emily Greenberg [http://cornellsun.com/node/46245 "Facebook, Censorship and Art"] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20111105104721/http://cornellsun.com/node/46245 |date=2011-11-05 }}, ''Cornell Daily Sun'', 8 March 2011&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Dépêche AFP du 17/02/10 [https://www.google.com/hostednews/afp/article/ALeqM5jvF1OWi_2s8sEFr2VEnAUYozmU0g?docId=CNG.9ddadf8072b82cd68b8e61e1dcc3a108.7e1 "''L'Origine du monde'' de Courbet interdit de Facebook pour cause de nudité"]&lt;/ref&gt;

In October 2011, again, a complaint was lodged against Facebook with the [[Tribunal de grande instance de Paris]] (Paris court of general jurisdiction) by a French Facebook user after his profile was disabled for showing a picture of {{Lang|fr|L'Origine du monde}}. The picture was a link to a television program aired on [[Arte]] about the history of the painting. As he got no answer to his emails to Facebook, he decided to lodge a complaint for "infringement of freedom of expression" and against the legality of Facebook's terms which define the courts located in Santa Clara County, California, as the exclusive place of jurisdiction for all litigating claims.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lepoint.fr/culture/l-origine-du-monde-assigne-facebook-en-justice-24-10-2011-1388626_3.php "''L'Origine du monde'' assigne Facebook en justice"], ''[[Le Point]]'', 24 October 2011&lt;/ref&gt; In February 2016, the Paris court ruled that Facebook could be sued in France.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/europe/facebook-faces-trial-in-france-over-nudity-censorship-case-a6871791.html "Facebook in landmark censorship case after banning French user who posted naked artwork" ''The Independent'' 13 February 2016]&lt;/ref&gt; 

The German-born Turkish artist [[Taner Ceylan]] has painted a work named ''1879 (From the Lost Paintings Series)'' (2011) in which a veiled Ottoman noblewoman stands before the framed canvas of ''L'Origine du monde''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Harris|first1=Garreth|title=Up front and personal: Turkish artist Taner Ceylan|url=https://www.ft.com/content/3d14ba7c-2d23-11e4-8105-00144feabdc0|accessdate=4 October 2017|work=Financial Times|date=12 September 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Taner Ceylan 1879 (FROM THE LOST PAINTING SERIES)|url=http://www.sothebys.com/en/auctions/ecatalogue/2011/contemporary-art-turkish-l11221/lot.14.html|publisher=Sothebys|accessdate=4 October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 29 May 2014, a Luxembourg performance artist, [[Deborah De Robertis]], sat on the floor in front of the painting and mimicked the view of the subject. This resulted in security guards closing the room and her arrest.{{sfn|Uparella|Jauregui|2018|pp=82-83}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.independent.co.uk/arts-entertainment/art/news/artist-arrested-again-for-nude-stunt-in-front-of-manets-olympia-in-paris-gallery-a6819886.html|title=An artist has been arrested (again) for a nude stunt in a Paris gallery|date=18 January 2016|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

US artist [[Candice Lin]] recreated ''L’Origine du monde'' in a video of her an audiovisual sculpture ''Hunter Moon / Inside Out'' (2015). In it, ''Courbet’s L’Origine du monde with eyes'' "looks back at the onlookers." From a feminist point of view, Lin's work challenges "the asymmetry of power [...] between those who look and those who are seen."{{sfn|Uparella|Jauregui|2018|p=85}}

== Filmography ==
*Jean Paul Fargier, {{Lang|fr|L'Origine du monde}}, 1996, 26 minutes&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |url         = http://www.arte.tv/fr/art-musique/Gustave-Courbet/A-l-antenne/1717472.html
 |title       = Documentaire de Jean-Paul Fargier
 |accessdate  = 14 July 2008
 |date        = 2 November 2007
 |publisher   = [[Arte|arte tv]]
 |language    = French
 |deadurl     = yes
 |archiveurl  = https://web.archive.org/web/20081229160344/http://www.arte.tv/fr/art-musique/Gustave-Courbet/A-l-antenne/1717472.html
 |archivedate = 29 December 2008
 |df          = 
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
'''Notes'''
&lt;references /&gt;

'''Sources'''
*{{cite journal|first=Philippe|last=Dagen|date=21 June 1995|title=Le Musée d'Orsay dévoile ''L'Origine du monde''|journal=[[Le Monde]]}} 
*{{cite journal|first=Philippe|last=Dagen|date=22 October 1996|title=Sexe, peinture et secret|journal=Le Monde}}
*{{cite book |last=Du Camp |first=Maxime |author-link=Maxime du Camp |date=1878 |title=Les Convulsions de Paris |volume=Volume II: ''Épisodes de la Commune'' |url=https://archive.org/stream/lesconvulsionsde02ducauoft#page/180/mode/2up |language=French |location=Paris |publisher=Hachette |ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|first=Isabelle Enaud|last=Lechien|title=James Whistler|publisher=ACR Édition}}
*{{cite book|first=Stéphane |last=Guégan|author2=Michèle Haddad|title=L'ABCdaire de Courbet|publisher=Flammarion}}
*{{cite news |last=Noiville |first=Florence |author-link=Florence Noiville |date=25 March 1994 |title=Le retour du puritanisme |work=Le Monde }}
*{{cite book|first=Thierry |last=Savatier|title=L'Origine du monde, histoire d'un tableau de Gustave Courbet|location=Paris|publisher=Bartillat|year=2006}}
*{{cite book|first=Thomas |last=Schlesser|chapter=L'Origine du monde|title=Dictionnaire de la pornographie|location=Paris|publisher=Presses Universitaires de France|year=2005}}
*{{cite book|first=Bernard |last=Teyssèdre|title=Le roman de l'Origine|location=Paris|publisher=Gallimard|year=1996}}
*{{cite journal |first1=Paola |last1=Uparella |first2=Carlos A. |last2=Jauregui |title=The Vagina and the Eye of Power (Essay on Genitalia and Visual Sovereignty) |journal=H-Art |volume=3 |date=2018 |pages=79-114 |url=https://www.academia.edu/37253337/The_Vagina_and_the_Eye_of_Power_Essay_on_Genitalia_and_Visual_Sovereignty_ |doi=10.25025/hart03.2018.04 |ref=harv }}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|L'Origine du monde}}
*[http://www.musee-orsay.fr/en/collections/works-in-focus/search/commentaire/commentaire_id/the-origin-of-the-world-3122.html Musée d'Orsay: ''L'Origine du monde''] {{en icon}}
* [http://www.musee-orsay.fr/index.php?id=851&amp;L=0&amp;tx_commentaire_pi1%5BshowUid%5D=125&amp;no_cache=1 Musée d'Orsay: ''L'Origine du monde''] {{fr icon}}
* [http://www.musee-orsay.fr/fr/collections/catalogue-des-oeuvres/notice.html?no_cache=1&amp;nnumid=69330 Musée d'Orsay: ''L'Origine du monde'' – Notice d´Oeuvre] {{fr icon}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20150217201825/http://www.caraa.fr/EN/detail-actu.php?actu=18 News from CARAA] {{fr icon}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20101205031018/http://www.franceculture.com/culture-ac-l-origine-du-monde-de-courbet-l-origine-du-monde-de-courbet.html Conference from Musée d'Orsay] {{fr icon}}
* [http://www.francois-murez.com/compocourbet%20en.htm Composition] of ''L'Origine du monde''
* [https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-45637037 2018 BBC story]

{{Courbet}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Origine Du Monde}}
[[Category:1866 paintings]]
[[Category:Collections of the Musée d'Orsay]]
[[Category:Paintings by Gustave Courbet]]
[[Category:Nude art]]
[[Category:Erotic art]]
[[Category:Art works that caused riots]]
[[Category:Censorship in the arts]]
[[Category:Vagina and vulva in art]]</text>
      <sha1>ktnrwb1eqyad1qaqaxx9sz2tkoo7yfx</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Mission muralismo</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>31727578</id>
    <revision>
      <id>743685435</id>
      <parentid>710588129</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-10T18:29:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Cydebot</username>
        <id>1215485</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Robot - Moving category San Francisco, California to [[:Category:San Francisco]] per [[WP:CFD|CFD]] at [[Wikipedia:Categories for discussion/Log/2016 September 6]].</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="5846">{{cleanup|date=May 2011}}
'''Mission Muralismo''' was an artistic movement that brought awareness of issues as well as depicted everyday life as lived by the people in the [[Mission District, San Francisco|San Francisco Mission District]] and other barrios around the world. The Mission was an artistic playground for muralists to speak out about injustices and social issues around their city, the country and the world. Latin American muralists voiced their cries for international attention and aimed to create awareness for the social and political problems of Latin America through the murals they painted. The [[Nicaraguan]] community especially contributed to artistic projects to shed light on the [[Nicaraguan Revolution]] and their struggles from 1979 to the 1990s.

== Origins and Influences ==

Murialismo can credit its origins to agencies like the [[Works Progress Administration]] (WPA), a [[New Deal]] federal program established during the Great Depression to employ millions of struggling Americans to carry out public works projects along with supporting large arts, drama, media, and literacy projects.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Kennedy|first=David|title=Freedom From Fear|year=1999|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=0-9650868-9-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; The WPA helped fund artists like [[Diego Rivera]] in the 1930s, who helped bring an international muralist perspective to the Mission District. Other muralists like [[David Siqueiros|David Alfaro Siquieros]] and [[José Clemente Orozco]] who, with Rivera, made up the group Los Tres Grandes, also continued to innovate and bring “stylistic orthodoxy” to make “ideological and religious tableaux”.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Jacoby|first=Annice|title=Street Art San Francisco: Mission Muralismo|year=2009|publisher=Abrams|isbn=978-0-8109-9635-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

This foundation and influence was at the core of Mission Muralismo as values like being “outscale” and “outspoken” became standard in the murals and projects painted throughout the decades. The nature of being outspoken is what helped contribute to the precedent that murals in the Mission District aimed to present.

== Solidarity with Latin American Movements ==

Beyond Mexican muralists in the 1930s to the 1960s, there was a growing Central American refugees escaping political turbulence and civil war in the 1970s, some of whom found refuge in the Mission District. Nicaraguan artists and poets in particular found a home in San Francisco to build a solidarity movement with the Nicaraguan struggle. [[Roberto Vargas (poet)|Roberto Vargas]], a famed literary figure in the Nicaraguan community, critically stated, “we came in the human wave fleeing the brutality of the Somoza regime”—the human wave being the vast migration of Nicaraguan refugees.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Perez|first=Gina M.|title=Beyond El Barrio|year=2010|publisher=New York University Press|location=New York|isbn=978-0-8147-9129-5|display-authors=etal}}&lt;/ref&gt; With poets and artists like Vargas, along with the aftermath of the political atmosphere of the late 1960s in the Bay Area, the struggle to liberate Nicaragua from Somoza’s regime continued in the Mission District. The Nicaraguans who came from that human wave banded together and created a movement from the barrio, showing a strong sense of solidarity for the Sandinista struggle in Nicaragua by setting up offices for the Sandinista Front and spreading the word on the uprising through La Prensa, a newspaper from Managua, Nicaragua.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Perez|first=Gina M.|title=Beyond El Barrio|year=2010|publisher=New York University Press|location=New York|isbn=978-0-8147-9129-5|display-authors=etal}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== The Murals ==

The Sandinista victory brought forth a great sense of pride from the Nicaraguan community as well as building bridges with other Latin American communities. The exterior of Casa Nicargua in the Mission District boasts a mural featuring “Chilean and Nicaraguan symbols beneath a handshake of support between the two countries,” reflecting the respect the Nicaraguan community has for the [[Chile]]an government under the fallen President [[Salvador Allende]] and celebrating the Sandinista victory.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Perez|first=Gina M.|title=Beyond El Barrio|year=2010|publisher=New York University Press|location=New York|isbn=978-0-8147-9129-5|display-authors=etal}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the decade that the Sandinistas controlled Nicaragua, “close to three hundred murals were created” by muralists who traveled to Nicaragua from the Bay Area to bring the solidarity movement back to the homeland, showing an American support from the barrio of the Mission District to the barrios in Nicaragua.

== Recognition ==

Although the murals exist in the Mission District and in Nicaragua, more notable movements like the United States’ government support for the Contra War, the effort to establish a counter military movement to combat and overthrow the Sandinista government, suppress the artistic movement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Perez|first=Gina M.|title=Beyond El Barrio|year=2010|publisher=New York University Press|location=New York|isbn=978-0-8147-9129-5|display-authors=etal}}&lt;/ref&gt; Mission Muralismo and its influence on the Nicaraguan solidarity struggle is imperative to understand how the politics and atmosphere of political turbulence affected the barrios in Nicaragua and the barrios created in the United States as a result of the conflict. The murals serve as a voice for the barrio, one of the many tools used to make concerns vocal and visible to their communities in Nicaragua and in their new American home.

== See also ==
* [[Clarion Alley Mural Project]] / [[Clarion Alley]]
* [[Balmy Alley]]
* [[Precita Eyes]]
* [[The Women's Building]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

[[Category:Art movements]]
[[Category:San Francisco]]</text>
      <sha1>jb97w6jx6mfteqfi5qswwaqbfluny4z</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Opus signinum</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6034513</id>
    <revision>
      <id>804619803</id>
      <parentid>804619519</parentid>
      <timestamp>2017-10-10T04:34:05Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>75.167.50.137</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Fixed/added reference text.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="4529">[[File:Canal Italica.jpg|thumb|right|An example of opus signinum: The [[Aqueduct (water supply)|aqueduct]] of Itálica near [[Seville]].]]
[[File:Haselburg_opus_signinum.jpg|thumb|''opus signinum''-piece from the ''Roman Villa Haselburg'', near [[Höchst im Odenwald]]]]
[[File:Opus Signinum.JPG|thumb|reconstructed ''opus signinum'' in the [[European Archaeological Park of Bliesbruck-Reinheim]]]]
'''Opus signinum''' ('cocciopesto' in modern Italian) is a building material used in [[ancient Rome]]. It is  made of tiles broken up into very small pieces, mixed with mortar, and then beaten down with a rammer.&lt;ref&gt;Signīnum Opus. Harry Thurston Peck, Harpers Dictionary of Classical Antiquities (1898). [http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus:text:1999.02.0137:book=35:chapter=46&amp;highlight=signinum%2Copus]&lt;/ref&gt; Pliny in his [[Natural History (Pliny)|Natural History]] describes its manufacture: "Even broken pottery has been utilized; it being found that, beaten to powder, and tempered with lime, it becomes more solid and durable than other substances of a similar nature; forming the cement known as the "Signine" composition, so extensively employed for even making the pavements of houses."&lt;ref&gt;[http://old.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/ptext?doc=Perseus:text:1999.02.0137&amp;layout=&amp;loc=35.46 Pliny, Natural History, book 35, chapter 46]&lt;/ref&gt; Pliny's use of the term "Signine" references "Signia (modern Segni), the name of a town in Latium which was famous for its tiles."&lt;ref&gt;[https://en.oxforddictionaries.com/definition/opus_signinum https://en.oxforddictionaries.com/definition/opus_signinum]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Origins, spread, disuse==
The technique began in North Africa, some time before 256 B.C., and spread north from there to Sicily and finally to the Italian peninsula.&lt;ref&gt;The Decorated Pavements of Morgantina II: The Opus Signinum. Author(s): Barbara Tsakirgis. [[American Journal of Archaeology]], Vol. 94, No. 3 (Jul., 1990), pp. 425-443. Archaeological Institute of America. {{jstor|505795}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The houses at Kerkouane on Cap Bon in Tunisia have opus signinum floors. The floors must date before 256 B.C., since the town was destroyed in that year by Regulus. Kerkouane I 79. H. Joyce, "Form, Function and Technique in the Pavements of Delos and Pompeii," AJA 83 (1979) 259.&lt;/ref&gt; Floors of signinum are found extensively in the Punic towns of North Africa and commonly in the Hellenistic houses on Sicily.&lt;ref&gt;For the signinum in the North African houses, see D. Harden, The Phoenicians (London 1962) 133-34; T. Carter, "Western Phoenicians at Lepcis Magna," AJA 69 (1965) 128, pl. 33; M. Fantar, "Pavimenta Punica et signe dit de Tanit dans les habitations de Kerkouane," Studi Magrebini 1 (1966) 57-65; M. Fantar, "Les Pavements puniques," Les Dossiers de l'Archeologie (1978) 6-11; Kerkouane I 502-503; Kerkouane II; S. Lancel, "Les Pavimenta Punica du quartier punique tardif de la colline de Byrsa," Cahiers des etudes anciennes 17 (1985) 157-77. For the signinum floors in Sicilian houses, see for Agrigento: R.P. Jones and E.A. Gardner, JHS 26 (1906) 207-12; E. Gabrici, NSc 1925, 425-37; for Avola: M.T. Currò, BdA 51 (1966) 94; for Gela: D. Adames- teanu, NSc 1956, 346; for Heraclea Minoa: E. De Miro, Kokalos 12 (1966) 227; for Monte Iato: H.P. Isler, AntK 26 (1983) 39; for Solunto: M. deVos, BABESCH 50 (1975) 195- 224; for Syracuse: G. Gentili, NSc 1951, 156-57, NSc 1957, 282, 292; for Tindari: L. Bernabò Brea, BdA 50 (1965) 207.&lt;/ref&gt; While some signinum pavements have been found in Rome, the technique is not common there.&lt;ref&gt;M.L. Morricone Matini. Mosaici antichi in Italia: Pavimenti di signino repubblicani di Roma e dintorni (Rome 1971).&lt;/ref&gt; [[Vitruvius]] describes the process of laying a floor, whether signinum or mosaic.&lt;ref&gt;[http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Vitruvius/7*.html Marcus Vitruvius Pollio: de Architectura, Book VII]&lt;/ref&gt; The trend began in the 1st century BC, proliferating in private homes as well as public buildings.&lt;ref&gt;F. Sear. Roman Wall and Vault Mosaics. Heidelberg 1977&lt;/ref&gt; By the 2nd century, opus signinum would give way to more patterned styles of pavement.

==References==
{{Reflist}}
* {{cite book | first=V. | last=Vassal | title=Les Pavements d'Opus signinum : technique, décor, fonction architecturale | location=Oxford | year=2006}}

==External links==

{{DEFAULTSORT:Opus Signinum}}
[[Category:Building materials]]
[[Category:Artistic techniques]]
[[Category:Ancient Roman architecture]]
[[Category:Concrete]]</text>
      <sha1>63z54kxa7cdkyf2vb8b9xwjqi58nkfu</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Origin story</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4374325</id>
    <revision>
      <id>856249529</id>
      <parentid>856249489</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-08-23T22:14:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Flowerpiep</username>
        <id>32266845</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Critical explorations of the origin story */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="27827">{{about|the back-stories of fictional characters|myths about origins of world phenomena|Origin myth|other uses of "origin"|Origin (disambiguation)}}
In [[entertainment]], an '''origin story''' is an account or [[back-story]] revealing how a [[Character (arts)|character]] or group of people become a [[protagonist]] or [[antagonist]], and it adds to the overall study of a [[narrative]], often giving reasons for their intentions.

In [[American comic book]]s, it also refers to how characters gained their [[Superpower (ability)|superpower]]s and/or the circumstances under which they became [[superhero]]es or [[supervillain]]s. In order to keep their characters current, comic book companies, as well as cartoon companies, game companies, children's show companies, and toy companies, frequently rewrite the origins of their oldest characters. This goes from adding details that do not contradict earlier facts to a totally new origin which makes it seem that it is an altogether different character.

A [[pourquoi story]], also dubbed an "origin story", is also used in [[mythology]], referring to narratives of how a world began, how creatures and plants came into existence, and why certain things in the cosmos have certain yet distinct qualities.

== Critical explorations of the origin story ==

In ''The Superhero Reader'' (nominated for a 2014 [[Eisner Award]] for Best Scholarly/Academic Work), edited by Charles Hatfield (Professor at University of Connecticut), Jeet Heer (Toronto-based journalist), and Dr. Kent Worcester (Professor of Political Science at [[Marymount Manhattan College]]), the editors write in "Section One: Historical Considerations":  "Almost all superheroes have an origin story: a bedrock account of the transformative events that set the protagonist apart from ordinary humanity. If not a prerequisite for the superhero genre, the origin... is certainly a prominent and popular trope that recurs so frequently as to offer clues to the nature of this narrative tradition. To read stories about destroyed worlds, murdered parents, genetic mutations, and mysterious power-giving wizards is to realize the degree to which the superhero genre is about transformation, about identity, about difference, and about the tension between psychological rigidity and a flexible and fluid sense of human nature. ... When surveying the superhero genre, preliminary questions often turn to the problem of roots." The book has a wealth of pertinent bibliographies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author= Hatfield, Charles|title= The Superhero Reader |location= Jackson, Mississippi |publisher= University Press of Mississippi |year= 2013 |page= 3 |ISBN= 9781617038068|display-authors=etal}}&lt;/ref&gt;

English professors Dr. Alex Romagnoli and Dr. Gian S. Pagnucci, of [[Indiana University of Pennsylvania]], discuss in their book ''Enter the Superheroes: American Values, Culture, and the Canon of Superhero Literature'' "the nature of superhero origin stories and how the writing of these origin stories helps make superhero narratives a unique literary genre."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1= Romagnoli |first1= Alex S. |last2= Pagnucci |first2= Gian S. |title= Enter the Superheroes: American Values, Culture, and the Canon of Superhero Literature |chapter= Introduction |location= Lanham, Maryland |publisher= [[Rowman &amp; Littlefield#Scarecrow Books|Scarecrow Books]] |year= 2013 |page= 3 |ISBN= 0-810-89171-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, they write, "Superheroes get very complicated when it comes to their histories, but one part of their stories remains forever constant and important. Even more than 'death' stories, [[Fictional crossover|crossovers]], event stories, and attire changes, origin stories are the core of superheroes' existences. Origins not only reflect the sociohistorical contexts in which heroes were created, but they also reflect a culture's understanding of what makes superheroes storytelling unique vehicles."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1= Romagnoli |first1= Alex S. |last2= Pagnucci |first2= Gian S. |title= Enter the Superheroes: American Values, Culture, and the Canon of Superhero Literature |chapter= 6. Superhero Storytelling |location= Lanham, Maryland |publisher= [[Rowman &amp; Littlefield#Scarecrow Books|Scarecrow Books]] |year= 2013 |page= 109 |ISBN= 0-810-89171-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thereafter, Romagnoli and Pagnucci go on to explain why the origin story is as important to the audience as to the generations of writers who continue heroic tales.

Dr. Randy Duncan (comics scholar and professor of communication, Henderson State University, Arkadelphia, Arkansas) and Dr. Matthew J. Smith (Department of Communication, Wittenberg University, Springfield, Ohio) use the origin story of [[Spider-Man]] as an example of how a [[Character (arts)|character]] can be created by the persistence of a writer who has definite preferences in creating a character's personality, even if the publisher resists. "It is difficult to discern which is more often told: Spider-Man's origin or the tales told around that origin. All reveal fascinating aspects of a teenage loner fatefully 'bitten by a radioactive spider' to find himself with 'the proportionate strength and agility of an arachnid'." Duncan and Smith explain how [[Stan Lee]] butted heads with publisher [[Martin Goodman (publisher)|Martin Goodman]], who worried about an "ick factor," but Lee prevailed. "The entire Spider-Man concept resonates with the primary attributes of many genres and traditions," the authors say. "Like a heady puree of [Mary] Shelley's ''[[Frankenstein]]'', Bob Kane's Batman, and Franz Kafka's ''Metamorphosis'', Spider-Man's origin invokes gothic and crime fiction motifs like the ostracized genius, doomed loved ones, the misuse or misfiring of science, the gritty noir city, the driven vigilante, and the fateful [[Uncanny|'return of the repressed']]."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1= Duncan |first1= Randy |last2= Smith |first2= Matthew J. |title= Icons of the American Comic Book: From Captain America to Wonder Woman |location= Santa Barbara, CA |publisher= Greenwood Press |series= (Series: Greenwood icons) |year= 2013 |volume= Vol. 1 |page= 684 |ISBN= 9780313399237}}&lt;/ref&gt; The authors proceed to investigate these various issues of the origin story.

== Examples==
{{Very long|list|date=September 2017}}
'''Heroes'''
*[[Batman]] – His parents murdered by a [[Joe Chill|mugger]], Bruce Wayne trained himself and used his vast family fortune to become Batman and wage a one-man war on crime.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= O'Neil |first= Dennis |authorlink= Dennis O'Neil |chapter= Introduction |title= Batman and Psychology: A Dark and Stormy Knight |editor= Travis Langley |location= Hoboken, New Jersey |publisher= John Wiley &amp; Sons, Inc. |year= 2012 |page= 2 |quote= He evolved. The essence of what his creators, Bill Finger and Bob Kane, brought to the party in 1939 hadn't changed much: the nocturnal vigilante endlessly and symbolically avenging his parents' murders; an origin tale stark and simple and primal and, I submit, perfect. But virtually everything else ''did'' change over the decades: costumes and supporting cast and crime-fighting gadgetry and the kinds of crimes fought and the kinds of villains... The range of stories appearing under the Batman logo went from farcical to macabre, while always being a Batman. Not ''the'' Batman – there is no ''the'' Batman – but a Batman, one appropriate to whatever was contemporary. |ISBN= 978-1-118-16765-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= Langley |first= Travis |chapter= 1. Beneath the Cowl: Who is Batman? |title= Batman and Psychology: A Dark and Stormy Knight |location= Hoboken, NJ |publisher= John Wiley &amp; Sons, Inc. |year= 2012 |page= 6 |quote= His origin is tragic and brutally believable. It taps the most primal of our childhood fears: A family outing twists into tragedy when a mugger guns his parents down before his eyes. |ISBN= 978-1-118-16765-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= Uslan |first= Michael |authorlink= Michael Uslan |editor= Travis Langley |chapter= 3. The Trauma |title= Batman and Psychology: A Dark and Stormy Knight |location= Hoboken, NJ |publisher= John Wiley &amp; Sons, Inc. |year= 2012 |page= 35 |quote= This is such a primal origin story. A kid watches his parents murdered in front of his eyes on a concrete altar of blood and at that moment sacrifices his childhood and makes a commitment, a commitment that he intends to honor even if he has to walk through hell for the rest of his life to get the guy who did this, to get all the bad guys... it all starts with the origin. |ISBN= 978-1-118-16765-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= Porter |first= Alan J. |authorlink= Alan J. Porter |chapter= The Dubious Origins of the Batman: Who Did What – And Does it Really Matter? |title= Batman Unauthorized: Vigilantes, Jokers, and Heroes in Gotham City |editor= [[Dennis O'Neil]] |location= Dallas, Texas |publisher= [[BenBella Books]], Inc. |year= 2013 |page= 86 |quote= The origin story of the Batman is an essential part of his mythos. The small details may vary with each interpretation, but the underlying theme of loss and vengeance is as integral to the legend as the cape and the cowl. From comics to books, radio, television, and the movies, almost every time the Batman story is told[,] this single event is referenced. |series= (Smart Pop series) |ISBN= 978-1-933-77130-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;   
*[[Spider-Man]] – Bitten by a radioactive spider, Peter Parker found himself bestowed with spider-based superpowers. He was motivated to fight crime by his [[uncle Ben|uncle's]] death, which he blames on himself.&lt;br/&gt;A 2012 comic book specifically addresses the origin of Peter's transformation: ''The Amazing Spider-Man: An Origin Story'' (authors given as [[Marvel Comics|Marvel]] Staff, [[Scott Peterson (comics)|Scott Peterson]], [[Stan Lee]], and [[Steve Ditko]]; 64 pp.; {{ISBN|978-1-74283-234-0}}); as well as its identically named revision ''The Amazing Spider-Man: An Origin Story'' (2013; {{ISBN|1742837271}}).&lt;br/&gt;Works both scholarly and entertaining discuss Peter's origin story and its variations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= Tallon |first= Philip |chapter= 6. With Great Power Comes Great Culpability: How Blameworthy is Spider-Man for Uncle Ben's Death? |title= Spider-Man and Philosophy: The Web of Inquiry |editor= Jonathan J. Sanford |location= Hoboken, New Jersey |publisher= John Wiley &amp; Sons, Inc. |year= 2012 |series= (Blackwell philosophy and pop culture series) |pages= 86, 99 |quote= Ben's death is not only an important event in the life of Peter Parker, it may also be the most famous fatality in all of comics – not to mention one of the only ''final'' fatalities. ... [T]he death of Peter Parker's uncle powerfully shapes his hero ethos and his desire to fight crime. ... [Footnote 1] There are three notable differences between the film and the comic versions of the Spider-Man origin. The first is that in the comic, Peter Parker was not provoked in any way to allow the thief to escape (as he was in the film by the rude behavior of the promoter). The second is that in ''Amazing Fantasy #15'', Uncle Ben never utters the line "With great power comes great responsibility." Rather, this line is stated in the final narration. The third is that in the film, Uncle Ben is killed while waiting for Peter in the car, but in the comic, he's killed in a home invasion. Notably, in more recent issues of the comic, Uncle Ben's murder and the origin of the "great responsibility" line have been retroactively changed ("[[Retroactive continuity|retconned]]") to fit with the movie version. |ISBN= 978-0-470-57560-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1= Duncan |first1= Randy |last2= Smith |first2= Matthew J. |title= Icons of the American Comic Book: From Captain America to Wonder Woman |location= Santa Barbara, CA |publisher= Greenwood Press |series= (Series: Greenwood icons) |year= 2013 |volume= 1 |page= 684 |isbn= 9780313399237 |quote= In the final panel of his origin story, a devastated Spider-Man turns away from readers: 'a lean and silent figure' fades 'into the gathering darkness, aware at last that in this world, with great power must also come – great responsibility!' (''[[Amazing Fantasy]]'' #15, 1962).}}&lt;/ref&gt;  
*[[Superman]] – Born on the planet [[Krypton (comics)|Krypton]], infant Kal-El was sent to Earth before an explosion destroyed his home planet. His strong sense of morality motivated him to fight for justice.
*[[Wonder Woman]] – Diana, the princess and appointed champion of the Amazon warrior women, who left her homeland to battle injustice in the world of men.
*[[Iron Man]] – American industrialist Tony Stark was captured by Communist Vietnamese military and forced to build weapons for them. Instead, he built powered armor to escape. He then uses his armor to fight crime.
*[[Fantastic Four]] – Four astronauts (Reed Richards, Sue and Johnny Storm, and Ben Grimm) who were exposed to cosmic rays, which gave them superpowers.
* [[The Flash]] – [[Flash (Barry Allen)|Barry Allen]], a [[forensic scientist]], was struck by lightning and bathed in electrically charged chemicals, connecting him to the [[Speed Force]] and giving him super-speed.
*[[Incredible Hulk]] – Dr. Bruce Banner, belted by gamma rays, now turns into the super-strong Hulk whenever he gets very mad.
*[[Green Lantern]] – Test pilot [[Hal Jordan]] receives a [[Power ring (DC Comics)|power ring]] from the dying alien police officer, [[Abin Sur]], and becomes a member of the [[Green Lantern Corps]].
*[[James T. Kirk]] – Inspired by both the adventures of Captain Jonathan Archer, and his own father, Kirk joined starfleet in order to explore the stars and defend the united federation of planets. In the [[Star Trek (2009)|2009 film]], Kirk was inspired by his father's sacrifice and chose to bring back the honor that his name once held.
*[[Sabrina Spellman]] – Hilda and Zelda Spellman mix magic potions and ingredients to create an evil, wicked witch. Unfortunately, they accidentally got a wrong potion as an extra ingredient and then Sabrina Spellman is born. This origin story, however, was later retconned as it is now said that Sabrina, a "half-witch" (her mother is an ordinary human, or "mortal" as witches refer to them, while her father is a witch) lives with Hilda and Zelda (both witches themselves)
*[[Bibi Blocksberg]] – After Bernhard and Barbara Blocksberg got married, Barbara mixes magic potions and ingredients to create her own daughter and then Bibi Blocksberg is born.
*[[Bobby Generic]] – Born on Bobbyland, a bright and happy magical world where he can play, have fun and having the exciting adventures happen every day as Bobby uses his imagination. One day, Bobby is banished to Earth by an evil queen and meets the Generic family, Roger the dog and pig-tailed tomboy, Jackie.
*[[Sophie (comics)|Sophie Karamazout]] – Mr. Karamazout is the inventor, which he had no wife and even no children. So, he decided to have his own daughter. He mixes the ingredients to create a little girl using a mixture of sugar, spice, and everything nice. Then, Sophie Karamazout is born.
*[[The Powerpuff Girls]] – Professor Utonium mixes the ingredients to create the perfect little girls using a mixture of sugar, spice, and everything nice. However, he accidentally spilled an extra ingredient called "Chemical X" into the mixture, due to being pushed by his monkey lab assistant, Jojo, creating, instead of the perfect little girl, Blossom, Bubbles and Buttercup.
*[[Judge Dredd]] – Awoken from his sleep with his clone Rico, Joseph Dredd witnesses nuclear war going on. They then split up. Rico becomes an evil-doer, Joseph becomes the toughest judge yet — Judge Dredd.
*[[Gigantor]] – Built as the 28th creation of a kind professor.
*[[Astro Boy]] – A robot created to replace his creator's son, who was killed in a car accident in the anime and by a robot in the film, and was equipped with weapons that he uses to fight crime.
*[[Inspector Gadget]] – John Brown is a security guard, who is dreaming of becoming a police officer. Brown chases Sanford Scolex (Dr. Claw) down in his car, which leads to it being killed by Scolex's explosive cigar, leaving Brown died. He was resurrected as a cyborg. Under Brenda’s guidance, John Brown becomes Inspector Gadget.
*[[Turbo (film)|Turbo]] – Theo is a garden snail who dreams of becoming a racer. As he wanders onto a freeway to admire the traffic, he wishes he was fast on the first star. Suddenly, he gets into a freak accident when he gets sucked into the supercharger of a drag racer, fusing his DNA with nitrous oxide, giving him super speed.
*[[Atomic Betty]] – Born on the planet Bane of Fragnog, she began training with her martial arts master, Spindly Tam Kanushu. As she grew up, she came to the planet Earth.
*[[Turbo Teen]] – Brett and his car were driving through a stormy mountain, and then a tree swerved them off the road into the path of Dr. Chase's experiment. He and his car are now one — Turbo Teen.
*The [[Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles]] – When a boy was walking, carrying his four turtles in a bowl of water, a toxic slime truck stood in his way. All four turtles and the slime fell into the sewers, where Splinter raised the turtles. They then came to fight an evil that invaded New York in the form of the Shredder.
*[[SuperTed]] – He was a discarded toy given life by Spotty and superpowers by Mother Nature.
*[[Optimus Prime]] – In the cartoon, Optimus Prime, his [[Autobots]], and the [[Decepticons]], led by [[Megatron]], are at war with each other until they crash landed on Earth in a 4-million-year-old sleep. That is until they scanned vehicles, weapons, and animals in order to become the Transformers we know. Optimus Prime scanned the truck he is now.
*The [[Mighty Morphin' Power Rangers]] – They were five ordinary teenagers chosen by Zordon to become the world's colorful superpowered heroes, the Power Rangers.
*[[Masked Rider (TV series)|Masked Rider]] – Dex was given powers by his grandfather, the king of Edenoi, and is sent to our world to protect it from the advancing evil of Count Dregon. Dex was raised by a family, and learns to live as a human. With his companion Ferbus by his side, Dex is ever vigilant, ready to call on his powers in order to become Masked Rider.
*[[RoboCop]] – Originally, Officer Alex Murphy is killed in the line of duty and brought back to life as a crime-fighting cyborg called RoboCop; in the remade film, he is horrifically wounded and rebuilt as a cyborg.
*[[Captain America]] – While taking on the [[Red Skull]], Captain America fell into the sea, where he was frozen until the present day.
*[[Thor (Marvel comics)|Thor]] – Thor was banished from his home realm, [[Asgard (comics)|Asgard]], and ended up on Earth.
*[[He-Man]] and [[She-Ra]] – They were brother and sister twins, separated due to their enemies Hordak and Skeletor. He-Man lived in Eternia, She-Ra lived in Etheria.
*[[Xena: The Warrior Princess|Xena]] – Xena was the chosen one to fight all that is evil, although she was separated from her parents during war.
*[[Conan the Barbarian]] – Conan's family was killed in the films or turned to stone in the cartoon. He swears to destroy all evil within his land.
*[[Daredevil (Marvel Comics series)|Daredevil]] – He was blinded by chemicals, and he devotes to fight crime as Daredevil, but he's normally Matt Murdock.
*The [[Punisher]] – His family was killed by mobsters, and Frank Castle devotes to fight crime as the Punisher.
*[[Harry Potter]] – He is a wizard and his parents were killed by Voldemort, who left him with a scar.
*[[Wolverine (character)|Wolverine]] – After he got bone claws, his claws fused with adamantium, and he escapes the pool he was in, the very same pool which made his bones become adamantium.
*[[Ghost Rider]] – He is a motorcycle stuntman. Possessed by a demon to take on crime.
*[[Machete (2010 film)|Machete]] – Machete was a man with an injured leg befriended by his priest brother.
*The [[Biker Mice From Mars]] – They came from Mars, their world that was enslaved by Plutarkians (1993) and Catatonians (2006), to our world. They consist of Modo, Vinnie, and their leader Throttle.
*[[Captain Marvel (Shazam)]] – A boy named Billy shouts "Shazam!" to become Captain Marvel.
*[[Strider Hiryu]] – A brave assassin sent by the Striders to kill Grandmaster Meio.
*[[Mega Man (character)|Mega Man]] – Mega Man was the second creation of Dr. Light/Dr. Wright after the failed Proto Man. Dr. Wily, a world dominator-to-be, wanted Mega Man dead or alive by turning Dr. Light's creations against the good doctor.
*[[King Arthur]] – According to legend, when he was a child, he pulled out a sword from a stone, thus becoming king.
*[[Puss in Boots (Shrek)|Puss in Boots]] – He was an orphaned talking cat, who befriended [[List of Shrek characters#Humpty Dumpty|Humpty Alexander Dumpty]] at an orphanage. They both stole different types of beans in the search of the magic beans. After some time, Puss gave up stealing things. But, Humpty, unable to steal without the cat's help, tricked him into a bank robbery. From then on, Puss became a fugitive from law, searching a way to clear his name.
*[[Arrow (TV series)|Arrow]] – Oliver Queen was a billionaire playboy who was shipwrecked on an island in the middle of the Pacific. Five years later he returns home on a quest to save his city.
*[[Danger Mouse (1981 TV series)|Danger Mouse]] – How Danger Mouse got his eyepatch remains a question, but one origin story in the 2015 series is that his eye got damaged by Baron Silas Greenback.
*[[Thunderbirds Are Go (TV series)|International Rescue]] – Formed by the Tracy family and run by their father Jeff, who supposedly perished in a boat or jet collision caused by their nemesis the Hood.
*[[Peter Pan (character)|Peter Pan]] – In [[Pan (2015 film)|the 2015 film]], Peter was kidnapped by Blackbeard. Then he befriended his future enemy [[Captain Hook]]. From the Indians of Neverland, he got his powers and his crowing to defeat Blackbeard.
*[[Loonatics Unleashed|The Loonatics]] – In the year 2772, a meteor strikes the planet Acmetropolis, knocking it off its axis. It gave Ace Bunny, his sister Lexi, Danger Duck, Slam Tasmanian, Tech E. Coyote, and Rev Runner special superpowers.
*Mr Woo – In 1969, Frank Woo was about to get married to his wife, Madame Wong, when a man who was secretly being controlled by the evil Fuzzball stole their ring. The couple chased after him, taking them on their first big adventure. Along the way, the two learned how to use various weapons and powers by utilizing mysterious manholes. In the Mr Woo Land series reboot, as the events of Mr Woo Land 3 never happened, Mr Woo and Madame Wong instead learned their abilities during this game. 
*[[Crash Bandicoot (character)|Crash Bandicoot]] – Crash was once an ordinary eastern barred bandicoot before he was snatched from the wild by [[Doctor Neo Cortex]] and subjected to the Evolvo-Ray as part of Cortex's plan to make Crash the "general" of his "Cortex Commandos", which would be used to dominate the world. However, he is later deemed unworthy of being in Cortex's army and escapes from Cortex's castle. As an act of revenge and to rescue a female bandicoot named Tawna, Crash travels through the Wumpa Islands, defeating Cortex's henchmen along the way. He eventually steals Cortex's airship, defeats Doctor Cortex, and escapes alongside Tawna.
'''Villains'''
*[[Joker (comics)|The Joker]] – Famous for not having a definitive origin story, claiming that he remembers his start in villainy under different circumstances, but the generally accepted (though not definitive) origin is described as follows: an unnamed criminal using the persona of the [[Red Hood]] fell in a vat of chemicals that turned his hair green, his skin pale, and his lips red. Driven insane by this trauma, he then makes various gag-themed weapons and a toxin that kills people and leaves them with hideous grins frozen on their cadavers' faces. During his criminal career, he becomes Batman's arch-enemy.
*[[Mojo Jojo]] – A chimpanzee named Jojo, Professor Utonium's hyperactive lab assistant who always broke everything he touched. He pushed the Professor towards a beaker of Chemical X, which caused an explosion, mutating his simian DNA, turning his skin green and causing his intelligence and brain to enlarge, growing out of his skull.
*[[Dr. Two-Brains]] – Professor Steven Boxleitner was one of WordGirl's best friends. He is a kind, but easily distracted scientist. He made a device that was supposed to help people read into the minds of rodents. While doing this experiment, he was hooked up to a lab rat named Squeaky. When Boxleitner wasn't looking, Squeaky pushes a button and the result fused his mind with Squeaky's. This causes him to turn his hair white and grew whiskers on his cheeks. When Boxleitner became Dr. Two-Brains, he became one of WordGirl's arch-enemies.
*[[Dr. Claw]] – After an exploding cigar kills John Brown (Inspector Gadget) and destroying his car, a bowling ball coming from the fiery blast of the car crushes Sanford Scolex's hand, forcing him to replace it with a mechanical claw. Sanford Scolex is becoming Dr. Claw.
*[[Two-Face]] – District Attorney Harvey Dent had the left side of his face horribly scarred after criminal [[Salvatore Maroni]] threw acid in his face on trial. Harvey took a two-headed silver dollar and carved one side to make a coin he'd use to decide if he would do an act of good or evil. Since that moment, Harvey Dent became the criminal Two-Face.
*[[Denzel Crocker|Denzel Quincy Crocker]] – As a young boy, Crocker happily lived in Dimmsdale with his fairy godparents. Unfortunately, after Timmy time travels to the year 1972, Timmy and Cosmo accidentally reveals Crocker's secret about his fairies in front of the whole town who had gathered to celebrate a day honoring Crocker. Because of this, Jorgen Von Strangle is forced to erase Crocker's memory of him ever having fairies, and because of an overdose from the memory wipers, Crocker lost his fairies and he became horribly disfigured, the town's people who had now completely forgotten all the nice things that Crocker did with his fairies assumed that they must be an angry mob and chased him down. He remembers nothing but he finds a DNA tracker device that Timmy left behind in the past on which he wrote "Fairy Godparents Exist" on the back before his mind was wiped, Crocker uses it to try and find the fairies.
*[[Green Goblin]] – Norman Osborn became the insane and malevolent Green Goblin after a side effect to his experimental super serum. He then invented weapons to use to combat Spider-Man.
*[[Doctor Octopus]] – Otto Octavius became one of Spider-Man's greatest enemies after an accident fused four mechanical tentacles to his body.
*[[Bizarro]] – An imperfect and evil duplicate of Superman formed from an attempt to clone the Man of Steel.

==Comic book depictions==
&lt;!--Please keep this list alphabetical as it expands--&gt;
*''[[Batman: Year One]]'' (1987)
*''[[Gods and Mortals|Wonder Woman: Gods and Mortals]]'' (1987)
*''[[Origins (Judge Dredd story)|Judge Dredd: Origins]]''
*''[[Secret Origins]]''
*The [[origin of Superman]]
**''[[Superman: Birthright]]'' (2004)
**''[[The Man of Steel (comic book)|The Man of Steel]]'' (1986)
**''[[Superman and the Men of Steel (comic book)|Superman and the Men of Steel]]'' (2011)
*''[[Rise of Apocalypse]]'' (1997)
*''[[Origin (comics)|Origin]]'' – [[Wolverine (character)|Wolverine]]

==See also==
* [[Continuity (fiction)|Continuity]]
* [[Prequel]]
* [[Reboot (fiction)|Reboot]]
* [[Retcon]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Continuity (fiction)]]
[[Category:Fiction]]</text>
      <sha1>3wslj23vj40cv5cyw45getw5q4k1ukd</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Parzenica (folk pattern)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>17220077</id>
    <revision>
      <id>849582936</id>
      <parentid>848025140</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-07-10T00:26:53Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>CitationCleanerBot</username>
        <id>15270283</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Various citation &amp; identifier cleanup (mostly volume/issues), plus AWB genfixes</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="4870">[[File:Parzenica close-up.jpg|thumb|Parzenica embroidery on 19th century men's trousers, Podhale. Collection of the Tatra Museum in Zakopane.]]
A '''parzenica''' is a heart-shaped pattern of a [[Folk art|traditional]] [[needlework|handicraft]] characteristic of the [[decorative art]] of the [[Poland|Polish]] [[Gorals|highlanders]], often found embroidered on the upper front side of men's [[trousers]].&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;Condra, Jill. 2013. ''Encyclopedia of National Dress: Traditional Clothing Around the World''. Santa Barbara, CA: ABC-CLIO, p. 600.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hinds, Joan. 2002. ''World of Embellishment: Add Global Designs to Contemporary Fashions &amp; Décor''. Iola, WI: Krause Publications, p. 77.&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
This characteristic decorative motif probably originated in [[Hungary]], and by the beginning of the 20th century it became one of the most recognisable decorative patterns in the [[Podhale]] region.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;
The origin of the term is unclear, it is possibly related to old-Polish verbs ''parznąć'' and ''parznić'' meaning to make some object filthy.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.pl/books?id=cEaMLpuIfhYC&amp;pg=PA67&amp;lpg=PA67&amp;dq=Joanna+Dziadowiec,+Zeszyty+Naukowe+TDUJ2010&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=Ktt5Xypaib&amp;sig=mFsxIhSopc6BfJ6W5XwnukT0t2I&amp;hl=pl&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwjvw73L4YLRAhWBqywKHYKmD7AQ6AEIHjAA#v=onepage&amp;q=Joanna%20Dziadowiec,%20Zeszyty%20Naukowe%20TDUJ2010&amp;f=false|title=Góralskie reprezentacje, czyli rzecz o Podhalanach i ich kulturze|last=Dziadowiec|first=Joanna|work=Zeszyty Naukowe Towarzystwa Doktorantów Uniwersytetu Jagiellońskiego|publisher=|year=2010|isbn=|editor-last=Tendera|editor-first=Paulina|location=Kraków|pages=67–90|language=pl|quote=|via=|issue=numer specjalny 1/2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Initially the name also applied to various other objects popular in everyday life of the Goral people, including wooden forms used in cheese production and heart-shaped motifs used in [[wood carving]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Strój górali podhalańskich = The dress of Podhale highlanders|last=Trebunia|first=Stanisława|last2=Kubienia|first2=Jacek|last3=Bielatowicz|first3=Anna|date=2011|publisher=Fundacja Braci Golec|year=|isbn=9788392551812|series=Stroje Ludowe w Karpatach Polskich, t. 4|location=Kraków; Milówka|pages=250|language=Polish and English|translator-last=Domańska|translator-first=Monika|oclc=804547001|quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;sup&gt;.&lt;/sup&gt;The origin of the pattern itself is also unclear, some authors believe that it was imported from [[Hungary]].&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; In the second half of the 19th century, the first parzenicas made in the Tatras were but simple string loops, used for reinforcing cuts in front of cloth trousers. Such loops prevented wool fabric from fraying. With time local craftsmen adopted navy blue or red string and added additional loops to create an ornamental design rather than a simple loop. With time appliqué design was replaced with embroidery and more colours were added.&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Nowak-Hermanowicz|first=Krystyna|date=2014|title=The Costume|url=|journal=Ethnologia Polona|volume= 35|pages=101–123|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Description ==
[[File:Members of the 'Wiyrchowianie' folklore group in Podhale costume.jpg|thumb|Folk costumes from [[Podhale]], parzenica embroidery on the men`s trousers]]
The parzenica [[embroidery]] (also called ''cyfra'') dates back to the mid-19th century. Initially they were simple string loops, used for reinforcing cuts in front of cloth trousers. They had practical functions and protected the cloth from fraying. The "Knightly knot" is a decorative motif laid in three-loop of string, characteristic for highlander's male costume,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Mulkiewicz|first=Olga|year=1955|title=Parzenice gorczańskie|url=http://www.cyfrowaetnografia.pl/dlibra/editions-content?id=4061|journal=Polska Sztuka Ludowa - Konteksty|volume=9 |issue=4|pages=217–222|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; often used as base for parzenica. It is one of the eldest type of parzenicas, present in the traditional costume of highladers of [[Beskid Sądecki]], [[Gorce Mountains]] and other areas.

The modern look parzenica got from those [[tailor]]s who began using red or navy blue string, simultaneously increasing the number of loops. Later the appliqué design was replaced with embroidery. Using [[wool]]len [[yarn]] allowed the parzenica to become more colourful and eventually it become a stand-alone trouser ornamentation, developed by talented tailors and [[embroider]]ers.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Birnbaum's Eastern Europe|last=Birnbaum|first=Alexandra Mayes|publisher=HarperPerennial|year=1992|isbn=9780062780836|location=|pages=625|quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
&lt;references /&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Gorals]]
* [[National costumes of Poland]]

[[Category:Polish clothing]]
[[Category:Needlework]]
[[Category:Folklore]]
[[Category:Folk costumes]]</text>
      <sha1>4ayx75ynvvf325kb99e7vfglz72vqiw</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Performance art</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>149281</id>
    <revision>
      <id>869735572</id>
      <parentid>869735419</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-11-20T01:17:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>AmandaA123</username>
        <id>34679233</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Fixed sentence structure by moving a few words to a different point in the sentence</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="32833">{{redirect|Live art|the Béla Fleck album|Live Art}}
{{distinguish|Performing arts}}
{{merge from|Feminist performance art|discuss=Talk:Performance art#Proposed merge with Feminist performance art|date=November 2017}}
[[File:Fleeting-glimpse-bryan-zanisnik.jpg|thumb|300px|[[Bryan Zanisnik]], performance of ''When I Was a Child I Caught a Fleeting Glimpse'', 2009]]

'''Performance art''' is a performance presented to an audience within a fine art context, traditionally [[interdisciplinarity|interdisciplinary]]. Performance may be either scripted or unscripted, random or carefully orchestrated, spontaneous or otherwise carefully planned with or without audience participation. The performance can be live or via media; the performer can be present or absent. It can be any situation that involves four basic elements: time, space, the performer's body, or presence in a medium, and a relationship between performer and audience. Performance art can happen anywhere, in any type of venue or setting and for any length of time. The actions of an individual or a group at a particular place and in a particular time constitute the work.

==Visual arts, performing arts, art performance==
[[File:Lubo Kristek,2007,Requiem für die Mobiltelephone,Wien.jpg|thumb|left|''Requiem für die Mobiltelephone'' by [[Lubo Kristek]], 2007, [[Vienna]]]]
Performance art is an essentially contested concept: any single definition of it implies the recognition of rival uses. As concepts like "democracy" or "art", it implies productive disagreement with itself.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last1 = Carlson | first1 = Marvin | title = Performance: A Critical Introduction | publisher = Routledge | year = 1998 (first 1996) | location = London and New York | pages = 1, 2 | isbn = 0-415-13703-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The meaning of the term in the narrower sense is related to postmodernist traditions in Western culture. From about the mid-1960s into the 1970s, often derived from concepts of visual art, with respect to [[Antonin Artaud]], [[Dada]], the [[Situationist]]s, [[Fluxus]], [[installation art]] and [[conceptual art]], performance art tended to be defined as an [[antithesis]] to [[theatre]], challenging orthodox art forms and cultural norms. The ideal had been an ephemeral and authentic experience for performer and audience in an event that could not be repeated, captured or purchased.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last1 = Parr | first1 = Adrian | title = Becoming + Performance Art | editors = Adrian Parr | work = The Deleuze Dictionary | publisher = Edinburgh University Press | year = 2005 | pages = 25, 2 | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=OsVOy4s1QLMC&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false | accessdate = 2010-10-26 | isbn = 0748618996}}&lt;/ref&gt; The widely discussed difference, how concepts of visual arts and concepts of performing arts are utilized, can determine the meanings of a performance art presentation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last1 = Carlson | first1 = Marvin | title = Performance: A Critical Introduction | publisher = Routledge | year = 1998 (first 1996) | location = London and New York | pages = 103–105 | isbn = 0-415-13703-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Performance art is a term usually reserved to refer to a [[conceptual art]] which conveys a content-based meaning in a more drama-related sense, rather than being simple performance for its own sake for entertainment purposes. It largely refers to a performance presented to an audience, but which does not seek to present a conventional theatrical play or a formal linear narrative, or which alternately does not seek to depict a set of fictitious characters in formal scripted interactions. It therefore can include action or spoken word as a communication between the artist and audience, or even ignore expectations of an audience, rather than following a script written beforehand.

Some kinds of performance art nevertheless can be close to performing arts. Such performance may utilize a script or create a fictitious dramatic setting, but still constitute performance art in that it does not seek to follow the usual dramatic norm of creating a fictitious setting with a linear script which follows conventional real-world dynamics; rather, it would intentionally seek to satirize or to transcend the usual real-world dynamics which are used in conventional theatrical plays.

Performance artists often challenge the audience to think in new and unconventional ways, break conventions of traditional arts, and break down conventional ideas about "what art is". As long as the performer does not become a player who repeats a role, performance art can include satirical elements; utilize robots and machines as performers, as in pieces of the [[Survival Research Laboratories]]; involve ritualised elements (e.g. [[Shaun Caton]]); or borrow elements of any [[performing arts]] such as dance, music, and [[circus (performing art)|circus]].

Some artists, e.g. the [[Viennese Actionism|Viennese Actionists]] and [[neo-Dada]]ists, prefer to use the terms "live art", "action art", "actions", "intervention" (see [[art intervention]]) or "manoeuvre" to describe their performing activities. As genres of performance art appear [[body art]], fluxus-performance, [[happening]], [[action poetry]], and [[intermedia]].

==Origins==
[[Image:Le Saut Dans le Vide.jpg|thumb|left|Conceptual work by [[Yves Klein]] at Rue Gentil-Bernard, Fontenay-aux-Roses, October 1960, photo by Shunk Kender. ''Le Saut dans le Vide'' (''Leap into the Void'')]]
Performance art activity is not confined to European or American art traditions; notable practitioners can be found in [[Asia]] and [[Latin America]]. Performance artists and theorists point to different traditions and histories, ranging from tribal to sporting and ritual or religious events. In an episode of ''[[In Our Time (BBC Radio 4)|In Our Time]]'' broadcast on Thu, 20 Oct 2005, 21:30 on BBC Radio 4, [[Angie Hobbs]], Lecturer in Philosophy, University of Warwick; [[Miriam Griffin]], Fellow of Somerville College, Oxford; and [[John Moles]], Professor of Latin, University of Newcastle discussed with [[Melvyn Bragg]] the idea that [[Antisthenes]] and [[Diogenes of Sinope|Diogenes]] in ancient Greece practiced a form of performance art and that they acquired the epithet of [[Cynicism (philosophy)|cynic]] which means "dog" due to Diogenes behaving repeatedly like a dog in his performances.

Western cultural theorists often trace performance art activity back to the beginning of the 20th century, to the [[Constructivism (art)|Russian constructivists]], [[Futurism|Futurists]] and [[Dada]]. Dada provided a significant progenitor with the unconventional performances of poetry, often at the [[Cabaret Voltaire (Zurich)|Cabaret Voltaire]], by the likes of [[Richard Huelsenbeck]] and [[Tristan Tzara]]. [[Russian Futurist]] artists could be identified as precursors of performance, such as [[David Burliuk]], who painted his face for his actions (1910–20) and [[Alexander Rodchenko]] and his wife [[Varvara Stepanova]].

According to the art critic [[Harold Rosenberg]] in the 1940s and 1950s [[Action Painting]] gave artists the freedom to perform — the canvas as "an arena in which to act", thereby rendering the paintings as traces of the artist's performance in his/her studio. [[Abstract expressionism]] and [[Action painting]] preceded the [[Fluxus movement]], [[Happenings]] and the emergence of Performance Art.

Performance art was anticipated, if not explicitly formulated, by [[Japan]]'s [[Gutai group]] of the 1950s, especially in such works as [[Atsuko Tanaka (artist)|Atsuko Tanaka]]'s ''Electric Dress'' (1956).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://nymag.com/nymetro/arts/art/reviews/9937/|title=Everything Is Illuminated|website=NYMag.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Yves Klein]] had been a precursor of performance art with the conceptual pieces of ''[[Zone de Sensibilité Picturale Immatérielle]]'' (''Zones of Immaterial Pictorial Sensibility'') 1959–62, ''Anthropométries'' (1960), and works like the photomontage, Saut dans le vide (Leap into the Void). In the late 1960s [[Land art|Earth artists]] as diverse as [[Robert Smithson]], [[Dennis Oppenheim]], [[Michael Heizer]] and [[Carl Andre]] created environmental pieces that predict the performance art of the 1970s. Works of conceptual artists in the early 1980s, like [[Sol LeWitt]], who converted mural-style drawing into an act of performance by others, were influenced by Yves Klein and the Earth artists as well.

==1960s==
[[Image:Schneemann-Interior Scroll.gif|thumb|[[Carolee Schneemann]], performing her piece ''Interior Scroll.'' [[Yves Klein]] in [[France]], and [[Carolee Schneemann]], [[Yayoi Kusama]], [[Charlotte Moorman]], and [[Yoko Ono]] in [[New York City]] were pioneers of performance based works of art, that often entailed nudity.]]
In the 1960s a variety of new works, concepts and the increasing number of artists led to new kinds of performance art.  Prototypic for the artform later explicitly labeled "performance art", were works of artists like [[Yoko Ono]] with her ''Wall piece for orchestra'' (1962), [[Carolee Schneemann]] with pieces like ''Meat Joy'' (1964) and ''Interior Scroll'' (1975);&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.caroleeschneemann.com/interiorscroll.html]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Wolf Vostell]] with his Happening ''YOU'' &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.medienkunstnetz.de/works/you/|title=Media Art Net - Vostell, Wolf: YOU|first=Media Art|last=Net|date=12 April 2018|website=www.medienkunstnetz.de}}&lt;/ref&gt; (1964 in New York); [[Joseph Beuys]] with ''How to Explain Pictures to a Dead Hare'' (1965); [[Yayoi Kusama]], with actions such as a naked flag-burning on the Brooklyn Bridge (1968) and [[Allan Kaprow]] in his many ''Happenings''.

Kaprow had coined the term [[Happening]] describing a new artform, at the beginning of the 1960s. A ''Happening'' allows the artist to experiment with body motion, recorded sounds, written and spoken texts, and even smells. One of Kaprow's earliest was "Happenings in the New York Scene," written in 1961 as the form was developing.&lt;ref&gt;Montfort, Nick, and Noah Wardrip-Fruin. The New Media Reader. Cambridge, Massachusetts [u.a.: MIT, 2003. Print.&lt;/ref&gt;  Notably in the Happenings of Allan Kaprow, the audience members become performers. While the audiences in Happenings had been welcomed as the performers, it is only sometimes and often unwittingly that they become an active part in a Performance. Other artists who created Happenings besides Kaprow include [[Jim Dine]], [[Claes Oldenburg]], [[Robert Whitman]], and [[Wolf Vostell]]: ''Theater is in the Street'' (Paris in 1958).

[[Hermann Nitsch]] in 1962 presented his "Theatre of Orgies and Mysteries" (Orgien- und Mysterien Theater), a precursor to performance art, close to the performing arts.

[[Andy Warhol]] during the early 1960s beginning to create films and video,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.warholstars.org/andy_warhol_films.html|title=Andy Warhol Films|author=|date=|website=www.warholstars.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; in the mid-60s sponsored the [[Velvet Underground]] and staged events and performances in New York, like the [[Exploding Plastic Inevitable]] (1966) that featured live Rock music, exploding lights, and film.

Indirectly influential for art-world performance, particularly in the United States, were new forms of theatre, embodied by the [[San Francisco Mime Troupe]] and the [[Living Theatre]] and showcased in Off-Off Broadway theaters in SoHO and at [[La MaMa Experimental Theatre Club|La MaMa]] in New York City. The Living Theatre chiefly toured in Europe between 1963 and 1968, and in the U.S. in 1968. A work of this period, ''Paradise Now'' was notorious for its audience participation and a scene in which actors recited a list of social taboos that included nudity, while disrobing.

The work of performance artists after 1968 often showed influences of the cultural and political events of that year. [[Barbara T. Smith]] with ''Ritual Meal'' (1969) was at the forefront of the feminist body-, and performance art of the 1970s; among others including: [[Carolee Schneemann]], and [[Joan Jonas]]. Schneemann and Jonas along with [[Yoko Ono]], [[Joseph Beuys]], [[Nam June Paik]], [[Wolf Vostell]], [[Allan Kaprow]], [[Vito Acconci]], [[Chris Burden]] and [[Dennis Oppenheim]] pioneered the relationship between ''[[Body art]]'' and performance art.

== 1970s ==
[[Image:BeuysAchberg78.jpg|thumb|[[Joseph Beuys]], 1978: ''Jeder Mensch ein Künstler — Auf dem Weg zur Freiheitsgestalt des sozialen Organismus'' ("Every person an artist — On the way to the libertarian form of the social organism")]]
At the beginning of the 1970s, artists whose work already before tended to be a performance art, as well as new artists, began to present performance art in a stricter form.

New artists with radical performances were [[Chris Burden]], with the 1971 performance piece ''Shoot'', in which he was shot in his left arm by an assistant from a distance of about five meters, and [[Vito Acconci]] in the same year with ''[[Seedbed (performance piece)|Seedbed]]''.

The book ''[[Expanded Cinema]]'', by [[Gene Youngblood]], marked a shift in the use of media by performance artists. The first book considering video art as an art form, mentions [[Jud Yalkut]] as a pioneering video artist. Since 1965 he had collaborated in dozens of intermedia performances throughout the United States, also with [[Nam June Paik]], who beginning of the 1960s already had been a fluxus performer on the way to become a media artist. As to the art of Paik, Youngblood refers to works of Carolee Schneemann and [[Robert Whitman]] from the 1960s, which had been pioneering for performance art, becoming an independent artform at the beginning of the 1970s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last1 = Youngblood | first1 = Gene | title = Expanded Cinema | publisher = A. Dutton | year = 1970 | location = New York, New York}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The British-based pair [[Gilbert and George]], already in 1970, had documented actions of themselves on video, and created their "living sculpture" performance, being painted in gold and singing "Underneath The Arches" for extended periods. [[Joan Jonas]] began to include video in her experimental performances in 1972.

In 1973, [[Laurie Anderson]] performed ''Duets on Ice'', on the streets of New York City. [[Marina Abramović]], in the performance ''Rhythm 10'', conceptually included the violation of her body.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.medienkunstnetz.de/works/rhythm-10-2/ | title = Marina Abramović Rhythm 10 | accessdate = 2011-03-24 | publisher = Media Art Net}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thirty years later, the theme of violation, shame, and sexual exploitation would be re-imagined in the contemporary performance works of artists such as  Clifford Owens,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://gothamist.com/2012/03/09/this_sunday_ps1_may_or_may_not_host.php|title=This Sunday MoMA PS1 May Or May Not Host A "Performance Art Rape"|work=[[Gothamist]]|date=9 March 2012|first=Jen|last=Carlson|accessdate=16 August 2013|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150810231244/http://gothamist.com/2012/03/09/this_sunday_ps1_may_or_may_not_host.php|archivedate=10 August 2015|df=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Gillian Walsh, [[Pat Oleszko]] and [[Rebecca Patek]], among others.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2013/07/31/arts/dance/the-margins-of-a-form-are-increasingly-not-where-they-used-to-be.html?smid=fb-share&amp;_r=0 |title=The Margins of a Form Are, Increasingly, Not Where They Used to Be |work= [[The New York Times]]|date=30 July 2013|first=Gia|last=Kourlas|accessdate=15 August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Since 1973, the Feminist Studio Workshop at the [[Woman's Building]] in Los Angeles had a formative impact on the wave of performances with feminist background.

[[Carolee Schneemann]] work in 1963, ''Eye Body'', already had been a prototype of performance art. Schneemann in 1975 drew on with innovative solo performances, like ''Interior Scroll'', showing the female body as an artistic medium.

In the mid seventies, behind the iron curtain, in the Eastern European capitals: Budapest, Kraków, Belgrade, Zagreb, Novi Sad and other cities, the performing art was flourishing. Against the political and social control, emerged [[Orshi Drozdik]] performance series, titled ''Individual Mythology'' 1975/77 and the ''NudeModel'' 1976/77. Critical of the patriarchal discourse of art and the equally patriarchal state forced "emancipation program", pioneering feminist point of view on both, made her forerunner in the 70s political and artistic environment.

In 1976, [[HA Schult]] filled [[Piazza San Marco|St. Mark's Square]] in [[Venice]] with old newspapers in an overnight action he called ''Venezia vive.''&lt;ref&gt;Gregory Battcock and Robert Nickas, ''The Art of Performance: A Critical Anthology'' (Boston, MA: E.P. Dutton, 1984), pp. 330-31.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;James Wines, ''De-Architecture'' (New York: Rizzoli International, 1987), p. 184.&lt;/ref&gt; In his 1977 performance, "Crash", the same artist let a [[Cessna]] crash into the garbage dump on [[Staten Island]], New York.&lt;ref&gt;Edward Lucie-Smith, ''Art in the Seventies'' (Cornell University Press, 1980), p. 88.&lt;/ref&gt;

Performance art, because of its relative transience, by the 1970s, had a fairly robust presence in the [[avant-garde]] of [[Eastern Bloc]] countries, especially [[Polish People's Republic|Poland]] and [[Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia|Yugoslavia]].

== 1980s ==
[[File:Intervention-58-02.jpg|thumb|[[Jocelyn Maltais]] in ''Intervention 58'', 1980]]
Until the 1980s, performance art had been demystifying virtuosity. Now it began to embrace technical brilliance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last1 = Banes | first1 = Sally | title = Subversive expectations: performance art and paratheater in New York, 1976–85 | publisher = The University of Michigan Press | year = 1998 | location = New York, New York | pages = 120, 1 | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=DdrVYfkAm6IC&amp;pg=PA10&amp;dq=1980s+performance+art&amp;ct=result#v=onepage&amp;q=1980s%20performance%20art&amp;f=false | accessdate = 2011-03-23 | isbn = 0-472-09678-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; In reference to ''Presence and Resistance''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last1 = Auslander | first1 = Philip | title = Presence and Resistance: Postmodernism and Cultural politics in Contemporary American Performance | publisher = University of Michigan Press | year = 1992 | location = Ann Arbour | pages = 64–65, 78–79}}&lt;/ref&gt; by [[Philip Auslander]], dance critic [[Sally Banes]] writes "… by the end of the 1980s, performance art had become so widely known that it no longer needed to be defined; [[mass culture]], especially television, had come to supply both structure and subject matter for much performance art; and several performance artists, including [[Laurie Anderson]], [[Spalding Gray]], [[Eric Bogosian]], [[Willem Dafoe]], and [[Ann Magnuson]], had indeed become crossover artists in mainstream entertainment."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last1 = Banes | first1 = Sally | title = Subversive expectations: performance art and paratheater in New York, 1976–85 | publisher = The University of Michigan Press | year = 1998 | location = New York, New York | pages = 10, 1 | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=DdrVYfkAm6IC&amp;pg=PA10&amp;dq=1980s+performance+art&amp;ct=result#v=onepage&amp;q=1980s%20performance%20art&amp;f=false | accessdate = 2011-03-23 | isbn = 0-472-09678-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite the fact that many performances are held within the circle of a small art-world group, [[RoseLee Goldberg]] notes in ''Performance Art: From Futurism to the Present'' that "performance has been a way of appealing directly to a large public, as well as shocking audiences into reassessing their own notions of art and its relation to culture. Conversely, public interest in the medium, especially in the 1980s, stems from an apparent desire of that public to gain access to the art world, to be a spectator of its ritual and its distinct community, and to be surprised by the unexpected, always unorthodox presentations that the artists devise."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0500203393|title=Performance Art: From Futurism to the Present|first=Roselee|last=Goldberg|date=1 June 2001|publisher=Thames &amp; Hudson|via=Amazon}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Among the performance art most discussed in the art-world of this decade were a performance by [[Linda Montano]] and [[Tehching Hsieh]] between July 1983 and July 1984, ''Art/Life: One Year Performance'' (Rope Piece), and [[Karen Finley]]’s ''I'm an Ass Man'' 1987.

Until the decline of the European eastern block during the late 1980s, performance art had actively been rejected by most communist governments. With the exception of Poland and Yugoslavia, performance art was more or less banned in countries where any independent public event was feared. In the GDR, Czechoslovakia, Hungary and Latvia it happened in apartments, at seemingly spontaneous gatherings in artist studios, in church-controlled settings, or covered as another activity, like a photo-shooting. Isolated of the western conceptual context, in different settings it could be like a playful protest or like a bitter comment, using subversive metaphors to express dissent with the political situation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://perfomap.de/current/kart/reclaiming-the-invisible | title = Reclaiming the Invisible Past of Eastern Europe | accessdate = 2011-03-23 | last = Zajanckauska | first = Zane | author2 = Interview with Ieva Astahovska | publisher = map - media archive performance | deadurl = yes | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20110416151339/http://perfomap.de/current/kart/reclaiming-the-invisible | archivedate = 2011-04-16 | df =  }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Prior to 1982, [[Hedwig Gorski]] designated the term [[performance poetry]], to distinguish her text-based vocal performances from performance art, especially the work of performance artists, such as Laurie Anderson, who worked with music at that time. Performance poets relied more on the rhetorical and philosophical expression in their poetics than performance artists, who arose from the visual art genres of painting and sculpture.{{citation needed|date=March 2013}}

From 1981 to 1994, the Dutch visual artist [[PINK de Thierry]] created what she came to call meta-performances: a conceptual mix of intervention art in public space, performance art — interacting with an audience, installation art — utilizing large structures to perform in or with, and media art — photography and film to register and exhibit.

== 1990s ==
[[File:Trash People Roma 2007.JPG|thumb|''Trash People'' by [[HA Schult]], Rome, 2007]]
While the [[Soviet bloc]] disintegrated, formerly repressed activities of performance artists like [[György Galántai]] in Hungary, or the Collective Action Group in Russia, became better known. Young artists from all over the former Eastern bloc, including Russia, turned to performance. Performance art at about the same time appeared in Cuba, the Caribbean and China. Chinese performance artists like [[Zhang Huan]] had been performing underground since the late 1980s. In the early 1990s [[Chinese performance art]] already was acclaimed in the international art scene.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last1 = Montano | first1 = Linda M. | title = Performance artists talking in the eighties | publisher = University of California Press Berkeley | year = 2000 | location = Los Angeles, London | pages = 479, 1 | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=5Bl6wm-cV_oC&amp;pg=PA479&amp;dq=performance+art+1990s&amp;ct=result#v=onepage&amp;q=performance%20art&amp;f=false | accessdate = 2011-03-31 | isbn = 0-520-21022-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

"In these contexts performance art became a critical new voice with a social force similar to that found in Western Europe, the United States and South America in the 1960s and early 1970s. It should be emphasized that the eruption of performance art in the 1990s in Eastern Europe, China, South Africa, Cuba, and elsewhere should never be considered either secondary to or imitative of the West."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last1 = Montano | first1 = Linda M. | title = Performance artists talking in the eighties | publisher = University of California Press University of California Press Berkeley | year = 2000 | location = Los Angeles, London | pages = 479, 2 | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=5Bl6wm-cV_oC&amp;pg=PA479&amp;dq=performance+art+1990s&amp;ct=result#v=onepage&amp;q=performance%20art&amp;f=false | accessdate = 2011-03-31 | isbn = 0-520-21022-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Since 1996, [[HA Schult]] has installed one thousand life sized "Trash People" made from garbage as "silent witnesses to a consumer age that has created an ecological imbalance worldwide". They travelled to [[Moscow]]'s [[Red Square]] (1999), the [[Giza Necropolis|Pyramids of Giza]] (2002) and the [[Great Wall of China]] (2001).&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=IaIwmEh-OpsC&amp;pg=PA163&amp;lpg=&amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Carlos Rojas, ''The Great Wall: A Cultural History''] (Harvard University Press, 2010), pp. 163-64.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ina-Maria Greverus and Ute Ritschel, eds., ''Aesthetics and Anthropology: Performing Life, Performed Lives'' (Berlin: LIT Verlag, 2009), p. 110.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Kim Levin]], ''ARTnews'', volume=6, 2011, pp. 92-93.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the western world in the 1990s, even sophisticated performance art became part of the cultural mainstream: performance art as a complete artform gained admittance into art museums and became a museal topic.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last1 = Targ Brill | first1 = Marlene | title = America in the 1990s | publisher = Lerner Publishing Group | year = 2009 | pages = 93, 1 | location = Minneapolis | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=BNXeIFQScocC&amp;dq=performance+art+1990s&amp;q=performance#v=snippet&amp;q=performance&amp;f=false | accessdate = 2011-03-31 | isbn = 978-0-8225-7603-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==2000s==
[[File:artistIsPresent.jpg|thumb|[[Marina Abramović]] performing ''The Artist Is Present'', [[Museum of Modern Art]], New York, 2010]]
In the second half of the decade, computer-aided forms of performance art began to take place.&lt;ref&gt;Anderson, Nate (2009), [https://arstechnica.com/web/news/2009/09/horrifically-bad-software-demos-become-performance-art.ars "Horrifically bad software demo becomes performance art"]&lt;/ref&gt;

Since January 2003, Tate Modern in London has had a curated programme of live art and performance and in 2012 The Tanks at Tate Modern were opened: the first dedicated spaces for performance, film, and installation in a major modern and contemporary art museum.

From March 14 to May 31, 2010, the [[Museum of Modern Art]] held a major retrospective and performance recreation of [[Marina Abramović]]'s work, the biggest exhibition of performance art in MoMA's history.&lt;ref&gt;Kino, Carol (March 10, 2010). "[https://www.nytimes.com/2010/03/14/arts/design/14performance.html?pagewanted=all A Rebel Form Gains Favor. Fights Ensue.]", ''[[The New York Times]]''. Retrieved 2010-04-16.&lt;/ref&gt; During the run of the exhibition, Abramović performed ''The Artist is Present'', a 736-hour and 30-minute static, silent piece, in which she sat immobile in the museum's atrium, while spectators were invited to take turns sitting opposite her.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/yazmany-arboleda/bringing-marina-flowers_b_592597.html|title=SBringing Marina Flowers|last=Arboleda|first=Yazmany|authorlink=Yazmany Arboleda|date=May 28, 2010|newspaper=The Huffington Post|accessdate=2010-06-16|archiveurl=https://www.webcitation.org/5vy37wSbU?url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/yazmany-arboleda/bringing-marina-flowers_b_592597.html|archivedate=2011-01-24|deadurl=no|df=}}&lt;/ref&gt; A support group for the "sitters," "Sitting with Marina," was established on [[Facebook]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.facebook.com/group.php?gid=122578407758954%22|title=Log In or Sign Up to View|website=www.facebook.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; The performance attracted celebrities such as [[Björk]] and [[James Franco]] and received coverage on the internet.&lt;ref&gt;[http://thoughtcatalog.com/2010/marina-abramovic-the-staring-woman-at-moma/ thoughtcatalog.com/2010/marina-abramovic]&lt;/ref&gt; During Marina's performance, other artists performed for her.

==Gallery==

&lt;gallery widths="150px" heights="150px"&gt;

Image:Stelarc ArsElectronica97.jpg|[[Stelarc]]: ''Parasite: Event for Invaded and Involuntary Body'' (1997) [[Ars Electronica]] Festival
File:Marina_1_1.jpg|[[Marina Abramović]]: ''[[Seven Easy Pieces]]'', 9. November 2005
File:Marta Minujín Leyendo las noticias1.jpg|[[Marta Minujín]] performing in 1965. The happening, ''Reading the news'', consisted of Minujín getting into the [[Río de La Plata]] wrapped in newspapers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.marta-minujin.com/happenings_performances.html |title=HAPPENINGS AND PERFORMANCES |accessdate= 25 July 2013|work=Marta-minujin.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==See also==
{{div col|colwidth=30em}}
* [[Radio drama]]
* [[Happening]]
* [[Fluxus]]
* [[Conceptual art]]
* [[Poetry slam]]
* [[Classificatory disputes about art]]
* [[Danger music]]
* [[Endurance art]]
* [[Guerrilla theatre]]
* [[COUM Transmissions]]
* [[Flash mob]]
* [[Noise music]]
* [[New media art]]
* [[Living statue]]
* [[List of performance artists]]
* [[Survival Research Laboratories]]
* [[ART/MEDIA]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Bibliography==
* Carlson, Marvin (1996). ''Performance: A Critical Introduction''. London and New York: Routledge. {{ISBN|0-415-13702-0}}, {{ISBN|0-415-13703-9}}
* Carr, C. (1993). ''On Edge: Performance at the End of the Twentieth Century''. Wesleyan University Press. {{ISBN|0-8195-5267-4}}, {{ISBN|0-8195-6269-6}}
* Thomas Dreher: ''Performance Art nach 1945. Aktionstheater und Intermedia.'' München: Wilhelm Fink 2001. {{ISBN|3-7705-3452-2}} (in German)
* Erika Fischer-Lichte: ''Ästhetik des Performativen''. Frankfurt: edition suhrkamp 2004. {{ISBN|3-518-12373-4}} (in German)
* [[Roselee Goldberg|Goldberg, Roselee]] (1998) ''Performance: Live Art Since 1960''. Harry N. Abrams, NY NY. {{ISBN|978-0-8109-4360-5}}
* Goldberg, Roselee (2001). ''Performance Art: From Futurism to the Present'' (World of Art). Thames &amp; Hudson
* Gómez-Peña, Guillermo (2005). ''Ethno-techno: Writings on performance, activism and pedagogy''. Routledge, London. {{ISBN|0-415-36248-2}}
* Jones, Amelia and [[Adrian Heathfield|Heathfield, Adrian]] (eds.) (2012), ''Perform, Repeat, Record. Live Art in History''. Intellect, Bristol. {{ISBN|978-1-84150-489-6}}
* Rockwell, John (2004). "Preserve Performance Art?" ''New York Times'', April 30.
* Schimmel, Paul (ed.) (1998). ''Out of Actions: Between Performance and the Object, 1949–1979''. Thames and Hudson, Los Angeles. Library of the Congress NX456.5.P38 S35 1998
* Smith, Roberta (2005). "Performance Art Gets Its Biennial". ''New York Times'', November 2.
* ''ArtSpeak: A Guide to Contemporary Ideas, Movements, and Buzzwords, 1945 to the Present'', by Robert Atkins, Abbeville Press, {{ISBN|978-0789211514}} (basic definition and basic overview provided)
* ''Art in the Modern Era: A Guide to Styles, Schools, &amp; Movements'', by Amy Dempsey, Publisher: Harry N. Abrams, {{ISBN|978-0810941724}} (basic definition and basic overview provided)
* {{cite book |last=Fischer-Lichte |first=Erika |year=2008 |title=The Transformative Power of Performance: A New Aesthetics |publisher=Routledge |location= New York and London |isbn=978-0415458566}}
* ''Beuys Brock Vostell. Aktion Demonstration Partizipation 1949-1983''. ZKM - Zentrum für Kunst und Medientechnologie, [[Hatje Cantz Verlag|Hatje Cantz]], Karlsruhe, 2014, {{ISBN|978-3-7757-3864-4}}.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hatjecantz.de/beuys-brock-vostell-6226-0.html|title=Beuys Brock Vostell - Zeitgenössische Kunst - Hatje Cantz Verlag|first=Hatje Cantz|last=Verlag|website=www.hatjecantz.de}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{cite book |last1=Fischer-Lichte |first1=Erika |last2=Arjomand |first2=Minou |year=2014 |title=The Routledge Introduction to Theatre and Performance Studies |publisher=Routledge |location= New York |isbn=978-0-415-50420-1}}
* {{cite book |last1=Fischer-Lichte |first1=Erika |last2=Wihstutz |first2=Benjamin |year=2018 |title=Transformative Aesthetics |publisher=Routledge |location= Oxon and New York |isbn=978-1-138-05717-3}}

==External links==
{{commons category|Performance art}}
{{wikiversity|Performance art}}
{{wikiquote}}
* [http://www.bris.ac.uk/theatrecollection/liveart/liveart_archivesmain.html Live Art Archives at the University of Bristol Theatre Collection]
* [http://dreher.netzliteratur.net/2_Performance_Kunst_Titel.html Thomas Dreher]: Intermedia Art: Performance Art (most articles in German)

{{performance art|state=expanded}}
{{Westernart}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Performance Art}}
[[Category:Performance art| 01]]
[[Category:Contemporary art]]
[[Category:Performing arts]]
[[Category:Theatre]]
[[Category:Culture jamming techniques]]
[[Category:Art movements]]
[[Category:Postmodern theatre]]</text>
      <sha1>147droe057gv436vy708i3q3wf85rvf</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Popular print</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7670949</id>
    <revision>
      <id>845934577</id>
      <parentid>843103857</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-06-15T04:10:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Randy Kryn</username>
        <id>4796325</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>italics in caption</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="7768">[[File:Mice-burying-the-cat.jpg|thumb|''The Mice are burying the Cat'', a 1760s Russian [[lubok]] hand-coloured woodcut. It probably originally dates from the reign of [[Peter the Great]], but this impression probably dates from c. 1766.  Possibly a satire on Peter's reforms, or just a representation of carnivalesque inversion, "turning the world upside down".]]

'''Popular prints''' is a term for [[printing|printed]] images of generally low artistic quality which were sold cheaply in Europe and later the New World from the 15th to 18th centuries, often with text as well as images. They were some of the earliest examples of [[mass media]]. After about 1800, the types and quantity of images greatly increased, but other terms are usually used to categorise them.

== 15th century ==
[[File:Zehen eygenschaft des altters der menschen BM 1872 0608 351.jpg|thumb|left|''The Seven Ages of Man'', German, 1482, [[British Museum]]]]
From about 1400, there began a "visual revolution that inundated Europe with images during the fifteenth century" (Field) as the [[woodcut]] technique was applied to [[paper]], which was now manufactured in Christian Europe, instead of being imported from Islamic Spain. In the 15th century, the great majority of these images were religious, if [[playing card]]s are excluded. They were sold at churches, fairs and places of pilgrimage. Most were coloured, usually crudely, by hand or later by [[stencil]].  One political [[cartoon]] relating to events in 1468-70 has survived in several different versions (many from years later).  [[Old master print]] is a term that at this period includes popular prints, but later is restricted to more expensive and purely artistic prints. 

Although early information as to prices is almost non-existent, it is clear from a number of sources that small [[woodcut]]s were affordable by at least the urban working-class, and much of the [[peasant]] class as well.

During the middle of the century, the quality of the images became typically very low, but there was an improvement towards the end, partly because it was necessary to keep pace with the quality of images in [[engraving]]s. [[Engraving]]s were always much more expensive to create, as they needed greater skill to create the plate, which would last for far fewer impressions than a [[woodcut]]. They did not come into the popular prints category until the 19th century, when different techniques made them much cheaper.

== 16th century ==
[[File:Zentralbibliothek Zürich - Von einem schrecklichen und wunderbarlichen Cometen so sich den Dienstag nach Martini dieses lauffenden M D LXXViJ Jahrs am Himmel erzeiget hat - 000003593.jpg|thumb|[[Great Comet of 1577|Der Große Komet]] über [[Prague|Prag]], 12. November 1577, [[Zentralbibliothek Zürich]]]]

Broadsheets, also known as broadsides, were a common format. They were usually single sheets of paper of various sizes, typically sold by street-vendors. Another format was the [[chapbook]], usually a single sheet cut or folded to make a small pamphlet or book. In Spain there were ''[[pliego]]''s, in Portugal the ''[[papel volante]]'', and in other countries other names. These covered a great variety of material, including pictures, popular history, political comment or [[satire]], news, [[almanac]]s (from c.   1470), poems and songs.  They could be very influential politically, and were often subsidized by political factions for propaganda purposes.  See [[Broadside (music)]] for their musical use.  The [[Protestant Reformation|Reformation]] hugely increased the market for satirical and polemical prints in all counties affected. In [[France]] the [[French Wars of Religion|Wars of Religion]], and in England the [[English Civil War]] and the political convulsions after the [[English Restoration|Restoration]] all produced huge quantities of propaganda and polemic, in images as well as text.

Despite being often issued in large numbers, their survival rate was extremely low, and they are now very rare, with most having not survived at all.  This has been demonstrated by analysis of the records of the [[London]] Stationers Company from 1550 onwards; some blocks were in print for over a century with no copies now surviving.  They were very commonly pasted to the walls of rooms.  Paper was still sufficiently expensive that all available spare pieces tended to be used in the toilet. One of the biggest surviving collections with 439 prints is [[Wickiana]] at the [[Zentralbibliothek Zürich]].

== After 1600 ==
[[Image:Caricature gillray plumpudding.jpg|thumb|left|[[James Gillray]]'s ''[[The Plumb-pudding in danger]]'' (1805),  which caricatured [[William Pitt the Younger|Pitt]] and [[Napoleon I|Napoleon]], was voted the most famous of all UK political cartoons.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |journal= Br J Rev |year=2006 |volume=17 |issue=1 |pages=59–64 |author= Preston O |title= Cartoons... at last a big draw |doi=10.1177/0956474806064768}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Library of Congress]]]]

Newspapers began in the early 17th century, as an upmarket and expensive form of broadsheet (still a [[broadsheet|term]] for a large-format newspaper).  The first in English came in 1620.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bl.uk/collections/britnews.html |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2006-04-17 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20081003170056/http://www.bl.uk/collections/britnews.html |archivedate=2008-10-03 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt; During this century [[book]]s also became much cheaper, and began to replace some types of popular print.  These trends continued during the next century, and although most of the traditional types of popular print lived on until the 19th century or beyond, they were by then part of a much wider print culture, and the term is generally not used of them. One type of publication continuing into the 20th century is the [[Brazil]]ian ''[[cordel literature]]'' ("string literature" - it is hung on strings by the sellers) that continue to use woodcuts, and is part of a continuous tradition going back to the Portuguese ''[[papel volante]]'' of the 17th century. [[Lubok]] prints in [[Russia]] were another local variant.

Political [[caricature]] prints for sale as single sheets are found as early as the 15th century, but reached the peak of their popularity in much of Europe in the 18th and early 19th century, before the form migrated into newspapers and magazines. Above all they were popular in England, where a high degree of [[freedom of the press]] meant that dedicated print-shops, often also acting as the publishers, could openly sell and display scathing images of the Royal Family and government politicians, a business that had to remain "under the counter" in much of Europe.
{{-}}
== See also ==
*[[Old master print]]s, which covers artistic prints.
*[[Line engraving]] is also relevant.
*[[Printmaking]] for all the printmaking techniques.

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

== References ==
*Field, Richard (1965). ''Fifteenth Century Woodcuts and Metalcuts''. National Gallery of Art
*Mayor, A. Hyatt (1980). ''Prints &amp; people: a social history of printed pictures''. Princeton, N.J.: Princeton University Press. {{ISBN|0-691-00326-2}}
*Watt, Tessa (1991). ''Cheap print and popular piety: 1550-1640''. Cambridge studies in early modern British history. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press. {{ISBN|0-521-38255-6}}

==External links==
*[http://libmma.contentdm.oclc.org/cdm/compoundobject/collection/p15324coll10/id/94303/rec/1 Prints &amp; People: A Social History of Printed Pictures], an exhibition catalog from The Metropolitan Museum of Art (fully available online as PDF)

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Popular Print}}
[[Category:Printing]]
[[Category:Printmaking]]
[[Category:Art genres]]
[[Category:Mass media]]</text>
      <sha1>pt5iki779rqfeht6unx1p1t7obybsgu</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Rice writing</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>14303790</id>
    <revision>
      <id>837736715</id>
      <parentid>833187834</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-04-22T18:34:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>174.0.169.35</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="2989">{{multiple issues|
{{Orphan|date=February 2009}}
{{unreferenced|date=July 2015}}
}}
[[File:Writing on a grain of rice.jpg|thumb|A person writing on a grain of rice.]]
'''Rice writing''' is the art and skill of being able to write small enough to write on a grain of [[rice]].

==History==
Rice writing originated in Ancient [[Anatolia]] in Turkey and India. Many rituals and rites use rice as a medium, but at some point in ancient [[Anatolia]] artisans who were skilled in making miniature paintings decided to turn their skill to making art with what had always been an ancient symbol of prosperity, the oldest example of which lies in [[Topkapi Palace]] in Istanbul, Turkey. The artisans would inscribe messages or names on a single grain of rice after it was treated and polished. Grains that were long and flat were favorites as they offered proper surfaces for writing. Apart from Turkey, India also had a large number of  artisans skilled in making miniature art including rice art.

==Rice art Symbolism==
Rice art is considered to bring good luck hence some of its most popular forms is good luck pendants, hope bracelets and cell phone charms.

==Rice art and Rice jewelry today==
[[File:Grain of rice necklace-2.jpg|thumb|A necklace containing a grain of rice with the name "Filip" written on it.]]
Within time rice writing and rice art evolved, soon creating rice jewelry where the rice grain was enclosed in a vial with a liquid/oil that magnifies the individual grain making it easier to appreciate the painstaking and intricate details. This went further with rice jewelry like good luck pendants, charm bracelets, anklets and earrings. In modern times most of these artisans and artists set up shop with street side stalls where they can personally write your message or name on a rice grain while displaying their wares and hard work.

==Technique==
Most modern day rice writers use the following tools:  
#Common long grain white rice:  This rice is a flat cylinder shape.  Because it is flat it provides two wide surfaces for writing.
#Sharp utility knife:  This is used to scrape the rice slightly to remove ridges to provide a smooth surface for writing.  This scraping method can also be used to remove minor mistakes. 
#[[Clay]]:  Some people use a utility gripper clay and others use a modeling clay.  The clay is used to hold the rice in place while performing the writing.
#[[Technical pen]]:  This is a drawing pen with an ultra-fine tip.  Most pens used are either size .18 (4x0) or .13 (6x0).  These can be purchased online, or at some arts and crafts stores.
#Waterproof Ink: This ink is sold with the technical pen.

Once the rice writing is complete, it is usually preserved in a small vial of liquid/oil.  Many craftsman mount these vials into [[jewelery]] such as necklaces, bracelets and key chains.

==References==
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Writing media]]
[[Category:Calligraphy]]
[[Category:Artistic techniques]]
[[Category:Asian art]]
[[Category:Rice]]</text>
      <sha1>bb0qam6oznb473wx4801ewq02sx3ea5</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Sara Danius</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>38744396</id>
    <revision>
      <id>862743485</id>
      <parentid>862095253</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-10-06T11:33:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Martinp</username>
        <id>455826</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* top */ Adding/removing wikilink(s)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="6322">{{Infobox philosopher
|region           = 
|era              = 
|image            = Sara Danius - 2016 (cropped).jpg
|caption          = Danius in October 2016
|name             = Sara Danius
|signature        =
|birth_date       = {{birth date and age|1962|4|5|df=y}}
|birth_name       = Sara Maria Danius
|birth_place      = [[Täby]], [[Sweden]]
|death_date       = 
|death_place      =  
|institutions     = [[Swedish Academy]] &lt;br&gt; [[Södertörn University]] &lt;br&gt; Uppsala University
|alma_mater       = [[Uppsala University]] &lt;br&gt; [[Duke University]] &lt;br&gt; [[University of Nottingham]] &lt;br&gt; [[University of Stockholm]]
|school_tradition = 
|main_interests   = 
|influences       = 
|influenced       = 
|notable_ideas    = 
}}

'''Sara Maria Danius''' (born 5 April 1962 in [[Täby]]&lt;ref name="vemardet"&gt;[http://runeberg.org/vemardet/1993/0235.html Sara Danius], ''Vem är det: Svensk biografisk handbok 1993'', p. 235&lt;/ref&gt;) is a [[Sweden|Swedish]] scholar of [[literature]] and [[aesthetics]]. Danius is Professor of Aesthetics at [[Södertörn University]]&lt;ref name="akademien"&gt;[http://www.svenskaakademien.se/information/pressinformation/2013/ny-ledamot-i-svenska-akademien  Ny ledamot i Svenska Akademien] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130311061421/http://www.svenskaakademien.se/information/pressinformation/2013/ny-ledamot-i-svenska-akademien |date=2013-03-11 }}, press release from the Swedish Academy, 7 March 2013 {{sv icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Docent]] of Literature at [[Uppsala University]].&lt;ref name="dn"&gt;[http://www.dn.se/kultur-noje/dn-medarbetare-tar-plats-i-svenska-akademien/ DN-medarbetare tar plats i Svenska akademien], ''[[Dagens Nyheter]]'' 7 March 2013 {{sv icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Danius is the daughter of the author Anna Wahlgren (b. 1942) and Lars Danius (1907-1996).&lt;ref name="vemardet" /&gt; She is the oldest of eight siblings and half-siblings.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.theguardian.com/news/2018/jul/17/the-ugly-scandal-that-cancelled-the-nobel-prize-in-literature&lt;/ref&gt;

Danius graduated from [[University of Stockholm]] in 1986. She received her [[Master of Arts]] in Critical Theory at the [[University of Nottingham]] in 1989. In 1997 she became a Ph.D. at [[Duke University]], and in 1999 she received a Ph.D. degree at Uppsala University.&lt;ref&gt;[http://webappl.web.sh.se/p3/ext/content.nsf/aget?openagent&amp;key=sh_personal_profil_sv_657229 Sara Danius], profile at [[Södertörn University]] {{sv icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; She has published on the relationship between literature and society, and written about [[Marcel Proust]], [[Gustave Flaubert]] and [[James Joyce]].

Danius has worked as a literary critic for the Swedish daily newspaper ''[[Dagens Nyheter]]'' since 1986.&lt;ref name="vemardet" /&gt; She is an executive member of the [[Royal Swedish Academy of Letters, History and Antiquities|Royal Swedish Academy of Letters]] since 2010.

In March 2013, Danius was elected to be a member of the [[Swedish Academy]], succeeding [[Knut Ahnlund]] on chair 7. Danius was formally installed in the Academy at a ceremony on 20 December 2013.&lt;ref name="akademien" /&gt;&lt;ref name="dn" /&gt; She took over the post as permanent secretary of the Academy from [[Peter Englund]] on 1 June 2015.&lt;ref name="dn2"&gt;[http://www.dn.se/kultur-noje/sara-danius-ersatter-peter-englund/ Sara Danius ersätter Peter Englund], ''[[Dagens Nyheter]]'' 20 December 2014 {{sv icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.svenskaakademien.se/en/the-academy/chair-no-7-sara-danius |title=Chair no. 7 - Sara Danius |publisher=The Swedish Academy |accessdate=7 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; She was asked to resign from her position and left the Academy on 12 April 2018 against the background of critique over the Academy's handling of the [[Jean-Claude Arnault]] scandal.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.aftenposten.no/verden/i/wEbb05/Sara-Danius-forlater-Svenska-Akademien|title=Sara Danius forlater Svenska Akademien|work=Aftenposten|access-date=2018-04-12|language=nb-NO}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.dn.se/kultur-noje/permanent-secretary-of-the-swedish-academy-leaves-her-position/ |title=Permanent Secretary of the Swedish Academy leaves her position|last=Jones|first=Evelyn|date=12 April 2018|newspaper=[[Dagens Nyheter]]|language=en|access-date=13 April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; Two former permanent secretaries, [[Sture Allén]] and [[Horace Engdahl]], called Danius a weak leader in her handling of the affair.&lt;ref name=canderson&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2018/04/12/world/europe/sara-danius-swedish-nobel-scandal.html |title=In Nobel Scandal, a Man Is Accused of Sexual Misconduct. A Woman Takes the Fall. |work=[[The New York Times]] |author=Christina Anderson |date=12 April 2018 |accessdate=13 April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Bibliography ==
*''Försök om litteratur'' (1998)
*''Prousts motor'' (2000)
*''The senses of modernism: technology, perception, and aesthetics'', Ithaca: Cornell University Press, 2002. {{ISBN|0-8014-3899-3}} 
*''The prose of the world: Flaubert and the art of making things visible'', Uppsala: Acta Universitatis Upsaliensis, 2006. {{ISBN|91-554-6599-4}}
*''Voices: contemporary ceramic art from Sweden'', Stockholm: Carlsson, 2006. {{ISBN|91-7203-778-4}}
*''Proust-Benjamin : om fotografin'', 2011. {{ISBN|978-91-86883-05-8}}
*''Näsa för nyheter : essä om James Joyce'', 2013. {{ISBN|978-91-87219-02-3}}
*''Den blå tvålen: Romanen och konsten att göra saker och ting synliga'', 2013. {{ISBN|978-91-0-012049-8}}
*''Knut Ahnlund'', 2014
*''Husmoderns död och andra texter'', 2014.
*''Om Bob Dylan'', 2018. {{ISBN|9789100177812}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{s-start}}
{{s-culture}}
{{succession box|title=[[Swedish Academy]],&lt;br&gt;[[List of members of the Swedish Academy#Seat 7|Seat No.7]]|before=[[Knut Ahnlund]]|after=[[incumbent]]|years=2013–}}
{{s-end}}
{{Members of the Swedish Academy}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Danius, Sara}}
[[Category:1962 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:People from Täby Municipality]]
[[Category:Swedish literary critics]]
[[Category:Swedish scholars and academics]]
[[Category:Philosophers of art]]
[[Category:21st-century philosophers]]
[[Category:Swedish philosophers]]
[[Category:Women philosophers]]
[[Category:Aesthetics]]
[[Category:20th-century philosophers]]
[[Category:Duke University alumni]]
[[Category:Swedish women academics]]</text>
      <sha1>ptcnv6dx6eafymlo4aj82xnok2dvs3h</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Silver (graphic novel series)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>58833260</id>
    <revision>
      <id>865384174</id>
      <parentid>865113473</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-10-23T16:25:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Vincelord</username>
        <id>14054348</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="6436">
'''Silver''' is a [[graphic novel]] series by American writer and artist [[Stephan Franck]].&lt;ref&gt;https://www.stephanfranck.com/&lt;/ref&gt; It follows the adventures of James Finnigan, a [[Pulp era]] [[conman]] who teams up with Rosalynd "Sledge" Van Helsing to steel a mythical treasure hidden in [[Dracula]]'s castle&lt;ref&gt;https://www.hollywoodreporter.com/heat-vision/silver-comic-book-end-crowdfunded-fourth-volume-1115226&lt;/ref&gt;. The first book in the series was nominated for the 2014 [[Russ Manning Award]]&lt;ref&gt;https://www.cbr.com/nominees-announced-for-2014-russ-manning-award/&lt;/ref&gt;. The four books in the series were released from 2014 to 2018.

== Books ==
=== Plot ===
The plot of ''Silver'' spans 4 volumes. It is told through the point of view of James Finnigan, whose [[narration]] guides the reader through the story.

'''''Silver Volume 1&lt;ref&gt;https://previewsworld.com/Catalog/SEP141231&lt;/ref&gt;''''': ''Silver'' begins in 1931 in New York city. We meet James Finnigan, who is an ethically challenged master-thief, and his partners in crime Mullins and Brantley, as they rob the mysterious Harker foundation. What was supposed to be their last job turns into a narrow escape from the FBI, and Finnigan loses the team’s retirement money. However, Finnigan discovers a mysterious ancient silver bar, and the late Jonathan Harker's secret ledger, which discloses the existence of a fabulous treasure made of silver, hidden away in Dracula's castle&lt;ref&gt;https://nerdist.com/you-need-to-read-this-crowdfunded-comic-about-the-plot-to-steal-draculas-silver/
&lt;/ref&gt;. Aware that he might be in over his head, Finnigan seeks the help of Rosalynd “Sledge” Van Helsing, grand-daughter of Abram Van Helsing, and Tao, a ten year old boy with the gift of second sight.

'''''Silver Volume 2&lt;ref&gt;https://www.previewsworld.com/Catalog/OCT151372&lt;/ref&gt;''''': The team boards the Orient Express, which is filled with Vampires on their way to Dracula’s castle. Romantic tension builds between Finnigan and Sledge, but she may have an ulterior motive for being on the team. It also becomes clear that Tao needs a role-model in Finnigan...something that the con man is not able to provide. Nonetheless, while constantly on the verge of disaster, the team succeeds in putting the heist in motion. As the team reaches the castle, and we discover a powerful, but broken Dracula, AKA Drah-Khan, who never recovered from the loss of Mina Harker. We also meet Lillian Duvalier, a cruel and ambitious vampire princess whose own agenda adds even more volatility to the situation.

'''''Silver Volume 3&lt;ref&gt;https://www.previewsworld.com/Catalog/MAR181559&lt;/ref&gt;''''': The long con progresses, but Tao is shaken by a close brush with death, and Finnigan grows concerned that the kid might be shakier than he thought. Meanwhile, Sledge is having increasing difficulty containing her hatred for the undead. When Lillian goes out with a small party to raid a local village, Sledge goes rogue and launches after them. Out of options, Finnigan follows. Sledge manages to dispatches several vampires, including Lillian’s personal maids, but fails to save a couple of babies kidnapped by Lillian. Finn confronts Sledge but can’t seem to get through to her. Hoping to rescue the babies, Sledge carries on a desperate attempt on Drah-Khan life. The entire plan collapses. As the captured team awaits its fate, it is revealed that Lillian has succeeded in moving Drah-Khan past Mina and any hope for redemption her memory might represent. Drah-Khan and Lillian will marry when the clock strikes midnight, and sanctify their union by drinking the blood of the kidnapped babies.

'''''Silver Volume 4&lt;ref&gt;https://previewsworld.com/Catalog/SEP181703&lt;/ref&gt;''''': In triumphant long-con fashion, we learn that the failure of the original plan and collapse of the team were fake-outs, all scripted and part of the actual plan. Using every single element of lore established earlier in the story against him, the team robs Drah-Khan of his treasure, while also saving the babies, and interrupting the wedding. As Drah-Khan's entire world falls apart, the team escapes on the train  treasure on board, but Lilith shows up for a final confrontation with Sledge, and we discover that Tao was gravely wounded in the escape. Meanwhile, Drah-Khan figures out how the team escaped, and catches up to them to settled things once and for all.

=== Setting ===
The series takes place in a world inspired by [[Bram Stoker]]'s [[novel]] ''[[Dracula]]'', 40 years after the events of the novel. The story starts in a 1930's pulp-era New York City, and moves across Europe until it reaches Transylvania. Combining various elements of 1930's literature, adventure strips and cinema, the series can be described as an adventure story with supernatural elements, and as taking place in a meta pulp world.

=== Themes ===
The series deals with [[existential]] themes, such as "what does it mean to really feel alive?" It is examined through the point of view of vampires: ''"The are the dead masquerading as the living. Returning from the grave only to find a dark empty hole where their soul used to be. Incapable of love, friendship, or shedding a tear, they forever feel compelled to hoard some sort of treasure to which they become obsessively attached. It's always shiny, preferably Silver."''

== Adaptation ==
During [[New York Comic Con]] 2017, [[Deadline Hollywood]] reported that writer [[Andrew Cosby]] was attached to pen a movie adaptation.&lt;ref&gt;''[https://deadline.com/2017/10/silver-stephan-franck-andrew-cosby-graphic-novel-movie-1202182792/ Deadline:‘Silver’ Mettle For ‘Hellboy’ Scribe Andrew Cosby]''&lt;/ref&gt;.

== Reception ==
The series' reception has been generally positive. In its review of the 2018 [[Free Comic Book Day]] titles, ''[[NPR]]'''s Glen Weldon wrote ''“Writer/artist Stephan Franck is firing on all cylinders.... Stylish black-and-white art, and a smart, charmingly roguish point-of-view-character draw you in.”''&lt;ref&gt;https://www.npr.org/2018/05/03/603652979/free-comic-book-day-2018-a-guide-to-the-best-bets-and-the-best-avoided&lt;/ref&gt;, and comic book reviews site ''[[Newsarama]]'' giving the first volume 10 stars out of 10&lt;ref&gt;https://www.newsarama.com/22752-best-shots-comic-reviews-all-new-captain-america-1-batman-36-more.html&lt;/ref&gt;.



[[Category:American graphic novels]]
[[Category:Horror graphic novels]]
[[Category:Creative works]]</text>
      <sha1>afv3wpz3lnia3dwm0nyqaf9nip546a0</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Silver bullet</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>528739</id>
    <revision>
      <id>845759996</id>
      <parentid>834099487</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-06-13T23:06:05Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>131.93.98.83</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* In folklore */  Made a slight correction to wording to avoid confusion and misinformation.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="6464">{{Other uses|Silver Bullet (disambiguation)}}
In folklore, a [[bullet]] cast from [[silver]] is often the only weapon that is effective against a [[werewolf]], [[witch]], or other [[monster]]s. The term is also a metaphor for a simple, seemingly magical, solution to a difficult problem: for example, [[penicillin]] was a silver bullet that cured many bacterial infections.

==In folklore==
*The idea of the [[werewolf]]'s supposed vulnerability to silver probably dates back to the legend of the [[Beast of Gévaudan]], in which a gigantic wolf is killed by a hunter with the name of "Argent" which comes from the Latin word for silver, wielding a gun loaded with silver bullets.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Robert|last=Jackson|year=1995|title=Witchcraft and the Occult|publisher=Devizes, Quintet Publishing|page=25|isbn=1-85348-888-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*In the [[Brothers Grimm]] fairy-tale of ''[[The Two Brothers]]'', a bullet-proof witch is shot down by silver buttons, fired from a gun.
*In some epic folk songs about [[Bulgarians|Bulgarian]] rebel leader [[Delyo]], he is described as invulnerable to normal weapons, driving his enemies to cast a silver bullet in order to murder him.&lt;ref name="narodna"&gt;{{cite book|last=Стойкова|first=Стефана|title=Българска народна поезия и проза в седем тома.|publisher=ЕИ "LiterNet"|location=Варна|volume= Т. III. Хайдушки и исторически песни|chapter=Дельо хайдутин|isbn=978-954-304-232-6|url=http://liternet.bg/folklor/sbornici/bnpp/haidushki/content.htm|chapterurl=http://liternet.bg/folklor/sbornici/bnpp/haidushki/58.htm|language=Bulgarian}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==The Lone Ranger==
Silver bullets also act as a calling card for [[The Lone Ranger]] in his adventures. The masked man decided to use bullets forged from the precious metal as a symbol of justice, law and order, and to remind himself and others that life, like silver, has value and is not to be wasted or thrown away. In the 3rd episode, his friend, who will be making his bullets for him, mentions killing villains with the bullets and the Lone Ranger explains that he will not shoot to kill; he will let the law dispense justice. The silver bullets will be as symbols of justice. Whether he actually used silver bullets in his guns varies depending on story and medium. In the radio series, the Lone Ranger used only lead bullets as weapons, while the silver bullets were used symbolically. In the [[The Legend of the Lone Ranger|1981 feature film]], The Lone Ranger used silver bullets in his guns as he was told that silver was far more solid than lead slugs and provided a straighter shot. The Lone Ranger's usage of bullet made from valuable metal like silver is satirized in an episode of ''[[Robot Chicken]]'' where after expertly shooting a tin can in the air, the Ranger's sidekick Tonto laments that the amount of silver the Ranger thoughtlessly wasted could have bought enough food to feed Tonto's entire village for a year.

==Ballistic effectiveness==
Silver bullets differ from lead bullets in several respects. [[Lead]] has a 10% higher density than [[silver]], so a silver bullet will have a little less mass than a lead bullet of identical dimensions. Pure silver is less [[malleable]] than lead and falls between [[lead]] and [[copper]] in terms of hardness (1.5 &lt; '''2.5''' &lt; 3.0 [[Mohs scale of mineral hardness|Mohs]]) and [[shear modulus]] (5.6 &lt; '''30''' &lt; 48 GPa). A silver bullet accepts the [[rifling]] of a gun barrel.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.patriciabriggs.com/articles/silver/silverbullet14.shtml | title = History Channel Shoot | first = Michael | last = Briggs | date = September 2008 | publisher = Patricia Briggs | accessdate = January 25, 2017 | quotation = In this photo, you can see the marks the rifling in the barrel left on the bullet when it was fired. I'd like to see a little more on the nose, but the driving bands show very nice engraving.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The terminal impact is somewhat speculative and will depend on a variety of factors including bullet size and shape, flight distance, and target material. At short ranges, the silver bullet will most likely give better penetration due to its higher shear modulus, and will not deform as much as a lead bullet. A 2007 episode of ''[[MythBusters]]''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite AV media | url = http://dsc.discovery.com/videos/mythbusters-silver-vs-lead-bullets.html | title = Mythbusters: Silver vs. Lead Bullets | date = 2007 | medium = Television production | publisher = The Discovery Channel | accessdate = January 25, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; demonstrated a greater penetration depth of lead bullets vs. silver bullets. Results cannot be considered conclusive, however, as the show utilized a 250-[[Grain (unit)|grain]] lead slug in a [[.45LC|.45-caliber Colt long]] shell vs a lighter (190-grain) silver slug fired at closer range. Another ''MythBusters'' episode, from 2012, showed that silver bullets are less accurate than lead bullets when fired from the M1 Garand.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite AV media | url = http://www.discovery.com/tv-shows/mythbusters/videos/hollywood-gunslingers/ | title = Mythbusters: Hollywood Gunslingers | date = June 17, 2012 | medium = Television production | publisher = The Discovery Channel | accessdate = }}&lt;/ref&gt; Michael Briggs also did some experiments with silver bullets compared to lead bullets. After making a custom mold to ensure that the sizes of the silver bullets were comparable to the lead bullets, he fired them. He found that the silver bullets were slightly slower than the lead bullets and less accurate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.patriciabriggs.com/books/silver/silverbullets.shtml | title = Silver Bullets | first = Michael | last = Briggs | date = | publisher = Patricia Briggs | accessdate = January 25, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Magic bullet (medical)]]
*[[Golden hammer]]
*''[[No Silver Bullet]]''
*[[List of topics characterized as pseudoscience]]
*''[[Silver Bullet (film)|Silver Bullet]]''
*[[M829]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Wiktionary}}
* [http://www.worldwidewords.org/qa/qa-sil1.htm More on the confusion between silver bullet and magic bullet]
* [http://hurog.com/articles/silver/silverbullets.shtml Casting Silver Bullets]
* [http://hurog.com/articles/silver/ranger/ Lone Ranger Go Away. Classic 1964 Article]

[[Category:English-language idioms]]
[[Category:Folklore]]
[[Category:Metaphors referring to objects]]</text>
      <sha1>qwj6bshn2xgeu193cq2ud198bmf011w</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>The Young Friends Society of African Diasporan Institutions</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>28852965</id>
    <revision>
      <id>755408646</id>
      <parentid>735989758</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-12-17T21:34:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>BrillLyle</username>
        <id>18911373</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>link [[Shantrelle P. Lewis]] using [[:en:User:Edward/Find link|Find link]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="6993">{{more footnotes|date=August 2016}}
{{Infobox organisation
 |name          = The Young Friends Society of African Diasporan Institutions
 |logo          = Yfs of adi logo-brown (hi res).jpg
 |image         = 
 |caption       =
 |formation     = 2007
 |location      = Philadelphia, PA; New Orleans, LA; New York, NY
 |type          = Arts and Cultural Organization
 |website       = [http://www.youngfriendssociety.org www.youngfriendssociety.org]
}}

'''The Young Friends Society of African Diasporan Institutions''' (YFS) exists to support, serve and promote [[African diaspora|African Diasporan]] cultural, historical, economic, educational, and community-based institutions through fundraising, event planning, educational and social programming. YFS also serves as a vehicle to promote networking opportunities and leadership development among its members to further strengthen the communities where these institutions are located. YFS is composed of individuals in their twenties, thirties and forties.&lt;ref name="The Young Friends Society of African Diasporan Institutions"&gt;[http://www.youngfriendssociety.org Official website of The Young Friends Society of African Diasporan Institutions]&lt;/ref&gt;

==African diasporan institutions==
African Diasporan Institutions are cultural, historic, educational, and economic institutions and organizations that are located in cities around the world that have large populations of people African descent. These institutions include but are not limited to museums, historical societies, theatre companies, dance companies, libraries and archives and performing arts groups.

==YFS history==
YFS began as an auxiliary group at the [[African American Museum in Philadelphia|African American Museum of Philadelphia]] (AAMP). While working as the educational coordinator at AAMP, [[Shantrelle P. Lewis]] witnessed a lack of young adult visitors. Following in the tradition of other arts and cultural organizations, Lewis developed a plan to attract a younger demographic that could inject a new energy into the museum.  YFS held its inaugural event, Soul Simpatico, in October 2005, and within a year it had brought in 100 new members to AAMP.

As the organization grew, it became apparent that similar institutions in Philadelphia needed innovative ways to engage young adults looking for alternatives to the conventional nightlife scene of clubs and bars. In January 2007, YFS incorporated as a Pennsylvania non-profit organization and secured 501(c)3 status by June of the same year. Over the next two years, YFS partnered with various cultural organizations in Philadelphia, grew its membership base and held several successful events. YFS also started chapters in New Orleans and New York City, with plans to expand domestically and internationally.

==Vision of YFS==

1) Institution Building: YFS will help to ensure the survival and growth of important institutions. Through the development of a young core of members, supporters and sponsors, YFS will assist in sustaining African Diasporan Institutions for future generations. Each YFS chapter will invite up to 7 institutions in its geographic area to become a partner institution. These institutions will receive direct support and benefits as a partner institution of the Young Friends Society.

2) Cross-cultural association: Over the next decade, YFS will establish chapters in major cities around the [[African Diaspora]]. This will serve as a link between the various people and cultures that exist within the African World. It serves to educate people about the similarities and variations of people of African descent. Chapters will be established in the [[United States|U.S.]], [[Caribbean]], [[South America]], [[Europe]] and the Continent of [[Africa]].

3) Individual Support: YFS serves as a major catalyst for leadership development and interaction amongst like-minded individuals who are passionate about achieving their own unique potential and developing a global society. Unlike other networking forums that tend to serve individuals from a narrow demographic, YFS will bridge positive young people from diverse socio-economic, political, cultural, intellectual and religious backgrounds to support culture. In the process, it will also provide support for its members and their respective endeavors.

==Past YFS events==
*Black and White Affair: The Harlem Renaissance Revisited
*R.E.D. Affair: Welcome to Storyville
*Shootout: A Photography Exhibition
*Soul Simpatico
*W.E.B. DuBois Lecture Series
*Wines of the World
*YFS Fest&lt;ref name="reelblack"&gt;[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rpBBCd8wxiM&amp;feature=channel Young Friends Society Of Philadelphia Presents YFS Fest 2008]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Liberator Magazine"&gt;[http://weblog.liberatormagazine.com/2008/06/yfs-fest-janelle-monae-uestlove-zap.html YFSFest = Janelle Monae, ?uestlove + Zap Mama]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Col-begin}}
{{Col-break}}
* [[List of topics related to the Black Diaspora]]
* [[African diaspora]]
* [[Afro-Anglo American]]
* ''[[African and Black Diaspora: an International Journal]]''
* ''[[African Diaspora Archaeology Newsletter]]''
* [[Africana womanism]]
* [[African-American history]]
* [[Afro Americans in the Americas]]
* [[Africans]]
* [[African American]]
* [[Australians of African descent]]
* [[African immigration to the United States]]
* [[Afro-Latino]]
* [[Black People]]
* [[Black Hispanic]]
* [[Afro-Brazilian]]
* [[African immigration to Puerto Rico|Afro-Puerto Rican]]
* [[Afro-Trinidadian]]
* [[Jamaicans of African ancestry|Afro-Jamaicans]]
* [[Afro-Arab]]
* [[Belizean Kriol people|Afro-Belizean]]
* [[Garinagu]]
* [[Afro-Colombian]] and [[Raizal]]
{{Col-break}}
* [[Afro-Cuban]]
* [[Afro-Ecuadorian]]
* [[Afro-German]]
* [[Indo-African]]
* [[Black people in Ireland|Afro-Irish]]
* [[Italians of African descent]]
* [[Afro-Mexican]]
* [[Afro-Peruvian]]
* [[Afro-Turks]]
* [[Black British]]
* [[Afro-Guyanese]]
* [[Black Canadian]]
* [[Afro-European]]
* [[Afro-French]]
* [[Black people in Ireland]]
* [[Afro-Russians]]
* [[Beta Israel]]
* [[Capoid]]
* [[Chagossians]]
* [[Dougla]]
* [[Negroid]]
* [[Siddi]] (Black African community in [[South Asia]])
{{Col-end}}

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.youngfriendssociety.org] The Young Friends Society of African Diasporan Institutions official website
* [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rpBBCd8wxiM&amp;feature=channel] YouTube: "Young Friends Society Of Philadelphia Presents YFS Fest 2008"
* [http://weblog.liberatormagazine.com/2008/06/yfs-fest-janelle-monae-uestlove-zap.html] YFSFest = Janelle Monáe, ?uestlove + Zap Mama
* [http://blog.nola.com/arts/2008/02/museum_of_african_american_art.html] Museum of African American Art celebrates grand reopening

{{DEFAULTSORT:Young Friends Society Of African Diasporan Institutions}}
[[Category:Arts-related lists]]
[[Category:Arts in the United States]]
[[Category:Arts organizations based in the United States]]
[[Category:501(c)(3) nonprofit organizations]]</text>
      <sha1>4lsjluawqbhjy4l5c77aocs82uco65k</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
