<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.33.0-wmf.4</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Anthrozoology</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3209753</id>
    <revision>
      <id>852969448</id>
      <parentid>835202182</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-08-01T15:26:29Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mccapra</username>
        <id>12109628</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* See also */ Adding link to orphaned article, Wikiproject Orphanage: [[Wikipedia:ORPHAN|You can help!]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="7967">{{refimprove|date=February 2014}}
[[File:Dogsled racing Alaska.jpg|thumb|Man's best friend: dogsled racing in Alaska]]

'''Anthrozoology''' (also known as '''human–non-human-animal studies''', or''' HAS''') is the subset of [[ethnobiology]] that deals with interactions between humans and other animals. It is an [[interdisciplinary]] field that overlaps with other disciplines including [[anthropology]], [[ethnology]], [[medicine]], [[psychology]], [[veterinary medicine]] and [[zoology]]. A major focus of anthrozoologic research is the quantifying of the positive effects of human-animal relationships on either party and the study of their interactions.&lt;ref&gt;Mills, Daniel S. [https://books.google.com/books?id=vrueZDfPUzoC&amp;pg=PA28 "Anthrozoology"], ''The Encyclopedia of Applied Animal Behaviour and Welfare''. CABI 2010, pp. 28–30.&lt;/ref&gt; It includes scholars from fields such as anthropology, sociology, biology, history and philosophy.&lt;ref&gt;DeMello, Margo. ''Teaching the Animal: Human–Animal Studies Across the Disciplines''. Lantern Books, 2010, p. xi. and Hurn, Samantha. ''Humans and Other Animals''. Pluto Press, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.animalsandsociety.org/content/index.php?pid=41 Animals &amp; Society Institute.] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130625044717/http://www.animalsandsociety.org/content/index.php?pid=41 |date=June 25, 2013 }} Accessed February 23, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Note: the term should not be confused with "animal studies," which often refers to [[animal testing]].&lt;/ref&gt;

Anthrozoology scholars, such as [[Pauleen Bennett]] recognize the lack of scholarly attention given to non-human animals in the past, and to the relationships between human and non-human animals, especially in the light of the magnitude of animal representations, symbols, stories and their actual physical presence in human societies. Rather than a unified approach, the field currently consists of several methods adapted from the several participating disciplines to encompass human-nonhuman animal relationships and occasional efforts to develop ''[[sui generis]]'' methods.
{{TOC left}}
{{Clear}}

==Areas of study==
* The [[interaction]] and enhancement within [[Captivity (animal)|captive animal]] interactions.
* [[Affect (psychology)|Affective]] (emotional) or relational bonds between humans and animals
* Human perceptions and beliefs in respect of other animals
* How some animals fit into human societies
* How these vary between cultures, and change over times
* The study of [[animal domestication]]: how and why [[domestic animal]]s evolved from wild species (paleoanthrozoology)&lt;ref&gt;College of Zoological Studies at London Hanover University - Paleoanthrozoology: Domestication of Species [http://londonhanoveruniversity.eu/b-sc--anthrozoology.html]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Captive [[zoo]] animal bonds with keepers
* The social construction of animals and what it means to be animal
* The zoological gaze&lt;ref name="Franklin1999"&gt;{{cite book|author=Adrian Franklin|title=Animals and Modern Cultures: A Sociology of Human-Animal Relations in Modernity|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=93RlP4PZvgQC|date=20 September 1999|publisher=SAGE Publications|isbn=978-0-7619-5623-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The human-animal bond
* Parallels between human-animal interactions and human-technology interactions
* The symbolism of animals in literature and art
* The history of animal [[domestication]]
* The intersections of [[speciesism]], racism, and sexism
* The place of animals in human-occupied spaces
* The religious significance of animals throughout human history
* Exploring the cross-cultural [[cruelty to animals|ethical treatment of animals]]
* The critical evaluation of [[animal abuse]] and exploitation
* Mind, self, and [[Personhood#Non-human animals|personhood in nonhuman animals]]
* The potential human health benefits of companion animal ownership

== Growth of the field ==
There are currently 23 college programs in HAS or a related field in the United States, Canada, Great Britain, Germany, Israel and the Netherlands, as well as an additional eight veterinary school programs in North America, and over thirty HAS organizations in the US, Canada, Great Britain, Australia, France, Germany, New Zealand, Israel, Sweden, and Switzerland.

In the UK, the University of Exeter runs an MA in Anthrozoology which explores human-animal interactions from anthropological (cross-cultural) perspectives. Human animal interactions (HAI) involving companion animals are also studied by the [[Waltham Centre for Pet Nutrition]], which partners with the US [[National Institutes of Health]] to research HAI in relation to child development and aging.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Processes in Social &amp; Affective Development: Human-Animal Interaction (HAI) Research|url=https://www.nichd.nih.gov/about/org/der/branches/cdbb/programs/psad/HAI|website=Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)|accessdate=7 April 2018|date=December 30, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are now three primary lists for HAS scholars and students—H-Animal, the Human-Animal Studies listserv, and NILAS, as well as the Critical Animal Studies list.

There are now over a dozen journals covering HAS issues, many of them founded in the last decade, and hundreds of HAS books, most of them published in the last decade (see for example, ''Humanimalia''). Brill, Berg, Johns Hopkins, Purdue, Columbia, Reaktion, Palgrave-McMillan, University of Minnesota, University of Illinois, and Oxford all offer either a HAS series or a large number of HAS books.

In addition, in 2006, Animals and Society Institute (ASI) began hosting the Human-Animal Studies Fellowship, a six-week program in which pre- and post-doctoral scholars work on a HAS research project at a university under the guidance of host scholars and distance peer scholars. Beginning in 2011, ASI has partnered with Wesleyan Animal Studies, who will be hosting the fellowship in conjunction with ASI. There are also a handful of HAS conferences per year, including those organized by ISAZ and NILAS, and the Minding Animals conference, held in 2009 in Australia. Finally, there are more HAS courses being taught now than ever before. The ASI website lists over 300 courses (primarily in North America, but also including Great Britain, New Zealand, Australia, Germany, and Poland) in twenty-nine disciplines at over 200 colleges and universities, not including over 100 law school courses.

==See also==
{{div col|colwidth=18em}}
* [[ethology|Animal behavior]]
* [[ABMAP]]
* [[Animal rights]]
* [[Animal studies]]
* [[Anthropomorphism]]
* [[Birds in culture]]
* [[Cognitive ethology]]
* [[Companion animal]]
* [[Critical animal studies]]
* [[Domestication of the horse]]
* [[Ethnozoology]]
* [[Human–animal bonding]]
* [[Human–canine bond]]
* [[Intersectionality]]
* [[Insects in culture]]
* [[Origin of the domestic dog]]
* [[Pauleen Bennett]]
* [[Service animal]]
* [[Social grooming]]
* [[Trans-species psychology]]
* [[Zooarchaeology]]

{{div col end}}

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.animalsandsociety.org/ Animals and Society Institute]
* [http://www.anthrozoologyresearchgroup.com/ Anthrozoology Research Group]
* [http://www.h-net.org/~animal/ H-Animal]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20090411230446/http://209.190.249.61/content/index.php?pid=58 Human-Animal Studies listserve]
* ''[http://www.depauw.edu/humanimalia/index.html Humanimalia: a journal of human-animal interface studies]''
* [http://www.h-net.org/~nilas/ NILAS]

{{Animal rights}}
{{Environmental humanities}}
{{Environmental social science}}
{{ethology}}
{{Zoology}}
{{Social sciences}}

[[Category:Animal rights]]
[[Category:Zoology]]
[[Category:Ethology]]
[[Category:Animals and humans| ]]
[[Category:Animal welfare]]
[[Category:Interdisciplinary subfields of sociology]]
[[Category:Anthropology]]
[[Category:Environmental humanities]]
[[Category:Environmental social science]]</text>
      <sha1>n0edj3zdwrsrgtqchn8yxhpxhupf4e0</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cosmorama</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1017350</id>
    <revision>
      <id>869200565</id>
      <parentid>860541125</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-11-17T01:34:59Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>StraussInTheHouse</username>
        <id>32545823</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* top */unreferenced to refimprove</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="3370">{{other uses}}
{{refimprove|date=January 2008}}
A '''cosmorama''' is an exhibition of [[perspective picture]]s of different places in the world, usually world [[landmark]]s. Careful use of illumination and lenses gives the images greater realism.

Cosmorama was also the name of an entertainment in 19th century London, at 207-209 [[Regent Street]], at which the public could view scenes of distant lands and exotic subjects through optical devices that magnified the pictures. It was later converted into an exhibition of curiosities named the [[Prince of Wales Bazaar]]. Exhibits included a sea lion, a sea serpent and L. Bertolotto's [[Flea circus]]. 

&lt;gallery class="center" widths=250px heights=180px&gt;
File:John vanderlyn, panoramic view of the palace and gardens of versailles, 1818-1819, 01.JPG|Cosmorama of [[Chateau Versailles]] (1819-1818), once in [[City Hall Park]], [[New York City]], now in the [[Metropolitan Museum of Art]]
File:John vanderlyn, panoramic view of the palace and gardens of versailles, 1818-1819, 02.JPG|Cosmorama of [[Chateau Versailles]] (1819-1818), once in [[City Hall Park]], [[New York City]], now in the [[Metropolitan Museum of Art]]
File:John vanderlyn, panoramic view of the palace and gardens of versailles, 1818-1819, 03.JPG|Cosmorama of [[Chateau Versailles]] (1819-1818), once in [[City Hall Park]], [[New York City]], now in the [[Metropolitan Museum of Art]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==Port-au-Prince Cosmorama==

Port-au-Prince Cosmorama was an exhibition of [[perspective picture]]s of different places and landmarks in the world, held on March 2, 1834 in Port-au-Prince, Haiti.

''Cosmoramic Views Exhibited''

# View of Paris, with Place Vendôme and the beautiful high column by Napoéon.
# View the Père Lachaise cemetery in Paris, presenting the graves of Molière, Lafontaine Delisle, Grétri etc.
# View of the beautiful and pistoresque fall of Te-quendama in Colombia, near Santa Fe de Bogota.
# Perspective view of Madrid and the palace King of Spain.
# Interior view of London with a view of the Thames from Black Friars Bridge, the prospect of the beautiful church of St. Paul.
# View of the Battle of New Orleans, between the Americans and the English. (January 8, 1815)

==See also==
*[[Cyclorama]]
*[[Diorama]]
*[[Eidophusikon]]
*[[Moving panorama|Myriorama]]
*[[Panorama]]
*[[Panoramic painting]]

==External links==
* {{cite book |last1=Toulmin |first1=Vanessa|last2=Popple|first2=Simon |title=Visual Delights Two: Exhibition and Reception |publisher=John Libbey |date=2006 |isbn=9780861966578 |pages=188–189 |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=9cWSHOsXuLQC&amp;pg=PA188 |accessdate=10 July 2016}}
* {{cite web |url=https://www.sheffield.ac.uk/nfa/researchandarticles/showsoflondon |title=Shows of London (Cosmorama Rooms) |website=National Fairground Archive |publisher= The University of Sheffield |accessdate=10 July 2016}}
* The Cosmorama {{cite book |title=The Literary Gazette: A Weekly Journal of Literature, Science, and the Fine Arts |date=1834 |page=380|url= https://books.google.com/books?id=r1CrW3RTWVUC&amp;pg=PA380&amp;lpg=PA380|accessdate=10 July 2016}}
* Port-au-Prince Cosmorama {{cite book |title= Feuille du commerce, petites affiches et annonces du Port-au-Prince  |date=1834 |page=4|url= http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/bpt6k5810231/f4.item.zoom}}

[[Category:Entertainment]]


{{art-technique-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>hqgpx8kxg4o0yjykooewb3ciehji5g6</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cultural group selection</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>35343748</id>
    <revision>
      <id>869579412</id>
      <parentid>869481774</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-11-19T14:21:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Anthony Appleyard</username>
        <id>119438</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>not histmerged: see [[Wikipedia:Requests for history merge#Rejected requests November 2018]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="16606">'''Cultural group selection''' is an explanatory model within [[cultural evolution]] of how cultural traits evolve according to the competitive advantage they bestow upon a group. This multidisciplinary approach to the question of human culture engages research from the fields of [[anthropology]], [[behavioural economics]], [[evolutionary biology]], [[evolutionary game theory]], [[sociology]], and [[psychology]].

While cultural norms are often beneficial to the individuals who hold them, they need not be.&lt;ref&gt;Diamond, Jared. "The Worst Mistake in the History of the Human Race." Discover Magazine. May. 64-66. 1987.&lt;/ref&gt; Norms can spread by cultural group selection when they are practiced within successful groups, and norms are more likely to spread from groups that are successful. But, for cultural group selection to occur, there must exist, between groups, cultural differences that when transmitted across time affect the persistence or proliferation of the groups.&lt;ref name="campbell"&gt;Campbell, D.T. Variation and selective retention in sociocultural evolution. Social change in developing areas: A reinterpretation of evolutionary theory. Cambridge: Schenkman. 1965. 19-49.&lt;/ref&gt; Cultural norms that provide these advantages will, in turn, lead to the displacement, absorption or even extinction of other, less successful cultural groups.&lt;ref name="sol" &gt;Soltis, J., Boyd, R., Richerson, P.J., 1995. Can group-functional behaviours evolve by cultural group selection? An empirical test. Current Anthropology 36 (3), 473–494.&lt;/ref&gt; However, [[game theory|game theoretic]] models suggest that if individuals are able to migrate between groups (which is common in small-scale societies), differences between groups should be difficult to maintain.&lt;ref name="joe" &gt;Henrich, J. Cultural group selection, coevolutionary processes and large-scale cooperation. Journal of Economic Behavior &amp; Organization. Volume 53, Issue 1, January 2004, 3–35.&lt;/ref&gt; Research in psychology reveals that humans have a particular set of traits, which include [[imitation]], [[conformity]], and [[in-group bias]], that are capable of supporting the maintenance of these group differences over extended periods of time.

Cultural group selection gives a compelling explanation for how large-scale complex societies have formed. While altruistic behaviour such as [[kin selection]] and [[Reciprocity (social and political philosophy)|reciprocity]] can explain the behaviour of small social groups common in many species, it is unable to explain the large complex societies of unrelated, anonymous individuals that we see in the human species.&lt;ref name="joe" /&gt; However, one of the major distinctions between humans and other species is our reliance on [[Observational learning|social learning]] in acquiring behaviours.&lt;ref name="chimp"&gt;Horner, V. Whiten, A. Causal knowledge and imitation/emulation switching in chimpanzees (Pan troglodytes) and children (Homo sapiens). Animal Cognition (2005) 8: 164–181&lt;/ref&gt; These instincts allow for the acquisition and persistence of culture.&lt;ref name="tomasello"&gt;Tomasello, M. The Human Adaptation for Culture. Annual Review of Anthropology, Vol. 28, (1999), pp. 509-529&lt;/ref&gt; Through cultural group selection, culturally specific cooperative behaviour can evolve to support large societies.&lt;ref name="joe" /&gt; For example, in a study that spanned a variety of cultures, testing behaviour in [[Ultimatum game|Ultimatum]], [[Dictator game|Dictator]], and [[Third-party punishment]] games, it was found that standards of fairness and inclination to punish were correlated with both participation in world religions and market integration.&lt;ref&gt;Henrich, J., et al. Markets, Religion, Community Size, and the Evolution of Fairness and Punishment. Science 327, 1480 (2010)&lt;/ref&gt; This indicates how many of the behaviours necessary for complex societies are the result of cultural exposure rather than any evolution of our psychology.

== Human adaptations for culture ==
For cultural knowledge and behaviour to persist across multiple generations, humans need to have the capacity to acquire, retain, and transmit cultural information. While many species engage in social learning, humans consistently rely upon it for behavioural cues and information about the environment. In a study comparing human children and young chimpanzees, it was shown that, when given a demonstration on how to retrieve a reward from a box, chimps copy relevant behaviour, while ignoring irrelevant behaviour, to solve the task. Meanwhile, human children will faithfully imitate both relevant and irrelevant behaviour to solve the same task.&lt;ref name="chimp" /&gt; While this may seem like a negative quality, it is what allows for reliable, high-fidelity transmission of cultural information, and produces stable behavioural equilibria within cultural groups.&lt;ref name="joe" /&gt;

[[Michael Tomasello]] suggests the following three adaptations are necessary for human culture:&lt;ref name="tomasello" /&gt;

=== Joint attention ===
At around 9–12 months infants begin engaging in [[joint attention]]. This involves following the gaze of an adult or using them as social reference points. Put simply, they become aware of the adult's attention and behaviour towards objects in the environment. In this sense, the child is beginning to understand people as goal-oriented intentional agents. This is vitally important for learning through imitation and, eventually, language acquisition.

=== Imitative learning ===
By about 1 year of age, children begin to learn by imitation. At this point, children are capable of discriminating intentional actions from unintentional ones, and will attempt to accurately copy those intentional actions to accomplish tasks they've seen adults do. Because of [[imitative learning]], children will copy those intentional acts which have no perceivable effect on the outcome,&lt;ref name="chimp" /&gt; as well as strange or unnatural actions when easier methods are available. For example, an [[Andrew Meltzoff]] study found that 14-month-old children will, after seeing an adult do it, bend at the waist and press a panel with their head to turn on a light, instead of using their hands.&lt;ref&gt;Meltzoff A. 1988. Infant imitation after a one-week delay: long term memory for novel acts and multiple stimuli. Dev. Psychol. 24:470-76&lt;/ref&gt; According to Tomasello, imitative learning is necessary for learning the symbolic conventions of language.

=== Linguistic symbols and cognitive representation ===
Through imitatively learning, the child comprehends that linguistic symbols are intended to focus attention to some specific aspect of the shared experience. In doing this, the child must be able to take the perspective of the speaker. Due to the intersubjectivity of linguistic symbols, language allows one to communicate various perspectives and shift attention to one aspect of the world over another. In learning a language, a child is inheriting a vast set of linguistic symbols that have been passed down many generations. What is inherited then is the methods of shifting attention and perspective that were historically of importance to the people of that culture.

== Mechanisms that maintain between-group variation ==
Without between-group variation, cultural group selection could not occur, as there would be no group differentiation to select for. While processes such as cultural drift, epidemics, and natural disasters increase between-group variation, migration and genetic mixing decrease between-group variation ''and'' increase within-group variation. Variation is only maintained when cultural groups have mechanisms that prevent the norms of outside groups from invading the cultural group. These ‘mechanisms’ are those uniquely human psychological traits and behaviours that encourage imitation, conformity, and in-group biases.

According to [[Joseph Henrich]], between-group variation is maintained by the following four mechanisms:&lt;ref name="joe" /&gt;

=== Conformist transmission ===
Conformist transmission refers to the psychological bias to preferentially imitate high frequency behaviors in the cultural group. This homogenizes the social group and reinforces widely held cultural norms. This explains why individuals within a social group hold the same beliefs and why these beliefs persist over time. While individuals will rely on copying high frequency behaviors under various conditions, this reliance increases when an individual is exposed to ambiguous environmental or social information.&lt;ref name="Boyd85"&gt;Boyd, R., Richerson, P.J., 1985. Culture and the Evolutionary Process. University of Chicago Press, Chicago, IL.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ellison, G., Fudenberg, D., 1993. Rules of thumb for social learning. Journal of Political Economy 101 (4),
612–643.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Baron, R., Vandello, J., Brunsman, B., 1996. The forgotten variable in conformity research: impact of task
importance on social influence. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology 71 (5), 915–927.&lt;/ref&gt; Conformist transmission can maintain between-group variation by reducing within-group variation, but it also facilitates the rapid spread of novel ideas, which increases between-group variation.&lt;ref name="Boyd85" /&gt; Taken together, reduced within-group variation and increased between-group variation lead to the cultural divergence between groups that is the driving force of cultural group selection.

=== Prestige-biased and self-similarity transmission ===
Prestige-biased transmission is the tendency the copy those members of the group that are more successful. Preferentially copying successful members of the group allows individuals to avoid costly trial-and-error learning by imitating the better-than-average skills of the more prestigious cultural models. Individual can determine the rank of potential models by how much deference they are shown by the rest of the group. Deference is shown to high-prestige individuals to gain the opportunity to copy their successful models. We can see evidence for this bias in how new technologies, or economic practices spread to different groups according to how quick "opinion leaders" adopt them.&lt;ref&gt;Rogers, E.M., 1995. Diffusion of Innovations. Free Press, New York.&lt;/ref&gt;

Meanwhile, [[self-similarity]] transmission is the tendency to copy those individuals who are similar in language, appearance, social standing and other behavioral and cultural traits. In the context of prestige-biased transmission, self-similarity means that individuals will preferentially imitate those high-prestige individuals who are similar to them. From the perspective of an imitator, this trait is adaptive. By only imitating those high-prestige individuals who are similar, the imitator avoids adopting traits or behaviors that are not compatible with his or her knowledge or social environment.&lt;ref&gt;Boyd, R., Richerson, P.J., 1987. The evolution of ethnic markers. Cultural Anthropology 2 (1), 27–38.&lt;/ref&gt;

These two social biases act together in reducing within-group variation. Additionally, prestige-biased transmission increases between-group variation by contributing to the spread of novel ideas.&lt;ref name="Boyd85" /&gt;

=== Punishment of non-conformists ===
Non-conformists threaten to increase within-group variation by introducing deviant behaviours to the group and must receive costly punishment to maintain a homogenous social group. As a consequence of being punished, non-conformists will be less successful than other members of the group. Prestige-biased transmission would suggest that non-conformist behaviors would, therefore, not spread through the population. Papers on the topic suggest that this kind of punishment is prevalent across many different societies.&lt;ref&gt;Sober, E., Wilson, D.S., 1998. Unto Others: The Evolution and Psychology of Unselfish Behavior. Harvard
University Press, Cambridge.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Roth, A.E., Prasnikar, V., Okuno-Fujiwara, M., Zamir, S., 1991. Bargaining and market behavior in Jerusalem, Ljubljana, Pittsburgh and Tokyo: an experimental study, Pittsburgh and Tokyo: an experimental study. American Economic Review 81 (5), 1068–1095.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Henrich, J., Boyd, R., Bowles, S., Gintis, H., Camerer, C., Fehr, E., McElreath, R., 2001. In search of Homo economicus: experiments in 15 small-scale societies. American Economic Review 91, 73–78.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Fehr, E., Gächter, S., 2002. Altruistic punishment in humans. Nature 415, 137–140.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Normative conformity ===
Normative conformity is the act of changing one’s visible behaviour, simply to appear to match the majority, and without actually internalizing the groups opinions. This differs from conformist transmission since normative conformity does not consider frequency of a behaviour as an indicator of worth. The [[Asch conformity experiments]] are a perfect example of how robust this effect is&lt;ref&gt;Asch, S.E., 1951. Effects of group pressure upon the modification and distortion of judgments. In: Guetzkow, H. (Ed.), Groups, Leadership and Men. Carnegie, Pittsburgh, pp. 177–190.&lt;/ref&gt; and its replication across many cultures shows that this behaviour is very common.&lt;ref&gt;Furnham, A., 1984. Studies of cross-cultural conformity: a brief and critical review. Psychologia: An International
Journal of Psychology in the Orient 27 (1), 65–72.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Neto, F., 1995. Conformity and independence revisited. Social Behavior and Personality 23 (3), 217–222.&lt;/ref&gt; Henrich suggests that normative conformity may have evolved to respond to the spread of punishing behaviour toward non-conformists.&lt;ref name="joe" /&gt; By appearing similar to the group, one can gain the advantages of in-group membership, while also avoiding punishment. A curious byproduct of normative conformity is that it can contribute to the conformity transmission of norms that the transmitter does not hold, because they were mistakenly attributed by the imitator.

== Mechanisms ==
As [[Donald T. Campbell]] says, for cultural group selection to occur, there must be cultural differences between groups which affect their persistence or proliferation.&lt;ref name="campbell" /&gt; This means groups are selected ''for'' or ''against'' according to their respective ''gains'' or ''losses'' relative to other groups.

Joseph Henrich describes the three mechanisms through which this process occurs:&lt;ref name="joe" /&gt;

=== Demographic swamping ===
Demographic swamping occurs when one or more cultural groups reproduces individuals faster than other groups in the region because of stable, culturally transmitted ideas or practices.  This is the slowest kind of cultural groups selection as it depends on natural selection of between-group cultural variation operating on a scale of millennia. It has been suggested that this is how early agriculturalist displaced hunter-gatherer societies.&lt;ref&gt;Cavalli-Sforza, L.L., Menozzi, P., Piazza, A., 1994. The History and Geography of Human Genes. Princeton
University Press, Princeton, NJ.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Young and Bettinger, 1992Young, D., Bettinger, R.L., 1992. The numic spread: a computer simulation. American Antiquity 57 (1), 85–99.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Diamond, J.M., 1997. Guns, Germs, and Steel: The Fates of Human Societies. W.W. Norton &amp; Company, New York.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Direct intergroup competition ===
Direct intergroup competition is the process by which cultural groups compete with each other over resources by engaging in warfare and raiding. The cultural practices and behaviour that gives an advantage to one group over another will proliferate at the expense of those who cannot compete. There are many possible traits that could contribute to a group's success, such as technological development, social and political organization, economic development, nationalism, etc. According to Joseph Soltis, it would take 500–1000 years for group selection to happen this way.&lt;ref name="sol" /&gt;

=== Prestige-biased group selection ===
In prestige-biased group selection, when individuals have opportunities to copy people from nearby groups, they will preferentially imitate the members of groups that are more cooperative than their own. Since cooperative groups have a higher average payoff than non-cooperative groups, members of cooperative groups will be considered more prestigious and worthy of imitation.

== See also ==
*[[Dual inheritance theory]]
*[[Evolutionary game theory]]
*[[Group selection]]
*[[Memetics]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

[[Category:Anthropology]]
[[Category:Cultural anthropology]]
[[Category:Evolutionary game theory]]
[[Category:Selection]]
[[Category:Memetics]]</text>
      <sha1>soeei5mjl73l1mqgdd09ypl2ayz6ed2</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Destruction of Mosul Museum artifacts</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>45229332</id>
    <revision>
      <id>863896847</id>
      <parentid>798296988</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-10-13T20:01:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jmertel23</username>
        <id>32942831</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* See also */ Adding/removing wikilink(s)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="13235">The '''destruction of Mosul Museum artifacts''' became publicly known on February 26, 2015 when the group known as [[Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant|ISIL]] released a video showing their destruction.

==Mosul Museum==
The [[Mosul Museum]], opened in 1952, is the second largest museum in Iraq, with the first being the [[National Museum of Iraq]]. The museum is split into four areas of focus: The Assyrian hall, the Hatrene hall, the Islamic hall, and the Prehistoric hall.

===Importance of the region===
Iraq's present day borders overlap with the historic extent of [[Mesopotamia]]. Mesopotamia is considered to be one of the first areas in which urbanization evolved, beginning around the 4th millennia B.C. The "city" became the center of the new social system, resulting in the need of centralized power.&lt;ref&gt;[Huot, J. Louis (2008). The Importance of Iraq's Cultural Heritage. In P.G. Stone &amp; J.F. Bajjaly (Eds.), ''The Destruction of Cultural Heritage in Iraq'' (pp. 20) The Boydell press.]&lt;/ref&gt; Artistically, the land of Iraq holds evidence of the switch from stylized and schematic figures to more realistic representations of the human form. Writing evolved during this time period as well, allowing people to describe divine figures and conceptualize religion.&lt;ref&gt;[Huot, J. Louis (2008). The Importance of Iraq's Cultural Heritage. In P.G. Stone &amp; J.F. Bajjaly (Eds.), ''The Destruction of Cultural Heritage in Iraq''.]&lt;/ref&gt; Archaeological efforts uncovered evidence of Mesopotamia as a world contemporary with the Bible, with many stories on cuneiform tablets describing versions of similar biblical texts.&lt;ref&gt;[Huot, J. Louis (2008). The Importance of Iraq's Cultural Heritage. In P.G. Stone &amp; J.F. Bajjaly (Eds.), ''The Destruction of Cultural Heritage in Iraq'' (pp. 22) The Boydell press.]&lt;/ref&gt;

The world's understanding of Iraq and its history comes from the archaeological efforts that have taken place on its land. Because of a lack of visible architectural remains in the area, Mesopotamia, and Iraq in particular, are where the "treasure hunting" of old transformed into the beginnings of  the real archaeological research we know today. Archaeologists have been researching in Iraq for over a century and a half, lending us a great amount of time to truly understand the region's impact on those who live there and ultimately, the rest of the world.&lt;ref&gt;[Huot, J. Louis (2008). The Importance of Iraq's Cultural Heritage. In P.G. Stone &amp; J.F. Bajjaly (Eds.), ''The Destruction of Cultural Heritage in Iraq'' (pp. 20) The Boydell press.]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Destruction (2015)==

===Contents of ISIL video===
In a video shared on February 26, 2015, ISIL entered the Mosul Museum with the purpose of destroying artifacts they deemed "idolatrous". Members of the group can be seen pushing over many statues, while using jackhammers and sledgehammers to damage the faces of others. A spokesperson appears in the beginning of the video, explaining the rationale behind the group's actions. The rationale pertains to the assumption that these objects (statues, figurines, etc.) were once worshiped instead of Allah.

A translation from the video is as follows: "These ruins that are behind me, they are idols and statues that people in the past used to worship instead of Allah. The so-called Assyrians and Akkadians and others looked to gods for war, agriculture and rain to whom they offered sacrifices…The Prophet Mohammed took down idols with his bare hands when he went into Mecca. We were ordered by our prophet to take down idols and destroy them, and the companions of the prophet did this after this time, when they conquered countries." &lt;ref&gt;[https://gatesofnineveh.wordpress.com/2015/02/27/assessing-the-damage-at-the-mosul-museum-part-1-the-assyrian-artifacts/ Assessing the Damage at the Mosul Museum, Part 1: The Assyrian Artifacts]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Damage===
Not all of the museum's collection was damaged by ISIL. However, the most impacted were the Assyrian and Hatrene areas of the museum. The Islamic hall, which still held many priceless antiquities, was not shown in the video. The Prehistoric hall was also never shown, though most of those artifacts had been removed prior to the destruction.

====Assyrian====
*Nergal Gate: The Nergal Gate is located on the north side of [[Nineveh]], an ancient Mesopotamian city located in present-day Mosul. The gate was built sometime between 704 and 690 BC, which was a time of expansion for Nineveh under the ruler [[Sennacherib]]. The gate is related to the ancient Mesopotamian god [[Nergal]], who was associated with the summer solstice, war, destruction, and the netherworld.   
*Lamassu: At the Nergal Gate's entrance, and just within the entrance, stand the [[lamassu]]. These mythological figures first began appearing in art and architecture during the first half of the second millennium B.C., and are described as large winged human-headed bulls. Aside from being decoration, the lamassu are protective figures, more specifically described as "a benevolent spirit attached to an individual, group, a place or an entrance." The lamassu erected at the entrance of the Nergal Gate at Nineveh are surrounded by relief sculpture that depicts the stages of transport of the human-headed bulls from quarries in Balatai.&lt;ref&gt;[Danrey, V. (2004). Winged Human-Headed Bulls of Ninevah: Genesis of an Iconographic Motif. Papers of the 49th Rencontre Assyriologique Internationale. Vol. 66, Ninevah.]&lt;/ref&gt;   
[[File:BM; RM6 - ANE, Assyrian Sculpture 13 West Wall (M + N) ~ Assyrian Empire + -Lamassu, Gates at Balawat, Relief Panel's) &amp; Full Projection.2.JPG|thumb|Lamassu and Balawat Gate in the British Museum]]

Before the release of the ISIL video on February 26, 2015, the lamassu were in various states of preservation. Of the two figures at the entrance of the gate, one still had its upper portion preserved. The video shows an ISIL member jackhammering face of the lamassu at the right side of the gate. The left one was probably untouched, as it has been missing its upper portion since the late 19th century. The ones located inside the gates were less well-preserved than their counterparts at the entrance. However, both were seen being damaged by jackhammers and sledgehammers. The Assyrian section within the Mosul Museum also holds other lamassu of an earlier style. These may also have become damaged.&lt;ref&gt;[https://gatesofnineveh.wordpress.com/2015/02/27/assessing-the-damage-at-the-mosul-museum-part-1-the-assyrian-artifacts/ Assessing the Damage at the Mosul Museum, Part 1: The Assyrian Artifacts]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Balawat Gates====
The Mosul Museum holds in its collection numerous bronze bands of the Balawat Gates, built during the reign of Ashurnasirpal II (883-859 BC). The bands are decorated with scenes of Assyrian war, hunt, and tribute.&lt;ref&gt;[J.E. Curtis &amp; N. Tallis. (2009). The Balawat gates of Ashurnasirpal II. In ''Journal of the American Oriental Society''. American Oriental Society. Vol. 129, No. 3. pp. 552-554.]&lt;/ref&gt; The Balawat Gates are of archaeological and historical significance because they are considered a "'major' find from a 'minor'" site.&lt;ref&gt;[Tucker, D.J. (1994). Representations of Igmur-Enlil on the Balawat Gates. In ''Iraq''. Vol. 56. pp. 107-116]&lt;/ref&gt; Tell-Balawat, the site from which the Balawat Gates originate, was considered a small site in comparison to the neighboring Assyrian sites of Nineveh and Nimrud. Through further research, Tell-Balawat (also known as the city of Igmur-Enlil), was found to be within a "hollow-way" between Nineveh and Nimrud, suggesting that its purpose included defending these two cities.&lt;ref&gt;[Tucker, D.J. (1994). Representations of Igmur-Enlil on the Balawat Gates. In ''Iraq''. Vol. 56. pp. 107-116]&lt;/ref&gt;

The displayed bands are shown on ISIL's video, but it is unknown whether they were destroyed at that time. Because the Mosul Museum was previously looted in 2003, some of the bands were already missing. Since the bands are considered portable, it is assumed that some were sold on the black market.&lt;ref&gt;[https://gatesofnineveh.wordpress.com/2015/02/27/assessing-the-damage-at-the-mosul-museum-part-1-the-assyrian-artifacts/ Assessing the Damage at the Mosul Museum, Part 1: The Assyrian Artifacts]&lt;/ref&gt; The British Museum holds a second pair of the Balawat Gates, built during the reign of Shalmaneser III. These are well documented, and can be used to aid in the identification of the Ashurnasirpal's bands if they arise.

====Hatrene statues====
Hatra was an ancient city located between the Roman Empire and the Parthian Empire, to the south of present-day Mosul. Its significance is great, as its historical and archaeological record indicate it was a wealthy trading city, influenced heavily by its neighboring peoples and empires. Hatra's artworks are of interest to scholars because they have been analyzed as hybrids of artistic styles from the West and East of the city. For example, a Hatrene statue of a seated goddess is described as having drapery consistent with Buddhist style, while also having the large, protruding eyes typical of Mesopotamian works.&lt;ref&gt;Ahmed, S. Said (1972). Hatra, Iraq. In ''Archaeology''. Archaeological Institute of America. Vol. 25, No. 2. pp. 103-111.]&lt;/ref&gt; 
[[File:Hercules Hatra Iraq Parthian period 1st 2nd century CE.jpg|thumb|Hatrene statue of Hercules]]

The Mosul Museum was home to a variety of Hatra's sculptures. Most of the sculptures were images of Hatrene kings or noblemen. The ISIL video shows many of these sculptures being hit with sledgehammers and toppled to the ground. Of the 27 known Hatrene sculptures of kings, 4 were seen damaged in the ISIL video. This represents a 15% loss of these sculptures that are known to be in existence.&lt;ref&gt;[https://gatesofnineveh.wordpress.com/2015/03/03/assessing-the-damage-at-the-mosul-museum-part-2-the-sculptures-from-hatra/ Assessing the Damange at the Mosul Museum, Part 2: The Sculptures from Hatra]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Questioned authenticity of damaged artifacts====
According to Iraqi archaeologists, some of the collection belonging to the Mosul Museum was moved to the National Museum of Iraq in Baghdad six months prior to the release of the ISIL video. This spared many priceless artifacts from becoming damaged. Additionally, sources have suggested that a portion of the artifacts shown being damaged in the video were in fact reproductions or reconstructions. However, Iraqi archaeologists state this may not be the case entirely. Some artworks known to have been genuine were not shown in the video, leading archaeologists to believe that the portable objects were looted, while larger, non-portable objects were the only ones to be damaged.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aljazeera.com/news/2015/03/full-story-isil-takeover-mosul-museum-150309053022129.html/ The full story behind ISIL's takeover of Mosul Museum]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Documentation===

The 2003 looting of the National Museum of Iraq showed the cultural heritage community the extreme importance of documentation within a museum or archaeological setting. The National Museum of Iraq lacked a complete inventory, which includes photographs of all objects. The problem became exacerbated when salvaged archaeological materials came into the museum in the late 1990s until the 2003 invasion of Iraq. The influx of artifacts made it very difficult for the staff to keep up with its documentation process.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ajaonline.org/online-review-museum/364 Learning from the Iraq Museum]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://professorhistoryx.wordpress.com/2015/03/15/what-isis-destroys-why-and-why-we-must-document-it-hyperallergic/ What ISIS Destroys, Why, and Why We Must Document It]&lt;/ref&gt;

The Mosul Museum may be in this same situation, though information on its documentation processes has not come to light. If photographs of their artifacts are in existence, they will be useful in identifying and recovering the looted artifacts.

===Responses===

====Agencies involved====
*[http://www.refworld.org/docid/54f064434.html UNESCO]

====Cultural Heritage Communities====
*[http://ww2.kqed.org/arts/2016/01/14/artist-uses-3d-tech-to-recreate-past-that-isis-destroyed/ Artist Uses 3D Tech to Recreate Past Destroyed by ISIS]
*[http://engagingplaces.net/2015/03/09/museums-responding-to-mosul-and-nimrud/ Museums Responding to Mosul and Nimrud]
*[http://www.dw.de/iraqs-national-museum-reopens-earlier-in-response-to-outrage-over-mosul/a-18286767/ Iraq's National Museum Reopens Earlier in Response to Outrage over Mosul]
*[http://www.ibtimes.co.uk/project-mosul-archaeologists-fight-back-isis-heritage-destruction-3d-museum-online-1492580/ Project Mosul: Archaeologists Fight Back ISIS Heritage Destruction with 3D Museum Online]

==See also==
*[[Mosul Museum]]
*[[Destruction of cultural heritage by ISIL]]
*[[Mesopotamia]]
*[[Archaeological looting in Iraq]]
*[[List of destroyed heritage]]
*[[UNESCO]]
*[[Rekrei]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.heritagemonitor.com/en Heritage Monitor]

{{Cultural Conservation-Restoration |state=expanded}}

[[Category:Collections care]]
[[Category:Museum collections]]
[[Category:Art history]]
[[Category:Museology]]
[[Category:Conservation and restoration]]</text>
      <sha1>t73id238f7veia2h6r3gj1dokhe0pt4</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Digital artifact</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2221235</id>
    <revision>
      <id>866766074</id>
      <parentid>855012203</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-11-01T12:26:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>94.65.216.254</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="2774">{{distinguish|Virtual artifact}}
{{refimprove|date=April 2013}}
[[File:HyperGridDigitalArtifacts.jpg|thumb|A complicated grid pattern is insufficiently processed by a [[smartphone]] camera.]]
[[File:Colonel Crawford Burn Site Monument drawing.jpg|thumb|200px|A scan of a drawing with large areas of whitespace; the diamond pattern is a scanning artifact.]]

'''Digital artifact''' in information science, is any undesired or unintended alteration in data introduced in a digital process by an involved technique and/or technology. In anthropology and archeology a digital artifact is an artifact that is of a digital nature or creation. For example, a gif is such an artifact.  

Digital artifact can be of any content types including text, audio, video, image, animation or a combination. 

== Information science ==
In information science, digital artifacts result from:
*Hardware malfunction: In computer graphics, [[visual artifact]]s may be generated whenever a hardware component such as the processor, memory chip, cabling malfunctions, etc., corrupts data. Examples of malfunctions include physical damage, overheating, insufficient voltage and [[GPU]] [[overclocking]]. Common types of hardware artifacts are [[Texture mapping|texture]] corruption and [[T-vertices]] in 3D graphics, and [[pixelization]] in MPEG compressed video.
*Software malfunction: Artifacts may be caused by algorithm flaws such as decoding/encoding audio or video, or a poor pseudo-random number generator that would introduce artifacts distinguishable from the desired noise into statistical models.
*[[Compression artifact|Compression]]: Controlled amounts of unwanted information may be generated as a result of the use of [[lossy compression]] techniques. One example is the artifacts seen in [[JPEG]] and [[MPEG]] compression algorithms that produce [[compression artifact|compression artifacts]].
*[[Aliasing]]: Digital imprecision generated in the process of converting analog information into digital space is due to the limited granularity of digital numbering space. In computer graphics, aliasing is seen as [[pixelation]].
*[[Rolling shutter]], the line scanning of an object that is moving too fast for the image sensor to capture a unitary image.
*[[Error diffusion]]: poorly-weighted kernel coefficients result in undesirable visual artifacts.

== References ==
{{reflist|30em}}

== External links ==
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20110610173132/http://dpreview.com/learn/?%2FGlossary%2FDigital_Imaging%2FArtifacts_01.htm DPReview: Glossary: Artifacts]
*[http://www.amores-project.eu/ AMORES project]

[[Category:Anthropology]]
[[Category:Archaeology]]
[[Category:Information science]]
[[Category:Error]]
[[Category:Computer graphic artifacts]]
[[Category:Digital photography]]</text>
      <sha1>kads2w8rpmeo1gugks1cws18f5ndbn4</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Ethnomycology</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3674853</id>
    <revision>
      <id>821400632</id>
      <parentid>818201465</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-01-20T06:57:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rescuing 4 sources and tagging 0 as dead. #IABot (v1.6.2) ([[User:Balon Greyjoy|Balon Greyjoy]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="8451">[[File:Amanita muscaria After Rain.jpg|thumb|right|''[[Amanita muscaria]]'' has a long and varied history of psychoactive use.]]
'''Ethnomycology''' is the study of the historical uses and sociological impact of [[fungi]] and can be considered a subfield of [[ethnobotany]] or [[ethnobiology]]. Although in theory the term includes fungi used for such purposes as [[tinder]], medicine ([[medicinal mushrooms]]) and food (including [[yeast]]), it is often used in the context of the study of psychoactive mushrooms such as [[psilocybin mushrooms]], the ''[[Amanita muscaria]]'' mushroom, and the [[ergot]] fungus.

American banker [[Robert Gordon Wasson]] pioneered interest in this field of study in the late 1950s, when he and his wife became the first Westerners on record allowed to participate in a mushroom ''[[Velada (Mazatec ritual)|velada]]'', held by the [[Mazatec people|Mazatec]] ''[[Curandero|curandera]]'' [[María Sabina]]. The biologist [[Richard Evans Schultes]] is also considered an ethnomycological pioneer.  Later researchers in the field include [[Terence McKenna]], [[Albert Hofmann]], [[Ralph Metzner]], [[Carl Ruck]], [[Blaise Daniel Staples]], [[Giorgio Samorini]], [[Keewaydinoquay Peschel]], [[John Marco Allegro]], [[Clark Heinrich]], [[Jonathan Ott]], and [[Paul Stamets]].

Besides mycological determination in the field, ethnomycology depends to a large extent on [[anthropology]] and [[philology]]. One of the major debates among ethnomycologists is Wasson's theory that the [[Soma (drink)|Soma]] mentioned in the [[Rigveda]] of the [[Indo-Aryans]] was the ''[[Amanita muscaria]]'' mushroom.&lt;ref name="ref2"&gt;{{cite book
  | last = Wasson
  | first = R. Gordon
  | authorlink = R. Gordon Wasson
  | title = Soma: Divine Mushroom of Immortality
  | year = 1968
  | isbn = 0-15-683800-1 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Following his example similar attempts have been made to identify psychoactive mushroom usage in many other (mostly) ancient cultures, with varying degrees of credibility. Another much written about topic is the content of the [[Kykeon]], the [[sacrament]] used during the [[Eleusinian mysteries]] in [[ancient Greece]] between approximately 1500 BCE and 396 CE.&lt;ref name="ref3"&gt;{{cite book
  | authorlink = R. Gordon Wasson
  | vauthors =Wasson RG, ((Albert Hofmann)), ((Ruck Carl A.P))
  | title = The Road to Eleusis: Unveiling the Secret of the Mysteries
  | publisher = Hermes Press
  | year = 1998|edition=second
  | isbn = 0-915148-20-X
  | page = 149}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although not an ethnomycologist as such, [[philologist]] [[John Allegro]] has made an important contribution suggesting, in a book controversial enough to have his academic career destroyed, that ''Amanita muscaria'' was not only consumed as a sacrament but was the main focus of worship in the more [[esoteric]] sects of [[Sumerian mythology|Sumerian religion]], [[Judaism]] and [[early Christianity]].&lt;ref name="ref4"&gt;{{cite book
  | last = Allegro
  | first = John
  | authorlink = John Allegro
  | title = The Sacred Mushroom and the Cross: The Study of the Nature and Origins of Christianity Within Fertility Cults of the Ancient Near East
  | publisher = Hodder &amp; Stoughton Ltd
  | year = 1970
  | isbn = 0-340-12875-5
  | page = 320 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Clark Heinrich]] claims that ''Amanita muscaria'' use in Europe was not completely wiped out by [[Orthodox Christianity]] but continued to be used (either consumed or merely symbolically) by individuals and small groups such as [[medieval]] [[Holy Grail]] [[myth]] makers, [[alchemy|alchemists]] and [[Renaissance]] artists.&lt;ref name="ref5"&gt;{{cite book
  | last = Heinrich
  | first = Clark
  | title = Magic Mushrooms in Religion and Alchemy
  | publisher = Park Street Press
  | year = 2002|edition=second
  | isbn = 0-89281-997-9
  | page = 256 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

While Wasson views historical mushroom use primarily as a facilitator for the [[shamanic]] or spiritual experiences core to these rites and traditions, McKenna takes this further, positing that the ingestion of psilocybin was perhaps primary in the formation of language and culture and identifying [[Psychedelic drug|psychedelic]] mushrooms as the original "[[Tree of the knowledge of good and evil|Tree of Knowledge]]".&lt;ref name="ref6"&gt;{{cite book
  | last = McKenna
  | first = Terence
  | authorlink = Terence McKenna
  | title = Food of the Gods: The Search for the Original Tree of Knowledge A Radical History of Plants, Drugs, and Human Evolution
  | publisher = [[Bantam Books|Bantam]]
  | year = 1993|edition=reprint| isbn = 0-553-37130-4 }}&lt;/ref&gt; There is indeed some research supporting the theory that [[psilocybin]] ingestion temporarily increases [[neurochemical]] activity in the language centers of the brain, indicating a need for more research into the uses of psychoactive plants and fungi in human history.&lt;ref name="ref7"&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://www.nature.com/npp/journal/v20/n6/full/1395272a.html
|publisher=Neuropsychopharmacology
|title=Neurometabolic Effects of Psilocybin, 3,4-Methylenedioxyethylamphetamine (MDE) and d-Methamphetamine in Healthy Volunteers A Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled PET Study with FDG
|year=1999

}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="ref8"&gt;{{cite news
 |url         = http://cognet.mit.edu/posters/TUCSON3/Vollenweider.html
 |title       = Neural Correlates of Hallucinogen-induced Altered States of Consciousness
 |deadurl     = yes
 |archiveurl  = https://web.archive.org/web/20050908035826/http://cognet.mit.edu/posters/TUCSON3/Vollenweider.html
 |archivedate = 2005-09-08
 |df          = 
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The 1990s saw a surge in the recreational use of [[psilocybin mushrooms]] due to a combination of a psychedelic revival in the [[rave]] culture, improved and simplified cultivation techniques, and the distribution of both the mushrooms themselves and information about them via the [[Internet]]. This "mushrooming of mushroom use" has also caused an increased popularization of ethnomycology itself as there are many websites and Internet forums where mushroom references in [[Christmas]] and [[fairy tale]] symbolism are discussed. It remains open to interpretation what effect this popularization has on ethnomycology in the academic world, where the lack of verifiable evidence has kept its theories with their often far-reaching implications shrouded in controversy.

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

==Sources==

* Oswaldo Fidalgo, ''The ethnomycology of the Sanama Indians'',  Mycological Society of America (1976), ASIN B00072T1TC
* E. Barrie Kavasch, Alberto C. Meloni, ''American Indian EarthSense: Herbaria of Ethnobotany and Ethnomycology'', Birdstone Press, the Institute for American Indian Studies (1996). {{ISBN|0-936322-05-5}}.
* Aaron Michael Lampman, ''[[Tzeltal people|Tzeltal]] ethnomycology: Naming, classification and use of mushrooms in the highlands of Chiapas, Mexico'', Dissertation, ProQuest Information and Learning (2004)
* Jagjit Singh (ed.), ''From Ethnomycology to Fungal Biotechnology: Exploiting Fungi from Natural Resources for Novel Products'', Springer (1999), {{ISBN|0-306-46059-9}}.
* Keewaydinoquay Peschel.  ''Puhpohwee for the people: A narrative account of some use of fungi among the Ahnishinaubeg'' (Ethnomycological studies) Botanical Museum of Harvard University (1978),ASIN: B0006E6KTU

==External links==
*[http://www.anbg.gov.au/fungi/aboriginal.html "Aboriginal use of fungi"], ''[[Australian National Botanic Gardens]] Fungi Web Site''.
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20070206142346/http://www.huh.harvard.edu/libraries/wasson.html R.G. Wasson] - Harvard University Herbaria
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20070320151934/http://www.bu.edu/classics/faculty/profiles/ruck.html Carl A.P. Ruck] - Boston University Department of Classical Studies
*[http://www.hofmann.org/ Albert Hofmann Foundation]
*[http://www.levity.com/eschaton/tm.html Terence McKenna] - Official site
*[http://www.johnallegro.org/ John M. Allegro] - Official site
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20070127105105/http://www.gnosticmedia.com/main/ Jan Irvin and Andrew Rutajit] - Official site
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20071009025208/http://www.danmerkur.com/ Dan Merkur] - Official site
*[http://www.egodeath.com/ Michael Hoffman]
* [http://www.stainblue.com Visionary Mushrooms] Studies in Ethnomycology with Contributions by Gaston Guzman and Albert Hofmann
{{-}}
{{Ethnobiology}}

[[Category:Mycology]]
[[Category:Anthropology]]
[[Category:Ethnobiology]]
[[Category:Branches of mycology]]</text>
      <sha1>82ha68co6vcffysynobg022e6ukley0</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Fire knife</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7149605</id>
    <revision>
      <id>864053156</id>
      <parentid>850694467</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-10-14T20:03:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>24.75.174.17</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* History */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="10573">{{redirect|Siva afi|the wrestler|Siva Afi}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=August 2016}}
{{multiple issues|
{{no footnotes|date=July 2010}}
{{refimprove|date=July 2009}}
}}

[[File:Fire dancer.JPG|thumb|300px|A Hawaiian fire knife dancer]]

The '''fire knife''' is a traditional [[Samoan culture|Samoan cultural]] implement that is used in ceremonial dances.  It was originally composed of a [[machete]] wrapped in towels on both ends with a portion of the blade exposed in the middle.   Tribal performers of fire knife dancing (or ''Siva Afi'' or even "Ailao Afi" as it is called in Samoa) dance while twirling the knife and doing other acrobatic stunts.  The towels are set afire during the dances thus explaining the name.

== History ==

The Siva Afi was originally performed with the Nifo Oti ( Samoan war club ) which is very dangerous as the steel of the Nifo oti heats up and burns  . The modern fire knife dance has its roots in the ancient Samoan exhibition called "ailao" – the flashy demonstration of a Samoan warrior's battle prowess through artful twirling, throwing and catching, and dancing with a war club. The 'ailao could be performed with any warclub, and some colonial accounts confirm that women also performed 'ailao at the head of ceremonial processions, especially daughters of high chiefs. During night dances torches were often twirled and swung about by dancers, although a warclub was the usual implement used for 'ailao. Before the introduction of metals, the most common clubs that were wielded and displayed in the 'ailao fashion were elaborately carved heirloom clubs called "anava". These 'anava were frequently carved with serrated edges and jagged "teeth" which characterized the unique Samoan weapon called the "nifo'oti".

When European and American whalers and traders began commercial ventures in Samoa, they introduced the natives to the long-handled blubber knife and the hooked [[cane knife]]. The characteristic metal hook of these tools was readily incorporated into the Samoan wooden nifo'oti, which bears the unique hooked element whether carved from wood or forged from steel. One common claim is that the word "nifo'oti" means "tooth of death", but this is not linguistically accurate as Samoan syntax places the modifier after the subject; according to Samoan grammar the term "nifo'oti" would actually mean "dead tooth", hardly as intimidating as the former translation. One more linguistic issue remains to be worked out in regards to 'oti (with the initial glottal stop) and "oti" (without the glottal stop). When pronounced with the glottal stop, the word 'oti does not mean "death" at all; as a verb, 'oti means "to cut" as in 'otiulu ("hair cut") or as a noun it refers to the domestic goat. Therefore, the most probable derivation of the term "nifo'oti" stems from the resemblance of the weapon's hook to the curved horn ("nifo) of a goat ('oti), or from the serrated teeth ("nifo") that formed the weapon's cutting edge ('oti).

=== The Expulsion of The Tu'i Tonga Talakaifaiki (King of Tonga) &amp; The Birth of [[Malietoa]] (King of Samoa): ===

Ancient Samoan Legend speaks of hundreds of warriors whom would practice ailao with the ends of their weapons on fire the Nifo Oti ( Samoan war club )as part of their training. The warriors became very skilled and began to use and add many skillful maneuvers and spinning tricks to their ailao fire training, eventually becoming highly skilled combatants. Samoan warriors were called upon to dance and entertain the Tu'i Tonga Talakaifaiki during a birthday celebration for the King of Tonga.  The Tongans had ruled parts of Samoa Upolu and Savai'i but were not able to conquer the Eastern Samoan Islands namely Manu'a (American Samoa) and Manono whose warriors famously held off Tongan and Fijian invasions on numerous occasions. The Manu'a warriors were renown throughout Eastern Polynesia for their strength and ferocity.  

For approximately 200 years the Tu'i Tonga Talakaifaiki established a long-term residence at Safotu, Savai'i, Samoa.  The location for the Tu'i Tonga Talakaifaiki's birthday Festivities was a beautiful famous stretch of beach in Aleipata a region on the Eastern side of Upolu.  The Samoan warriors arrived to prepare their entertainment for Tu'i Tonga Talakaifaiki, the [[Samoans]] buried weapons nifo oti, in the sand all around the beach area, as they plied the Tongans with "bush gin".  Then they utilized their nifo oti, which has remained the same design for the last millennia, as those favored when the Samoans were actually head hunters, and the nifo-oti beheaded the victim while the hook carried the trophy.  Of course this way of life had long since been abandoned but the nifo-oti were still extremely lethal.  

As the Festivities and party progressed, and more "bush gin" was consumed, as night set in the Samoan warriors "performed" for the king.  They had wrapped both ends of their nifo-oti with dry palm sennit which was then dipped into the fires to create a blaze on one end of the knife.  They danced and pointed out the locations of the buried weapons, to other Samoan warriors who waited, in small paopaos (canoes) offshore. The warriors then stormed the beach, recovered the weapons and set them ablaze as they proceeded to drive the Tongans in a bloody battle all the way across the island, from east to the western most point of Upolu, where the Tongans whom were not killed, eventually boarded boats and left Samoa for good.&lt;ref&gt;[[Malietoa]]&lt;/ref&gt;

The young man Tavita Vaoifi revived the Samoan ailao Siva Afi dance, to eventually bring it home to Samoa.  He had won a scholarship from the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter Day Saints.  This was while WWII was being fought in part, in his beloved South Pacific.  When he was able to come to America he went to school, worked, and danced.  After he read this information, in his spare time, he researched anything that he could find about his homeland.  This story stuck him deeply, because he had never heard of this from his elders.  He was determined to incorporate this treasure into his island dance routine.  After many cuts, burns, and narrow escapes he was able to perfect this dance to the point where he performed it nightly at clubs and shows throughout, not only the San Francisco area but the entire country.

Fire was added to the knife in 1946 by a Samoan knife dancer named [[Freddie Letuli]], later to become Paramount Chief Letuli Olo Misilagi.
Letuli was performing in San Francisco and noticed a Hindu [[Fire eating|Fire eater]] and a little girl with lighted batons. The fire eater loaned him some fuel, he wrapped some towels around his knife, and the fire knife dance was born.

Although today many commercial performers perform the dance with short staffs or unbladed knives, this is not authentic fire knife dance and is unacceptable in the Samoas except for training purposes. The knives used by performers in [[American Samoa]] are still made of machetes, although they are often dulled for younger dancers.

== Competition ==

Traditional competitions were hotly contested.  Their exhibitionists would almost rather die than seek medical care for injuries incurred while performing.{{citation needed|date=March 2012}}  Today, modern competitions are held annually at the [[Polynesian Cultural Center]] to name the World Fireknife Champion.  The competition began in 1992 and is always held during the third week of May.  In 2007, the championships were expanded to welcome competitors in a duet category and a women's category. In 2010 the event expanded to four nights including a two-night, three-person final competition.

Champions by year are:
* 2017: Falaniko Penesa (Samoa)
* 2016: Mikaele Oloa (Waialua, Hawaii)
* 2015: Joseph Cadousteau (Papeete, Tahiti)
* 2014: Viavia Tiumalu,Jr. (Orlando,Florida)
* 2013: Joseph Cadousteau (Papeete, Tahiti)
* 2012: Joseph Cadousteau (Papeete, Tahiti)
* 2011: Viavia Tiumalu, Jr. (Orlando, Florida)
* 2010: Mikaele Oloa (Waialua, Hawaii)
* 2009: Mikaele Oloa (Waialua, Hawaii)
* 2008: Viavia Tiumalu, Jr. (Orlando, Florida)
* 2007: Andrew "Umi" Sexton (Orlando, Florida)
* 2006: Mikaele Oloa (Orlando, Florida)
* 2005: Mikaele Oloa (Orlando, Florida)
* 2004: Alex Galeai (Laie, Hawaii)
* 2003: David Galeai (Cook Islands)
* 2002: Pati Levasa (Samoa)
* 2001: Pati Levasa (Samoa)
* 2000: David Galeai (Cook Islands)
* 1999: David Galeai (Cook Islands)
* 1998: Pati Levasa (Samoa)
* 1997: Pati Levasa (Samoa)
* 1996: Ifi Soo (Maui, Hawaii)
* 1995: Ifi Soo (Maui, Hawaii)
* 1994: Ifi Soo (Maui, Hawaii)
* 1993: Tauasa Sielu Avea (Laie, Hawaii)

== Modern use ==

The Samoan Siva Afi has become an integral part of any Polynesian Luau or show. Many other Polynesian Islands have implemented the Siva Afi into their own Island shows especially in the Islands of Tahiti, Hawai'i, Cook Islands Fiji and Tonga. Because of the close familial Tribal ties with the aforementioned Islands and the Samoa Islands, the fire knife dance has almost become homogenized as part of those Islands own culture.
In the mid 20th century, the ancient traditions were commercialized and westernized.  Over time the performing implement has changed.  The wooden handle gradually lengthened and the blade got shorter.  Eventually, the exposed portion was part of the handle.  Some of the moves performed in shows now are more modern and flashy than traditional battle preparations.  As such, they are often performed at accelerated speeds.  It is probable that the danger of sharpened blades and the demand for multiple daily shows by top performers has caused the sharpened blade to disappear entirely from commercial performances.  Now, when one travels to [[Hawaii]], it is quite common to see commercial '''Fire Knife Dancing''' performed with wooden or aluminum poles wrapped in towels.  These performances are often part of [[Luau]] festivities or [[Polynesian culture|Polynesian]] shows that include [[Poi (juggling)|Poi Ball]] performances.

== See also ==

* [[Fire dancing]]
* [[Fire staff]]
* [[Sword dance]]

== References ==

{{refbegin}}
* {{ cite book | title = Flaming Sword of Samoa: The Story of the Fire Knife Dance | author = Freddie Letuli as told to Patricia Letuli | ISBN = 978-0-9742672-6-5 }}
{{refend}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.kapsamoa.com/ Polynesian Cultural Center: Kap Samoa]

[[Category:Anthropology]]
[[Category:History of Samoa]]
[[Category:History of the Pacific Ocean]]
[[Category:Samoan culture]]
[[Category:Traditions involving fire]]
[[Category:Fire arts]]
[[Category:War dances]]</text>
      <sha1>l1aypf2ozc3lt0xsud1d92jjpfm15ng</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Gender binary</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4519053</id>
    <revision>
      <id>860299368</id>
      <parentid>860299359</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-09-19T18:24:44Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ClueBot NG</username>
        <id>13286072</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverting possible vandalism by [[Special:Contribs/134.231.31.47|134.231.31.47]] to version by Flyer22 Reborn. [[WP:CBFP|Report False Positive?]] Thanks, [[WP:CBNG|ClueBot NG]]. (3479378) (Bot)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="10309">{{More footnotes|date=September 2012}}
{{Transgender sidebar}}
The '''gender binary''', also referred to as '''gender binarism''' (sometimes shortened to just '''binarism'''),&lt;ref name="Garber1997"&gt;{{cite book | author = Marjorie Garber | title = Vested Interests: Cross-dressing and Cultural Anxiety | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=rCzYJisHWHAC | accessdate = 18 September 2012 | date = 25 November 1997 | publisher = Psychology Press | isbn = 978-0-415-91951-7 | pages = 2, 10, 14–16, 47}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Card1994"&gt;{{cite book | author = Claudia Card | title = Adventures in Lesbian Philosophy | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=_pIRGizLcMkC&amp;pg=PA127 | accessdate = 18 September 2012 | year = 1994 | publisher = Indiana University Press | isbn = 978-0-253-20899-6| page = 127}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Rosenblum2000"&gt;{{cite journal | author = Rosenblum, Darren | year = 2000 | title = 'Trapped' in Sing-Sing: Transgendered Prisoners Caught in the Gender Binarism | journal = Michigan Journal of Gender &amp; Law | volume = 6 | ssrn = 897562 | accessdate = }}&lt;/ref&gt; is the classification of [[sex]] and [[gender]] into [[binary opposition|two distinct]], opposite and disconnected forms of [[Masculinity|masculine]] and [[Femininity|feminine]]. Gender binary is one general type of a [[gender systems|gender system]]. Sometimes in this binary model, "sex", "gender" and "sexuality" are assumed by default to align. For example, when a male is born, gender binarism assumes the male will be masculine in appearance, character traits, and behavior, including having a [[heterosexual]] attraction to females.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Keating |first1=Anne |title=glbtq &gt;&gt; literature &gt;&gt; Gender |url=http://www.glbtq.com/literature/gender.html |website=www.glbtq.com |publisher=glbtq: An Encyclopedia of Gay, Lesbian, Bisexual, Transgender, and Queer Culture |accessdate=2 April 2015 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150403155153/http://www.glbtq.com/literature/gender.html |archivedate=3 April 2015 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Overview==
The term ''gender binary'' describes the system in which a society splits its members into one of two sets of [[gender role]]s, [[gender identity|gender identities]] and attributes based on the shape of genitalia.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://www.worldcat.org/oclc/64453299|title=Gendered bodies : feminist perspectives|last=Judith.|first=Lorber,|date=2007|publisher=Roxbury Pub. Co|others=Moore, Lisa Jean, 1967-|year=|isbn=1933220414|location=Los Angeles, Calif.|pages=2|oclc=64453299}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the case of people born with organs that fall outside this system ([[intersex]] people), enforcement of the binary often includes coercive surgical gender reassignment.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Fausto-Sterling|first1=Anne|title=The Five Sexes, Revisited|journal=The Sciences|volume=40|issue=4|pages=18–23|publisher=New York Academy of Sciences|doi=10.1002/j.2326-1951.2000.tb03504.x|pmid=12569934|year=2000}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Fausto-Sterling|first1=Anne|title=Sexing the Body: Gender Politics and the Construction of Sexuality|date=2000|publisher=Basic Books|location=New York, NY|edition=1st|url=https://books.google.com/?id=c3lhYfZzIXkC&amp;pg=PR9&amp;dq=anne+fausto+sterling#v=onepage&amp;q=anne%20fausto%20sterling&amp;f=false|accessdate=18 November 2016|isbn=9780465077144}}&lt;/ref&gt; Gender roles are a major aspect of the gender binary. Gender roles shape and constrain people's life experiences, impacting aspects of self-expression ranging from clothing choices to occupation.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.chicagotribune.com/lifestyles/style/sc-cons-0728-less-gendered-clothing-20160727-story.html|title=Breaking down the gender stereotypes in kids clothing|last=D'Innocenzio|first=Anne|work=chicagotribune.com|access-date=2017-03-11|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://www.worldcat.org/oclc/799022013|title=World development report 2012 : Gender equality and development|last=Bank.|first=World|date=2011-01-01|publisher=World Bank|isbn=9780821388129|oclc=799022013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Traditional gender roles continue to be enforced by the media, religion, mainstream education, political and other cultural and social systems.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Johnson|first1=Joy|last2=Repta|first2=Robin|title=Sex and Gender: Beyond the Binaries|journal=Designing and conducting gender, sex, &amp; health research|date=2002|pages=17–39|url=http://www.sagepub.com/upm-data/40428_Chapter2.pdf|accessdate=2 April 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Major religions such as [[Islam]] and [[Catholic Church|Catholicism]], in particular, act as authorities for gender roles. Islam, for example, teaches that mothers are the primary care givers to their children and Catholics only allow [[cisgender]] men to serve as priests.

Worldwide, there are many individuals and even several subcultures that can be considered exceptions to the gender binary or specific [[transgender]] identities. In addition to individuals whose bodies are naturally [[intersex]], there are also specific social roles that involve aspects of both or neither of the binary genders. These include the [[Two-Spirit]]ed [[Indigenous peoples of the Americas|Native Americans]] and [[hijra (South Asia)|hijra]] of [[India]]. In the contemporary [[Western world|West]], [[genderqueer]] people break the gender binary by refusing terms like "male" and "female". [[Transgender]] people have a unique place in relation to the gender binary. In some cases, their gender expression aligns with their sex. Attempting to conform to societal expectations for their gender, transsexual individuals may opt for surgery, hormones, or both, which can be difficult if the individual does not "pass" as [[cisgender]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book
| title = Transmen and FTMs: Identities, Bodies, Genders, and Sexualities
| last = Cromwell
| first = Jason
| publisher = University of Illinois
| year = 1999
| isbn = 978-0252068256
| location = Chicago, Illinois
| pages = 511
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Thomas Keith in ''Masculinities in Contemporary American Culture'', the longstanding cultural assumption that male–female dualities are "natural and immutable" partly explains the persistence of systems of [[patriarchy]] and [[male privilege]] in modern society.&lt;ref name="Keith"&gt;{{cite book |last1=Keith |first1=Thomas |title=Masculinities in Contemporary American Culture: An Intersectional Approach to the Complexities and Challenges of Male Identity |date=2017 |publisher=Routledge |isbn=978-1-31-759534-2 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=r_niDQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT30&amp;dq=binary+%22patriarchy+and+male+privilege%22 |page=2 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Limitations==
Some feminist scholars have contested the existence of a clear gender binary. [[Judith Lorber]] explains the problem of failing to question dividing people into these two groups “even though they often find more significant within-group differences than between-group differences.”&lt;ref name="lorber"&gt;Lorber, Judith. "Believing is Seeing: Biology as Ideology." In ''The Gendered Society Reader,'' edited by Michael S. Kimmel, Amy Aronson, and Amy Kaler, 11-18. Toronto, ON: Oxford University Press, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Lorber argues that this corroborates the fact that the gender binary is arbitrary and leads to false expectations of both men and women. Instead, there is growing support for the possibility of utilizing additional categories that compare people without "prior assumptions about who is like whom".&lt;ref name="lorber"/&gt; By allowing for a more fluid approach to gender, people will be able to better identify themselves however they choose and scholarly research will find different similarities and differences.{{Ambiguous|date=March 2017}}

==Rejection==
[[Anne Fausto-Sterling]] suggests a classification of 23 sexes and a move away from the socially constructed gender binary classification of male and female. In her paper "The Five Sexes: Why Male and Female Are Not Enough", she discusses the existence of intersex people, individuals possessing a combination of male and female sexual characteristics, who are seen as deviations from the norm and who frequently undergo coercive surgery at a very young age in order to maintain the two-gender system. The existence of these individuals challenges the standards of gender binaries and put into question society's role in constructing gender.&lt;ref name="Drowninginlimbo"&gt;{{cite book | author = Morgan Holmes | title = Intersex: A Perilous Difference
 | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=YYTnmY2EelUC&amp;dq | accessdate = 29 April 2014 | date = 2008 | publisher = Associated University Presse | isbn = 978-1-575-91117-5 | pages = 17}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fausto-Sterling indicates that modern practitioners encourage the idea that gender is a [[cultural construct]] and concludes that, "we are moving from an era of sexual dimorphism to one of variety beyond the number 2."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Fausto-Sterling|first=Anne|authorlink=Anne Fausto-Sterling|title=The Five Sexes: Why Male and Female Are Not Enough|journal=The Sciences|date=March–April 1993|pages=20–24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{columns-list|colwidth=30em|
* [[Androgyny]]
* ''[[Anti-Oedipus]]''
* [[Butch and femme]]
* [[Coloniality of gender]]
* [[Dioecy]]
* [[Eleno de Céspedes]]
* [[Gender dysphoria]]
* [[Gender in Bugis society]]
* [[Gender polarization]]
* [[Gender policing]]
* [[Non-binary discrimination]]
* [[Postgenderism]]
* [[Sexual dimorphism]]
* [[Social construction of gender difference]]
* [[List of transgender-related topics]]
* [[Transphobia]]
* [[XY sex-determination system]]
}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
* binaohan, b. ''decolonizing trans/gender 101.'' biyuti publishing, 2014. {{ISBN|9780993793516}}
*''GenderQueer: Voices from Beyond the Sexual Binary'' (Alyson), ([[Joan Nestle]], Clair Howell Co-Editors) 2002 {{ISBN|1-55583-730-1}}
* {{cite web|url=https://arstechnica.com/science/2012/09/pregnant-males-and-pseudopenises-complex-sex-in-the-animal-kingdom/|title=Pregnant males and pseudopenises: complex sex in the animal kingdom|publisher=[[Ars Technica]]}}

{{Sexual identities}}{{LGBT}}
{{Sex}}

[[Category:Gender]]
[[Category:Gender studies]]
[[Category:Queer theory]]
[[Category:Dichotomies]]
[[Category:Sexuality and gender-related prejudices]]
[[Category:Feminist terminology]]
[[Category:Feminist theory]]</text>
      <sha1>c8ljbacwf0sizjw0h1ebtj7f64sr1nv</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Gottlob Frege</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>48416</id>
    <revision>
      <id>867508126</id>
      <parentid>858903756</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-11-06T04:43:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ser Amantio di Nicolao</username>
        <id>753665</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Removing from [[Category:German male writers]] (parent category) using [[c:Help:Cat-a-lot|Cat-a-lot]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="42966">{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2012}}
{{Infobox philosopher
| region = [[Western philosophy]]
| era = [[19th-century philosophy]]&lt;br /&gt;[[20th-century philosophy]]
| image = Young frege.jpg
| caption = Frege in c. 1879
| name = Gottlob Frege
| birth_date  = 8 November 1848
| birth_place = [[Wismar]], [[Grand Duchy of Mecklenburg-Schwerin|Mecklenburg-Schwerin]], [[German Confederation|Germany]]
| death_date  = {{Death date and age|df=yes|1925|7|26|1848|11|8}}
| death_place = [[Bad Kleinen]], [[Free State of Mecklenburg-Schwerin|Mecklenburg-Schwerin]], [[Weimar Republic|Germany]]
| education   = [[University of Göttingen]] ([[PhD]], 1873)&lt;br&gt;[[University of Jena]] ([[Dr. phil. hab.]], 1874)
| school_tradition = [[Analytic philosophy]]&lt;br&gt;[[Linguistic turn]]&lt;br&gt;[[Logical objectivism]]&lt;br&gt;[[Modern Platonism]]&lt;ref name=SEP-P&gt;[https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/platonism/ Platonism in Metaphysics (Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy)]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;[[Logicism]]&lt;br&gt;[[Transcendental idealism]]&lt;ref&gt;[[Hans Sluga]], "Frege's alleged realism," ''Inquiry'' 20 (1–4):227–242 (1977).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Resnik"&gt;[[Michael Resnik]], "II. Frege as Idealist and then Realist," ''Inquiry'' 22 (1–4):350–357 (1979).&lt;/ref&gt; (before 1891)&lt;br&gt;[[Metaphysical realism]]&lt;ref name="Resnik" /&gt; (after 1891)&lt;br&gt;[[Foundationalism]]&lt;ref&gt;[[Tom Rockmore]], ''On Foundationalism: A Strategy for Metaphysical Realism'', Rowman &amp; Littlefield, 2004, p. 111.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;[[Indirect realism]]&lt;ref&gt;Frege criticized [[direct realism]] in his "[[On Sense and Reference|Über Sinn und Bedeutung]]" (see Samuel Lebens, ''Bertrand Russell and the Nature of Propositions: A History and Defence of the Multiple Relation Theory of Judgement'', Routledge, 2017, p. 34).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;[[Redundancy theory of truth]]&lt;ref name=IEP-T/&gt;
| main_interests   = [[Philosophy of mathematics]], [[mathematical logic]], [[philosophy of language]]
| influences       = [[Immanuel Kant]], [[Kuno Fischer]], [[Bruno Bauch]],&lt;ref&gt;[[Hans Sluga]] (1980), ''Gottlob Frege'', Routledge, pp. 53ff.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Friedrich Adolf Trendelenburg]],&lt;ref name="Brandom"&gt;[[Robert Boyce Brandom]], "Frege's Technical Concepts", in [https://books.google.com/books?id=DwxUZZF21mQC&amp;hl=el&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s ''Frege Synthesized: Essays on the Philosophical and Foundational Work of G. Frege''], L. Haaparanta and J. Hintikka, Synthese Library, D. Reidel, 1986, pp. 253–295&lt;/ref&gt; [[Hermann Lotze]],&lt;ref name="Brandom" /&gt; [[Otto Liebmann]],&lt;ref&gt;Gottfried Gabriel, "Frege, Lotze, and the Continental Roots of Early Analytic Philosophy," in: Erich H. Reck (ed.). ''From Frege to Wittgenstein: Perspectives on Early Analytic Philosophy'', Oxford University Press, 2002, pp. 39–51, esp. 44–48.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Benno Kerry]],&lt;ref&gt;Tom Ricketts, Michael Potter, ''The Cambridge Companion to Frege'', Cambridge University Press, 2010, p. 179.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Ernst Abbe]], [[David Hume]], [[Gottfried Wilhelm Leibniz|G. W. Leibniz]], [[Bernard Bolzano]]&lt;ref&gt;Sundholm, B. G., [https://openaccess.leidenuniv.nl/handle/1887/10421 "When, and why, did Frege read Bolzano?"], LOGICA Yearbook 1999, 164–174 (2000).&lt;/ref&gt;
| influenced = [[Giuseppe Peano]], [[Bertrand Russell]], [[Rudolf Carnap]], [[Ludwig Wittgenstein]], [[Michael Dummett]], [[Edmund Husserl]], [[Gershom Scholem]], [[Karl Popper]], and most of the [[Analytic philosophy|analytic tradition]] |[[Analytic Philosophy]], [[Ordinary language philosophy|Ordinary Language Philosophy]]
| notable_ideas    = [[Principle of compositionality]], [[context principle]], [[quantification theory]], [[predicate calculus]], [[logicism]],&lt;br&gt;[[sense and reference]], [[Frege's puzzles]], [[concept and object]], [[sortal]], [[Third Realm (Frege)|Third Realm]], [[mediated reference theory]] (Frege–Russell view), [[descriptivist theory of names]], [[redundancy theory of truth]],&lt;ref name=IEP-T&gt;[http://www.iep.utm.edu/truth/#SH7a Truth – Internet Encyclopedia of Philosophy]; [http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/truth-deflationary/#HisDef The Deflationary Theory of Truth (Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy)].&lt;/ref&gt; [[set-theoretic definition of natural numbers]], [[Hume's principle]], [[Basic Law V]], [[Frege's theorem]], [[Frege–Church ontology]], [[Frege–Geach problem]], [[law of trichotomy]], [[Currying|technique for binding arguments]]&lt;ref&gt;[[Willard Van Orman Quine]], introduction to "Bausteine der mathematischen Logik", pp.&amp;nbsp;305–316. Translated by Stefan Bauer-Mengelberg as "On the building blocks of mathematical logic" in [[Jean van Heijenoort]] (1967), ''A Source Book in Mathematical Logic, 1879–1931''. Harvard University Press, pp. 355–66.&lt;/ref&gt;
|notable_works = ''[[Begriffsschrift]]'' (1879)&lt;br /&gt;''[[The Foundations of Arithmetic]]'' (1884)
|thesis_title = Ueber&lt;!--[sic; see 'Talk:Gottlob Frege#Ueber']--&gt; eine geometrische Darstellung der imaginären Gebilde in der Ebene (On a Geometrical Representation of Imaginary Forms in a Plane)
|thesis_url   = http://reader.digitale-sammlungen.de/de/fs1/object/goToPage/bsb11160343.html?pageNo=2
|thesis_year  = 1873
|doctoral_advisor  = [[Ernst Christian Julius Schering]] (PhD adv.)
|academic_advisors = [[Alfred Clebsch|Rudolf Friedrich Alfred Clebsch]]
}}
'''Friedrich Ludwig Gottlob Frege''' ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|f|r|eɪ|g|ə}};&lt;ref&gt;[http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/frege "Frege"]. ''[[Random House Webster's Unabridged Dictionary]]''.&lt;/ref&gt; {{IPA-de|ˈɡɔtloːp ˈfreːɡə|lang}}; 8 November 1848 – 26 July 1925) was a German [[philosopher]], [[Mathematical logic|logician]], and [[mathematics|mathematician]].  He is understood by many to be the father of [[analytic philosophy]], concentrating on the philosophy of language and mathematics. Though largely ignored during his lifetime, [[Giuseppe Peano]] (1858–1932) and [[Bertrand Russell]] (1872–1970) introduced his work to later generations of logicians and philosophers.

His contributions include the development of modern logic in the ''[[Begriffsschrift]]'' and work in the [[foundations of mathematics]].  His book the ''[[Foundations of Arithmetic]]'' is the seminal text of the [[logicist]] project, and is cited by [[Michael Dummett]] as where to pinpoint the [[linguistic turn]].  His philosophical papers "[[On Sense and Reference]]" ("Über Sinn und Bedeutung") and "The Thought" ("Der Gedanke") are widely cited.

== Life ==

=== Childhood (1848–69) ===
Frege was born in 1848 in [[Wismar]], [[Grand Duchy of Mecklenburg-Schwerin|Mecklenburg-Schwerin]] (today part of [[Mecklenburg-Vorpommern]]). His father Carl (Karl) Alexander Frege (1809–1866) was the co-founder and headmaster of a girls' high school until his death. After Carl's death, the school was led by Frege's mother Auguste Wilhelmine Sophie Frege (née Bialloblotzky, 12 January 1815 – 14 October 1898); her mother was Auguste Amalia Maria Ballhorn, a descendant of [[Philipp Melanchthon]]&lt;ref&gt;Lothar Kreiser, ''Gottlob Frege: Leben - Werk - Zeit'', Felix Meiner Verlag, 2013, p. 11.&lt;/ref&gt; and her father was Johann Heinrich Siegfried Bialloblotzky, a descendant of a [[Poles|Polish]] noble family who left Poland in the 17th century.&lt;ref&gt;Arndt Richter, [http://www.genetalogie.de/gg/alfrege.pdf "Ahnenliste des Mathematikers Gottlob Frege, 1848-1925"]&lt;/ref&gt;

In childhood, Frege encountered philosophies that would guide his future scientific career. For example, his father wrote a [[textbook]] on the German language for children aged 9–13, entitled ''Hülfsbuch zum Unterrichte in der deutschen Sprache für Kinder von 9 bis 13 Jahren'' (2nd ed., Wismar 1850; 3rd ed., Wismar and Ludwigslust: Hinstorff, 1862), the first section of which dealt with the structure and [[logic]] of [[language]].

Frege studied at a [[gymnasium (school)|''gymnasium'']] in Wismar and graduated in 1869. His teacher Gustav Adolf Leo Sachse (5 November 1843 – 1 September 1909), who was a poet, played the most important role in determining Frege's future scientific career, encouraging him to continue his studies at the [[University of Jena]].

=== Studies at University: Jena and Göttingen (1869–74) ===
Frege matriculated at the University of Jena in the spring of 1869 as a citizen of the [[North German Confederation]]. In the four semesters of his studies he attended approximately twenty courses of lectures, most of them on mathematics and physics. His most important teacher was [[Ernst Karl Abbe]] (1840–1905; physicist, mathematician, and inventor). Abbe gave lectures on theory of gravity, galvanism and electrodynamics, complex analysis theory of functions of a complex variable, applications of physics, selected divisions of mechanics, and mechanics of solids. Abbe was more than a teacher to Frege: he was a trusted friend, and, as director of the optical manufacturer Carl Zeiss AG, he was in a position to advance Frege's career. After Frege's graduation, they came into closer correspondence.

His other notable university teachers were Christian Philipp Karl Snell (1806–86; subjects: use of infinitesimal analysis in geometry, analytical geometry of [[plane (geometry)|planes]], analytical mechanics, optics, physical foundations of mechanics); [[Hermann Schaeffer|Hermann Karl Julius Traugott Schaeffer]] (1824–1900; analytical geometry, applied physics, algebraic analysis, on the telegraph and other [[electronics|electronic machines]]); and the philosopher [[Kuno Fischer]] (1824–1907; Kantian and critical philosophy).

Starting in 1871, Frege continued his studies in Göttingen, the leading university in mathematics in German-speaking territories, where he attended the lectures of [[Alfred Clebsch|Rudolf Friedrich Alfred Clebsch]] (1833–72; analytical geometry), [[Ernst Christian Julius Schering]] (1824–97; function theory), [[Wilhelm Eduard Weber]] (1804–91; physical studies, applied physics), Eduard Riecke (1845–1915; theory of electricity), and [[Hermann Lotze]] (1817–81; philosophy of religion). Many of the philosophical doctrines of the mature Frege have parallels in Lotze; it has been the subject of scholarly debate whether or not there was a direct influence on Frege's views arising from his attending Lotze's lectures.

In 1873, Frege attained his doctorate under Ernst Christian Julius Schering, with a dissertation under the title of "Ueber&lt;!--[sic; see 'Talk:Gottlob Frege#Ueber']--&gt; eine geometrische Darstellung der imaginären Gebilde in der Ebene" ("On a Geometrical Representation of Imaginary Forms in a Plane"), in which he aimed to solve such fundamental problems in geometry as the mathematical interpretation of projective geometry's infinitely distant (imaginary) points.

Frege married Margarete Katharina Sophia Anna Lieseberg (15 February 1856 – 25 June 1904) on 14 March 1887.

== Work as a logician ==
{{Main|Begriffsschrift}}
Though his education and early mathematical work focused primarily on geometry, Frege's work soon turned to logic. His {{Citation | title = [[Begriffsschrift]], eine der arithmetischen nachgebildete Formelsprache des reinen Denkens | place = Halle a/S | publisher = Verlag von Louis Nebert | year = 1879 |trans-title=Concept-Script: A Formal Language for Pure Thought Modeled on that of Arithmetic}} marked a turning point in the history of logic. The ''Begriffsschrift'' broke new ground, including a rigorous treatment of the ideas of [[function (mathematics)|functions]] and [[Variable (mathematics)|variables]]. Frege's goal was to show that mathematics grows out of [[logic]], and in so doing, he devised techniques that took him far beyond the Aristotelian syllogistic and Stoic propositional logic that had come down to him in the logical tradition.

[[File:Begriffsschrift Titel.png|right|thumb|250px|Title page to ''Begriffsschrift'' (1879)]] In effect, Frege invented [[axiomatization|axiomatic]] [[predicate logic]], in large part thanks to his invention of [[Quantification (logic)|quantified variables]], which eventually became ubiquitous in [[mathematics]] and logic, and which solved the [[problem of multiple generality]]. Previous logic had dealt with the [[logical constant]]s ''and'', ''or'', ''if... then...'', ''not'', and ''some'' and ''all'', but iterations of these operations, especially "some" and "all", were little understood: even the distinction between a sentence like "every boy loves some girl" and "some girl is loved by every boy" could be represented only very artificially, whereas Frege's formalism had no difficulty expressing the different readings of "every boy loves some girl who loves some boy who loves some girl" and similar sentences, in complete parallel with his treatment of, say, "every boy is foolish".

A frequently noted example is that Aristotle's logic is unable to represent mathematical statements like [[Euclid's theorem]], a fundamental statement of number theory that there are an infinite number of [[prime number]]s. Frege's "conceptual notation" however can represent such inferences.&lt;ref&gt;Horsten, Leon and Pettigrew, Richard, "Introduction" in ''The Continuum Companion to Philosophical Logic'' (Continuum International Publishing Group, 2011), p. 7.&lt;/ref&gt;  The analysis of logical concepts and the machinery of formalization that is essential to ''[[Principia Mathematica]]'' (3 vols., 1910–13) (by [[Bertrand Russell]], 1872–1970, and [[Alfred North Whitehead]], 1861–1947), to Russell's [[theory of descriptions]], to [[Kurt Gödel]]'s (1906–78) [[Gödel's incompleteness theorem|incompleteness theorems]], and to [[Alfred Tarski]]'s (1901–83) theory of truth, is ultimately due to Frege.

One of Frege's stated purposes was to isolate genuinely logical principles of inference, so that in the proper representation of mathematical proof, one would at no point appeal to "intuition". If there was an intuitive element, it was to be isolated and represented separately as an axiom: from there on, the proof was to be purely logical and without gaps. Having exhibited this possibility, Frege's larger purpose was to defend the view that [[arithmetic]] is a branch of logic, a view known as [[logicism]]: unlike geometry, arithmetic was to be shown to have no basis in "intuition", and no need for non-logical axioms. Already in the 1879 ''Begriffsschrift'' important preliminary theorems, for example a generalized form of [[law of trichotomy]], were derived within what Frege understood to be pure logic.

This idea was formulated in non-symbolic terms in his ''[[The Foundations of Arithmetic]]'' (1884). Later, in his ''Basic Laws of Arithmetic'' (vol. 1, 1893; vol. 2, 1903; vol. 2 was published at his own expense), Frege attempted to derive, by use of his symbolism, all of the laws of arithmetic from axioms he asserted as logical. Most of these axioms were carried over from his ''[[Begriffsschrift]]'', though not without some significant changes. The one truly new principle was one he called the {{nowrap|[[Basic Law V]]}}: the "value-range" of the function ''f''(''x'') is the same as the "value-range" of the function ''g''(''x'') if and only if ∀''x''[''f''(''x'') = ''g''(''x'')].

The crucial case of the law may be formulated in modern notation as follows. Let {''x''|''Fx''} denote the [[extension (predicate logic)|extension]] of the [[Predicate (logic)|predicate]] ''Fx'', i.e., the set of all Fs, and similarly for ''Gx''. Then Basic Law V says that the predicates ''Fx'' and ''Gx'' have the same extension [[iff]] ∀x[''Fx'' ↔ ''Gx'']. The set of Fs is the same as the set of Gs just in case every F is a G and every G is an F. (The case is special because what is here being called the extension of a predicate, or a set, is only one type of "value-range" of a function.)

In a famous episode, Bertrand Russell wrote to Frege, just as Vol. 2 of the ''Grundgesetze'' was about to go to press in 1903, showing that [[Russell's paradox]] could be derived from Frege's Basic Law V. It is easy to define the relation of ''membership'' of a set or extension in Frege's system; Russell then drew attention to "the set of things ''x'' that are such that ''x'' is not a member of ''x''". The system of the ''Grundgesetze'' entails that the set thus characterised ''both'' is ''and'' is not a member of itself, and is thus inconsistent. Frege wrote a hasty, last-minute Appendix to Vol. 2, deriving the contradiction and proposing to eliminate it by modifying Basic Law V. Frege opened the Appendix with the exceptionally honest comment: "Hardly anything more unfortunate can befall a scientific writer than to have one of the foundations of his edifice shaken after the work is finished. This was the position I was placed in by a letter of Mr. Bertrand Russell, just when the printing of this volume was nearing its completion." (This letter and Frege's reply are translated in [[Jean van Heijenoort]] 1967.)

Frege's proposed remedy was subsequently shown to imply that there is but one object in the [[universe of discourse]], and hence is worthless (indeed, this would make for a contradiction in Frege's system if he had axiomatized the idea, fundamental to his discussion, that the True and the False are distinct objects; see, for example, [[Michael Dummett|Dummett]] 1973), but recent work has shown that much of the program of the ''Grundgesetze'' might be salvaged in other ways:
* Basic Law V can be weakened in other ways. The best-known way is due to philosopher and mathematical logician [[George Boolos]] (1940–1996), who was an expert on the work of Frege. A "concept" ''F'' is "small" if the objects falling under ''F'' cannot be put into one-to-one correspondence with the universe of discourse, that is, unless: ∃''R''[''R'' is 1-to-1 &amp; ∀''x''∃''y''(''xRy'' &amp; ''Fy'')]. Now weaken V to V*: a "concept" ''F'' and a "concept" ''G'' have the same "extension" if and only if neither ''F'' nor ''G'' is small or ∀''x''(''Fx'' ↔ ''Gx''). V* is consistent if [[second-order arithmetic]] is, and suffices to prove the axioms of second-order arithmetic.
* Basic Law V can simply be replaced with [[Hume's principle]], which says that the number of ''F''s is the same as the number of ''G''s if and only if the ''F''s can be put into a one-to-one correspondence with the ''G''s. This principle, too, is consistent if second-order arithmetic is, and suffices to prove the axioms of second-order arithmetic. This result is termed [[Frege's theorem]] because it was noticed that in developing arithmetic, Frege's use of Basic Law V is restricted to a proof of Hume's principle; it is from this, in turn, that arithmetical principles are derived. On Hume's principle and Frege's theorem, see "Frege's Logic, Theorem, and Foundations for Arithmetic".&lt;ref&gt;[http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/frege-logic/ Frege's Logic, Theorem, and Foundations for Arithmetic, ''Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy''] at plato.stanford.edu&lt;/ref&gt;
* Frege's logic, now known as [[second-order logic]], can be weakened to so-called [[Impredicativity|predicative]] second-order logic. Predicative second-order logic plus Basic Law V is provably consistent by [[finitism|finitistic]] or [[Mathematical constructivism|constructive]] methods, but it can interpret only very weak fragments of arithmetic.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Burgess, John|title=Fixing Frege|year=2005|isbn=0-691-12231-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Frege's work in logic had little international attention until 1903 when Russell wrote an appendix to ''[[The Principles of Mathematics]]'' stating his differences with Frege. The diagrammatic notation
that Frege used had no antecedents (and has had no imitators since). Moreover, until Russell and Whitehead's ''[[Principia Mathematica]]'' (3 vols.) appeared in 1910–13, the dominant approach to [[mathematical logic]] was still that of [[George Boole]] (1815–64) and his intellectual descendants, especially [[Ernst Schröder]] (1841–1902). Frege's logical ideas nevertheless spread through the writings of his student [[Rudolf Carnap]] (1891–1970) and other admirers, particularly Bertrand Russell and [[Ludwig Wittgenstein]] (1889–1951).

== Philosopher ==
Frege is one of the founders of [[analytic philosophy]], whose work on logic and language gave rise to the [[linguistic turn]] in philosophy. His contributions to the [[philosophy of language]] include:
* [[Function (mathematics)|Function]]–argument analysis of the [[proposition]];
* Distinction between [[concept and object]] (''Begriff und Gegenstand'');
* Principle of [[compositionality]];
* [[Context principle]];
* Distinction between the [[sense and reference]] (''Sinn und Bedeutung'') of names and other expressions, sometimes said to involve a [[mediated reference theory]].

As a philosopher of mathematics, Frege attacked the [[psychologism|psychologistic]] appeal to mental explanations of the content of judgment of the meaning of sentences. His original purpose was very far from answering general questions about meaning; instead, he devised his logic to explore the foundations of arithmetic, undertaking to answer questions such as "What is a number?" or "What objects do number-words ("one", "two", etc.) refer to?" But in pursuing these matters, he eventually found himself analysing and explaining what meaning is, and thus came to several conclusions that proved highly consequential for the subsequent course of analytic philosophy and the philosophy of language.

It should be kept in mind that Frege was employed as a mathematician, not a philosopher, and he published his philosophical papers in scholarly journals that often were hard to access outside of the German-speaking world. He never published a philosophical monograph other than ''The Foundations of Arithmetic'', much of which was mathematical in content, and the first collections of his writings appeared only after World War II. A volume of English translations of Frege's philosophical essays first appeared in 1952, edited by students of Wittgenstein, [[Peter Geach]] (1916-2013) and [[Max Black]] (1909–88), with the bibliographic assistance of Wittgenstein (see Geach, ed. 1975, Introduction). Despite the generous praise of Russell and Wittgenstein, Frege was little known as a philosopher during his lifetime. His ideas spread chiefly through those he influenced, such as Russell, Wittgenstein, and Carnap, and through work on logic and semantics by Polish logicians.

== Sense and reference ==
{{Main|Sense and reference}}
Frege's 1892 paper, "On Sense and Reference" ("Über Sinn und Bedeutung"), introduced his influential distinction between ''sense'' ("Sinn") and ''reference'' ("Bedeutung", which has also been translated as "meaning", or "denotation"). While conventional accounts of meaning took expressions to have just one feature (reference), Frege introduced the view that expressions have two different aspects of significance: their sense and their reference.

''Reference'', (or, "Bedeutung") applied to [[proper names]], where a given expression (say the expression "Tom") simply refers to the entity bearing the name (the person named Tom). Frege also held that propositions had a referential relationship with their truth-value (in other words, a statement "refers" to the truth-value it takes). By contrast, the ''sense'' (or "Sinn") associated with a complete sentence is the thought it expresses. The sense of an expression is said to be the "mode of presentation" of the item referred to, and there can be multiple modes of representation for the same referent.

The distinction can be illustrated thus: In their ordinary uses, the name "Charles Philip Arthur George Mountbatten-Windsor", which for logical purposes is an unanalyzable whole, and the functional expression "the Prince of Wales", which contains the significant parts "the prince of ξ" and "Wales", have the same ''reference'', namely, the person best known as Prince Charles. But the ''sense'' of the word "Wales" is a part of the sense of the latter expression, but no part of the sense of the "full name" of Prince Charles.

These distinctions were disputed by Bertrand Russell, especially in his paper "[[On Denoting]]"; the controversy has continued into the present, fueled especially by [[Saul Kripke]]'s famous lectures "[[Naming and Necessity]]".

== 1924 diary ==
Frege's published philosophical writings were of a very technical nature and divorced from practical issues, so much so that Frege scholar [[Michael Dummett|Dummett]] expresses his "shock to discover, while reading Frege's diary, that his hero was an anti-Semite."&lt;ref&gt;Hersh, Reuben, ''What Is Mathematics, Really?'' (Oxford University Press, 1997), p. 241.&lt;/ref&gt;  After the [[German Revolution of 1918–19]] his political opinions became more radical. In the last year of his life, at the age of 76, his diary contains extreme [[right-wing]] political opinions, opposing the parliamentary system, democrats, liberals, Catholics, the French and Jews, who he thought ought to be deprived of political rights and, preferably, expelled from Germany.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Dummett: ''Frege: Philosophy of Language'', p. xii.&lt;/ref&gt;  Frege confided "that he had once thought of himself as a liberal and was an admirer of [[Otto von Bismarck|Bismarck]]", but then sympathized with General [[Erich Ludendorff|Ludendorff]] and [[Adolf Hitler]]. Some interpretations have been written about that time.&lt;ref&gt;[[Hans Sluga]]: ''Heidegger's Crisis: Philosophy and Politics in Nazi Germany'', pp. 99ff. Sluga's source was an article by Eckart Menzler-Trott: "Ich wünsch die Wahrheit und nichts als die Wahrheit: Das politische Testament des deutschen Mathematikers und Logikers Gottlob Frege". In: ''Forum'', vol. 36, no. 432, 20 December 1989, pp. 68–79.&lt;/ref&gt;  The diary contains a critique of [[universal suffrage]] and socialism. Frege had friendly relations with Jews in real life: among his students was [[Gershom Scholem]] who much valued his teacher;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www-history.mcs.st-andrews.ac.uk/~history/Biographies/Frege.html|title=Frege biography|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.iep.utm.edu/f/frege.htm|title=Frege, Gottlob – Internet Encyclopedia of Philosophy|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; and he encouraged [[Ludwig Wittgenstein]] to leave for England.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bu.edu/philo/files/2011/01/Frege-WittCorrespondence.pdf Juliet Floyd, The Frege-Wittgenstein Correspondence: Interpretive Themes]&lt;/ref&gt; The 1924 diary was published posthumously in 1994.&lt;ref&gt;Gottfried Gabriel, Wolfgang Kienzler (editors): "Gottlob Freges politisches Tagebuch". In: ''Deutsche Zeitschrift für Philosophie'', vol. 42, 1994, pp. 1057–98. Introduction by the editors on pp. 1057–66. This article has been translated into English, in: ''Inquiry'', vol. 39, 1996, pp. 303–342.&lt;/ref&gt; Frege apparently never spoke in public about his political viewpoints.

== Personality ==
Frege was described by his students as a highly introverted person, seldom entering into dialogue, mostly facing the blackboard while lecturing though being witty and sometimes bitterly sarcastic.&lt;ref&gt;''Frege's Lectures on Logic'', ed. by Erich H. Reck and [[Steve Awodey]], Open Court Publishing, 2004, pp. 18–26.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Important dates ==
* Born 8 November 1848 in [[Wismar]], [[Grand Duchy of Mecklenburg-Schwerin|Mecklenburg-Schwerin]].
* 1869&amp;nbsp;— attends the [[University of Jena]].
* 1871&amp;nbsp;— attends the [[University of Göttingen]].
* 1873&amp;nbsp;— PhD, doctor in [[mathematics]] ([[geometry]]), attained at Göttingen.
* 1874&amp;nbsp;— [[Habilitation]] at Jena; [[Privatdozent|private teacher]].
* 1879&amp;nbsp;— Ausserordentlicher Professor at Jena.
* 1896&amp;nbsp;— Ordentlicher Honorarprofessor at Jena.
* 1917 or 1918&amp;nbsp;— retires.
* Died 26 July 1925 in [[Bad Kleinen]] (now part of [[Mecklenburg-Vorpommern]]).

== Important works ==

=== Logic, foundation of arithmetic ===
''[[Begriffsschrift|Begriffsschrift: eine der arithmetischen nachgebildete Formelsprache des reinen Denkens]]'' (1879), Halle a. S.
* In English: ''Begriffsschrift, a Formula Language, Modeled Upon That of Arithmetic, for Pure Thought'', in: [[Jean van Heijenoort|J. van Heijenoort]] (ed.), ''From Frege to Gödel: A Source Book in Mathematical Logic, 1879-1931'', Harvard, MA: Harvard University Press, 1967, pp.&amp;nbsp;5–82.
* In English (selected sections revised in modern formal notation): R. L. Mendelsohn, ''The Philosophy of Gottlob Frege'', Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2005: "Appendix A. Begriffsschrift in Modern Notation: (1) to (51)" and "Appendix B. Begriffsschrift in Modern Notation: (52) to (68)."
''[[The Foundations of Arithmetic|Die Grundlagen der Arithmetik: Eine logisch-mathematische Untersuchung über den Begriff der Zahl]]'' (1884), Breslau.
* In English: ''[[The Foundations of Arithmetic]]: A Logico-Mathematical Enquiry into the Concept of Number'', translated by [[J. L. Austin]], Oxford: Basil Blackwell, 1950.
''Grundgesetze der Arithmetik'', Band I (1893); Band II (1903), Jena: Verlag Hermann Pohle ([https://archive.org/download/diegrundlagende00freggoog/diegrundlagende00freggoog.pdf online version]).
* In English (translation of selected sections), "Translation of Part of Frege's ''Grundgesetze der Arithmetik''," translated and edited [[Peter Geach]] and [[Max Black]] in ''Translations from the Philosophical Writings of Gottlob Frege'', New York, NY: Philosophical Library, 1952, pp.&amp;nbsp;137–158.
* In German (revised in modern formal notation): ''Grundgesetze der Arithmetik'', Korpora ([[University of Duisburg-Essen]]), 2006: [https://korpora.zim.uni-duisburg-essen.de/Frege/PDF/gga1_o_corr.pdf Band I] and [https://korpora.zim.uni-duisburg-essen.de/Frege/PDF/gga2_o_corr.pdf Band II].
* In German (revised in modern formal notation): ''Grundgesetze der Arithmetik – Begriffsschriftlich abgeleitet. Band I und II: In moderne Formelnotation transkribiert und mit einem ausführlichen Sachregister versehen'', edited by T. Müller, B. Schröder, and R. Stuhlmann-Laeisz, Paderborn: mentis, 2009.
* In English: ''Basic Laws of Arithmetic'', translated and edited with an introduction by Philip A. Ebert and Marcus Rossberg. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2013. {{ISBN|978-0-19-928174-9}}.

=== Philosophical studies ===
"Function and Concept" (1891)
* Original: "Funktion und Begriff"; in ''Jenaische Gesellschaft für Medizin und Naturwissenschaft'', Jena, 9 January 1891;
* In English: "[[Function and Concept]]''.
"On Sense and Reference" (1892)
* Original: "Über Sinn und Bedeutung", in ''[[Zeitschrift für Philosophie und philosophische Kritik]] C'' (1892): 25–50;
* In English: "[[On Sense and Reference]]", alternatively translated (in later edition) as "On Sense and Meaning".
"Concept and Object" (1892)
* Original: "Ueber&lt;!--[sic; see 'Talk:Gottlob Frege#Ueber']--&gt; Begriff und Gegenstand", in ''Vierteljahresschrift für wissenschaftliche Philosophie XVI'' (1892): 192–205;
* In English: "[[Concept and Object]]".
"What is a Function?" (1904)
* Original: "Was ist eine Funktion?", in ''Festschrift Ludwig Boltzmann gewidmet zum sechzigsten Geburtstage'', 20 February 1904, S. Meyer (ed.), Leipzig, 1904, pp.&amp;nbsp;656–666 (Internet Archive: [https://archive.org/details/festschriftludw00meyegoog], [https://archive.org/details/festschriftludw01meyegoog], [https://archive.org/details/festschriftludw02meyegoog]);
* In English: "What is a Function?".

''Logical Investigations'' (1918–1923).
Frege intended that the following three papers be published together in a book titled ''Logische Untersuchungen'' (''Logical Investigations''). Though the German book never appeared, the papers were published together in ''Logische Untersuchungen'', ed. G. Patzig, Vandenhoeck &amp; Ruprecht, 1966, and English translations appeared together in ''Logical Investigations'', ed. Peter Geach, Blackwell, 1975.
* 1918–19. "Der Gedanke: Eine logische Untersuchung" ("The Thought: A Logical Inquiry"), in ''Beiträge zur Philosophie des Deutschen Idealismus I'':&lt;ref name=DPG&gt;The journal ''Beiträge zur Philosophie des Deutschen Idealismus'' was the organ of {{Interlanguage link multi|Deutsche Philosophische Gesellschaft|de}}.&lt;/ref&gt; 58–77.
* 1918–19. "Die Verneinung" ("Negation") in ''Beiträge zur Philosophie des Deutschen Idealismus I'': 143–157.
* 1923. "Gedankengefüge" ("Compound Thought"), in ''Beiträge zur Philosophie des Deutschen Idealismus III'': 36–51.

=== Articles on geometry ===
* 1903: "Über die Grundlagen der Geometrie". II. ''Jahresbericht der deutschen Mathematiker-Vereinigung XII'' (1903), 368–375;
** In English: "On the Foundations of Geometry".
* 1967: ''Kleine Schriften''. (I. Angelelli, ed.). Darmstadt: Wissenschaftliche Buchgesellschaft, 1967 and Hildesheim, G. Olms, 1967. "Small Writings," a collection of most of his writings (e.g., the previous), [[posthumous work|posthumously]] published.

== See also ==
{{Portal|Philosophy|Logic}}
* [[Frege system]]
* [[List of pioneers in computer science]]
* [[Neo-Fregeanism]]
{{-}}

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== Sources ==
=== Primary ===
* [http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/frege/catalog.html Online bibliography of Frege's works and their English translations (compiled by E. N. Zalta, ''Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy'').]
* 1879. ''[[Begriffsschrift]], eine der arithmetischen nachgebildete Formelsprache des reinen Denkens''. Halle a. S.: Louis Nebert. Translation: ''Concept Script, a formal language of pure thought modelled upon that of arithmetic'', by S. Bauer-Mengelberg in [[Jean Van Heijenoort]], ed., 1967. ''From Frege to Gödel: A Source Book in Mathematical Logic, 1879–1931''. Harvard University Press.
* 1884. ''Die Grundlagen der Arithmetik: Eine logisch-mathematische Untersuchung über den Begriff der Zahl''. Breslau: W. Koebner. Translation: [[J. L. Austin]], 1974. ''The Foundations of Arithmetic: A Logico-Mathematical Enquiry into the Concept of Number'', 2nd ed. Blackwell.
* 1891. "Funktion und Begriff." Translation: "Function and Concept" in Geach and Black (1980).
* 1892a. "Über Sinn und Bedeutung" in ''Zeitschrift für Philosophie und philosophische Kritik'' 100:25–50. Translation: "On Sense and Reference" in Geach and Black (1980).
* 1892b. "Ueber&lt;!--[sic; see 'Talk:Gottlob Frege#Ueber']--&gt; Begriff und Gegenstand" in ''Vierteljahresschrift für wissenschaftliche Philosophie'' 16:192–205. Translation: "Concept and Object" in Geach and Black (1980).
* 1893. ''Grundgesetze der Arithmetik, Band I''. Jena: Verlag Hermann Pohle. ''Band II'', 1903. [http://korpora.zim.uni-duisburg-essen.de/Frege Band I+II online]. Partial translation of volume 1: Montgomery Furth, 1964. ''The Basic Laws of Arithmetic''. Univ. of California Press. Translation of selected sections from volume 2 in Geach and Black (1980). Complete translation of both volumes: Philip A. Ebert and Marcus Rossberg, 2013, ''Basic Laws of Arithmetic''. Oxford University Press.
* 1904. "Was ist eine Funktion?" in Meyer, S., ed., 1904. ''Festschrift Ludwig Boltzmann gewidmet zum sechzigsten Geburtstage, 20. Februar 1904''. Leipzig: Barth: 656–666. Translation: "What is a Function?" in Geach and Black (1980).
* 1918–1923. Peter Geach (editor):  ''Logical Investigations'', Blackwell, 1975.
* 1924. Gottfried Gabriel, Wolfgang Kienzler (editors): ''Gottlob Freges politisches Tagebuch''. In: ''Deutsche Zeitschrift für Philosophie'', vol. 42, 1994, pp.&amp;nbsp;1057–98. Introduction by the editors on pp.&amp;nbsp;1057–66. This article has been translated into English, in: ''Inquiry'', vol. 39, 1996, pp.&amp;nbsp;303–342.
* [[Peter Geach]] and [[Max Black]], eds., and trans., 1980. ''Translations from the Philosophical Writings of Gottlob Frege'', 3rd ed. Blackwell (1st ed. 1952).

=== Secondary ===
;Philosophy
* [[Alain Badiou|Badiou, Alain]]. "On a Contemporary Usage of Frege", trans. [[Justin Clemens]] and [[Sam Gillespie]]. ''UMBR(a)'', no. 1, 2000, pp.&amp;nbsp;99–115.
* Baker, Gordon, and P.M.S. Hacker, 1984. ''Frege: Logical Excavations''. Oxford University Press.&amp;nbsp;— Vigorous, if controversial, criticism of both Frege's philosophy and influential contemporary interpretations such as Dummett's.''
* Currie, Gregory, 1982. ''Frege: An Introduction to His Philosophy''. Harvester Press.
* [[Michael Dummett|Dummett, Michael]], 1973. ''Frege: Philosophy of Language''. Harvard University Press.
* ------, 1981. ''The Interpretation of Frege's Philosophy''. Harvard University Press.
* Hill, Claire Ortiz, 1991. ''Word and Object in Husserl, Frege and Russell:  The Roots of Twentieth-Century Philosophy''. Athens OH: Ohio University Press.
* ------, and Rosado Haddock, G. E., 2000. ''Husserl or Frege: Meaning, Objectivity, and Mathematics''. Open Court.&amp;nbsp;— On the Frege-Husserl-Cantor triangle.
* [[Anthony Kenny|Kenny, Anthony]], 1995. ''Frege&amp;nbsp;— An introduction to the founder of modern analytic philosophy''. Penguin Books.&amp;nbsp;— Excellent non-technical introduction and overview of Frege's philosophy.
* Klemke, E.D., ed., 1968. ''Essays on Frege''. University of Illinois Press.&amp;nbsp;— 31 essays by philosophers, grouped under three headings: 1. [[Ontology]]; 2. [[Semantics]]; and 3. [[Logic]] and [[Philosophy of Mathematics]].
* Rosado Haddock, Guillermo E., 2006. ''A Critical Introduction to the Philosophy of Gottlob Frege''. Ashgate Publishing.
* Sisti, Nicola, 2005. ''Il Programma Logicista di Frege e il Tema delle Definizioni''. Franco Angeli.&amp;nbsp;— On Frege's theory of definitions.
* [[Hans Sluga|Sluga, Hans]], 1980. ''Gottlob Frege''. Routledge.
* Nicla Vassallo, 2014, ''Frege on Thinking and Its Epistemic Significance'' with Pieranna Garavaso, Lexington Books–Rowman &amp; Littlefield, Lanham, MD, Usa.
* Weiner, Joan, 1990. ''Frege in Perspective'', Cornell University Press.

;Logic and mathematics
* Anderson, D. J., and [[Edward Zalta]], 2004, "Frege, Boolos, and Logical Objects," ''Journal of Philosophical Logic 33'': 1–26.
* Blanchette, Patricia, 2012, ''Frege's Conception of Logic''. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2012
* Burgess, John, 2005. ''Fixing Frege''. Princeton Univ. Press.&amp;nbsp;— A critical survey of the ongoing rehabilitation of Frege's logicism.
* [[George Boolos|Boolos, George]], 1998. ''Logic, Logic, and Logic''. MIT Press.&amp;nbsp;— 12 papers on [[Frege's theorem]] and the [[logicism|logicist]] approach to the foundation of [[arithmetic]].
* [[Michael Dummett|Dummett, Michael]], 1991. ''Frege: Philosophy of Mathematics''. Harvard University Press.
* Demopoulos, William, ed., 1995. ''Frege's Philosophy of Mathematics''. Harvard Univ. Press.&amp;nbsp;— Papers exploring [[Frege's theorem]] and Frege's mathematical and intellectual background.
* Ferreira, F. and [[Kai Wehmeier|Wehmeier, K.]], 2002, "On the consistency of the Delta-1-1-CA fragment of Frege's ''Grundgesetze''," ''Journal of Philosophic Logic 31'': 301–11.
* [[Ivor Grattan-Guinness|Grattan-Guinness, Ivor]], 2000. ''The Search for Mathematical Roots 1870–1940''. Princeton University Press.&amp;nbsp;— Fair to the mathematician, less so to the philosopher.
* [[Donald A. Gillies|Gillies, Donald A.]], 1982. ''Frege, Dedekind, and Peano on the foundations of arithmetic''. Methodology and Science Foundation, 2. Van Gorcum &amp; Co., Assen, 1982.
* Gillies, Donald: The Fregean revolution in logic. [[Revolutions in mathematics]], 265–305, Oxford Sci. Publ., Oxford Univ. Press, New York, 1992.
* [[Andrew David Irvine|Irvine, Andrew David]], 2010, "Frege on Number Properties," ''Studia Logica,'' 96(2): 239-60.
* [[Charles Parsons (philosopher)|Charles Parsons]], 1965, "Frege's Theory of Number." Reprinted with Postscript in Demopoulos (1965): 182–210. The starting point of the ongoing sympathetic reexamination of Frege's logicism.
* Gillies, Donald: The Fregean revolution in logic. [[Revolutions in mathematics]], 265–305, Oxford Sci. Publ., Oxford Univ. Press, New York, 1992.
* Heck, Richard G., Jr: ''Frege's Theorem''. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2011
* Heck, Richard G., Jr: ''Reading Frege's Grundgesetze''. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2013
* [[Crispin Wright|Wright, Crispin]], 1983. ''Frege's Conception of Numbers as Objects''. Aberdeen University Press.&amp;nbsp;— A systematic exposition and a scope-restricted defense of Frege's ''Grundlagen'' conception of numbers.

;Historical context
*{{Citation|last=Everdell|first=William R. |year=1997 |title=The First Moderns: Profiles in the Origins of Twentieth Century Thought |location= Chicago |publisher=University of Chicago Press}}

== External links ==
{{Sister project links|wikt=no|commons=Category:Gottlob Frege|b=no|n=no|q=Gottlob Frege|s=Author:Gottlob Frege|v=no|species=no }}
* {{Internet Archive author |sname=Gottlob Frege}}
* [http://www.genealogy.math.ndsu.nodak.edu/id.php?id=46166 Frege at Genealogy Project]
* [http://www.ocf.berkeley.edu/~brianwc/frege/ A comprehensive guide to Fregean material available on the web] by Brian Carver.
* [https://www.iep.utm.edu/frege/ Frege, Gottlob – Internet Encyclopedia of Philosophy]
* [[Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy]]:
** "[http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/frege/ Gottlob Frege]"&amp;nbsp;— by [[Edward Zalta]].
** "[http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/frege-logic/ Frege's Logic, Theorem, and Foundations for Arithmetic]"&amp;nbsp;— by [[Edward Zalta]].
* [[Internet Encyclopedia of Philosophy]]:
** [http://www.iep.utm.edu/f/frege.htm Gottlob Frege]&amp;nbsp;— by Kevin C. Klement.
** [http://www.utm.edu/research/iep/f/freg-lan.htm Frege and Language]&amp;nbsp;— by Dorothea Lotter.
* Metaphysics Research Lab: [http://mally.stanford.edu/frege.html Gottlob Frege.]
* [http://www.ontology.co/fregeg.htm Frege on Being, Existence and Truth.]
* {{MacTutor Biography|id=Frege}}
* [http://ctan.org/tex-archive/macros/latex/contrib/begriff/ Begriff], a [[LaTeX]] package for typesetting Frege's logic notation, earlier version
* [http://www.ctan.org/pkg/grundgesetze grundgesetze], a [[LaTeX]] package for typesetting Frege's logic notation, mature version
* [http://www.frege.info/ Frege's Basic Laws of Arithmetic], info website, incl. corrigenda and [[LaTeX]] typesetting tool&amp;nbsp;— by P.A. Ebert and M. Rossberg

{{analytic philosophy}}
{{philosophy of language}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Frege, Gottlob}}
[[Category:1848 births]]
[[Category:1925 deaths]]
[[Category:19th-century German mathematicians]]
[[Category:19th-century German writers]]
[[Category:19th-century male writers]]
[[Category:19th-century philosophers]]
[[Category:19th-century German philosophers]]
[[Category:20th-century German mathematicians]]
[[Category:20th-century German writers]]
[[Category:20th-century philosophers]]
[[Category:Analytic philosophers]]
[[Category:German logicians]]
[[Category:German philosophers]]
[[Category:Linguistic turn]]
[[Category:People from the Grand Duchy of Mecklenburg-Schwerin]]
[[Category:Philosophers of language]]
[[Category:Philosophers of mathematics]]
[[Category:Set theorists]]
[[Category:University of Jena alumni]]
[[Category:20th-century German male writers]]</text>
      <sha1>41l392mlx2wqv8o4vjvjhcujrz884wi</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Human migration</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>221773</id>
    <revision>
      <id>870214641</id>
      <parentid>870214604</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-11-23T06:56:23Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Shellwood</username>
        <id>2366721</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contributions/103.255.4.250|103.255.4.250]] ([[User talk:103.255.4.250|talk]]) ([[WP:HG|HG]]) (3.4.4)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="40976">{{about|contemporary migration|a historical overview|History of human migration|pre-modern history (Neolithic to AD 1800)|Pre-modern human migration}}
{{For|specific types of migration|Immigration|Emigration}}
{{lead too long|date=November 2018}}
{{split|International migration|Internal migration|History of human migration|date=February 2018|discuss=Talk:Human migration#Merge}}
[[File:Net Migration Rate.svg|right|upright=1.35|thumb|Net Migration Rate]]
[[File:Net migration by Nation.png|upright=1.35|right|thumb|Net migration by Nation (2008 -2012)]]

'''Human migration''' is the movement by people from one place to another with the intentions of settling, permanently or temporarily in a new location. The movement is often over long distances and from one country to another, but [[internal migration]] is also possible; indeed, this is the dominant form globally. People may migrate as individuals, in family units or in [[Mass migration|large groups]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://migrationsmap.net/#/USA/arrivals |title=  Migrations country wise|accessdate=7 June 2014}}. One of the major migration rushes took place in the gold run in 19th century in California, Australia, and Africa.&lt;/ref&gt; A person who moves from their home to another place because of natural disaster or civil disturbance may be described as a [[refugee]] or, especially within the same country, a [[displaced person]]. A person seeking refuge from political, religious, or other forms of persecution is usually described as an [[asylum seeker]].

[[Nomad]]ic movements are normally not regarded as migrations as there is no intention to settle in the new place and because the movement is generally [[Seasonal human migration|seasonal]]. Only a few nomadic people have retained this form of lifestyle in modern times. Also, the temporary movement of people for the purpose of travel, tourism, pilgrimages, or the commute is not regarded as migration, in the absence of an intention to live and settle in the visited places.

[[File:Migrants in the world 1960-2015-en.png|thumb|upright=1.8|The number of migrants in the world 1960–2015.&lt;ref&gt;{{webbrefSV|url=https://data.worldbank.org/indicator/SM.POP.TOTL|titel=International migrant stock, total|verk=The World Bank Data|hämtdatum=2017-09-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
Many estimates of statistics in worldwide migration patterns exist.

The [[World Bank]] has published its ''Migration and Remittances Factbook'' annually since 2008.&lt;ref&gt;http://siteresources.worldbank.org/INTLAC/Resources/Factbook2011-Ebook.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; The [[International Organisation for Migration]] (IOM) has published a yearly ''World Migration Report'' since 1999. The [[United Nations Statistics Division]] also keeps a database on worldwide migration.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=http://esa.un.org/unmigration/wallchart2013.htm | title=United Nations Population Division &amp;#124; Department of Economic and Social Affairs}}&lt;/ref&gt; Recent advances in research on migration via the Internet promise better understanding of migration patterns and migration motives.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Oiarzabal | first1 = P. J. | last2 = Reips | first2 = U.-D. | year = 2012 | title = Migration and diaspora in the age of information and communication technologies | url = | journal = Journal of Ethnic and Migration Studies | volume = 38 | issue = 9 | pages = 1333–1338 | doi = 10.1080/1369183X.2012.698202 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Reips, U.-D., &amp; Buffardi, L. (2012). Studying migrants with the help of the Internet: Methods from psychology, Journal of Ethnic and Migration Studies, 38(9), 1405–1424. doi:10.1080/1369183X.2012.698208 http://www.uni-konstanz.de/iscience/reips/pubs/papers/2012ReipsBuffardi_JEMS.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

Substantial internal migration can also take place within a country, either [[seasonal human migration]] (mainly related to agriculture and to tourism to urban places), or shifts of population into cities ([[urbanisation]]) or out of cities ([[suburbanisation]]). Studies of worldwide migration patterns, however, tend to limit their scope to [[international migration]].

The World Bank's ''Migration and Remittances Factbook'' of 2011 lists the following estimates for the year 2010: total number of immigrants: 215.8 million or 3.2% of world population.  In 2013, the percentage of international migrants worldwide increased by 33% with 59% of migrants targeting developed regions.&lt;ref name="UNFrPA"&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.unfpa.org/resources/international-migration-2013-wall-chart|title= International Migration 2013 (wall chart) |year= 2013 |publisher= UNFPA}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Almost half of these migrants are women, which is one of the most significant migrant-pattern changes in the last half century.&lt;ref name="UNFrPA" /&gt; Women migrate alone or with their family members and community. Even though female migration is largely viewed as associations rather than independent migration, emerging studies argue complex and manifold reasons for this.&lt;ref&gt;Thapan, M. (2008). Series Introduction in Palriwala and Uberoi (Eds.), Women and Migration in Asia (p. 359). New Delhi: Sage Publications. {{ISBN|978-0-7619-3675-6}} (Pb)&lt;/ref&gt;

Often{{quantify|date=September 2015}} a distinction is made {{by whom|date=September 2015}} between voluntary and involuntary migration, or between [[refugee]]s fleeing political conflict or natural disaster vs. economic or [[labour migration|labor migration]], but these distinctions are difficult to make and partially subjective, as the motivators for migration are often correlated. The World Bank's report estimates that, as of 2010, 16.3 million or 7.6% of migrants qualified as refugees. At the end of 2012, approximately 15.4 million people were refugees and persons in refugee-like situations - 87% of them found asylum in developing countries.&lt;ref name="UNFrPA" /&gt;

Structurally, there is substantial South-South and North-North migration, i.e., most emigrants from high-income O.E.C.D. countries migrate to other high-income countries, and a substantial part (estimated at 43%) of emigrants from developing countries migrate to other developing countries. The [[United Nations Population Fund]] says that "[while the North has experienced a higher absolute increase in the migrant stock since 2000 (32 million) compared to the South (25 million), the South recorded a higher growth rate.&lt;ref name="UNFrPA" /&gt; Between 2000 and 2013 the average annual rate of change of the migrant population in the developing regions (2.3%) slightly exceeded that of the developed regions (2.1%).&lt;ref name="UNFrPA" /&gt;


==Migration Patterns and Numbers related to them==


The top [[immigration|immigration countries]] are{{when|date=September 2015}}:

* the [[United States]]
* the [[Russian Federation]]
* [[Germany]]
* [[Saudi Arabia]]
* [[Canada]]
* the [[UK]]
* [[France]]
* [[Australia]]
* [[India]]


The top [[emigration|countries of origin]] are:

* [[Mexico]]
* [[India]]
* [[China]]
* [[Ukraine]]
* [[Bangladesh]]
* [[Pakistan]]
* the [[Philippines]]
* [[South Korea]]
* [[Turkey]]
* [[Romania]]
* the [[UK]]
&lt;ref&gt;India, Russia and the UK figure in both lists, as they have substantial immigration and substantial emigration, but also because the ranking reflects absolute numbers and thus favours large countries.&lt;/ref&gt;{{citation needed|date=April 2015}}

The top migration corridors worldwide are{{when|date=September 2015}}:&lt;br&gt;1. [[European migrant crisis|Libya–European Union]] &lt;br&gt;2. [[Mexican American|Mexico–United States]]&lt;br&gt;3.  [[Moroccan diaspora|Morocco-European Union]]&lt;br&gt;4.  [[Russians in Ukraine|Russia–Ukraine]]&lt;br&gt;5. [[Ukrainians in Russia|Ukraine–Russia]]&lt;br&gt;6. [[Bangladeshis in India|Bangladesh–India]]&lt;br&gt;7.  [[Non Resident Nepali|Nepal-India]]&lt;br&gt;8. [[Turks in Germany|Turkey–Germany]]&lt;br&gt;9. [[Kazakhs in Russia|Kazakhstan–Russia]]&lt;br&gt;10. [[Russians in Kazakhstan|Russia–Kazakhstan]]&lt;br&gt;11.  [[Cuban American|Cuba-United States]]&lt;br&gt;12.  [[Chinese diaspora|China–Northern America]]&lt;br&gt;13.  [[Algerians in France|Algeria-France]]&lt;br&gt;14. [[Indian diaspora |India-Northen America]]&lt;br&gt;15. [[Filipino diaspora|Philippines-Northern America]]&lt;br&gt;16. [[Korean diaspora|South Korea-Northern America]]&lt;br&gt;17. [[Vietnamese diaspora|Vietnam-Northern America]]&lt;br&gt;18.  [[Immigration to Hong Kong|China mainland–Hong Kong]]&lt;br&gt;19.  [[Vietnamese Australian|Vietnam-Australia]]&lt;br&gt;20.  [[Hong Kong Canadian|Hong Kong-Canada]]

==Economics related to Human Migration==

[[Remittance]]s, i.e., funds transferred by migrant workers to their home country, form a substantial part of the economy of some countries. The top ten remittance recipients in 2017.
{| class="wikitable sortable"
!bgcolor="efefef"|Rank
!bgcolor="efefef"|Country
!bgcolor="efefef"|Remittance (in billions of US dollars)
!bgcolor="efefef"|Percent of GDP
|-
||1||{{Flag|India}}||69||2.64
|-
||2||{{Flag|China}}||64||0.53
|-
||3||{{Flag|Philippines}}||33||10.5
|-
||4||{{Flag|Mexico}}||31||2.69
|-
||5||{{Flag|France}}||25||0.96
|-
||6||{{Flag|Nigeria}}||22||5.84
|-
||7||{{Flag|Egypt}}||20||8.43
|-
||8||{{Flag|Pakistan}}||20||6.57
|-
||9||{{Flag|Bangladesh}}||15||5.73
|-
||10||{{Flag|Vietnam}}||14||6.35
|}

==Forced Migration==


The Global Commission on International Migration (GCIM), launched in 2003, published a report in 2005.&lt;ref&gt;The 90-page report, along with supporting evidence, is available on the GCIM website [http://www.gcim.org gcim.org]&lt;/ref&gt; International migration challenges at the global level are addressed through the [[Global Forum on Migration and Development]] and the [[Global Migration Group]], both established in 2006.

The United Nations reported that 2014 had the highest level of forced migration on record: 59.5 million individuals, caused by "persecution, conflict, generalized violence, or human rights violations", as compared with 51.2 million in 2013 (an increase of 8.3 million) and with 37.5 million a decade prior. {{As of | 2015}} one of every 122 humans is a refugee, internally displaced, or seeking asylum.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title = Worldwide displacement hits all-time high as war and persecution increase |url = http://www.unhcr.org/558193896.html |accessdate = 2015-09-21 |first = United Nations High Commissioner for |last = Refugees}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[National Geographic Society|National Geographic]] has published 5 maps showing human migrations in progress in 2015 based on the UN report.&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite web
|title = The World's Congested Human Migration Routes in 5 Maps
|url = http://news.nationalgeographic.com/2015/09/150919-data-points-refugees-migrants-maps-human-migrations-syria-world/
|website = National Geographic News|accessdate = 2015-09-21|first = Matthew|last = Chwastyk|first2 = Ryan
|last2 = Williams
|date = 2015-09-19
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

==Labor migration theories in the 21st century==

===Overview===

Numerous causes impel migrants to move to another country. For instance, [[globalization]] has increased the demand for workers in order to sustain national economies. Thus one category of [[economic migrant]]s - generally from impoverished developing countries - migrates to obtain sufficient income for survival.&lt;ref name="unfpa.org"&gt;{{Cite web | url=http://www.unfpa.org/migration | title=Migration}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{qn|date=October 2018}}&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book
 | last1 = Yeoh
 | first1 = Brenda S. A.
 | last2 = Huang
 | first2 = Shirlena
 | last3 = Lam
 | first3 = Theodora
 | chapter = Transnational family dynamics in Asia
 | editor1-last = Triandafyllidou
 | editor1-first = Anna
 | title = Handbook of Migration and Globalisation
 | chapter-url = https://books.google.com/books?id=S1RMDwAAQBAJ
 | series = Handbooks on Globalisation Series
 | location = Cheltenham, UK
 | publisher = Edward Elgar Publishing
 | date = 2018
 | page = 416
 | isbn = 9781785367519
 | access-date = 2018-10-29
 | quote = [...] families may assume transnational morphologies with the strategic intent of ensuring economic survival or maximising social mobility.
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
Such migrants often send some of their income home to family members in the form of [[remittances|economic remittances]], which have become an economic staple in a number of developing countries.&lt;ref&gt;Jason de Parle, "A Good Provider is One Who Leaves", ''New York Times'', April 22, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; People may also move or are forced to move as a result of conflict, of [[human rights violations | human-rights violations]], of violence, or to escape persecution. In 2013 it was estimated{{by whom?|date=October 2018}} that around 51.2 million people fell into this category.&lt;ref name="unfpa.org"/&gt;{{qn|date=October 2018}} Other reasons people may move include to gain access to opportunities and services or to escape extreme weather. This type of movement, usually from rural to urban areas, may class as [[internal migration]].&lt;ref name="unfpa.org"/&gt;{{qn|date=October 2018}} Socio-cultural and geo-historical factors also play a major role. In North Africa, for example, emigrating Europe counts as a sign of social prestige. Moreover, many countries were former [[colony | colonies]]. This means that many have relatives who live legally in the (former) colonial [[metropole]], and who often provide important help for immigrants arriving in that metropole.&lt;ref&gt;
For example: [[Moroccans in France]], [[Filipino Americans | Filipinos in the United States of America]], [[Koreans in Japan]] or [[Samoans in New Zealand]].
&lt;/ref&gt;
Relatives may help with job research and with accommodation. The geographical proximity of Africa to Europe and the long historical ties between Northern and Southern Mediterranean countries also prompt many to migrate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1= Fanack|title= The Key Drivers of North African Illegal Migration to Europe|url= https://chronicle.fanack.com/specials/international-affairs/north-african-illegal-migration-to-europe/|website= Fanack.com|accessdate= 14 July 2015|deadurl= yes|archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20150714172715/https://chronicle.fanack.com/specials/international-affairs/north-african-illegal-migration-to-europe/|archivedate= 14 July 2015|df= | quote = The proximity of North Africa to southern Europe, the liberal mobility policies of most European countries, and the historical links between northern and southern Mediterranean countries are all key factors encouraging people to migrate to Europe.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A number of theories attempt to explain the international flow of capital and people from one country to another.&lt;ref name="Jennissen, R 2007"&gt;
Jennissen, R. 2007. "Causality Chains in the International Migration Systems Approach." Population Research and Policy Review 26(4). 411 – 36.
&lt;/ref&gt;

===Neoclassical economic theory===
{{main|Neoclassical economics}}This theory of migration states that the main reason for labor migration is wage difference between two geographic locations. These wage differences are usually linked to geographic labor demand and supply. It can be said that areas with a shortage of labor but an excess of capital have a high relative wage while areas with a high labor supply and a dearth of capital have a low relative wage. Labor tends to flow from low-wage areas to high-wage areas. Often, with this flow of labor comes changes in the sending as well as the receiving country. Neoclassical economic theory is best used to describe transnational migration, because it is not confined by international immigration laws and similar governmental regulations.&lt;ref name="Jennissen, R 2007" /&gt;

===Dual labor market theory===

Dual labor market theory states that migration is mainly caused by pull factors in more developed countries. This theory assumes that the labor markets in these developed countries consist of two segments: the primary market, which requires high-skilled labor, and the secondary market, which is very labor-intensive requiring low-skilled workers. This theory assumes that migration from less developed countries into more developed countries is a result of a pull created by a need for labor in the developed countries in their secondary market. [[Migrant worker]]s are needed to fill the lowest rung of the labor market because the native laborers do not want to do these jobs as they present a lack of mobility. This creates a need for migrant workers. Furthermore, the initial dearth in available labor pushes wages up, making migration even more enticing.&lt;ref name="Jennissen, R 2007"/&gt;

===New economics of labor migration===

This theory states that migration flows and patterns can't be explained solely at the level of individual workers and their economic incentives, but that wider social entities must be considered as well. One such social entity is the household. Migration can be viewed as a result of risk aversion on the part of a household that has insufficient income. The household, in this case, is in need of extra capital that can be achieved through remittances sent back by family members who participate in migrant labor abroad. These [[remittances]] can also have a broader effect on the economy of the sending country as a whole as they bring in capital.&lt;ref name="Jennissen, R 2007"/&gt; Recent research has examined a decline in U.S. interstate migration from 1991 to 2011, theorizing that the reduced interstate migration is due to a decline in the geographic specificity of occupations and an increase in workers’ ability to learn about other locations before moving there, through both information technology and inexpensive travel.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.minneapolisfed.org/research/wp/wp697.pdf Federal Reserve Bank of Minneapolis, ''Understanding the Long-Run Decline in Interstate Migration'', April 2012]&lt;/ref&gt; Other researchers find that the location-specific nature of housing is more important than moving costs in determining labour reallocation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.chicagofed.org/digital_assets/publications/working_papers/2010/wp2010_18.pdf Federal Reserve Bank of Chicago, ''The Role of Housing in Labour Reallocation'', November 2010]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Relative deprivation theory===
{{main|Relative deprivation}}
Relative deprivation theory states that awareness of the income difference between neighbors or other households in the migrant-sending community is an important factor in migration. The incentive to migrate is a lot higher in areas that have a high level of economic inequality. In the short run, remittances may increase inequality, but in the long run, they may actually decrease it. There are two stages of migration for a worker: first, they invest in human capital formation, and then they try to capitalize on their investments. In this way, successful migrants may use their new capital to provide for better schooling for their children and better homes for their families. Successful high-skilled emigrants may serve as an example for neighbors and potential migrants who hope to achieve that level of success.&lt;ref name="Jennissen, R 2007"/&gt;

===World systems theory===

[[World-systems theory]] looks at migration from a global perspective. It explains that interaction between different societies can be an important factor in social change within societies.  Trade with one country, which causes economic decline in another, may create incentive to migrate to a country with a more vibrant economy. It can be argued that even after decolonization, the economic dependence of former colonies still remains on mother countries. This view of [[international trade]] is controversial, however, and some argue that free trade can actually reduce migration between developing and developed countries. It can be argued that the developed countries import labor-intensive goods, which causes an increase in employment of unskilled workers in the less developed countries, decreasing the outflow of migrant workers. The export of capital-intensive goods from rich countries to poor countries also equalizes income and employment conditions, thus also slowing migration. In either direction, this theory can be used to explain migration between countries that are geographically far apart.&lt;ref name="Jennissen, R 2007"/&gt;

===Osmosis: the unifying theory of human migration===

Old migration theories are generally embedded in geography, sociology or economics. They explain migration in specific periods and spaces. In fact, Osmosis theory explains the whole phenomenon of human migration. Based on the [[history of human migration]], Djelti (2017a)&lt;ref&gt;Djelti S, "The Evolution of the Human Migration Determinants" draft paper présented in the international conference on “Crossing Boundaries: Youth, Migration, and Development”, At Alakhawayn university in Ifran, Morocco – March 2–4, 2017 https://www.researchgate.net/publication/320427737_The_Evolution_of_the_Human_Migration_Determinants_1_Draft_paper&lt;/ref&gt; studies the evolution of its natural determinants. According to him, human migration is divided into two main types: the simple migration and the complicated one. The simple migration is divided, in its turn, into diffusion, stabilisation and concentration periods. During these periods, water availability, adequate climate, security and population density represent the natural determinants of human migration. For the complicated migration, it is characterised by the speedy evolution and the emergence of new sub-determinants notably earning, unemployment, networks and migration policies. Osmosis theory (Djelti, 2017b)&lt;ref&gt;Djelti S, "Osmosis: the Unifying Theory of Human Migration" Revue Algérienne d’Economie et du Management Vol. 08, N°: 02(2017) http://www.asjp.cerist.dz/raem{{Dead link|date=July 2018 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }} https://www.researchgate.net/publication/320427688_Osmosis_the_unifying_theory_of_human_migration&lt;/ref&gt; explains analogically human migration by the biophysical phenomenon of [[osmosis]]. In this respect, the countries are represented by [[animal cells]], the borders by the [[semipermeable membranes]] and the humans by [[ions]] of water. As to osmosis phenomenon, according to the theory, humans migrate from countries with less migration pressure to countries with high migration pressure. In order to measure the latter, the natural determinants of human migration replace the variables of the [[second principle of thermodynamics]] used to measure the [[osmotic pressure]].

==Sociological and Political Science theories==

===Sociology===
{{main|Sociology of immigration}}A number of social scientists have examined immigration from a [[Sociology|sociological]] perspective, paying particular attention to how immigration affects, and is affected by, matters of [[Race (human categorization)|race]] and [[Ethnic group|ethnicity]], as well as [[social structure]]. They have produced three main sociological perspectives: [[symbolic interactionism]], which aims to understand migration via face-to-face interactions on a micro-level; [[social conflict theory]] examines migration through the prism of competition for power and resources; [[structural functionalism]], based on the ideas of [[Émile Durkheim]], examines the role of migration in fulfilling certain functions within each society, such as the decrease of [[Anomie|despair and aimlessness]] and the consolidation of [[social network]]s.

More recently, as attention shifted away from countries of destination, sociologists have attempted to understand how [[transnationalism]] allows us to understand the interplay between migrants, their countries of destination, and their countries of origins.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/?id=sBJTOhDpauQC&amp;pg=PT5&amp;dq=schiller+basch#v=onepage&amp;q=schiller%20basch&amp;f=false|title=Nations Unbound: Transnational Projects, Postcolonial Predicaments, and Deterritorialized Nation-States|last=Basch|first=Linda|last2=Schiller|first2=Nina Glick|last3=Blanc|first3=Christina Szanton|date=2005-09-26|publisher=Routledge|isbn=9781135307035|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; In this framework, work on social remittances by [[Peggy Levitt]] and others has led to a stronger conceptualisation of how migrants affect socio-political processes in their countries of origin.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Levitt|first=Peggy|date=1998|title=Social Remittances: Migration Driven Local-Level Forms of Cultural Diffusion|jstor=2547666|journal=The International Migration Review|volume=32|issue=4|pages=926–948|doi=10.2307/2547666}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Political Science===
Political scientists have put forth a number of theoretical frameworks on migration, offering different perspectives on processes of [[International security|security]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|last=Faist|first=Thomas|date=2006|pages=103–119|publisher=Palgrave Macmillan US|language=en|doi=10.1057/9781403984678_6|isbn=9781349532650|title=Migration, Citizenship, Ethnos|chapter=The Migration-Security Nexus: International Migration and Security Before and After 9/11|hdl=2043/686}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Adamson|first=Fiona B.|date=July 2006|title=Crossing Borders: International Migration and National Security|journal=International Security|language=en|volume=31|issue=1|pages=165–199|doi=10.1162/isec.2006.31.1.165|issn=0162-2889}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[citizenship]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://global.oup.com/academic/product/the-oxford-handbook-of-citizenship-9780198805854?cc=gb&amp;lang=en&amp;|title=The Oxford Handbook of Citizenship|date=2017-08-03|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=9780198805854|editor-last=Shachar|editor-first=Ayelet|series=Oxford Handbooks in Law|location=Oxford, New York|editor-last2=Bauboeck|editor-first2=Rainer|editor-last3=Bloemraad|editor-first3=Irene|editor-last4=Vink|editor-first4=Maarten}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[international relations]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/?id=wERHBAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PP1&amp;dq=Oxford+handbook+citizenship+migration|title=Migration Theory: Talking across Disciplines|last=Brettell|first=Caroline B.|last2=Hollifield|first2=James F.|date=2014-08-25|publisher=Routledge|isbn=9781317805984|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; The political importance of [[diaspora]]s has also become a growing field of interest, as scholars examine questions of diaspora [[activism]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Bauböck|first=Rainer|date=2006-02-23|title=Towards a Political Theory of Migrant Transnationalism|journal=International Migration Review|volume=37|issue=3|pages=700–723|doi=10.1111/j.1747-7379.2003.tb00155.x|issn=0197-9183}}&lt;/ref&gt; state-diaspora relations,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Délano|first=Alexandra|last2=Gamlen|first2=Alan|date=July 2014|title=Comparing and theorizing state–diaspora relations|journal=Political Geography|volume=41|pages=43–53|doi=10.1016/j.polgeo.2014.05.005|issn=0962-6298|hdl=2440/102448}}&lt;/ref&gt; out-of-country [[voting]] processes,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Lafleur|first=Jean-Michel|date=2014|title=The enfranchisement of citizens abroad: variations and explanations|journal=Democratization|volume=22 |issue=5|pages=840–860|doi=10.1080/13510347.2014.979163|url=https://orbi.uliege.be/handle/2268/181007}}&lt;/ref&gt; and states' [[soft power]] strategies.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Tsourapas|first=Gerasimos|date=2018|title=Authoritarian emigration states: Soft power and cross-border mobility in the Middle East|journal=International Political Science Review|volume=39 |issue=3|pages=400–416|doi=10.1177/0192512118759902}}&lt;/ref&gt; In this field, the majority of work has focused on immigration politics, viewing migration from the perspective of the country of destination.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/?id=oec_BAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PR5&amp;dq=Oxford+handbook+citizenship+migration#v=onepage&amp;q=Oxford%20handbook%20citizenship%20migration&amp;f=false|title=Controlling Immigration: A Global Perspective, Third Edition|last=Hollifield|first=James|last2=Martin|first2=Philip L.|last3=Orrenius|first3=Pia|date=2014-07-30|publisher=Stanford University Press|isbn=9780804787352|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; With regard to [[emigration]] processes, political scientists have expanded on [[Albert O. Hirschman|Albert Hirschman's]] framework on 'voice' vs. 'exit' to discuss how emigration affects the politics within the countries of origin.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Hirschman|first=Albert O.|date=January 1993|title=Exit, Voice, and the Fate of the German Democratic Republic: An Essay in Conceptual History|url=https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/world-politics/article/exit-voice-and-the-fate-of-the-german-democratic-republic-an-essay-in-conceptual-history/F80371FDC6F34ED2A8BFA9D31C95992A|journal=World Politics|language=en|volume=45|issue=2|pages=173–202|doi=10.2307/2950657|issn=1086-3338|jstor=2950657}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Brubacker|first=Rogers|date=1990|title=Frontier theses: Exit, voice, and loyalty in East Germany|url=http://www.sscnet.ucla.edu/soc/faculty/brubaker/Publications/27_frontier_theses.pdf|journal=Migration World|volume=|pages=|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Historical theories==

===Ravenstein===
Certain laws of [[social sciences|social science]] have been proposed to describe human migration. The following was a standard list after [[Ernst Georg Ravenstein|Ravenstein's]] (1834–1913) proposal in the 1880s. The laws are as follows:

# ''every migration flow generates a return or counter migration.''
# ''the majority of migrants move a short distance.
# ''migrants who move longer distances tend to choose big-city destinations.
# ''urban residents are often less migratory than inhabitants of rural areas.
# ''families are less likely to make international moves than young adults.
# ''most migrants are adults.
# ''large towns grow by migration rather than natural increase.
# ''migration stage by stage.
# ''urban rural difference.
# ''migration and technology.
# ''economic condition.

===Lee===
Lee's laws divide factors causing migrations into two groups of factors: push and pull factors. Push factors are things that are unfavourable about the area that one lives in, and pull factors are things that attract one to another area.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |jstor= 2060063|title= A Theory of Migration|author= Everett S. Lee|year= 1966|publisher= University of Pennsylvania|volume=3|pages=47–57}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Push factors'''
*Not enough jobs
*Few opportunities
*Inadequate conditions
*Desertification
*Famine or drought
*Political fear or persecution
*Slavery or forced labor
*Poor medical care
*Loss of wealth
*Natural disasters
*Death threats
*Desire for more political or religious freedom
*Pollution
*Poor housing
*Landlord/tenant issues
*Bullying
*Mentallity
*Discrimination
*Poor chances of marrying
*Condemned housing (radon gas, etc.)
*War
'''Pull factors'''
*Job opportunities
*Better living conditions
*The feeling of having more political or religious freedom
*Enjoyment
*Education
*Better medical care
*Attractive climates
*Security
*Family links
*Industry
*Better chances of marrying

See also article by Gürkan Çelik, in [https://web.archive.org/web/20111023113817/http://www.turkishreview.org/tr/newsDetail_getNewsById.action?newsId=223107 Turkish Review: Turkey Pulls, The Netherlands Pushes?] An increasing number of Turks, the Netherlands’ largest ethnic minority, are beginning to return to Turkey, taking with them the education and skills they have acquired abroad, as the Netherlands faces challenges from economic difficulties, social tension and increasingly powerful far-right parties. At the same time Turkey’s political, social and economic conditions have been improving, making returning home all the more appealing for Turks at large. (pp.&amp;nbsp;94–99)

===Climate cycles===
The modern field of climate history suggests that the successive waves of Eurasian nomadic movement throughout history have had their origins in [[Climate change|climatic cycles]], which have expanded or contracted pastureland in Central Asia, especially [[Mongolia]] and to its west the [[Altai mountains|Altai]]. People were displaced from their home ground by other tribes trying to find land that could be grazed by essential flocks, each group pushing the next further to the south and west, into the highlands of [[Anatolia]], the [[Pannonian Plain]], into [[Mesopotamia]], or southwards, into the rich pastures of China. Bogumil Terminski uses the term "migratory domino effect" to describe this process in the context of [[Sea People]] invasion.&lt;ref&gt;Terminski, Bogumil. ''Environmentally-Induced Displacement. Theoretical Frameworks and Current Challenges''. CEDEM, Université de Liège, 2012&lt;/ref&gt;

===Other models===
* ''Migration occurs because individuals search for food, sex and security outside their usual habitation.''&lt;ref&gt;Idyorough, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;  Idyorough is of the view that towns and cities are a creation of the human struggle to obtain food, sex and security. To produce food, security and reproduction, human beings must, out of necessity, move out of their usual habitation and enter into indispensable social relationships that are cooperative or antagonistic.  Human beings also develop the tools and equipment to enable them to interact with nature to produce the desired food and security. The improved relationship (cooperative relationships) among human beings and improved technology further conditioned by the push and pull factors all interact together to cause or bring about migration and higher concentration of individuals into towns and cities.  The higher the technology of production of food and security and the higher the cooperative relationship among human beings in the production of food and security and in the reproduction of the human species, the higher would be the push and pull factors in the migration and concentration of human beings in towns and cities.  Countryside, towns and cities do not just exist but they do so to meet the human basic needs of food, security and the reproduction of the human species.  Therefore, migration occurs because individuals search for food, sex and security outside their usual habitation. Social services in the towns and cities are provided to meet these basic needs for human survival and pleasure.
* [[Zipf's law|Zipf's inverse distance law]] (1956)
* [[Gravity model of migration]] and the [[friction of distance]]
* [[Radiation law for human mobility]]
* [[Buffer theory]]
* Stouffer's [[theory of intervening opportunities]] (1940)
* [[Zelinsky Model|Zelinsky's Mobility Transition Model]] (1971)
* Bauder's regulation of [[labour economics|labour markets]] (2006) "suggests that the international migration of workers is necessary for the survival of industrialised economies...[It] turns the conventional view of international migration on its head: it investigates how migration regulates labour markets, rather than labour markets shaping migration flows."&lt;ref&gt;Bauder, Harald. ''Labour Movement: How Migration Regulates Labour Markets''. Oxford University Press, 1st edition, February 2006, English, 288 pages, {{ISBN|978-0-19-518088-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Div col|colwidth=16em}}
* [[Colonization]]
* [[Diaspora]]
* [[Early human migrations]]
* [[Environmental migrant]]
* [[Existential migration]]
* [[Expatriate]]
* [[Feminisation of migration]]
* [[Genographic Project]]
* [[Geographic mobility]]
* [[Globalization]]
* [[Humanitarian crisis]]
* [[Illegal immigration]]
* ''[[Linguistic Diversity in Space and Time]]''
* [[Immigration to Europe]]
* [[List of diasporas]]
** [[Jewish diaspora]]
* [[Migrant literature]]
* [[Migration in China]]
* [[Most recent common ancestor]]
* [[Offshoring]]
* [[People flow]]
* [[Political demography]]
* [[Queer migration]]
* [[Refugee roulette]]
* [[Religion and human migration]]
* [[Replacement migration]]
* [[Separation barrier]]
* [[Settler colonialism]]
* [[Snowbird (person)]]
* [[Space colonization]]
{{Div col end}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite book |title=Who We Are And How We Got Here - Ancient DNA and the New Science of the Human Past |first=David |last=Reich |publisher=[[Pantheon Books]] |year=2018 |isbn=978-1101870327 }}&lt;ref name="NYT-20180420"&gt;{{cite news |last=Diamond |first=Jared |title=A Brand-New Version of Our Origin Story |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2018/04/20/books/review/david-reich-who-we-are-how-we-got-here.html |date=April 20, 2018 |newspaper=[[The New York Times]] |accessdate=April 23, 2018 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Sources==
===Books===
* Bauder, Harald. ''Labour Movement: How Migration Regulates Labour Markets'', New York: Oxford University Press, 2006.
* Behdad, Ali. ''A Forgetful Nation: On Immigration and Cultural Density in the United States'', Duke UP, 2005.
* Chaichian, Mohammad. ''Empires and Walls: Globalisation, Migration, and Colonial Control'', Leiden: Brill, 2014.
* [[Jared Diamond]], ''[[Guns, Germs, and Steel|Guns, germs and steel. A short history of everybody for the last 13'000 years]]'', 1997.
* [[Miguel A. De La Torre|De La Torre, Miguel A.]], ''Trails of Terror: Testimonies on the Current Immigration Debate'', Orbis Books, 2009.
* Fell, Peter and Hayes, Debra. ''What are they doing here? A critical guide to asylum and immigration'', Birmingham (UK): Venture Press, 2007.
* Hanlon, Bernadette and Vicino, Thomas J. ''Global Migration: The Basics'', New York and London: Routledge, 2014.
* Hoerder, Dirk. ''Cultures in Contact. World Migrations in the Second Millennium'', Duke University Press, 2002
* Idyorough, Alamveabee E. "Sociological Analysis of Social Change in Contemporary Africa", Makurdi: Aboki Publishers, 2015.
* Kleiner-Liebau, Désirée. ''Migration and the Construction of National Identity in Spain'', Madrid / Frankfurt, Iberoamericana / Vervuert, Ediciones de Iberoamericana, 2009. {{ISBN|978-84-8489-476-6}}.
* Knörr, Jacqueline. ''Women and Migration. Anthropological Perspectives'', Frankfurt &amp; New York: Campus Verlag &amp; St. Martin's Press, 2000.
* Knörr, Jacqueline. ''Childhood and Migration. From Experience to Agency'', Bielefeld: Transcript, 2005.
* Manning, Patrick. ''Migration in World History'', New York and London: Routledge, 2005.
* ''Migration for Employment'', Paris: OECD Publications, 2004.
* ''OECD International Migration Outlook 2007'', Paris: OECD Publications, 2007.
* Pécoud, Antoine and Paul de Guchteneire (Eds): ''Migration without Borders, Essays on the Free Movement of People '' (Berghahn Books, 2007)
* Abdelmalek Sayad. ''The Suffering of the Immigrant'', Preface by [[Pierre Bourdieu]], Polity Press, 2004.
* Stalker, Peter. ''No-Nonsense Guide to International Migration'', New Internationalist, second edition, 2008.
* ''The Philosophy of Evolution'' (A.K. Purohit, ed.), Yash Publishing House, Bikaner, 2010. {{ISBN|81-86882-35-9}}.

===Journals===
* ''International Migration Review''
* ''[[Migration Letters]]''
* ''International Migration''
* ''[[Journal of Ethnic and Migration Studies]]''
* ''[[Review of Economics of the Household]]''

===Websites===
* ''[http://www.oecd.org/document/25/0,3343,en_2649_33729_38797017_1_1_1_1,00.html OECD International Migration Outlook 2007]'' (subscription service)
* ''[http://www.migrationpolicycentre.eu/ Migration Policy Centre]''

===Films===
* ''[[El Inmigrante]]'', Directors: David Eckenrode, John Sheedy, John Eckenrode. 2005. 90 min. (U.S./Mexico)

==External links==
{{Library resources box|by=no|onlinebooks=no|about=yes|wikititle=human migration}}
{{Commons category|Human migration}}
* [https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/1911_Encyclopædia_Britannica/Civilization 1911 Encyclopædia Britannica article]
* [https://www.iom.int iom.int International Organisation for Migration]
* [https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/fields/2112.html CIA World Factbook], up-to-date statistics on net immigration by country
* [http://uni-nke.hu/uploads/media_items/aarms-2014-2.original.pdf Western Sahara and Migration]
* [http://www.pstalker.com/migration/index.php Stalker's Guide to International Migration], a comprehensive interactive guide to modern migration issues, with maps and statistics
* [http://www.unaoc.org/communities/migrationintegration Integration: Building Inclusive Societies (IBIS)], a UN Alliance of Civilisations online community on good practices of integration of migrants across the world
* [http://educate.si.edu/migrations Migrations in history]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20131129032557/http://www.accademiapulia.org/en/events/home-my-place-in-the-world---summer-exhibition-580.html The importance of migrants in the modern world]
* [http://www.business-of-migration.com Mass migration as a travel business]
* [http://www.undp.org/content/undp/en/home/ourwork/sustainable-development/development-planning-and-inclusive-sustainable-growth/migration-refugees-and-displacement.html Migration, refugees and displacement (UNDP)], provides background and statistics on human migration.
* [https://www.giga-hamburg.de/en/flight-and-migration Online-Dossier on Flight and Migration] by the German Institute for Global and Area Studies

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Human Migration}}
[[Category:Human migration| ]]
[[Category:Anthropology]]
[[Category:Demographic economics]]
[[Category:Genetic genealogy]]
[[Category:Human overpopulation|Migration]]
[[Category:Demography]]</text>
      <sha1>nl6y9jt68mbie1ogyvm7w5h1ah3m7ga</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Humanities College</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9952791</id>
    <revision>
      <id>839297282</id>
      <parentid>774132817</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-05-02T14:56:53Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Entranced98</username>
        <id>27199084</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rm 'see also' red link - page would not be created anyway as the specialist schools programme is now defunct</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="1036">[[File:Humanities College.png|thumb|logo used to show Humanities status]]'''Humanities Colleges''' were introduced in 2004 as part of the [[Specialist school|Specialist Schools Programme]] in the [[United Kingdom]]. The system enables [[Secondary education#England, Wales and Northern Ireland|secondary schools]] to specialise in certain fields, in this case, [[humanities]]. Schools that successfully apply to the [[Specialist Schools Trust]] and become Humanities Colleges will receive extra funding from this joint private sector and government scheme. Humanities Colleges also act as a local point of reference for other schools and businesses in the area, with an emphasis on promoting humanities within the community.

== References ==
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20020806144059/http://www.standards.dfes.gov.uk/specialistschools/what_are/arts/ Department for Education and Skills]

[[Category:Humanities education]]
[[Category:Specialist schools]]
[[Category:2004 introductions]]
[[Category:2004 in education]]

{{UK-edu-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>nbpk9g9e50la9zca4ptbtvmegz5g8lo</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Idiom (language structure)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>43293772</id>
    <revision>
      <id>852421756</id>
      <parentid>846846185</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-07-28T22:00:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>81.66.232.87</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Emic and etic views */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="3926">{{about|language structure|words with a figurative meaning|Idiom|other uses|Idiom (disambiguation)}}
{{Multiple issues|
{{refimprove|date=September 2014}}
{{original research|date=June 2015}}
{{Context|date=June 2015}}
}}
'''Idiom''' is the syntactical, grammatical, or structural form peculiar to a [[language]].&lt;ref name="MWCD"&gt;{{Citation | author = Merriam-Webster | authorlink = Merriam-Webster | title = Merriam-Webster's Collegiate Dictionary | publisher = Merriam-Webster |url=http://unabridged.merriam-webster.com/collegiate/ |postscript=.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Idiom is the realized structure of a language, as opposed to possible but unrealized structures that could have developed to serve the same [[semantic]] functions but did not.

Language grammar and syntax is often inherently arbitrary and peculiar to a particular language or a [[language family|group of related languages]]. For example, although in English it is ''idiomatic'' (accepted as structurally correct) to say "cats are associated with agility", other forms could have developed, such as "cats associate toward agility" or "cats are associated of agility".&lt;ref name="Garner_2016_headword_accompanied"&gt;{{Citation |last=Garner |first=Bryan A. |author-link=Bryan A. Garner |year=2016 |title=Garner's Modern English Usage |edition=4th |location=headword "accompanied" |url=http://www.lawprose.org/bryan-garner/books-by-bryan-garner/garners-modern-english-usage-4th-edition-2016/ |isbn=978-0190491482 |quote=Idiom requires ''accompanied by'', not ''*accompanied with''—e.g.: '[…] sliced in half and accompanied with [read ''accompanied by''] no more than a small scoop of ice cream.' |postscript=.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Unidiomatic constructions sound wrong to fluent speakers, although they are often entirely comprehensible. For example, the title of the classic book ''[[English As She Is Spoke]]'' is easy to understand (its idiomatic counterpart is ''English As It Is Spoken''), but it deviates from English idiom in the [[grammatical gender|gender]] of the pronoun and the [[inflection]] of the verb. [[Accidental gap|Lexical gaps]] are another key example of idiom.

==Emic and etic views==
[[Monolingual]] native speakers in an insulated monolingual-native environment are mostly not conscious of ''idiomaticness'' (the quality or state of a construction matching the idiom of the given language), because in general their minds never reach for, or hear, other possible structures. The main exception is when they hear the natural experimentation of children acquiring the language, when they may encounter, for example, [[overregularization]] (for example, ''I seed two deers'' for ''I saw two deer''). By this correlation, [[solecism]] to native-speaking monolingual minds often sounds childish. However, when adults study a foreign language, they become consciously aware of idiomaticness and the lack of it. For example, in English it is idiomatic to use an [[article (grammar)#Indefinite article|indefinite article]] when describing a person's occupation (''I am '''a''' plumber''; ''she is '''an''' engineer''), but in Spanish and many other languages it is not (''soy plomero''; ''ella es ingeniera''), and a native speaker of English learning Spanish must encounter and accept that fact to become fluent.

The [[count noun|count]] [[word sense|sense]] of the word ''idiom'', referring to [[idiom|a saying with a figurative meaning]], is related to the present sense of the word by the arbitrariness and peculiarity aspects; the idiom "she is pulling my leg" (meaning "she is humorously misleading me") is idiomatic because it belongs, by convention, to the language, whether or not anyone can identify the original logic by which it was coined (arbitrariness), and regardless of whether it translates literally to any other language (peculiarity).

== See also==
* [[Programming idiom]]
* [[Collocation]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

[[Category:Linguistics]]</text>
      <sha1>4f01ixbas6pdwibiwejhg8qkmc1olq4</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Kitab</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7870501</id>
    <revision>
      <id>868664137</id>
      <parentid>854354968</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-11-13T17:25:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>DocWatson42</username>
        <id>38455</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Performed minor cleanup on punctuation and grammar.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="2648">'''Kitab''' ({{lang-ar|کتاب}}), also transcribed as '''kitaab''', '''kitáb''', or '''kitāb''', is the Arabic word for [[book]], from the root [[K-T-B]]. The word is also used in the [[Persian language|Persian]], [[Hindi language|Hindi]], [[Bengali language|Bengali]], [[Sylheti language|Sylheti]], [[Nepali language|Nepalese]], [[Azerbaijani language|Azerbaijani]], [[Kazakh language|Kazakh]], [[Punjabi language|Punjabi]], [[Indonesian language|Indonesian]], [[Urdu language|Urdu]], and [[Rutul language|Rutulian]], as (''kitab''), as well as in [[Assamese language|Assamese]] (as "kitap"), [[Swahili language|Swahili]] (as "kitabu"), [[Tatar language|Tatar]], [[Kyrgyz language|Kyrgyz]], [[Turkish language|Turkish]] (as "kitap"), [[Serbo-Croatian]] (as "ćitap") languages and in some contexts in [[Greek language|Greek]] ("κιτάπι"). The word is also related to '''katav''', the [[Hebrew language|Hebrew]] word for [[reporter]]. It is part of titles of many Arabic language books. Some prominent examples are:

*[[Al-]]Kitab: a reference to itself in the [[Quran]], also called "Kitabullah", The Book of God. In [[Indonesian language|Indonesian]] the word refers to the [[Bible]].
*[[Kitab al-Aghani]]: ''The Book of Songs''
*[[Kitab al-Buldan (disambiguation)|Kitab al-Buldan]]: ''Book of Lands''
*[[Kitab al-Hiyal]]: ''The Book of Ingenious Devices''
*[[Kitab al Majmu]]: ''Book of the Sum Total''
*Kitab [[Ash-Shifa bi ta'rif huquq al-Mustafa]]: ''Healing by the recognition of the Rights of the Chosen one''
*[[Kitab al-Musiqi al-Kabir]]: ''Great Book of Music''
*[[Kitab al-Tabikh (disambiguation)|Kitab al-Tabikh]] - ''The Book of Dishes''
*[[Kitáb-i-Aqdas]]: ''Most Holy Book'', the central book of the [[Bahá'í Faith]].
*[[Kitáb-i-Íqán]]: ''Book of Certitude'' regarded as [[Bahá'u'lláh]]'s primary theological work.
*[[Kitab al Khazari]]: ''Book of the Khazars'', dialogues between the Khazar King and a religious sage, originally written in Arabic in Medieval Spain, but since translated into Hebrew and English, perhaps incorrectly so.  The original Arabic version has been lost, and therefore there is no way to validate the accuracy of the Hebrew translation, which occurred 700 years after the work was originally written in Arabic.

==See also==
*[[Kitab-Verlag]] - a publishing house in Klagenfurt, Austria
*[[Mus'haf]]
*[[Kitab, Uzbekistan]]

== External links ==
{{wiktionary|kitab}}
* [http://www.kitab.az/ Kitab.az electronic library network in Azerbaijan]
* [http://www.akacademy.eu/ Dars Kitab Sahih Bukhari]

[[Category:Arabic words and phrases]]
[[Category:Books]]

{{Semitic-lang-stub}}
{{word-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>h12ibnoetin0ph7uafxxh8oeifos7sv</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Noun particle</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9736120</id>
    <revision>
      <id>839646195</id>
      <parentid>839643732</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-05-04T19:16:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>AnomieBOT</username>
        <id>7611264</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Dating maintenance tags: {{Morecat}}</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="2328">{{Unreferenced|date=February 2007}}
A '''noun particle''' is any [[morpheme]] that denotes or marks the presence of a [[noun]].  Noun particles do not exist in [[English language|English]], but can be found in other languages such as [[Korean language|Korean]] and [[Japanese language|Japanese]]. &lt;!-- I'm pretty sure Arabic has object and topic particles as well; someone knowledgeable in Arabic should add something below. -Roehl Sybing --&gt;

==Korean particles==
&lt;!-- The following section is based on the Korean reference found on Wikibooks, as I have very little experience with Korean.  Romanization - as well as clarifications/corrections - is most certainly encouraged and requested. -RS --&gt;
{{Main|Korean language}}
Korean particles are [[postposition]]s, which differ from English [[preposition]]s in that they come ''after'' the word they mark.
*'''Example #1:''' {{lang|ko|새가 지붕 '''위에''' 있어요.}} (There's a bird '''on''' the roof.)
The particle "{{lang|ko|위에}}" is used to mean "on" or "above." It follows the word "{{lang|ko|지붕}}" ("roof").
*'''Example #2:''' {{lang|ko|도서관이 시장 옆에 있어요.}} (The library is '''next to''' the market.)
The particle "{{lang|ko|옆에}}" means "next to," and it follows "{{lang|ko|시장}}" ("market").

==Japanese particles==
{{Main|Japanese grammar}}

Just as in Korean, noun particles follow the noun being marked, and can serve any of several functions in a given sentence.
*'''Example #1:''' {{lang|ja|昨日スーパーへ行きました。}} (Yesterday, I went '''to''' the supermarket.)
**Kinoo suupaa '''e''' ikimashita.
In this example, "e" is the noun particle for "suupaa" ("supermarket").  This particular noun particle denotes direction towards a place, being "supermarket."

*'''Example #2:''' {{lang|ja|昼ごはんは私がピザを食べた。}} (I ate pizza for lunch. '''lit.''' '''As for''' lunch, I ate pizza.)
**Hirugohan '''wa''' watashi '''ga''' piza '''o''' tabeta.
The three noun particles ("wa," "ga," and "o") all serve different functions:
* "wa" - ''topic marker'' ("hirugohan" - lunch)
* "ga" - ''subject marker'' ("watashi" - I)
* "o" - ''object marker'' ("piza" - pizza)

{{Lexical categories|state=collapsed}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Noun Particle}}
{{morecat|date=May 2018}}
[[Category:Linguistics]]


{{Ling-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>ce1g6ds9e6ai9l1gjmmb7nedwove50q</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Politics of the International Space Station</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>41550219</id>
    <revision>
      <id>868651240</id>
      <parentid>829956052</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-11-13T15:59:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Cléééston</username>
        <id>22911531</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Brazil */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="17935">{{double image|right|ISS Main Contributors.svg|250|ISS Hardware Allocation.png|200|{{legend|#B00000|Primary contributing nations}}{{legend|#F07568|Formerly contracted nations}}|Allocation of [[US Orbital Segment]] hardware usage between contributors|alt1=A world map highlighting Belgium, Denmark, France, Germany, Italy, Netherlands, Norway, Spain, Sweden and Switzerland in red and Brazil in pink. See adjacent text for details.|alt2=Four pie charts indicating how each part of the American segment of the ISS is allocated. See adjacent text for details.}}
'''Politics of the International Space Station'''  begins with the 1972 milestone in co-operation between the United States and the Soviet Union in space, the [[Apollo-Soyuz Test Project]]. This cooperative venture resulted in the July 1975 docking of [[Soyuz 19]] with an [[Apollo Command/Service Module|Apollo]] spacecraft. From 1978 to 1987, the USSR's [[Interkosmos]] programme included allied Warsaw Pact countries, and countries which were not Soviet allies, such as India, Syria and France, in manned and unmanned missions to Space stations Salyut 6 and 7. In 1986 the USSR extended this co-operation to a dozen countries in the [[Mir]] programme. From 1994 to 1998, NASA Space Shuttles and crew visited MIR in the [[Shuttle–Mir Program]]me. In 1998, assembly of the [[International Space Station]] began.&lt;ref name="OnOrbit"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nasa.gov/externalflash/ISSRG/pdfs/on_orbit.pdf |title=On-Orbit Elements |publisher=NASA |author=NASA |date=18 February 2010 |accessdate=19 June 2010 |format=PDF |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20091029013438/http://www.nasa.gov/externalflash/ISSRG/pdfs/on_orbit.pdf |archivedate=29 October 2009 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In March 2012, a meeting in Quebec City between the leaders of the Canadian Space Agency and those from Japan, Russia, the United States and involved European nations resulted in a renewed pledge to maintain the International Space Station until at least 2020. NASA reports to be still committed to the principles of the mission but also to use the station in new ways, which were not elaborated. CSA President Steve MacLean stated his belief that the station's Canadarm will continue to function properly until 2028, alluding to Canada's likely extension of its involvement beyond 2020.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vancouversun.com/technology/Canada+renews+pledge+International+Space+Station+until+2020/6235789/story.html Canada renews pledge to International Space Station until 2020.] The Vancouver Sun. 1 March 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

Ownership of modules, station usage by participant nations, and responsibilities for station resupply are established by the Space Station Intergovernmental Agreement (IGA). This international treaty was signed on 28 January 1998 by the United States of America, Russia, Japan, Canada and eleven member states of the European Space Agency (Belgium, Denmark, France, Germany, Italy, The Netherlands, Norway, Spain, Sweden, Switzerland, and the United Kingdom).&lt;ref name="PartStates"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.esa.int/esaHS/partstates.html|title=Human Spaceflight and Exploration—European Participating States|accessdate=17 January 2009|publisher=European Space Agency (ESA)|date=2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="ESA-IGA"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.spaceflight.esa.int/users/index.cfm?act=default.page&amp;level=11&amp;page=1980|title=ISS Intergovernmental Agreement|publisher=European Space Agency (ESA)|accessdate=19 April 2009|date=19 April 2009|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090610083738/http://www.spaceflight.esa.int/users/index.cfm?act=default.page&amp;level=11&amp;page=1980|archivedate=10 June 2009|df=}}&lt;/ref&gt; With the exception of the United Kingdom, all of the signatories went on to contribute to the Space Station project. A second layer of agreements was then achieved, called Memoranda of Understanding (MOU), between NASA and ESA, CSA, RKA and JAXA. These agreements are then further split, such as for the contractual obligations between nations, and trading of partners' rights and obligations.&lt;ref name="ESA-IGA" /&gt; Use of the Russian Orbital Segment is also negotiated at this level.&lt;ref name="RSA-MOU"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nasa.gov/mission_pages/station/structure/elements/nasa_rsa.html|title=Memorandum of Understanding Between the National Aeronautics and Space Administration of the United States of America and the Russian Space Agency Concerning Cooperation on the Civil International Space Station|publisher=NASA|accessdate=19 April 2009|date=29 January 1998}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:ISS Agreements.jpg|thumb|right|Dated January 29, 1998]]
&lt;!-- {{double image|left|Russian Orbital Segment.png|300|US Orbital Segment - May 2011.jpg|140|Annotated image of the Russian Orbital Segment configuration as of 2011|The [[USOS]] is shared by [[NASA]], [[European Space Agency|ESA]], [[Canadian Space Agency|CSA]] and [[Japan Aerospace Exploration Agency|JAXA]]||}} --&gt;
In addition to these main intergovernmental agreements, Brazil originally joined the programme as a bilateral partner of the United States by a contract with NASA to supply hardware.&lt;ref name="Brazil"&gt;{{cite web|title=NASA Signs International Space Station Agreement With Brazil|url=http://www.nasa.gov/centers/johnson/news/releases/1996_1998/h97-233.html|date=14 October 1997|accessdate=18 January 2009|publisher=NASA}}&lt;/ref&gt; In return, NASA would provide Brazil with access to its ISS facilities on-orbit, as well as a flight opportunity for one Brazilian astronaut during the course of the ISS programme. However, due to cost issues, the subcontractor [[Embraer]] was unable to provide the promised ExPrESS pallet, and Brazil left the programme in 2007.&lt;ref name="Emerson Kimura 2009"&gt;{{cite web|title=Made in Brazil O Brasil na Estação Espacial Internacional|url=http://www.gizmodo.com.br/conteudo/made-brazil-o-brasil-na-estacao-espacial-internacional/|publisher=Gizmodo Brazil|accessdate=9 March 2011|author=Emerson Kimura|language=Portuguese|date=2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Italy has a similar contract with NASA to provide comparable services, although Italy also takes part in the programme directly via its membership in ESA.&lt;ref name="Italy"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.asi.it/en/flash_en/living/the_international_space_station_iss|title=International Space Station (ISS)|publisher=Italian Space Agency|date=18 January 2009|accessdate=18 January 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Expanding the partnership would require unanimous agreement of the existing partners. Chinese participation has been prevented by unilateral US opposition.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Spotts|first=Pete|title=NASA's Bolden walks tight rope on China trip|url=http://www.csmonitor.com/Science/2010/1016/NASA-s-Bolden-walks-tight-rope-on-China-trip|work=The Christian Science Monitor|accessdate=5 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Kulacki|first=Gregory|title=US and China need contact, not cold war|journal=Nature|date=June 2011|doi=10.1038/474444a}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The heads of both the South Korean and Indian space agency [[ISRO]] announced at the first plenary session of the 2009 [[International Astronautical Congress]] that their nations wished to join the ISS programme, with talks due to begin in 2010. The heads of agency also expressed support for extending ISS lifetime.&lt;ref name="ISRO and KARI to join ISS"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.flightglobal.com/articles/2009/10/14/333406/south-korea-india-to-begin-iss-partnership-talks-in.html|title=South Korea, India to begin ISS partnership talks in 2010|work=Flight International|accessdate=14 October 2009|date=19 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; European countries not part of the programme will be allowed access to the station in a three-year trial period, [[ESA]] officials say.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.space-travel.com/reports/EU_mulls_opening_ISS_to_more_countries_999.html|title=EU mulls opening ISS to more countries|publisher=Space-travel.com|accessdate=16 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Russian part of the station is operated and controlled by the Russian Federation's space agency and provides Russia with the right to nearly one-half of the crew time for the ISS. The allocation of remaining crew time (three to four crew members of the total permanent crew of six) and hardware within the other sections of the station is as follows: ''[[Columbus (ISS module)|Columbus]]'': 51% for the ESA, 46.7% for NASA, and 2.3% for CSA.&lt;ref name="ESA-IGA" /&gt; ''[[Japanese Experiment Module|Kibō]]'': 51% for the JAXA, 46.7% for NASA, and 2.3% for CSA.&lt;ref name="JAXA-MOU"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nasa.gov/mission_pages/station/structure/elements/nasa_japan.html|title=Memorandum of Understanding Between the National Aeronautics and Space Administration of the United States of America and the Government of Japan Concerning Cooperation on the Civil International Space Station|publisher=NASA|accessdate=19 April 2009|date=24 February 1998}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Destiny (ISS module)|Destiny]]'': 97.7% for NASA and 2.3% for CSA.&lt;ref name="CSA-MOU"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nasa.gov/mission_pages/station/structure/elements/nasa_csa.html|title=Memorandum of Understanding Between the National Aeronautics and Space Administration of the United States of America and the Canadian Space Agency Concerning Cooperation on the Civil International Space Station|publisher=NASA|accessdate=19 April 2009|date=29 January 1998}}&lt;/ref&gt; Crew time, electrical power and rights to purchase supporting services (such as data upload and download and communications) are divided 76.6% for NASA, 12.8% for JAXA, 8.3% for ESA, and 2.3% for CSA.&lt;ref name="ESA-IGA" /&gt;&lt;ref name="JAXA-MOU" /&gt;&lt;ref name="CSA-MOU" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Manifest"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nasa.gov/mission_pages/station/structure/iss_manifest.html|title=Consolidated Launch Manifest|accessdate=8 July 2008|publisher=NASA|author=NASA|date=2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="SSSM"&gt;{{cite book|first=David|last=Harland|title=The Story of Space Station Mir|publisher=Springer-Verlag New York Inc|date=30 November 2004|location=New York|isbn=978-0-387-23011-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== China ==

{{further|Chinese exclusion policy of NASA}}
China is not an ISS partner, and no Chinese nationals have been aboard. China has its own contemporary manned space programme, [[Project 921]], and has carried out co-operation and exchanges with countries such as Russia and Germany in manned and unmanned space projects.&lt;ref name="english.mofcom.gov.cn"&gt;{{cite web|author=28 September 2011 Posted: 20:25 BJT(25 GMT) xinhuanet |url=http://english.mofcom.gov.cn/aarticle/newsrelease/counselorsoffice/westernasiaandafricareport/201109/20110907761198.html |title=Ministry of Commerce People'S Republic of China |publisher=English.mofcom.gov.cn |date=28 September 2011 |accessdate=1 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="fpc.state.gov"&gt;https://fpc.state.gov/documents/organization/106143.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; China launched its first experimental space station,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nasa.gov/directorates/heo/reports/iss_reports/2011/09292011_prt.htm |title=NASA – 09-29-2011 |publisher=Nasa.gov |date=29 September 2011 |accessdate=1 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Tiangong 1]], in September 2011,&lt;ref name="Tiangong I"&gt;{{cite web|title=Tiangong I | publisher = Chinese Space Agency  |date=4 June 2011 | url = http://en.cmse.gov.cn/list.php?catid=44 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and has officially initiated the permanently manned [[Chinese space station]] project.&lt;ref name="China modular space station"&gt;{{cite web|title=China modular space station program officially initiated | publisher = Chinese Space Agency |date=4 June 2011 | url = http://en.cmse.gov.cn/list.php?catid=64 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2007, Chinese vice-minister of science and technology Li Xueyong said that China would like to participate in the ISS.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Sebastian Rice |url=http://www.itwire.com/science-news/space/14908-china-wants-to-help-with-space-station |title=China wants to help with Space Station |publisher=iTWire |date=17 October 2007 |accessdate=1 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2010, ESA Director-General Jean-Jacques Dordain stated his agency was ready to propose to the other 4 partners that China be invited to join the partnership, but that this needs to be a collective decision by all the current partners.&lt;ref name="ESAproposesInvite"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://spacenews.com/esa-chief-lauds-renewed-us-commitment-space-station-earth-science/|title=ESA Chief Lauds Renewed U.S. Commitment to Space Station, Earth Science|last=|first=|date=2 March 2010|website=|publisher=Peter B. de Selding, Space News|archive-url=|archive-date=|dead-url=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; While ESA is open to China's inclusion, the US is against it. US concerns over the transfer of technology that could be used for military purposes echo similar concerns over Russia's participation prior to its membership.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.universetoday.com/82368/can-china-enter-the-international-space-family/|title=Can China enter the international space family?|publisher=Universetoday.com|date=10 January 2011|accessdate=16 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Concerns over Russian involvement were overcome and NASA became solely dependent upon Russian crew capsules when its shuttles were grounded after the Columbia accident in 2003,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gao.gov/new.items/d04201t.pdf |title=GAO-04-201T NASA: Shuttle Fleet's Safe Return to Flight Is Key to Space Station Progress |format=PDF |accessdate=1 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; and again after its retirement in 2011.&lt;ref&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20120303003122/http://www.hq.nasa.gov/legislative/hearings/10-12-11_OPENING_STATEMENT.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://science.house.gov/sites/republicans.science.house.gov/files/documents/hearings/102611_Gerstenmaier.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; The Chinese government has voiced a belief that international exchanges and co-operation in the field of aerospace engineering should be intensified on the basis of mutual benefit, peaceful use and common development.&lt;ref name="english.mofcom.gov.cn" /&gt; China's manned [[Shenzhou (spacecraft)|Shenzhou]] spacecraft use an [[APAS]] docking system, developed after a 1994–1995 deal for the transfer of Russian Soyuz spacecraft technology. Included in the agreement was training, provision of Soyuz capsules, life support systems, docking systems, and space suits. American observers comment that Shenzhou spacecraft could dock at the ISS if it became politically feasible, whilst Chinese engineers say work would still be required on the rendezvous system. [[Shenzhou 7]] passed within about 50 kilometres of the ISS.&lt;ref name="fpc.state.gov" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Sullivan|first=Patricia|title=Vladimir Syromyatnikov; Designed Docking System for Space Capsules|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/09/30/AR2006093001038.html|newspaper=The Washington Post|date=1 October 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://english.cri.cn/6909/2011/11/14/2941s667032.htm |title=China Ready to Conduct 2nd Space Docking |publisher=English.cri.cn |accessdate=1 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

American co-operation with China in space is limited, though efforts have been made by both sides to improve relations,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://english.mofcom.gov.cn/aarticle/newsrelease/commonnews/200609/20060903267934.html |title=Ministry of Commerce People'S Republic of China |publisher=English.mofcom.gov.cn |date=26 September 2006 |accessdate=1 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; but in 2011 new American legislation further strengthened legal barriers to co-operation, preventing NASA co-operation with China or Chinese owned companies, even the expenditure of funds used to host Chinese visitors at NASA facilities, unless specifically authorised by new laws,&lt;ref name="justice1"&gt;{{citation|first=Virginia|last=Seitz|title=Memorandum Opinion for the General Counsel, Office of Science and Technology Policy|url=http://www.justice.gov/olc/2011/conduct-diplomacy.pdf|journal=Office of Legal Counsel|volume=35|date=11 September 2011|accessdate=23 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!--page3--&gt;
&lt;!--These sentences are spread across the refs in this section, I need some help organising them--&gt;at the same time China, Europe and Russia have a co-operative relationship in several space exploration projects.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.xinhuanet.com/english2010/china/2010-06/01/c_13326632.htm |title=China may become space station partner |agency=Xinhua News Agency |date=1 June 2010 |accessdate=1 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Between 2007 and 2011, the space agencies of Europe, Russia and China carried out the ground-based preparations in the [[Mars500]] project, which complement the ISS-based preparations for a manned mission to Mars.&lt;ref name="Mars500 partners"&gt;{{cite web|title=Mars500 partners | publisher = ESA |date=4 June 2011 | url = http://mars500.imbp.ru/en/partners.html }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Brazil==
Brazil joined the ISS as a partner of the United States and this included a contract with NASA to supply hardware to the Space Station.&lt;ref name="Brazil"/&gt; In return, NASA would provide Brazil with access to NASA ISS facilities on-orbit, as well as a flight opportunity for one Brazilian astronaut during the course of the ISS programme. However, due to cost issues, the subcontractor [[Embraer]] was unable to provide the promised ExPrESS pallet, and Brazil left the programme in 2007.&lt;ref name="Emerson Kimura 2009"/&gt; Regardless, the first Brazilian astronaut, [[Marcos Pontes]], was sent to ISS in April 2006 for [[Expedition 13]].&lt;ref name="space.com"&gt;[http://www.space.com/2222-brazils-astronaut-fresh-iss-crew-reach-orbit.html]&lt;/ref&gt; This was Brazil's first space traveler and he returned to Earth safely.&lt;ref name="space.com"/&gt; Pontes trained on the Space Shuttle and Soyuz, but ended up going up with the Russians, although he did work at the U.S. Johnson Space Center after returning to Earth.

==See also==
*[[Space advocacy]]
*[[Space law]]
*[[Space policy]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

{{Use British English|date=January 2014}}

[[Category:International Space Station]]
[[Category:Politics]]</text>
      <sha1>hn36i9e8j5pn9okzduv4j6477wwrfpi</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Public interest</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>340401</id>
    <revision>
      <id>858331124</id>
      <parentid>848094799</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-09-06T12:33:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>BD2412</username>
        <id>196446</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Government */ dab fix</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="6555">{{About||the journal|The Public Interest}}
{{Politics|expanded=Policy}}

'''Public interest''' is "the [[welfare]] or [[well-being]] of the [[general public]]".&lt;ref&gt;[http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/public+interest "Public interest"], ''[[Random House Dictionary]]''.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Overview==
Economist Lok Sang Ho in his ''Public Policy and the Public Interest''&lt;ref&gt;Routledge, 2012 (first published published in 2011).&lt;/ref&gt; argues that the public interest must be assessed impartially and, therefore, defines the public interest as the "''[[ex ante]]'' welfare of the representative individual." &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.routledge.com/books/details/9780415664660/ Ho, Lok Sang, Public Policy and the Public Interest, Routledge, 2011]&lt;/ref&gt; Under a [[thought experiment]], by assuming that there is an equal chance for one to be anyone in society and, thus, could benefit or suffer from a change, the public interest is by definition enhanced whenever that change is preferred to the status quo ''ex ante''. This approach is "''ex ante''", in the sense that the change is not evaluated after the fact but assessed before the fact without knowing whether one would actually benefit or suffer from it.

This approach follows the "[[veil of ignorance]]" approach, which was first proposed by [[John Harsanyi]] but popularized by [[John Rawls]] in his 1971 ''Theory of Justice''.&lt;ref&gt;Rawls, John (1971) ''A Theory of Justice'', Cambridge: Harvard University Press.&lt;/ref&gt; Historically, however, the approach can be traced to [[John Stuart Mill]], who, in his letter to [[George Grote]], explained that "human happiness, even one's own, is in general more successfully pursued by acting on general rules, than by measuring the consequences of each act; and this is still more the case with the general happiness, since any other plan would not only leave everybody uncertain what to expect, but would involve perpetual quarrelling..."&lt;ref&gt;Francis E. Mineka and Dwight N. Lindley (ed.), ''The Collected Works of John Stuart Mill, Volume XIV - The Later Letters of John Stuart Mill 1849-1873 Part I, Toronto: University of Toronto Press, London: Routledge and Kegan Paul, 1972, Vol. XV, p.&amp;nbsp;762, 1862.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Institute of Chartered Accountants in England and Wales]] argues that applying a detailed definition is likely to result in [[unintended consequences]], in [http://www.icaew.com/publicinterest Acting in the Public Interest](2012). Instead, each circumstance needs to be assessed based on criteria such as the relevant public, wants, and constraints. The key to assessing any public interest decision is transparency of the decision-making process, including balancing competing interests.

==Law==
{{main|Public interest law}}
[[File:Brandeis office 1916.jpg|thumb|Brandeis (center) in his office 1916.]]
“Public interest law” is a term that became widely adopted in the United States during and after the social turmoil of the 1960s. It built upon a tradition exemplified by [[Louis Brandeis]], who before becoming a U.S. Supreme Court justice incorporated advocacy for the interests of the general public into his legal practice. 
In a celebrated 1905 speech, Brandeis decried the legal profession, complaining that “able lawyers have to a large extent allowed themselves to become adjuncts of great corporations and have neglected their obligation to use their powers for the protection of the people.” &lt;ref&gt;Edwin Rekosh, et al.,ed. "Pursuing the Public Interest, A Handbook for Legal Professionals and Activists" (http://www.pilnet.org/component/docman/doc_download/35-pursuing-the-public-interest-a-handbook-for-legal.html); Scott L. Cummings, The Politics of Pro Bono, 52 UCLA L. Rev. 1, 13-14(2004)&lt;/ref&gt; In the late 1960s and 1970s, large numbers of American law school graduates began to seek “relevance” in their work — wishing to have an effect on the social issues that were so visibly and hotly debated within American society at that time. They defined themselves as public interest lawyers in order to distinguish themselves from the “corporate adjuncts” referred to by Brandeis.&lt;ref&gt;Rekosh, supra; See also Joel F. Handler, Ellen Jane Hollingsworth &amp; Howard S. Erlanger, Lawyers and the Pursuit of Legal Rights 24-39 (1978); Note, The New Public Interest lawyers, 79 Yale L.J. 1069, 1069-70 (1970)&lt;/ref&gt;

Public interest law does not describe a body of law or a legal field; the term was adopted to describe whom the public interest lawyers were representing, rather than what matters they would work on. Instead of representing powerful economic interests, they chose to be advocates for otherwise underrepresented individuals. Consequently, a significant current in public interest lawyering has always emphasized the need to provide legal services to those living in poverty. The term has grown, however, to encompass a broader range of activities of lawyers and non-lawyers working toward a multitude of objectives, including civil rights, civil liberties, women’s rights, consumer rights, environmental protection, and so on. Nevertheless, a common denominator for public interest lawyers in the United States and in a growing number of countries remains the ethic of “fighting for the little guy”—that is, representing the underrepresented and vulnerable segments of society.&lt;ref name=Cummings&gt;Scott L. Cummings &amp; Ingrid V. Eagly, After Public Interest Law, NWU L. Rev. 1251, 1251-1259, 2075-2077(2006)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Government==

{{globalize|date=February 2017}}

Public interest has been considered as the core of "[[democratic theories of government]]” and often paired with two other concepts, "[[convenience]]" and "[[Need|necessity]]".&lt;ref&gt;Napoli, Philip M. (2001). Foundations of Communications Policy. Principles and Process in the Regulation of Electronic Media. Cresskill, NJ: Hampton Press&lt;/ref&gt; Public interest, convenience and necessity appeared for the first time in the Transportation Act of 1920 and also appeared in the [[Radio Act of 1927]]. After that, these three concepts became critical criteria for making communication policies and solving some related disputes.

==See also==

*[[Cause lawyering]]
*[[Common good]]
*[[Condorcet paradox]]
*[[National interest]]
*[[Pareto optimality]]
*[[Radio Act of 1927]]
*[[Telecommunications Act of 1996]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Authority control}}
{{Portal bar|Human rights|Law|Politics}}

[[Category:Human rights]]
[[Category:Law]]
[[Category:Politics]]
[[Category:Public sphere|Interest]]
[[Category:Thought experiments in ethics]]</text>
      <sha1>98ckp6aosv84owsikhi418ru2vq2yxf</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Stereopticon</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>363786</id>
    <revision>
      <id>856259724</id>
      <parentid>831413369</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-08-24T00:02:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>76.6.140.48</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="2309">[[File:Phoenix Stereopticon.png|alt=|thumb|right|Illustration of a stereopticon]]
A '''stereopticon''' is a [[slide projector]] or "[[magic lantern]]", which has two lenses, usually one above the other.
These devices date back to the mid 19th century,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
  | last =  Robinson
  | first = David
  | title = From Peep Show to Palace: The Birth of American Film
  | publisher = [[Columbia University Press]]
  | date = 1996
  | isbn = 0-231-10339-5
}}&lt;/ref&gt; and were a popular form of entertainment and education before the advent of [[motion picture|moving pictures]]. Americans William and [[Frederick Langenheim]] introduced stereopticon slide technology—slide shows of projected images on glass—in 1850.  For a usual fee of ten cents, people could view realistic images of nature, history, and science themes.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.magiclanternsociety.org/about-magic-lanterns/lantern-slides/|title=Lantern Slides {{!}} Magic Lantern Society|website=www.magiclanternsociety.org|language=en-US|access-date=2018-03-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; The two lenses are used to dissolve between images when projected. At first, the shows used random images, but over time, lanternists began to place the slides in logical order, creating a narrative.  This "visual storytelling" with technology directly preceded the development of the first moving pictures.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
  | last =  Clee
  | first = Paul
  | title = Before Hollywood: From Shadow Play to the Silver Screen
  | publisher = [[Clarion Books]]
  | date = 2005
  | isbn = 0-618-44533-1
}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The term stereopticon has been widely misused to name a [[stereoscope]]. A stereopticon will not project or display stereoscopic/[[Three-dimensional space|three-dimensional]] images on cards. All stereopticons can be classified as [[Magic lantern|magic lanterns]], but not all magic lanterns are stereopticons.

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Further reading==
*{{cite book
  | last = Lev
  | first = Peter
  |author2=Charles Musser| title = Transforming the Screen, 1950–1959
  | publisher = [[University of California Press]]
  | date = 2003
  | isbn = 0-520-08533-7
|display-authors=etal}}

[[Category:1850 introductions]]
[[Category:Entertainment]]
[[Category:Display technology]]
[[Category:History of film]]
[[Category:American inventions]]</text>
      <sha1>41h1ghbkjkobdowkyqz47c6bo12mr8x</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Susan Hockey</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>47135208</id>
    <revision>
      <id>867443519</id>
      <parentid>867442547</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-11-05T19:24:57Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mhockey</username>
        <id>6008650</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Career */ link</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="6033">{{Use dmy dates|date=April 2018}}
{{Use British English|date=April 2018}}
{{Infobox person
| name          = Susan Hockey
| image         = 
| caption       = 
| birth_date    = 1946
| birth_place   = [[Halifax, West Yorkshire]]
| death_date    = &lt;!-- {{Death date and age|df=yes|YYYY|MM|DD|YYYY|MM|DD}} (death date then birth date)  --&gt;
| death_place   = 
| nationality   = English
| occupation    = Emeritus Professor of Library and Information Studies
| years_active  = 
| known_for     = [[Association for Literary and Linguistic Computing|ALLC]], [[Association for Computers and the Humanities|ACH]], [[Text Encoding Initiative|TEI]]
| notable_works = 
}}

'''Susan Hockey''' is an Emeritus Professor of Library and Information Studies at [[University College London]]. She has written about the history of [[digital humanities]], the development of text analysis applications, electronic textual mark-up, teaching computing in the humanities, and the role of libraries in managing digital resources.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Boot|first1=Peter|title=Mesotext. Digitised emblems, modelled annotations and humanities scholarship.|date=2009|publisher=Amsterdam University Press|location=Amsterdam|isbn=9085550521|pages=223}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=About The Susan Hockey Lecture in Digital Humanities|url=http://www.ucl.ac.uk/dh/events/SusanHockeyLecture|publisher=University College of London}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2014, the University College of London created a Digital Humanities lecture series in her honour.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Launch of the annual Susan Hockey Lecture in Digital Humanities|url=http://www.greatparchmentbook.org/2015/05/01/launch-of-the-annual-susan-hockey-lecture-in-digital-humanities/|website=The Great Parchment Book|accessdate=3 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early life==
Hockey was born Susan Petty in 1946 in [[Halifax, West Yorkshire]], and educated at [[Princess Mary High School]], Halifax and [[Lady Margaret Hall, Oxford]].  
== Career ==
In 1969 she joined the [[Atlas Computer Laboratory]] at [[Chilton, Oxfordshire|Chilton]] in Oxfordshire. She became a founding member of the [[Association for Literary and Linguistic Computing]] (ALLC) in 1973 and in 1975 she joined [[Oxford University Computing Services]]. At Atlas she developed software for the display of non-Western characters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chilton-computing.org.uk/acl/associates/permanent/hockey.htm|title=Susan Hockey|website=Chilton Computing|accessdate=2 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;  At Oxford she was instrumental in developing the Oxford Concordance Program from [[COCOA (digital humanities)|COCOA]], an early piece of software used in humanities computing.  These tools have become central to the practice of the digital humanities in the United States and UK.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Vanhoutte|first1=edited by Melissa Terras, Julianne Nyhan, Edward|title=Defining digital humanities : a reader|date=2013|publisher=Ashgate|location=Farnham|isbn=1409469638|pages=131}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Siemens|first1=Ray|last2=Schreibman|first2=Susan|title=A Companion to Digital Literary Studies|date=2013|publisher=Wiley|location=New York|isbn=1118508831}}&lt;/ref&gt;

From 1991 to 1997 Hockey was director of the Center for Electronic Texts in the Humanities at [[Rutgers University|Rutgers]] and [[Princeton University|Princeton Universities]] in [[New Jersey]].  From 1997 to 1999 she was Professor and Director of the Canadian Institute for Research Computing in Arts at the [[University of Alberta]] in [[Edmonton]].  In 2000 she joined [[University College London]] as Professor of Library and Information Studies, and from 2001 was Director of the [[School of Library, Archive and Information Studies]] at UCL.  She retired in 2004.&lt;ref name=eadh&gt;{{cite web|url=http://eadh.org/susan-hockey-curriculum-vitae-publications|publisher=European Association for Digital Humanities|title=Susan Hockey - Curriculum Vitae &amp; Publications|accessdate=4 November 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2004, Hockey was awarded the [[Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations]]'s Roberto Busa Prize in recognition of "outstanding lifetime achievements in the application of information and communications technologies to humanities research".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://adho.org/awards/roberto-busa-prize|title=Roberto Busa Prize|website=Alliance of Digital Humanities Organisations (ADHO)|publisher=Alliance of Digital Humanities Organisations (ADHO)|accessdate=2 July 2015|ref=adhobusaprize}}&lt;/ref&gt;

She is a founding member of several major digital humanities-related associations such as the [[Association for Literary and Linguistic Computing]] (ALLC), 1973, and the [[Association for Computers and the Humanities]] (ACH), 1978, and an editor of the Association for [[Literary and Linguistic Computing]] (ALLC) Bulletin, 1979–83, chair of the Association for Literary and Linguistic Computing (ALLC), 1984–97 and member of the steering committee of the [[Text Encoding Initiative]] (TEI), 1987–99.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/SClist.html|title=Text Encoding Initiative|website=TEI 2008 Steering Committee|accessdate=3 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Publications ==
*''A Guide to Computer Applications in the Humanities'' (1980, [[Duckworth Overlook|Duckworth]] {{ISBN|978-0715613153}})
*''[[SNOBOL]] Programming for the Humanities'' (1986, [[Oxford University Press]] {{ISBN|978-0198246756}})
*''Electronic Texts in the Humanities: Principles and Practice'' (2000, [[Oxford University Press]] {{ISBN|978-0198711940}})

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Hockey, Susan}}
[[Category:1946 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Academics of University College London]]
[[Category:Digital humanities]]
[[Category:British computer scientists]]
[[Category:British women computer scientists]]
[[Category:Alumni of Lady Margaret Hall, Oxford]]
[[Category:People from Halifax, West Yorkshire]]
[[Category:Fellows of St Cross College, Oxford]]
[[Category:University of Alberta faculty]]
[[Category:Rutgers University faculty]]</text>
      <sha1>fbut4d28yyxed1jbursuty8gqsej2ke</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>The Common Topics</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8531069</id>
    <revision>
      <id>824518596</id>
      <parentid>711594586</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-02-07T20:51:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Emk9</username>
        <id>32634809</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>not an orphaned page</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="988">In classical [[rhetoric]], the '''Common Topics''' were a short list of four traditional topics regarded as suitable to structure an argument.

==Four Traditional Topics==
#Past Fact (Circumstance)
#Possible/Impossible (Possibility)
#Future Fact (Circumstance)
#Greater/Lesser (Comparison)

==Expanded List of Topics==

[[Edward P.J. Corbett]] and Robert J. Connors expanded the list in their 1971 book ''Classical Rhetoric for the Modern Student'' to include:

*Definition
**genus / division / species
**etymology
**description
**definition
**example
**synonyms
*Comparison
**similarity
**difference
**degree
*Circumstance
**cause and effect
**timing
*Relationship
**contraries
**exclusion
*Testimony
**statistics
**maxims
**law
**precedents
**personal example
**historical example
**authoritative quotes

==See also==
* [[Rhetoric (Aristotle)]]

==References==
* [http://www.u.arizona.edu/~tkinney/pdf/handouts/commontopics.pdf]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Common Topics, The}}
[[Category:Rhetoric]]</text>
      <sha1>hs0i4nhqzblt9zak7nccrhluhkxi9lk</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
