<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.33.0-wmf.4</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Agnesium</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>46588607</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749348597</id>
      <parentid>749307714</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-13T22:02:05Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Marcocapelle</username>
        <id>14965160</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>removed [[Category:Marketing performance measurement]] using [[WP:HC|HotCat]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="949">Agnesium is a [[neologism]] coined to describe a powerful, efficient and effective organization as an entity.&lt;ref&gt;Introducing Organizational Behaviour and Management
 By David Knights, Hugh Willmott&lt;/ref&gt; Agnesium is a combination of [https://translate.google.ch/?oe=UTF-8&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;hl=en&amp;client=tw-ob#la/en/Agnes Agnes] (Latin for powerful, efficient and effective) and the suffix -ium &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thefreedictionary.com/-ium -ium]&lt;/ref&gt; (indicating a biological structure).

The basic principle of Agnesium is that for complex structures/organizations there are many interdependencies between the members that are not known, understood or leveraged. By recognizing, understanding and leveraging these hidden interdependencies an organization can be proactive, adaptive and exploitive.

== References ==
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Brand management]]
[[Category:Business intelligence]]
[[Category:Complex dynamics]]
[[Category:Innovation economics]]</text>
      <sha1>55oko1kyes746bk66rr506b8irv4ovj</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Available-to-promise</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>13712439</id>
    <revision>
      <id>832812856</id>
      <parentid>806990992</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-03-28T03:52:54Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>BobKilcoyne</username>
        <id>7770027</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Wording</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="3032">'''Available-to-promise''' ('''ATP''') is a business function that provides a response to customer order enquiries, based on resource availability.&lt;ref&gt;Ball, M.O. et al. (2004), "Available to Promise" in ''Handbook of Quantitative Supply Chain Analysis - Modeling in the E-Business Era'', Kluwer&lt;/ref&gt; It generates available quantities of the requested product, and delivery due dates. Therefore, ATP supports order promising and fulfillment, aiming to manage demand and match it to production plans.

Available-to-promise functions are IT-enabled and usually integrated in enterprise management [[software]] packages. However, ATP execution may need to be adjusted for the way a certain company operates.

== Classification ==
A fundamental distinction between ATP functions is based on the [[push-pull strategy]]. Push-based ATP is based on forecasts regarding future demand - based on anticipation of demand, ATP quantities and availability dates are computed. A prominent example is the traditional determination of ATP based on the [[Master Production Schedule]]. The push-based approach is fundamentally limited by dependence on [[forecasts]], which may prove inaccurate. Gross ATP represents the total available supply, and net ATP represents the supply remaining to support new demands, after existing commitments to customers have been accounted for.

Pull-based models, on the other hand, dynamically allocate resources in response to actual customer orders. This means that pull-based ATP is able to balance forecast-driven resource replenishment with order-triggered resource utilization,&lt;ref&gt;Zhao, Z. (2005), "Optimization-based Available-to-promise with Multi Stage Resource Availability", Annals of Operations Research 135, 65-85&lt;/ref&gt; but because resources are allocated with each coming order, the process will yield myopic results.

== ATP Execution ==
ATP functions can be executed in real time, driven by each individual order, or in batch mode – meaning that at a certain time interval, the system checks availability for orders piled up in that period of time. The process is triggered by the need to check resource availability before making a commitment to deliver an order. For example, ATP calculation using SAP [[software]] depends on the level of "stock, planned receipts (production orders, purchase orders, planned orders and so on), and planned requirements (sales orders, deliveries, reservations, etc.)"

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
* [http://help.sap.com/saphelp_scm50/helpdata/en/b2/887941a51a1809e10000000a155106/frameset.htm SAP Library on Product Availability Check using ATP]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20080725192049/http://www.oracle.com/applications/planning/ds_global_order.pdf Oracle Data Sheet on Available-to-promise (PDF)]
* [http://pic.dhe.ibm.com/infocenter/ssfs/v9r2/index.jsp?topic=%2Fcom.ibm.help.prod.concepts.doc%2Fc_OrderPromisingAndScheduling.html IBM Order Management Order Promising and Scheduling for Sterling v9.2]

[[Category:Business terms]]</text>
      <sha1>98fqxueogpy7pisncjvo9pmi807i6c8</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Ayasdi</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>38722262</id>
    <revision>
      <id>864119476</id>
      <parentid>864119268</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-10-15T06:30:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Llywrch</username>
        <id>5094</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>links</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="9818">{{advert|date=January 2017}}
{{Infobox company
|name=Ayasdi 
|logo=Ayasdi_logo.png
|type=Private
|founded=2008 
|founders = 
|location=[[Menlo Park, California]]
|key_people= Bob Griffin &lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;(CEO)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Gurjeet Singh&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;(Executive Chairman &amp; Co-Founder)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[[Gunnar Carlsson]]&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;(Co-Founder)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Harlan Sexton&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;(VP of Research &amp; Co-Founder)&lt;/small&gt;
|industry= [[Enterprise software]] 
|products=
|revenue=
|operating_income= 
|net_income=
|num_employees= 150+ (2016)
|parent= 
|services = Big Data Analytics [[Machine Learning]]
|subsid=
|homepage=[http://www.ayasdi.com/ Ayasdi]

}}
'''Ayasdi''' is a [[machine intelligence]] software company that offers a software platform and applications to organizations looking to analyze and build predictive models using [[big data]] or highly dimensional data sets. Organizations and governments have deployed Ayasdi's software across a variety of use cases including the development of clinical pathways for hospitals,&lt;ref name="HITNEWS-2016-03-12"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.healthcareitnews.com/news/intermountain-deploy-clinical-variation-management-software-ayasdi |title=Intermountain to deploy clinical variation management software from Ayasdi |publisher=Health Care IT News |date=March 2, 2016 |access-date=March 2, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; anti-[[money laundering]], fraud detection, trading strategies, customer segmentation, oil and gas well development, drug development, disease research, information security, anomaly detection, and national security applications.&lt;ref name="NYT-2013-01-16"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://bits.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/01/16/ayasdi-a-big-data-start-up-with-a-long-history/ |title=Ayasdi: A Big Data Start-Up With a Long History |publisher=The New York Times |date=January 16, 2013 |access-date=March 5, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="VB-2013-01-16"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://venturebeat.com/2013/01/16/ayasdi/#1FPlL7mgRXdxYWOX.99 |title=A cure for cancer? This 'big data' startup says it can deliver |publisher=Venturebeat |date=January 16, 2013 |access-date=March 5, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Ayasdi focuses on hypothesis-free, automated analytics at scale.&lt;ref name="datanami-2016-02-01"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.datanami.com/2016/02/01/knowing-whats-possible-a-big-obstacle-for-big-data/ |title=Knowing What’s Possible a Big Obstacle for Big Data |publisher=Datanami |date=February 1, 2016 |access-date=February 1, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; In effect, the Ayasdi system consumes the target data set, runs many different unsupervised and supervised [[machine learning]] algorithms on the data, automatically finds and ranks best fits, and then applies [[topological data analysis]] to find similar groups within the resultant data.  It presents the end analysis in the form of a network similarity map, which is useful for an analyst to use to further explore the groupings and correlations that the system has uncovered.  This reduces the risk of bias since the system surfaces "what the data says" in an unbiased fashion, rather than relying on analysts or data scientists manually running algorithms in support of pre-existing hypotheses.&lt;ref name=datanami-2016-01-04&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.datanami.com/2016/01/04/how-a-nuisance-variable-turned-into-potential-lifesaver/ |title=How a ‘Nuisance Variable’ Turned Into Potential Lifesaver |publisher=Datanami |date=January 4, 2016 |access-date=January 4, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ayasdi then generates mathematical models which are deployed in predictive and operational systems and applications.

Organizations using Ayasdi have found Ayasdi's automated, platform-based approach to machine intelligence to be two to five orders of magnitude more efficient than existing approaches to big data analytics, as measured in the amount of time and expense required to complete analysis and build models using large and complex data sets.  One widely reported example at a top five global systemically important bank was that to build models required for the annual [[Comprehensive Capital Analysis and Review]] (CCAR) process took 1,800 person-months with traditional manual big data analytics and machine learning tools, but took 6 person-months with Ayasdi.  A project at a second global systemically important bank showed Ayasdi reducing the time to build risk models from 3,000 person-hours to 10 minutes.{{Citation needed|date=July 2017}}

==History and funding==
Ayasdi was founded in 2008 by [[Gunnar Carlsson]], Gurjeet Singh, and Harlan Sexton after 12 years of research and development at [[Stanford University]].&lt;ref name="NYT-2013-01-16"/&gt;&lt;ref name="VB-2013-01-16"/&gt; While at Stanford, the founders received [[United States dollar|$]]1.25 million in [[DARPA]] and [[IARPA]] grants for "high-risk, high-payoff research".&lt;ref name="NYT-2013-01-16"/&gt; In 2012 Ayasdi landed a Series A round of funding led by [[Floodgate Capital]] and [[Khosla Ventures]] for $10.25 million.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://finance.fortune.cnn.com/2013/01/16/venture-capital-deals-272/ |title=Venture capital deals |publisher=CNNMoney |date=January 16, 2013 |access-date=March 5, 2013 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130312171418/http://finance.fortune.cnn.com/2013/01/16/venture-capital-deals-272/ |archivedate=2013-03-12 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt; On July 16, 2013, Ayasdi closed $30.6 million in Series B funding from [[Institutional Venture Partners]], [[GE Ventures]], and [[Citi Ventures]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ayasdi.com/connect/pr-ayasdi-raises-30-million-in-series-b-funding-from-institutional-venture-partners-ge-ventures-and-citi-ventures.html|title=News and Events - Ayasdi|author=|date=|website=Ayasdi.com|access-date=July 3, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; On March 25, 2015, Ayasdi announced a new $55 million round of Series C funding, led by [[Kleiner Perkins Caufield &amp; Byers]], and joined by four current investors, Institutional Venture Partners, Khosla Ventures, Floodgate Capital, Citi Ventures, and two new investors, [[Centerview Capital|Centerview Capital Technology]] and [[Draper Nexus]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ayasdi.com/company/media/seriesc/|title=News and Events - Ayasdi|author=|date=|website=Ayasdi.com|access-date=July 3, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Product==
Ayasdi is a machine intelligence platform.  It includes dozens of statistical and both supervised and unsupervised machine learning algorithms and can be extended to include whatever algorithms are required for a particular class of analysis.  The platform is extensively automated and is in production at scale at many global 100 companies and at governments in the world. It features [[Topological Data Analysis]] as a unifying analytical framework, which automatically calculates groupings and similarity across large and highly dimensional data sets, generating network maps with greatly assist analysts in understanding how data clusters and which variables are relevant.  When compared with manual approaches to statistical analysis and machine learning, results with Ayasdi will typically be achieved much faster to achieve and more accurate due to the automation and scalability built into the platform.  The Ayasdi platform also develops mathematical models, including predictive models, based on the results of the analysis. This allows Ayasdi to deployed as an operational system, or as a part of operational systems, and not just for analysis.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Erin Bury|url=http://betakit.com/2013/01/16/ayasdi-comes-out-of-stealth-with-10-25m-to-answer-unknown-data-questions/ |title=BetaKit &amp;raquo; Ayasdi Comes Out of Stealth With $10.25M to Answer Unknown Data Questions | publisher=Betakit | date=January 16, 2013 |access-date=July 3, 2017 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130308102846/http://betakit.com/2013/01/16/ayasdi-comes-out-of-stealth-with-10-25m-to-answer-unknown-data-questions |archivedate=2013-03-08 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Ayasdi can be deployed on-premises using [[Intel]]-based servers, or on either public or private cloud infrastructure. The platform runs on [[Linux]] and [[Hadoop]].

== Applications ==
{{unreferenced|section|date=March 2018}}
Ayasdi also develops machine intelligence applications.  One example is Ayasdi Care, which is a suite of cloud-based applications for healthcare providers that is focused on managing and improving patient outcomes, revenue and population health. For example, Ayasdi clinical variation, one of the applications in Ayasdi Care, automatically discovers the ideal care paths for medical procedures based on analyzing historical patient data, billing records and insurance claims.

== Users and industries ==
Ayasdi customers include many large enterprises, medical research institutions and governments across industries including health care, financial services, oil and gas, security, life sciences, and the public sector.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://techcrunch.com/2013/01/16/darpa-backed-ayasdi-launches-with-10m-from-khosla-floodgate-to-uncover-the-hidden-value-in-big-data/ |title=DARPA-Backed Ayasdi Launches With $10M From Khosla, Floodgate To Uncover The Hidden Value In Big Data |publisher=Techcrunch |date=January 16, 2013 |access-date=March 5, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nature.com/srep/2013/130207/srep01236/full/srep01236.html |title=Extracting insights from the shape of complex data using topology |publisher=Nature |date=September 13, 2012 |access-date=April 1, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
* [http://ecorner.stanford.edu/author/gurjeet_singh Ayasdi founders and investor lecture and discussion with entrepreneurship students], [[Stanford Entrepreneurship Corner]], 2014.02.05

[[Category:Business software]]
[[Category:Business software companies]]
[[Category:Big data companies]]
[[Category:Companies based in Palo Alto, California]]</text>
      <sha1>6q7l0j1qtzbazmu7tu10g4xr33izcc2</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Brand development index</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9516940</id>
    <revision>
      <id>833287440</id>
      <parentid>804981015</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-03-30T17:38:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Widefox</username>
        <id>1588193</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Widefox moved page [[Brand development index (marketing)]] to [[Brand development index]]: not an ambig title - parenthetic is not needed</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="3629">The '''brand development index''' or '''BDI''' quantifies how well a brand performs in a market, compared with its average performance among all markets.&lt;ref name=Marketing_Metrics&gt;Farris, Paul W.; Neil T. Bendle; Phillip E. Pfeifer; David J. Reibstein (2010). ''Marketing Metrics: The Definitive Guide to Measuring Marketing Performance.'' Upper Saddle River, New Jersey: Pearson Education, Inc. {{ISBN|0-13-705829-2}}. The [[Marketing Accountability Standards Board (MASB)]] endorses the definitions, purposes, and constructs of classes of measures that appear in ''Marketing Metrics'' as part of its ongoing [http://www.commonlanguage.wikispaces.net/ Common Language in Marketing Project].&lt;/ref&gt; That is, it measures the relative sales strength of a brand within a specific market (e.g., the Pepsi brand among 10–50-year-olds).&lt;ref name=AMA&gt;[[American Marketing Association]] Dictionary. {{cite web |url=http://www.marketingpower.com/_layouts/Dictionary.aspx |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2012-11-29 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20121121033809/http://www.marketingpower.com/_layouts/dictionary.aspx |archivedate=2012-11-21 |df= }}. Retrieved 2012-11-29. The [[Marketing Accountability Standards Board (MASB)]] endorses this definition as part of its ongoing [http://www.themasb.org/common-language-project/ Common Language: Marketing Activities and Metrics Project] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130212100753/http://www.themasb.org/common-language-project/ |date=2013-02-12 }}.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Purpose==

The purpose of the BDI metric is to quantify the relative performance of a brand within specified customer groups. The index helps marketers identify strong and weak segments (usually demographic or geographic) for individual brands.&lt;ref name=Marketing_Metrics /&gt;

The BDI is especially useful in conjunction with the [[category development index (marketing)|category development index]] (CDI). It can be used in deciding the allocations in the media to which a specific brand is advertised. It can also be used to determine how much advertising, or promotion effort is, or should be put in that specific market.

==Construction==
'''BDI''': An index of how well a brand performs within a given market group, relative to its performance in the market as a whole.&lt;ref name=Marketing_Metrics /&gt;

::BDI (I) = 	
::[Brand sales to group (#) ÷ Households in group (#)] ÷ 
::[Total brand sales (#) ÷ Total households (#)]
::
::''Note: Although defined here with respect to households, these indexes could also be calculated for customers, accounts, businesses, or other entities.'' &lt;ref name=Marketing_Metrics /&gt;

For example, one might hypothesize that sales per capita of [[Ben &amp; Jerry's]] brand ice cream would be greater in the brand's home state, Vermont, than in the rest of the country. By calculating Ben &amp; Jerry's BDIs for Vermont and for the rest of the country, marketers could test this hypothesis quantitatively.

Govoni also defined the BDI as the index of brand sales to category sales,&lt;ref&gt;Govoni, Norman A. ''[http://promoprof.babson.edu/Glossary/b/GlossaryB.htm  Dictionary of Marketing Communications]'', Sage Publications, Inc, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; though this ratio is more commonly referred to as market share.

== See also ==
* [[Philip Kotler]] et al. ''Marketing Management,'' 13th Edition, Prentice Hall, 2009

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.kovick.org/ Kovick | Brand Development Tailors]
* [http://www.themasb.org/ MASB official website]

[[Category:Business indices]]
[[Category:Brand management]]
[[Category:Marketing terminology]]</text>
      <sha1>hn3bqbe5kw67u41j7jubse2n5z1ootu</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Business Intelligence Markup Language</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>37179317</id>
    <revision>
      <id>810455348</id>
      <parentid>752391654</parentid>
      <timestamp>2017-11-15T10:21:19Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>217.20.33.68</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="12263">{{Infobox programming language
| name                   = Biml
| logo                   = [[File:Business Intelligence Markup Language (Biml) Logo.png|220px]]
| year                   = 2008&lt;ref name="Leonard2012" /&gt;
| designer               = Scott Currie&lt;ref name="Leonard2012" /&gt;
| developer              = [[Varigence]]&lt;ref name="Leonard2012" /&gt;
| latest release version = 3.0
| latest release date    = {{Start date|2012|11|01}}
| implementations        = Mist IDE, [[BIDS Helper]]&lt;ref name="Tok2012" /&gt;
| operating system       = [[Microsoft Windows]]
| file ext               = .biml
| website                = {{URL|http://www.bimlscript.com/}}
}}
'''Business Intelligence Markup Language''' (Biml) is a domain-specific [[XML]] dialect for defining [[business intelligence]] (BI) assets.  Biml authored BI assets can currently be used by the [[BIDS Helper]] add-on for [[Microsoft SQL Server]] [[Business Intelligence Development Studio]] (BIDS) and the [[Varigence]] Mist (now called BimlStudio) [[integrated development environment]]; both tools translate Biml metadata into [[SQL Server Integration Services]] (SSIS) and [[Microsoft Analysis Services|SQL Server Analysis Services]] (SSAS) assets for the [[Microsoft SQL Server]] platform. However, emitters can be created to compile Biml for any desired BI platform.

While Biml’s declarative design is sufficient to author BI assets, BimlScript extends the language by enabling authors to embed [[C Sharp (programming language)|C#]] or [[VB.NET]] code within Biml, similar to how [[ASP.NET]] includes .NET code within static [[HTML]] markup.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Chenn|first=Ronen|title=BIDS helper new features ( April 2011 )|url=http://blogs.microsoft.co.il/blogs/bilive/archive/2011/05/16/bids-helper-new-features-april-2011.aspx|accessdate=October 1, 2012|newspaper=Business Intelligence,Technology, Thoughts, Thinking|date=May 16, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  BimlScript is used to merge changes into existing Biml assets, automatically generate Biml code, and apply changes across multiple Biml files during compilation.

==History==

===Biml===

Biml is an XML dialect that specifies all aspects of a BI solution, including relational models, data transformation packages, multi-dimensional models, and tabular models.

Unlike other BI solutions, Biml has a "write once, target any platform" philosophy. This enables Biml users to switch their target platform without needing to change their code. Currently, Biml targets SQL Server versions 2005, 2008, 2008 R2, 2012 and 2014, emitting SSIS packages and SSAS cubes.

Because Biml is XML, it can leverage the vast ecosystem of tools for XML based languages. This also makes it human readable/writeable, so it is easier to edit by hand than the SSIS/SSAS files it generates.

In late 2009, Biml was extended with BimlScript. BimlScript allows C# or VB.NET code nuggets to be embedded directly within Biml. BimlScript's goal is to automate repetitive work in reusable scripts. Additionally, it's been used to automate package generation and build reusable patterns for BI tasks. BimlScript is also used to take metadata from various sources (relational database structure, relational data, flat files, annotations, etc...) and automatically generate Biml code from it.

===Mist===
[[Mist (IDE)|Mist]] is an IDE for authoring Biml code and building BI assets. Mist leverages visual design capabilities and [[debugging]] features to simultaneously edit entire business intelligence models, including relational tables, SSIS packages, and [[OLAP cube|cubes]].&lt;ref name="Leonard2012"&gt;{{cite book|last=Leonard|first=Andy|title=SQL Server 2012 Integration Services Design Patterns|year=2012|publisher=APress|isbn=978-1430237716|pages=456|author2=Masson, Matt |author3=Mitchell, Tim |author4=Moss, Jessica |author5= Ufford, Michelle |chapter=Chapter 17: Business Intelligence Markup Language}}&lt;/ref&gt;   Mist also incorporates modern programming IDE features, including text editors with syntax highlighting, Intelliprompt and quick-info displays, source control integration, and multi-monitor support.

===BIDS Helper===
As Biml’s popularity has grown, key portions of the Biml engine, including dynamic package generation, have been contributed to the [http://bidshelper.codeplex.com BIDS Helper] open source project hosted on CodePlex.&lt;ref name="Tok2012"&gt;{{cite book|last=Tok|first=Wee-Hyong|title=Microsoft SQL Server 2012 Integration Services|year=2012|publisher=O'Reilly Media, Inc.|isbn= 978-0735665859|author2=Parida, Rakesh |author3=Masson, Matt |author4=Ding, Xiaoning |author5= Sivashanmugam, Kaarthik  |page=511}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Welch|first=John|title=Biml Package Generator|url=http://bidshelper.codeplex.com/wikipage?title=Biml%20Package%20Generator|work=BIDS Helper|accessdate=September 30, 2011|date=June 7, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===BimlScript community===
[http://www.bimlscript.com BimlScript.com] is a community website for developing and sharing Biml solutions to BI problems, and contributing Biml content to share with others. Along with tutorials, walkthroughs, and videos, the site provides an online Biml editor.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Welcome to BimlScript.com|url=http://bimlscript.com/Blog|work=BimlScript.com|accessdate=October 4, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Code generation==
Biml files are compiled to produce BI assets for a chosen platform. Currently, it’s possible to generate assets for Microsoft’s SSIS, SSAS, and SQL Server platforms, for the 2005, 2008 (R2), 2012 and 2014 releases. Other platforms may be targeted in the future.

==Syntax==
{{See also|XML#Key_terminology|l1=XML Terminology}}
Biml has a syntax that’s common to all XML languages. Tags begin and end with &lt; and &gt;, respectively. Furthermore, tags can have attributes and nested elements.

===Biml===

====Declaration====
Biml documents begin with a common declaration
&lt;source lang = "xml" &gt;
&lt;Biml xmlns="http://schemas.varigence.com/biml.xsd"&gt;
&lt;/source&gt;

====Root types====
Biml has a well-defined set of root types, indicating the various kinds of BI assets that can be created

* Connections
* Databases
* Schemas
* Tables
* Dimensions
* Facts
* Packages
* File Formats
* Script Projects
* Cubes
* Principals

====Example====
This is an example of the AdventureWorks DimCurrency table, authored in Biml

&lt;source lang = "xml" &gt;
&lt;Biml xmlns="http://schemas.varigence.com/biml.xsd"&gt;
  &lt;Dimensions&gt;
    &lt;Dimension Name="DimCurrency" SchemaName="Target.dbo" AttributeAllMemberName="All Source Currencies" DimensionType="Currency" FriendlyName="Currency"&gt;
      &lt;Columns&gt;
        &lt;Column Name="CurrencyKey" /&gt;
        &lt;Column Name="CurrencyAlternateKey" DataType="StringFixedLength" Length="3" /&gt;
        &lt;Column Name="CurrencyName" DataType="String" Length="50" /&gt;
      &lt;/Columns&gt;
      &lt;Keys&gt;
        &lt;Identity Name="IK_DimCurrency"&gt;
          &lt;Columns&gt;
            &lt;Column ColumnName="CurrencyKey" /&gt;
          &lt;/Columns&gt;
        &lt;/Identity&gt;
        &lt;UniqueKey Name="AK_DimCurrency_CurrencyAlternateKey"&gt;
          &lt;Columns&gt;
            &lt;Column ColumnName="CurrencyAlternateKey" /&gt;
          &lt;/Columns&gt;
        &lt;/UniqueKey&gt;
      &lt;/Keys&gt;
      &lt;Indexes&gt;&lt;/Indexes&gt;
      &lt;Attributes&gt;
        &lt;Attribute Name="Source Currency" EstimatedCount="101" OrderBy="Name" AttributeType="CurrencySource" GroupingBehavior="DiscourageGrouping"&gt;
          &lt;InstanceSelection&gt;DropDown&lt;/InstanceSelection&gt;
          &lt;KeyColumns&gt;
            &lt;KeyColumn ColumnName="CurrencyName" NullProcessing="Error" /&gt;
          &lt;/KeyColumns&gt;
        &lt;/Attribute&gt;
        &lt;Attribute Name="Source Currency Code" EstimatedCount="105" OrderBy="Name" AttributeType="CurrencyIsoCode" Usage="Key" GroupingBehavior="DiscourageGrouping"&gt;
          &lt;InstanceSelection&gt;DropDown&lt;/InstanceSelection&gt;
          &lt;KeyColumns&gt;
            &lt;KeyColumn ColumnName="CurrencyKey" NullProcessing="Error" /&gt;
          &lt;/KeyColumns&gt;
          &lt;NameColumn ColumnName="CurrencyAlternateKey" /&gt;
        &lt;/Attribute&gt;
      &lt;/Attributes&gt;
      &lt;Relationships&gt;
        &lt;Relationship Name="Source Currency" ParentAttributeName="Source Currency Code" ChildAttributeName="Source Currency" Type="Rigid" /&gt;
      &lt;/Relationships&gt;
    &lt;/Dimension&gt;
  &lt;/Dimensions&gt;
&lt;/Biml&gt;
&lt;/source&gt;

===BimlScript===
All BimlScript tags begin and end with &lt;# and #&gt; delimiters, respectively. Special types of BimlScript tags use augmented versions of these delimiters, to indicate specific usages.

====Directives====
A Biml file, with BimlScript, begins with at least one directive. Directives provide instructions to the Biml engine, regarding how to process the BimlScript and generate its Biml. Directives are single tags that begin with &lt;#@. Each directive begins with a single term, followed by attributes that supply required values.

The two most common directives are template and import.

=====Template=====
This directive indicates that the file's BimlScript uses the C# programming language.
&lt;source lang = "xml" &gt;
&lt;#@ template language="C#" #&gt;
&lt;/source&gt;

=====Import=====
This directive specifies .NET namespaces that should be imported for the file. It is functionally equivalent to the C# using statement or VB.NET Imports statement.
&lt;source lang = "xml" &gt;
&lt;#@ import namespace="Varigence.Languages.Biml.Connection" #&gt;
&lt;/source&gt;

====Delimiters====
When authoring BimlScript, additional delimiters may be used. These delimiters match the behavior of T4 template delimiters.

{| class="wikitable"
|-
! Delimiter !! Description
|-
| &lt;# || Defines statements, in .NET code, that provide control flow in a Biml file.
|-
| &lt;#= || Evaluates .NET code, converts it to a string, and then embeds it in the Biml file.
|-
| &lt;#+ || Defines properties, methods, and files that are excluded from the Biml file but may be accessed by other BimlScript code nuggets.
|}

====Example====
This BimlScript example imports a database's assets via a connection, declared in a separate file, named "AdventureWorksLT". Each schema and table from the imported database is then embedded directly within the Schemas and Tables collections, respectively.
&lt;source lang = "xml" &gt; 
&lt;#@ template language="C#" hostspecific="True" tier="2" #&gt;
&lt;#@ import namespace="Varigence.Languages.Biml.Connection" #&gt;
&lt;#@ import namespace="Varigence.Hadron.Extensions" #&gt;
&lt;#@ import namespace="Varigence.Hadron.Extensions.SchemaManagement" #&gt;
&lt;#@ import namespace="Varigence.Hadron.CoreLowerer.SchemaManagement" #&gt;

&lt;#+ public ImportResults Results
{ 
    get 
    { 
        return ((AstOleDbConnectionNode)RootNode.Connections["AdventureWorksLT"]).ImportDB();
    }
}
#&gt; 

&lt;Biml xmlns="http://schemas.varigence.com/biml.xsd"&gt;
    &lt;Databases&gt;
        &lt;Database Name="MyDatabase" ConnectionName="AdventureWorksLT" /&gt;
    &lt;/Databases&gt;
    &lt;Schemas&gt;
        &lt;#=Results.SchemaNodes.GetBiml()#&gt;
    &lt;/Schemas&gt;
    &lt;Tables&gt; 
        &lt;#=Results.TableNodes.GetBiml()#&gt;
    &lt;/Tables&gt;
&lt;/Biml&gt;
&lt;/source&gt;

This example shows how developers can use Biml and BimlScript to:
# Import schemas and tables directly from a database, and use them without needing to manually copy their structure.
# Have any changes to the assets be automatically reflected the next time this code is run.
# Import the assets and convert them to Biml using only two simple lines of code.

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.bimlscript.com bimlscript.com] - Biml online community
* [http://bidshelper.codeplex.com BIDS Helper] - Microsoft SQL Server extension with Biml capabilities
* [http://www.varigence.com/Documentation/Language/Element/AstRootNode Biml Language Reference] - by the Varigence Corporation
* [http://www.microsoft.com/sqlserver/en/us/default.aspx Microsoft SQL Server] - Further information on the Microsoft SQL Server platform.
* [http://www.varigence.com/samples/mist Mist Walkthrough] - Biml examples using the Mist IDE

&lt;!-- This will add a notice to the bottom of the page and won't blank it! The new template which says that your draft is waiting for a review will appear at the bottom; simply ignore the old (grey) drafted templates and the old (red) decline templates. A bot will update your article submission. Until then, please don't change anything in this text box and press "Save page". --&gt;

[[Category:XML markup languages]]
[[Category:Business intelligence]]</text>
      <sha1>1kwq3frebb3y1fcjevcirnu05qsr3a3</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Business economics</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8613151</id>
    <revision>
      <id>868848928</id>
      <parentid>868065020</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-11-14T21:05:05Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rescuing 1 sources and tagging 0 as dead. #IABot (v2.0beta10)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="8814">{{Economics sidebar}}
'''Business economics''' is a field in [[applied economics]] which uses [[economic theory]] and quantitative methods to analyze [[Business|business enterprises]] and the factors contributing to the diversity of organizational structures and the relationships of firms with labour, [[Capital (economics)|capital]] and product markets.&lt;ref name="Moschandreas"&gt;Moschandreas, Maria (2000). ''Business Economics'', 2nd Edition, Thompson Learning,  [https://books.google.com/books?id=ncVfjhTULyAC&amp;printsec=find&amp;pg=PA410#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Description] and chapter-preview [https://books.google.com/books?id=ncVfjhTULyAC&amp;printsec=find&amp;pg=PR5#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false links].&lt;/ref&gt; A professional focus of the journal ''[[Business Economics (journal)|Business Economics]]'' has been expressed as providing "practical information for people who apply economics in their jobs."&lt;ref&gt;National Association for Business Economics, ''[http://www.nabe.com/busecon.htm ''Business Economics] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20111111082746/http://www.nabe.com/busecon.htm |date=November 11, 2011 }}''®&lt;/ref&gt;
Business economics is an integral part of traditional economics. It is an extension of economic concepts to the real business situations. It is an applied science in the sense of a tool of managerial decision-making and forward planning by management. In other words, Business economics is concerned with the application of economic theory to business management.

==Subject matter==
Business economics is concerned with economic issues and problems related to business organization, management, and strategy. Issues and problems include: an explanation of why ''corporate'' firms emerge and exist; why they expand: horizontally, vertically and spacially; the role of entrepreneurs and entrepreneurship; the significance of organizational structure; the relationship of firms with the employees, the providers of capital, the customers, the government; the interactions between firms and the business environment.&lt;ref name="Moschandreas"/&gt;

==Ambiguity in the use of term==
The term 'business economics' is used in a variety of ways.  Sometimes it is used as synonymously with industrial economics/[[industrial organisation]], [[managerial economics]], and economics for business. Still, there may be substantial differences in the usage of 'economics for business' and 'managerial economics' with the latter used more narrowly.
One view of the distinctions between these would be that business economics is wider in its scope than industrial economics in that it would be concerned not only with "industry" but also businesses in the service sector. Economics for business looks at the major principles of economics but focuses on applying these economic principles to the real world of business.&lt;ref&gt;Sloman, J and Sutcliffe (2004) Economics for Business, Financial Times/ Prentice Hall; 3 edition&lt;/ref&gt; Managerial economics is the application of economic methods in the managerial decision-making process.&lt;ref&gt;• Jones, Trefor, 2004 ''Business Economics and Managerial Decision Making'', Wiley. [http://www.wiley.com/WileyCDA/WileyTitle/productCd-EHEP000988.html Description] and chapter-preview  [https://books.google.com/books?id=qr7TORfhBwQC&amp;printsec=find&amp;pg=PR7#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false links].&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; • Wilkinson, Nick (2005). ''Managerial Economics: A Problem-Solving Approach'', Cambridge University Press. [http://www.cambridge.org/gb/knowledge/isbn/item1170271/?site_locale=en_GB Description] and [https://books.google.com/books?id=O-Fv7B4J-6EC&amp;printsec=find&amp;pg=PR5#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false preview.]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Interpretations from various universities ==
Many universities offer courses in business economics and offer a range of interpretations as to the meaning of the word.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.uel.ac.uk/programmes/business/undergraduate/summary/businesseco.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

The Bachelor of Business Economics (BBE) Program at [[University of Delhi]] is designed to meet the growing need for an analytical and quantitative approach to problem solving in the changing corporate world by the application of the latest techniques evolved in the fields of economics and business.&lt;ref&gt;http://du.ac.in/du/index.php?page=business-economics-2&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Autonomous University of Barcelona]] (UAB), the [[Universidad Pública de Navarra]] (UPNa) and the [[University of the Balearic Islands]] (UIB) developed an official Master of Science in Management, Organization and Business Economics focused on management and business topics to train professionals in the study of organizations, on a conceptual and quantitative basis. To achieve this, advanced analysis tools are used from the fields of [[Neoclassical economics]], [[New institutional economics]], [[Statistics]], [[Econometrics]] and [[Operations research]]. This focus is complemented with contributing ideas and theories to develop the necessary instruments to facilitate the management of sophisticated and complex organizations.&lt;ref&gt;UAB,UPNa, UIB - Master of Science (M.Sc.) in Management, Organization and Business Economics - MMOBE Program. [http://pagines.uab.cat/mmobe/ Link]&lt;/ref&gt;

The program at [[Harvard University]] uses economic methods to analyze practical aspects of business, including [[business administration]], management, and related fields of business economics.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.gsas.harvard.edu/programs_of_study/business_economics_4.php&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[University of Miami]] defines business economics as involving the study of how we use our resources for the production, distribution, and consumption of goods and services.  This requires business economists to analyze social institutions, banks, the stock market, the government and their relationships with labor negotiations, taxes, international trade, and urban and environmental issues.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.miami.muohio.edu/academics/majorsminors/majors/businesseconomics.cfm |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2009-01-06 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090725091346/http://www.miami.muohio.edu/academics/majorsminors/majors/businesseconomics.cfm |archivedate=2009-07-25 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Courses at the [[University of Manchester]] interpret business economics to be concerned with the economic analysis of how businesses contribute to welfare of society rather than on the welfare of an individual or a business. This is done via an examination of the relationship between ownership, control and firm objectives; theories of the growth of the firm; the behavioural [[theory of the firm]]; theories of entrepreneurship; the factors that influence the [[Structure-conduct-performance paradigm|structure, conduct and performance]] of business at the industry level.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.socialsciences.manchester.ac.uk/undergraduate/courses/modules/modulelist.html?department%3D3%26newcode%3DECON2 |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2009-01-13 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20081224053759/http://www.socialsciences.manchester.ac.uk/undergraduate/courses/modules/modulelist.html?department=3&amp;newcode=ECON2 |archivedate=2008-12-24 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Italian Universities borrow their concept of business economics from the tradition of [[Gino Zappa]], for example a standard course&lt;ref&gt;https://www11.ceda.polimi.it/schedaincarico/schedaincarico/controller/scheda_pubblica/SchedaPublic.do?&amp;evn_default=evento&amp;c_classe=618079&amp;__pj0=0&amp;__pj1=6f3356db456e221b165cf3ee421a14ec&lt;/ref&gt;  at the [[Politecnico di Milano]] involves studying [[corporate governance]], [[accounting]], [[investment analysis]], [[budgeting]] and [[business strategy]].

[[La Trobe University]] of Melbourne, Australia associates business economics with the process of demand, supply and equilibrium coordinating the behaviour of individuals and businesses in the market. Also, business economics extends to government policy, economic variables and international factors which influence business and competition.

== See also ==
* [[Industrial organisation]]
* [[Business studies]]

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==Journals==
* ''Business Economics'': [https://web.archive.org/web/20111111082746/http://www.nabe.com/busecon.htm Description] and archived article-abstract [https://web.archive.org/web/20081222000712/http://www.nabe.com/pubs.htm links]

== External links ==
* [[National Association for Business Economics]] (NABE, United States): [http://www.nabe.com/ Homepage]
* [http://www.cabe.ca Canadian Association for Business Economics (CABE)]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20120423013601/http://www.abe.org.au/ Australian Business Economists]
* [http://www.businesseconomics.com/ Directory of Business Economics and Finance links with relevant news]

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Business]]
[[Category:Business economics| ]]</text>
      <sha1>d9s0q97ktixj13aheulj251u8281fa3</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Center for Business and Economic Research</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>25059538</id>
    <revision>
      <id>815500618</id>
      <parentid>793464136</parentid>
      <timestamp>2017-12-15T05:39:07Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mais oui!</username>
        <id>394460</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>added [[Category:Forecasting organizations]] using [[WP:HC|HotCat]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="23985">{{Infobox Organization
|name         = Center for Business and Economic Research
|image        = CBER-logo-twocolor.jpg
|image_border = 
|size         = 200px
|caption      = 
|map          = 
|msize        = 
|mcaption     = 
|abbreviation = CBER
|motto        = 
|formation    = 1965 (Bureau of Business Research)
|extinction   = 
|type         =
|status       = 
|purpose      = Policy Forecasting and Research
|headquarters = [[Muncie, Indiana|Muncie]], [[Indiana]]
|location     = 
|region_served = [[United States]], Indiana 
|membership   = 
|language     = 
|leader_title = Director
|leader_name  = [[Michael J. Hicks]]
|main_organ = 
|parent_organization = [[Ball State University]] 
|affiliations = 
|num_staff    = 22 (2009)
|num_volunteers =
|budget       = 
|website      = http://www.bsu.edu/cber
|remarks =
}}

The [[Ball State University]] '''''Center for Business and Economic Research (CBER)''''', formerly the Bureau of Business Research, is an economic policy and forecasting research center housed within the [[Miller College of Business]] at [[Ball State University]] in [[Muncie, Indiana]], USA. CBER research encompasses health care, public finance, regional economics, transportation, and energy sector studies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cms.bsu.edu/Academics/CentersandInstitutes/BBR.aspx |title=Center for Business and Economic Research, Ball State University - Ball State University |publisher=Cms.bsu.edu |date= |accessdate=2015-11-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to research, CBER serves as the forecasting element in the [[Muncie, Indiana|Muncie]] area – hosting five state and federal economic forecasting roundtables.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cms.bsu.edu/Academics/CentersandInstitutes/BBR/Forecasts/BSUForecastingRoundtable.aspx|title=Search Results: academics centersandinstitutes bbr forecasts bsuforecastingroundtable|work=bsu.edu}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
The Center for Business and Economic Research was founded the late 1960s as the Bureau of Business Research at Ball State University. The founding was initiated by Dr. Robert P. Bell soon after being hired as the first dean of the College of Business. Dr. Joseph Brown from the University of Georgia became the first director of the bureau.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://bsurentalhouses.com/about.htm |title=About Us |publisher=Bsurentalhouses.com |date= |accessdate=2015-11-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; The focus of the bureau was to look for research opportunities and provide faculty with help pursuing those opportunities. Also, focus was placed on using faculty in applied business research.&lt;ref&gt;E. Bruce Geelhoed (1990), ''The First 25 Years'', Ball State University Bureau of Business Research p.7&lt;/ref&gt;

The focus of the center has changed significantly since its inception. An official name change from the Bureau of Business Research to the Center for Business and Economic Research occurred in 2008. Currently, the center works in the community through services of economic policy research, national, state, and local forecasting, and data analysis.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cms.bsu.edu/Academics/CentersandInstitutes/BBR/AboutUs.aspx|title=Search Results: academics centersandinstitutes bbr aboutus|work=bsu.edu}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Recent studies==
CBER regularly releases studies and publications on various topics including health care, public finance, regional economics, transportation, and energy.

{| class="wikitable"
|-
!  Study Name
!  Publication Date
|-
| Labor Markets After the Great Recession: Unemployment and Policy for Indiana&lt;ref&gt;http://cms.bsu.edu/-/media/WWW/DepartmentalContent/MillerCollegeofBusiness/BBR/Publications/StructuralUnemp.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| March 2013
|-
| Which Hoosier Occupations May Suffer from a Skills Gap?&lt;ref&gt;http://cms.bsu.edu/-/media/WWW/DepartmentalContent/MillerCollegeofBusiness/BBR/Publications/OccSkillsGap.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| 2013
|-
| Indiana Migration Flows&lt;ref&gt;http://cms.bsu.edu/-/media/WWW/DepartmentalContent/MillerCollegeofBusiness/BBR/Publications/MigrationFlows.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| February 2013
|-
| Public Transportation in Indiana: An Analysis of Ridership Surveys&lt;ref&gt;http://cms.bsu.edu/-/media/WWW/DepartmentalContent/MillerCollegeofBusiness/BBR/Publications/ITA-BusRoute-small.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| January 2013
|-
| The Effect of Gasoline Prices on Public Bus Ridership in Indiana&lt;ref&gt;http://cms.bsu.edu/-/media/WWW/DepartmentalContent/MillerCollegeofBusiness/BBR/Publications/ITA-GasPrice-small.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| January 2013
|-
| Fixed Route and Demand-Response Systems: Funding Methods, Benefits, and Costs in Indiana &lt;ref&gt;http://cms.bsu.edu/-/media/WWW/DepartmentalContent/MillerCollegeofBusiness/BBR/Publications/ITA-FiscalFed-small.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| January 2013
|-
| Economic Forecast for 2013: East Central Indiana &lt;ref&gt;http://cms.bsu.edu/-/media/WWW/DepartmentalContent/MillerCollegeofBusiness/BBR/Publications/Forecast2013-ECI-web.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;&amp; Southeast Indiana&lt;ref&gt;http://cms.bsu.edu/-/media/WWW/DepartmentalContent/MillerCollegeofBusiness/BBR/Publications/Forecast2013-SEI-web.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| December 2012
|-
| 2012 Holiday Retail Sales Forecast &lt;ref&gt;http://cms.bsu.edu/-/media/WWW/DepartmentalContent/MillerCollegeofBusiness/BBR/Publications/HolidaySales2012.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| November 2012
|-
| Manufacturing: Elkhart County, Indiana &lt;ref&gt;http://cms.bsu.edu/-/media/WWW/DepartmentalContent/MillerCollegeofBusiness/BBR/Publications/ElkhartMFG2012.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| October 2012
|-
| The Relative Tax Burden of Indiana’s Business: A Micro-Simulation of State Tax Liabilities &lt;ref&gt;http://cms.bsu.edu/-/media/WWW/DepartmentalContent/MillerCollegeofBusiness/BBR/Publications/TaxBurden-web.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| September 2012
|-
| 2012 Manufacturing and Logistics Report: National Report  &lt;ref&gt;http://cms.bsu.edu/-/media/WWW/DepartmentalContent/MillerCollegeofBusiness/BBR/Publications/Conexus2012-National.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; &amp; Indiana Report &lt;ref&gt;http://cms.bsu.edu/-/media/WWW/DepartmentalContent/MillerCollegeofBusiness/BBR/Publications/Conexus2012-Indiana.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| June 2012
|-
| Indiana Community Asset Inventory and Rankings 2012 &lt;ref&gt;http://cms.bsu.edu/-/media/WWW/DepartmentalContent/MillerCollegeofBusiness/BBR/Publications/CAIR-Report2012.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| April 2012
|-
| Special Districts and Local Government Reform&lt;ref&gt;http://cms.bsu.edu/-/media/WWW/DepartmentalContent/MillerCollegeofBusiness/BBR/Publications/SpecialDistricts2012.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| February 2012
|-
| Gasoline Prices: An Update  &lt;ref&gt;http://cms.bsu.edu/-/media/WWW/DepartmentalContent/MillerCollegeofBusiness/BBR/Publications/GasPrices2012.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| February 2012
|-
| The Effect of State-Level Add-On Legislation to the Federal New Market Tax Credit Program  &lt;ref&gt;http://cms.bsu.edu/-/media/WWW/DepartmentalContent/MillerCollegeofBusiness/BBR/Publications/NMTC.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| February 2012
|-
| Home Health Care Industry Growth in Indiana &lt;ref&gt;http://cms.bsu.edu/-/media/WWW/DepartmentalContent/MillerCollegeofBusiness/BBR/Publications/HomeHealthCare.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| January 2012
|-
| Right-to-Work Legislation and the Manufacturing Sector&lt;ref&gt;http://cms.bsu.edu/-/media/WWW/DepartmentalContent/MillerCollegeofBusiness/BBR/Publications/RightToWork/RightToWork.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| January 2012
|-
| The Indiana Econometric Model: 2012 Economic Forecast &lt;ref&gt;http://cms.bsu.edu/-/media/WWW/DepartmentalContent/MillerCollegeofBusiness/BBR/EconOutlook/2012%20Outlook%20Handout.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| December 2011
|-
| Indiana Toll Road Economic Development Corridor Initiative &lt;ref&gt;http://cms.bsu.edu/-/media/WWW/DepartmentalContent/MillerCollegeofBusiness/BBR/Publications/TollRd/99-TollRdPhase3.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| November 2011
|-
| To Collect Sales Tax or Not?  Indiana's Ecommerce Conundrum&lt;ref&gt;http://cms.bsu.edu/-/media/WWW/DepartmentalContent/MillerCollegeofBusiness/BBR/Publications/IFPISalesTax112111.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| November 2011
|-
| The Puzzle of Indiana's Economy through the Great Recession&lt;ref&gt;http://cms.bsu.edu/-/media/WWW/DepartmentalContent/MillerCollegeofBusiness/BBR/Publications/SagamoreMIINRecession091611.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| 2011
|-
| Local Government Conslidation in New Jersey: Potential Savings Due to Eonomies of Scale &amp; Efficiency Gains | Analysis of Government Functions&lt;ref&gt;http://cms.bsu.edu/-/media/WWW/DepartmentalContent/MillerCollegeofBusiness/BBR/Publications/NJ-LGC-Gov.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; &amp; Analysis of Public School Districts&lt;ref&gt;http://cms.bsu.edu/-/media/WWW/DepartmentalContent/MillerCollegeofBusiness/BBR/Publications/NJ-LGC-Schools.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| October 2011
|-
| An Examination of the Economic Impact of Property Tax Levy Caps on Economic Activity in New Jersey&lt;ref&gt;http://cms.bsu.edu/-/media/WWW/DepartmentalContent/MillerCollegeofBusiness/BBR/Publications/NJPropertyTaxLevyCaps093011.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| October 2011
|-
| The Economic Impact of the Super Bowl in Indianapolis&lt;ref&gt;http://cms.bsu.edu/-/media/WWW/DepartmentalContent/MillerCollegeofBusiness/BBR/Publications/SuperBowl-Redesign.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| October 2011, March 2008
|-
| A Technical Analysis of the Economic Impact of U.S. Department of Defense Contracts in Indiana&lt;ref&gt;http://cms.bsu.edu/-/media/WWW/DepartmentalContent/MillerCollegeofBusiness/BBR/Publications/DefenseIndiana100311.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| September 2011
|-
| 2011 Holiday Retail Sales Forecast&lt;ref&gt;http://cms.bsu.edu/-/media/WWW/DepartmentalContent/MillerCollegeofBusiness/BBR/Publications/holidayForecast2011.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| September 2011
|-
| An Analysis of the Short Run Effects of the American Jobs Act&lt;ref&gt;http://cms.bsu.edu/-/media/WWW/DepartmentalContent/MillerCollegeofBusiness/BBR/Publications/Short%20Term%20Impact%20of%20President%20Obamas%20Job%20Plan.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| September 2011
|-
| Foster Care Cost Survey of Indiana&lt;ref&gt;http://cms.bsu.edu/-/media/WWW/DepartmentalContent/MillerCollegeofBusiness/BBR/Publications/DCS-SurveyFindingsReport_08-16-11.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| August 2011
|-
| Manufacturing Trends: Madison County, Ind., 1973 - 2009&lt;ref&gt;http://cms.bsu.edu/-/media/WWW/DepartmentalContent/MillerCollegeofBusiness/BBR/Publications/MfgTrends2011_Madison.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| July 2011
|-
| Manufacturing Trends: Delaware County, Ind., 1969 - 2009&lt;ref&gt;http://cms.bsu.edu/-/media/WWW/DepartmentalContent/MillerCollegeofBusiness/BBR/Publications/MfgTrends2011_Delaware.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| July 2011
|-
| Educational Attainment in Indiana&lt;ref&gt;http://cms.bsu.edu/-/media/WWW/DepartmentalContent/MillerCollegeofBusiness/BBR/Publications/EdAttainment.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| July 2011
|-
| Public vs. Private Investment in College: An Exploratory Analysis&lt;ref&gt;http://cms.bsu.edu/-/media/WWW/DepartmentalContent/MillerCollegeofBusiness/BBR/Publications/HigherEducation082911.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| June 2011
|-
| 2011 Manufacturing and Logistics Report: National Report&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://cber.iweb.bsu.edu/research/conexus11/NationalReport11.pdf |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2013-04-04 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110901235415/http://cber.iweb.bsu.edu/research/conexus11/NationalReport11.pdf |archivedate=2011-09-01 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt; &amp; Indiana Report&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cber.iweb.bsu.edu/research/conexus11/IndianaReport11.pdf |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2012-08-19 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120326002136/http://cber.iweb.bsu.edu/research/conexus11/IndianaReport11.pdf |archivedate=2012-03-26 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| June 2011
|-
| Preliminary Flood Damage Estimates for the Memphis, Tennessee, MSA&lt;ref&gt;http://cms.bsu.edu/-/media/WWW/DepartmentalContent/MillerCollegeofBusiness/BBR/Publications/MemphisFlood.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| May 2011
|-
|  U.S. Export Adaptability at the State Level &lt;ref name="autogenerated1"&gt;http://cms.bsu.edu/-/media/WWW/DepartmentalContent/MillerCollegeofBusiness/BBR/Publications/ExportAdaptability-web.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| May 2011
|-
|  Local Option Income Taxes in Indiana&lt;ref name="autogenerated1"/&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| March 2011
|-
|  The Effects of Higher Fuel Prices on Indiana's Economy&lt;ref&gt;http://cms.bsu.edu/-/media/WWW/DepartmentalContent/MillerCollegeofBusiness/BBR/Publications/gasPrices_final.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| January 2011
|-
|  Reflections on State Tax Incentives&lt;ref name="autogenerated2"&gt;http://cms.bsu.edu/-/media/WWW/DepartmentalContent/MillerCollegeofBusiness/BBR/Publications/holidayForecast2010.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| December 2010
|-
|  2010 Holiday Retail Sales Forecast&lt;ref name="autogenerated2"/&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| November 2010
|-
|  Media in the Workplace: An Analysis of the Video Consumer Mapping Study Data&lt;ref&gt;http://cms.bsu.edu/-/media/WWW/DepartmentalContent/MillerCollegeofBusiness/BBR/Publications/MediaWorkplace_web.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| August 2010
|-
|  Preliminary Damage Estimates for [[2010 Pakistan floods|Pakistani Flood]] Events, 2010&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://cber.iweb.bsu.edu/research/PakistanFlood.pdf |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2010-08-18 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110719154812/http://cber.iweb.bsu.edu/research/PakistanFlood.pdf |archivedate=2011-07-19 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| August 2010
|-
|  Comprehensive Examination of the Performance 
of the Indiana 21st Century Research and Technology Funds &lt;ref&gt;http://cms.bsu.edu/Academics/CentersandInstitutes/BBR/~/media/DepartmentalContent/MillerCollegeofBusiness/BBR/Publications/21stCentury/21st%20century100610.ashx&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| September 2010
|-
|  Indiana's Manufacturing Employment Trends&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cber.iweb.bsu.edu/research/MfgTrends_indiana.pdf |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2010-08-19 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110719154853/http://cber.iweb.bsu.edu/research/MfgTrends_indiana.pdf |archivedate=2011-07-19 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| July 2010
|-
|  The Economic Effects of Indiana's [[Property Tax]] Rate Limits&lt;ref&gt;http://cms.bsu.edu/Academics/CentersandInstitutes/BBR/~/media/DepartmentalContent/MillerCollegeofBusiness/BBR/Publications/PropTaxCaps%20Feb25.ashx&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| February 2010
|-
|  Who Lost Jobs When the [[Minimum wage in the United States|Minimum Wage]] Rose?&lt;ref&gt;http://cms.bsu.edu/Academics/CentersandInstitutes/BBR/~/media/DepartmentalContent/MillerCollegeofBusiness/BBR/Publications/MinWage.ashx&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| February 2010
|-
|  Intrastate Distribution of State Government Revenues and Expenditures in Indiana&lt;ref&gt;http://cms.bsu.edu/Academics/CentersandInstitutes/BBR/~/media/DepartmentalContent/MillerCollegeofBusiness/BBR/Publications/IFPI_IntrastateTax.ashx&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| January 2010
|-
|  Business Brief: Trends in Employment and Earnings in [[Delaware County, Indiana|Delaware County]]&lt;ref&gt;http://cms.bsu.edu/Academics/CentersandInstitutes/BBR/~/media/DepartmentalContent/MillerCollegeofBusiness/BBR/Publications/EmploymentTrends.ashx&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| January 2010
|-
|  Cluster Analysis of Key Sectors: [[Boone County, Indiana|Boone County]] and Surrounding Areas&lt;ref&gt;http://cms.bsu.edu/Academics/CentersandInstitutes/BBR/~/media/DepartmentalContent/MillerCollegeofBusiness/BBR/Publications/BooneNov30.ashx&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| December 2009
|-
|  Some Preliminary Evaluation of the [[Cash for Clunkers]] Program&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cms.bsu.edu/Academics/CentersandInstitutes/BBR/~/media/DF360CADE9424CA0AB9B8CDA68AAA952.ashx|title=Search Results: errors page-not-found|work=bsu.edu|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100527142231/http://cms.bsu.edu/Academics/CentersandInstitutes/BBR/~/media/DF360CADE9424CA0AB9B8CDA68AAA952.ashx|archivedate=2010-05-27|df=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| November 2009
|-
|  A Forecasting Mea Culpa – Maybe?&lt;ref name="autogenerated3"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cms.bsu.edu/Academics/CentersandInstitutes/BBR/~/media/78E89B779359407B8D68DF2D5692E616.ashx|title=Search Results: errors page-not-found|work=bsu.edu|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100527141839/http://cms.bsu.edu/Academics/CentersandInstitutes/BBR/~/media/78E89B779359407B8D68DF2D5692E616.ashx|archivedate=2010-05-27|df=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| October 2009
|-
|  The 2009 Holiday Retail Sales Forecast&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cms.bsu.edu/Academics/CentersandInstitutes/BBR/~/media/F6535546E9F04E75A047AF1B1EEC3686.ashx|title=Search Results: errors page-not-found|work=bsu.edu|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100527142001/http://cms.bsu.edu/Academics/CentersandInstitutes/BBR/~/media/F6535546E9F04E75A047AF1B1EEC3686.ashx|archivedate=2010-05-27|df=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| November 2009
|-
|  The Indiana State Fair: 2008 Economic Impact and 2009 Projections&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cber.iweb.bsu.edu/research/StateFairImpact09.pdf |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2009-11-12 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110719154325/http://cber.iweb.bsu.edu/research/StateFairImpact09.pdf |archivedate=2011-07-19 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| October 2009
|-
|  Cultural Tourism in Indiana: The Impact and Clustering of the Arts and Creative Sectors in This Recession &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://cber.iweb.bsu.edu/research/CulturalTourism.pdf |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2009-11-12 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20091229205704/http://cber.iweb.bsu.edu/research/CulturalTourism.pdf |archivedate=2009-12-29 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| May 2009
|-
|  2009 Manufacturing and Logistics Report Card &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://cber.iweb.bsu.edu/research/conexus09/ |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2009-11-12 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090823093106/http://cber.iweb.bsu.edu/research/conexus09/ |archivedate=2009-08-23 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| February 2009
|-
|  Local Government Reform in Indiana &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cms.bsu.edu/Academics/CentersandInstitutes/BBR/~/media/995AFE81828E409193E6C8273059A552.ashx|title=Search Results: errors page-not-found|work=bsu.edu|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100527141546/http://cms.bsu.edu/Academics/CentersandInstitutes/BBR/~/media/995AFE81828E409193E6C8273059A552.ashx|archivedate=2010-05-27|df=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| January 2009
|-
|  Tourism-Related Commerce in Indiana &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cms.bsu.edu/Academics/CentersandInstitutes/BBR/~/media/49D31B2CE57A4C75BA3CF0B37A59BF9F.ashx|title=Search Results: errors page-not-found|work=bsu.edu|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100527141317/http://cms.bsu.edu/Academics/CentersandInstitutes/BBR/~/media/49D31B2CE57A4C75BA3CF0B37A59BF9F.ashx|archivedate=2010-05-27|df=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| January 2009
|-
|  Did the Increase in Minimum Wage Cause Our Unemployment Rate to Rise? &lt;ref name="autogenerated3"/&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| September 2008
|-
|  Understanding the Sub-Prime Markets: A Narrative &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cms.bsu.edu/Academics/CentersandInstitutes/BBR/~/media/BC0DDDEB4DE543BF955EA7D40CD4DB1C.ashx|title=Search Results: errors page-not-found|work=bsu.edu|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100527141451/http://cms.bsu.edu/Academics/CentersandInstitutes/BBR/~/media/BC0DDDEB4DE543BF955EA7D40CD4DB1C.ashx|archivedate=2010-05-27|df=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| October 2008
|-
|  Understanding Regional Poverty: What is Poverty? &lt;ref name="autogenerated3"/&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| September 2008
|-
|  New Media, Information Technology and Indiana: A Retrospective on the 2000 Battelle Study &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cms.bsu.edu/Academics/CentersandInstitutes/BBR/~/media/EED7125B3E3A420A903BB83D61CA88B7.ashx|title=Search Results: errors page-not-found|work=bsu.edu|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100527141729/http://cms.bsu.edu/Academics/CentersandInstitutes/BBR/~/media/EED7125B3E3A420A903BB83D61CA88B7.ashx|archivedate=2010-05-27|df=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| January 2009
|-
|  2008 National Manufacturing and Logistics Report Card &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cms.bsu.edu/Academics/CentersandInstitutes/BBR/~/media/83F126DC3C234420A3C6665AB9374829.ashx|title=Search Results: errors page-not-found|work=bsu.edu|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090814165656/http://cms.bsu.edu/Academics/CentersandInstitutes/BBR/~/media/83F126DC3C234420A3C6665AB9374829.ashx|archivedate=2009-08-14|df=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| style="text-align:center;"| May 2008
|}

==Publications==

===American Journal of Business===
CBER houses the managing office of the [[American Journal of Business]], a [[peer-reviewed]] journal that publishes articles aimed at improving business practices or enhancing instructional efforts through application, transfer, and interpretation of knowledge.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cms.bsu.edu/Academics/CentersandInstitutes/BBR/AmericanJournalofBusiness.aspx|title=Search Results: academics centersandinstitutes bbr americanjournalofbusiness|work=bsu.edu}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Indiana Business Bulletin===
CBER also publishes the online publication, [[Indiana Business Bulletin]] (IBB). The IBB provides weekly economic analysis, forecasting, and leading economic indicators to the business community, media, and policymakers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cms.bsu.edu/Academics/CentersandInstitutes/BBR/IndianaBusinessBulletin.aspx|title=Search Results: academics centersandinstitutes bbr indianabusinessbulletin|work=bsu.edu}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Awards and recognitions==

* 2009 Association for University Business and Economic Research (AUBER) Award of Excellence in Websites for CBER Data Center – County Profiles
* 2009 AUBER Award of Excellence in Newsletters, Brochures and Other Promotional Materials for CBER Open House
* 2009 AUBER Award of Excellence in Special Studies, Technical or Contract Reports for Local Government Reform in Indiana&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bsu.edu/news/article/0,1370,7273-850-63179,00.html|title=Search Results: newsarticle 0,1370,7273-850-63179,00|work=bsu.edu|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100121174316/http://www.bsu.edu/news/article/0%2C1370%2C7273-850-63179%2C00.html|archivedate=2010-01-21|df=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 2008 AUBER Award of Excellence in Electronic Publications for State of Manufacturing and Logistics in Indiana  &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bsu.edu/news/article/0,1370,7273-850-60347,00.html|title=Search Results: newsarticle 0,1370,7273-850-60347,00|work=bsu.edu|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100604122351/http://www.bsu.edu/news/article/0%2C1370%2C7273-850-60347%2C00.html|archivedate=2010-06-04|df=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

== External links ==
*[http://www.bsu.edu/cber CBER Website]
*[http://www.bsu.edu/mcobwin/ibb/ Indiana Business Bulletin]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20081122030821/http://www.ajbonline.org/ American Journal of Business]

{{coord|40.2033|-85.4063|type:landmark_region:US-IN|display=title}}

{{Ball State University}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Center For Business And Economic Research}}
[[Category:Business economics]]
[[Category:Forecasting organizations]]</text>
      <sha1>81cahaadfmo8udiqvnkzt2pl76326u1</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Center for International Business Education and Research</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>22846990</id>
    <revision>
      <id>793466608</id>
      <parentid>778688543</parentid>
      <timestamp>2017-08-01T22:40:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rescuing 2 sources and tagging 0 as dead. #IABot (v1.5beta)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="3348">{{Infobox Organization
|name         = Centers for International Business Education and Research
|image        = 
|image_border = 
|size         = 
|caption      = 
|map          = 
|msize        = 
|mcaption     = 
|abbreviation = CIBER
|motto        = 
|formation    =1988
|extinction   = 
|type         =
|status       = 
|purpose      = International business education
|headquarters = 
|location     = 
|region_served =United States 
|membership   = 
|language     = 
|leader_title = 
|leader_name  = 
|main_organ = 
|parent_organization =U.S. Department of Education 
|affiliations = 
|num_staff    = 
|num_volunteers =
|budget       = $10,960,000 in 2008&lt;ref name="mandate"&gt;[http://www.ed.gov/programs/iegpscibe/index.html U.S. Department of Education Program Description]&lt;/ref&gt;
|website      = [http://ciberweb.msu.edu/ CIBERweb]
|remarks =
}}

The '''Centers for International Business Education and Research''' ('''CIBERs''') are resources for international [[business education]] in the United States funded by through the [[United States Department of Education]]. The centers were established in 1988 as part of the [[Omnibus Foreign Trade and Competitiveness Act|Omnibus Foreign Trade and Competitiveness Act of 1988]]&lt;ref name="Omnibus Foreign Trade and Competitiveness Act of 1988"&gt;[http://thomas.loc.gov/cgi-bin/bdquery/R?d100:FLD002:@1(100+418) Omnibus Foreign Trade and Competitiveness Act of 1988]&lt;/ref&gt; As part of the legislation, CIBERs are mandated to provide six specific services&lt;ref name="Executive"&gt;[http://ciberweb.msu.edu/NationalImpact/GrantProposalAbstracts2006-2010.pdf Executive Summary CIBER abstracts 2006-2010]&lt;/ref&gt; among their services. There are CIBERs at 17 universities in the United States.&lt;ref name="Executive" /&gt;

==CIBERS==
*[http://marriottschool.byu.edu/gmc/ Brigham Young University]
*[http://www.business.gwu.edu/CIBER/ George Washington University]
*[http://ciber.gatech.edu/ Georgia Institute of Technology]
*[http://ciber.gsu.edu/ Georgia State University]
*[http://www.kelley.indiana.edu/CIBER/ Indiana University]
*[http://global.broad.msu.edu/ Michigan State University]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20090228082030/http://www-rohan.sdsu.edu/dept/ciber/ San Diego State University]
*[http://www.fox.temple.edu/ciber/ Temple University]
*[http://cibs.tamu.edu/ Texas A&amp;M University]
*[http://fisher.osu.edu/international/index.php?page=CIBER The Ohio State University]
*[http://www.mccombs.utexas.edu/research/ciber/ The University of Texas at Austin]
*[http://www.ed.gov/about/offices/list/ope/iegps/index.html U.S. Department of Education]
*[http://www.ucdenver.edu/academics/InternationalPrograms/CIBER/Pages/IIB_CIBER.aspx University of Colorado at Denver]
*[http://www.business.uconn.edu/CIBER/ University of Connecticut]
*[http://www.rhsmith.umd.edu/ciber/ University of Maryland]
*[http://www.bus.miami.edu/faculty-and-research/ciber/index.html University of Miami]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20090510101939/http://mooreschool.sc.edu/moore/ciber University of South Carolina]
*[http://foster.washington.edu/ciber/ University of Washington]

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Center For International Business Education And Research}}
[[Category:Foreign trade of the United States]]
[[Category:Business education]]
[[Category:Business organizations based in the United States]]</text>
      <sha1>c5pyffeerscy5bs9wo8ewpnmcnrwku5</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Customer delight</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>36910423</id>
    <revision>
      <id>833275145</id>
      <parentid>798049137</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-03-30T16:27:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Randykitty</username>
        <id>17843555</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Removing link(s): [[Wikipedia:Articles for deletion/Ron Kaufman]] closed as delete ([[WP:XFDC|XFDcloser]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="8100">'''Customer delight''' is surprising a [[customer]] by exceeding his or her expectations and thus creating a positive emotional reaction. This emotional reaction leads to [[word of mouth]]. Customer delight directly affects [[sales]] and [[profitability]] of a company as it helps to distinguish the company and its products and services from the [[competition (economics)|competition]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Gross|first=Scott|title=Positively Outrageous Service. How to delight and astound your customers and win them for life|year=2004|publisher=Dear Born Trade Publishing|location=USA|isbn=978-0-7931-8823-9|page=8}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Seth|first=Rakesh Seth, Kirti|title=Creating customer delight : the how and why of CRM|year=2005|publisher=Response Books|location=New Delhi|isbn=9780761932963|page=19}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In the past [[customer satisfaction]] has been seen as a [[key performance indicator]]. Customer satisfaction measures the extent to which the expectations of a customer are met (compared to expectations being exceeded). However, it has been discovered that mere customer satisfaction does not create [[brand loyalty]] nor does it encourage positive word of mouth.

Customer delight can be created by the product itself, by accompanied standard services and by interaction with people at the front line. The interaction is the greatest source of opportunities to create delight as it can be personalized and tailored to the specific needs and wishes of the customer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Carlzon|first=Jan; [foreword by Tom Peters]|title=Moments of truth|year=1989|publisher=Perennial Library|location=New York|isbn=0060915803|page=2|edition=Repr.}}&lt;/ref&gt; During contacts with [[touch point]]s in the company, more than just [[customer service]] can be delivered. The person at the front line can surprise by showing a sincere personal interest in the customer, offer small attentions that might please or find a solution specific to particular needs. Those front-line employees are able to develop a relationship between the customer and the brand. Elements in creating [[work motivation|motivated]] staff are: recruiting the right people, motivating them continuously and leading them in a clear way.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Hsieh|first=Tony|title=Delivering happiness : a path to profits, passion, and purpose|year=2010|publisher=Business Plus|location=New York|isbn=9780446563048|pages=144, 145|edition=1st}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Michelli|first=Joseph|title=The Zappos experience : 5 principles to inspire, engage, and wow|publisher=McGraw-Hill|location=New York|isbn=9780071749589|page=136}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Purpose of customer delight==
There are three objectives when implementing Customer Delight:
# make [[customer loyalty|customers loyal]]. As described by Sewell,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.amazon.com/Customers-Life-One-Time-Lifetime-Customer/dp/0385504454 |title=Customers for Life: How to Turn That One-Time Buyer Into a Lifetime Customer: Carl Sewell, Paul B. Brown: 9780385504454: Amazon.com: Books |publisher=Amazon.com |date=2002-11-19 |accessdate=2013-11-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; that finding new customers costs 4 to 9 times more time and money than reselling to an existing client. It is thus commercially intelligent to retain as many clients as possible.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Sewell|first=Carl|title=Customers for life : how to turn that onetime buyer into a lifetime customer|year=2002|publisher=Doubleday|location=New York|isbn=9780385504454|page=13|edition=Rev.|author2=Brown, Paul B.}}&lt;/ref&gt;
# have customers that are more profitable. Average delighted customers spend more with less hassle. As can be seen with the list of Van Setten,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.managementboek.nl/boek/9789047004004/de-klantenfluisteraar-jan-van-setten |title=De klantenfluisteraar door J. (Jan) van Setten (Boek) |publisher=Managementboek.nl |accessdate=2013-11-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; when all other elements are correct, clients accord less importance to price (as long as their perception of price remains reasonable).  
# have clients talk positively about your product, brand or shop, the so-called word of mouth. In a world of informed customers, 92% of customers consider word of mouth as the most reliable source of information.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nielsen.com/us/en/insights/press-room/2012/nielsen-global-consumers-trust-in-earned-advertising-grows.html |title=Global Consumers' Trust in 'Earned' Advertising Grows in Importance |publisher=Nielsen |accessdate=2013-11-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; Delighted clients can be a valuable source of [[advertisement]] for a company.  
The effect of achieving those objectives, according to Reichheld&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.netpromotersystem.com/speaking-engagements/fred-reichheld.aspx |title=Bain &amp; Company: Net Promoter System℠ - Fred Reichheld |publisher=Netpromotersystem.com |accessdate=2013-11-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; as described in The Ultimate Question 2.0,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.netpromotersystem.com/book/index.aspx |title=Bain &amp; Company: NET PROMOTER SYSTEM℠ - About The Ultimate Question 2.0 |publisher=Netpromotersystem.com |accessdate=2013-11-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; only 9% of the world’s major firms achieve real sustainable profit and [[sustainable growth|growth]] over 10- year period from 1999 to 2009. Customer Delight is the only kind of growth that can be sustained over the long term according to Reichheld and Markey. The authors mention that their company [[Bain &amp; Company]] have researched and concluded that a 5% increase in [[customer retention]] could yield anywhere between 25% to 100% increase in profits. The book explains the [[net promoter score|Net Promoter Score]]; a system which measures what customers are feeling and thus creating accountability for the customer experience.

In order to consistently deliver Customer Delight at all customer touch points throughout the company, a [[customer-centric]] [[corporate culture]] is key. With this corporate culture all processes, systems, people and leadership are aligned: everyone in the organization shares the same set of values, attitudes and practices. Developing the culture is a continuous exercise of innovation and improvement, involving every employee of the company.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Gallo|first=Carmine|title=The Apple experience : the secrets of delivering insanely great customer service|year=2012|publisher=McGraw-Hill|location=New York|isbn=978-0071793209|page=25|edition=1st}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ron Kaufman {{cite book |title=Uplifting service : the proven path to delighting your customers, colleagues, and everyone else you meet|year=2012|publisher=Evolve Publishing|location=[New York, NY]|isbn=978-0984762507|pages=22, 23, 24, 25}}&lt;/ref&gt; An absolutely necessary step is linking Customer Delight behaviour to the core values of the brand.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Michelli|first=Joseph|title=The Zappos experience : 5 principles to inspire, engage, and wow|publisher=McGraw-Hill|location=New York|isbn=9780071749589|page=48}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Core values are operating principles that guide an organization’s internal conduct as well as its relationship with customers, partners and shareholders. Once core values are clearly outlined it is critical to incorporate them into every process, from [[Recruitment|hiring]], to [[employee appraisal]]s and [[decision making]].

==See also==
*[[Customer Service]]
*[[Service quality]]
*[[Customer Loyalty]]
*[[Brand Management]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Bibliography==
*''Spoil 'em Rotten!, Five-Star Customer Delight in Action'' by Jane &amp; Ted Coine, {{ISBN|9780595424122}}
*''The Ultimate Question 2.0'' (revised and expanded edition): How Net Promoter Companies Thrive in a Customer-Driven World, {{ISBN|978-1422173350}}
*''The New Gold Standard: 5 Leadership Principles for Creating a Legendary Customer Experience Courtesy of the Ritz-Carlton Hotel Company'', {{ISBN|978-0-07-154833-5}}
*"You make the difference", by Marieke van der Laan &amp; Johannes van de Water, {{ISBN|978-94-6228-410-4}}

[[Category:Articles created via the Article Wizard]]
[[Category:Customer experience]]
[[Category:Business terms]]</text>
      <sha1>48kqgkbme1fx69w62n4vrfgvm2se82j</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Customer involvement management</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>21687181</id>
    <revision>
      <id>746623139</id>
      <parentid>746618642</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-28T14:22:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Marcocapelle</username>
        <id>14965160</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>new key for [[Category:Customer relationship management]]: "Involvement" using [[WP:HC|HotCat]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="1598">'''Customer involvement management''', ''CIM'', is a marketing management method that takes customer orientation further than [[customer relationship management]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dagensmedia.se/mallar/dagensmedia_mall.asp?version=220452], 2009-02-26, Dagens Media (in swedish)&lt;/ref&gt; CIM identifies and develops ways to involve customers in the business and product development process, such as design, marketing, sales, customer service, etc. The degree of involvement can be as far as to make the customer a part of the product, experience, and delivery.

Within CIM, the product is considered a subset in what meets the customer's need of identification, problem solving, and consumption. The possibility to influence the design and the consumption itself is assumed to be of great importance for the customers buying decision and loyalty.

One example of a company that uses CIM is [[Nike, Inc.|Nike]]. With the concept [[NikeiD]] they let the customers design their own sport shoes.

More recently companies have started to build Web portals that involve customers in the idea generation, selection, development, and commercialization.&lt;ref&gt;Rohrbeck, R., Steinhoff, F. and F. Perder(2010) [http://ssrn.com/abstract=1533575 ''Sourcing Innovation from You Customer: How Multinational Enterprises use Web Platforms for Virtual Customer Integration''], Technology Analysis &amp; Strategic Management, Vol. 22, No. 4, pp. 117–131&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==

&lt;references/&gt;

{{DEFAULTSORT:Customer Involvement Management}}
[[Category:Customer relationship management|Involvement]]
[[Category:Business terms]]</text>
      <sha1>pgi2bkr1cm0b74a2gwrpro43iqjmpwl</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Fayolism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>33616691</id>
    <revision>
      <id>847244235</id>
      <parentid>826148389</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-06-23T22:29:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Gene Wilson</username>
        <id>6713489</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>AccessDate parameter removed    No URL in citation</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="14015">
'''Fayolism''' was a theory of [[management]] that [[Analysis|analyzed]] and [[wikt:synthesis#Noun|synthesized]] the role of [[management]] in organizations, developed around 1900 by the [[France|French]] [[management]] theorist [[Henri Fayol]] (1841–1925).  It was through Fayol's work as a philosopher of administration that he contributed most widely to the theory and practice of organizational management.
[[Image:Fonds henri fayol.jpg|thumb|right|Henri Fayol]]

== Research and Teaching of Management ==
Fayol believed by focusing on managerial practices he could minimize misunderstandings and increase [[efficiency]] in organizations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Pietri|first=P. H|title=Organizational communication: the pioneers|journal=Journal of Business Communication|date=1974|volume=11|issue=4|pages=3–6}}&lt;/ref&gt;  He enlightened managers on how to accomplish their managerial duties, and the practices in which they should engage.  In his book ''General and Industrial Management'' (published in French in 1916, then published in English in 1949), Fayol outlined his theory of general management, which he believed could be applied to the administration of myriad industries.  His concern was with the administrative apparatus (or functions of administration), and to that end he presented his ''administrative theory'', that is, principles and elements of management.

His theories and ideas were ideally a result of his environment—a post revolutionized France with an emerging republic [[bourgeois]]. A bourgeois himself, he believed in controlling workers to  achieve greater productivity over all other managerial considerations. However, through reading ''General and Industrial Management,'' it is apparent that Fayol advocated a flexible approach to management, one he believed could be applied to any circumstance whether in the home, the workplace, or within the state. He stressed the importance and the practice of [[forecasting]] and [[planning]] in order to apply these ideas and techniques, which demonstrated his ability and emphasis in being able to adapt to any sort of situation. In ''General and Industrial Management'' he outlines an agenda whereby, under an accepted theory of management, every citizen is exposed and taught some form of management education and allowed to exercise management abilities first at school and later on in the workplace.

{{quote|Everyone needs some concepts of management; in the home, in affairs of state, the need for managerial ability is in keeping with the importance of the undertaking, and for individual people the need is everywhere in greater accordance with the position occupied.|excerpt from ''General and Industrial Management''}}

== Fayol vs. Frederick Taylor's Scientific Management==
Fayol has been regarded by many as the father of the modern operational management theory, and his ideas have become a fundamental part of modern [[management concept]]s.  Fayol is often compared to [[Frederick Winslow Taylor]] who developed [[Scientific Management]]. Taylor's Scientific Management deals with the efficient organization of production in the context of a competitive enterprise that is concerned with controlling its [[production cost]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Almashaqba|first=Z. S|author2=Nemer Al-Qeed, M|title=The Classical Theory of Organization and {{not a typo|it's}} Relevance|journal=International Research Journal of Finance &amp; Economics|year=2010|volume=41|pages=60–67}}&lt;/ref&gt; Taylor's system of scientific management is the cornerstone of classical theory.  Fayol was also a classical theorist, and referred to Taylor in his writing and considered him a visionary and pioneer in the management of organizations.

However, Fayol differed from Taylor in his focus. Taylor's main focus was on the task, whereas Fayol was more concerned with management.  Another difference between the two theorists is their treatment of workers.  Fayol appears to have slightly more respect for the worker than Taylor had, as evidenced by Fayol's proclamation that workers may indeed be motivated by more than just money.  Fayol also argued for equity in the treatment of workers.

According to Claude George (1968), a primary difference between Fayol and Taylor was that Taylor viewed management processes from the bottom up, while Fayol viewed it from the top down. In Fayol's book ''General and Industrial Management,'' Fayol wrote that {{quote|Taylor's approach differs from the one we have outlined in that he examines the firm from the bottom up. He starts with the most elemental units of activity—the workers' actions—then studies the effects of their actions on productivity, devises new methods for making them more efficient, and applies what he learns at lower levels to the hierarchy...|Fayol, 1987, p.&amp;nbsp;43}} He suggests that Taylor has staff analysts and advisors working with individuals at lower levels of the organization to identify the ways to improve efficiency. According to Fayol, the approach results in a "negation of the principle of unity of command". Fayol criticized Taylor’s functional management in this way. {{quote|… the most marked outward characteristics of functional management lies in the fact that each workman, instead of coming in direct contact with the management at one point only, … receives his daily orders and help from eight different bosses…|Fayol, 1949, p.&amp;nbsp;68.}} Those eight, Fayol said, were 
#route clerks,
#instruction card men
#cost and time clerks
#gang bosses
#speed bosses
#inspectors
#repair bosses, and the
#shop disciplinarian (p.&amp;nbsp;68).
This, he said, was an unworkable situation, and that Taylor must have somehow reconciled the dichotomy in some way not described in Taylor's works.

Fayol's desire for teaching a generalized theory of management stemmed from the belief that each individual of an organization at one point or another takes on duties that involve managerial decisions. Unlike Taylor, however, who believed management activity was the exclusive duty of an organizations dominant class. Fayol's approach was more in sync with his idea of Authority, which stated, "...that the right to give orders should not be considered without the acceptance and understanding of responsibility."

Noted as one of the early fathers of the ''Human Relations'' movements, Fayol expressed ideas and practices different from Taylor, in that they showed flexibility and adaptation, and stressed the importance of interpersonal interaction among employees.

=== Fayol's Principles of Management ===
During the early 20th century, Fayol developed 14 principles of management to help managers manage their affairs more effectively. Organizations in technologically advanced countries interpret these principles quite differently from the way they were interpreted during Fayol's time as well. These differences in interpretation are in part a result of the cultural challenges managers face when implementing this framework. The fourteen principles are: 
#[[Division of work]],
#Delegation of authority,
#Discipline,
#[[Command chain|Unity of commands]],
#Unity of direction,
#Interrelation between individual interests and common organizational goals,
#[[Financial compensation|Compensation package]],
#Centralization,
#Scalar chains,
#Order,
#Equity,
#[[Job guarantee]],
#Initiatives,
#Team-Spirit or [[Esprit de corps]]. 
&lt;!-- This image seems to be a copyright violation and should not be used until it is become clear that it isn't. This chart shows the difference how these applied today and how they were applied in the past. [[File:Fayol.jpg]]
--&gt;

=== Fayol's Elements (or functions) of Management ===
Within his theory, Fayol outlined five elements of management that depict the kinds of behaviors managers should engage in so that the goals and objectives of an organization are effectively met. The five elements of management are:

#[[Planning]]:  creating a plan of action for the future, determining the stages of the plan and the technology necessary to implement it. Deciding in advance what to do, how to do it, when to do it, and who should do it. It maps the path from where the organization is to where it wants to be. The planning function involves establishing goals and arranging them in a logical order. Administrators engage in both short-range and long-range planning.
#[[Organizing (management)|Organizing]]:  Once a plan of action is designed, managers need to provide everything necessary to carry it out; including raw materials, tools, capital and human resources. Identifying responsibilities, grouping them into departments or divisions, and specifying organizational relationships.
#[[Leadership|Command]]:  Managers need to implement the plan.  They must have an understanding of the strengths and weaknesses of their personnel. Leading people in a manner that achieves the goals of the organization requires proper [[allocation of resources]] and an effective support system.  Directing requires exceptional interpersonal skills and the ability to motivate people. One of the crucial issues in directing is the correct balance between staff needs and production.
#[[Coordination problem|Coordination]]:  High-level managers must work to "harmonize" all the activities to facilitate organizational success.  Communication is the prime coordinating mechanism. Synchronizes the elements of the organization and must take into account delegation of authority and responsibility and span of control within units.
#[[Control (management)|Control]]:  The final element of management involves the comparison of the activities of the personnel to the plan of action, it is the evaluation component of management. Monitoring function that evaluates quality in all areas and detects potential or actual deviations from the organization's plan, ensuring high-quality performance and satisfactory results while maintaining an orderly and problem-free environment. Controlling includes information management, measurement of performance, and institution of corrective actions.

===Effects of Written Communication===
Fayol believed that animosity and unease within the workplace occurred among employees in different departments.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Brunsson|first=K.|title=Some Effects of Fayolism|journal=International Studies Of Management &amp; Organization|year=2008|volume=38|issue=1|pages=30–47}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Many of these "misunderstandings" were thought to be caused by improper communication, mainly through letters (or in present-day emails).  Among scholars of organizational communication and psychology, letters were perceived to induce or solidify a hierarchical structure within the organization.  Through this type of vertical communication, many individuals gained a false feeling of importance.  Furthermore, it gave way to selfish thinking and eventual conflict among employees in the workplace.

This concept was expressed in Fayol's book, ''General and Industrial Management'', by stating," in some firms... employees in neighboring departments with numerous points of contact, or even employees within a department, who could quite easily meet, communicate with each other in writing... there is to be observed a certain amount of animosity prevailing between different departments or different employees within a department. The system of written communication usually brings this result. There is a way of putting an end to this deplorable system ... and that is to forbid all communication in writing which could easily and advantageously be replaced by verbal ones."

==Administrative Theory in the Modern Workplace==

Fayol believed that managerial practices were key to predictability and efficiency in organizations. The Administrative theory views communication as a necessary ingredient to successful management and many of Fayol's practices are still alive in today's workplace.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=McLean|first=Jacqueline|title=Fayol-Standing the test of time|journal=British Journal of Administrative Management|year=2011|issue=74|pages=32–33}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The elements and principles of management can be found in modern organizations in several ways: as accepted practices in some industries, as revamped versions of the original principles or elements, or as remnants of the organization's history to which alternative practices and philosophies are being offered. The U.S. military is a prime example of an organization that has continued to use these principles.

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== Further reading ==
* Breeze, John D., and Frederick C. Miner. "Henri Fayol: A New Definition of" Administration"." ''Academy of Management Proceedings.'' Vol. 1980. No. 1. Academy of Management, 1980.
* [[Henri Fayol|Fayol, Henri]], and John Adair Coubrough. ''Industrial and general administration.'' (1930).
* [[Henri Fayol|Fayol, Henri]]. ''General and industrial management.'' (1954).
* [[Henri Fayol|Fayol, Henri]]. ''General Principles of Management.'' (1976).
* Modaff, Daniel P., Sue DeWine, and Jennifer A. Butler.'' Organizational communication: Foundations, challenges, and misunderstandings.'' Pearson/Allyn &amp; Bacon, 2008.
* Pearson, Norman M. "Fayolism as the necessary complement of Taylorism." ''American Political Science Review'' 39.01 (1945): 68-80.
* Parker, Lee D., and Philip A. Ritson. "Revisiting Fayol: anticipating contemporary management." ''British Journal of Management'' 16.3 (2005): 175-194.
* Pugh, Derek S. "Modern organization theory: A psychological and sociological study." ''Psychological Bulletin'' 66.4 (1966): 235.
* Reid, Donald. "The genesis of fayolism." ''Sociologie du travail'' 28.1 (1986): 75-93.
* Carl A Rodrigues.  (2001). "Fayol's 14 principles of management then and now: A framework for managing today's organizations effectively." ''Management Decision,'' 39(10), 880-889.
* [[Wren, Daniel A.]] "Was Henri Fayol a Real Manager?." ''Academy of Management Proceedings.'' Vol. 1990. No. 1. Academy of Management, 1990.

[[Category:Management]]</text>
      <sha1>6dq6c8idjct0273jekcvk2m8nq38xhr</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>List of business terms</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3349994</id>
    <revision>
      <id>860598738</id>
      <parentid>860422862</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-09-21T19:39:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Colonies Chris</username>
        <id>577301</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* References */minor fixes</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="9578">The following terms are in everyday use in financial regions, such as commercial '''[[business]]''' and the '''[[management]]''' of large [[organisation]]s such as [[corporation]]s.
{{Dynamic list}}

== Abbreviations ==

{| class="wikitable sortable" border="1" 
|-
! Abbreviation
! Definition
|-deser
| 24/7
| [[24/7|24 hours a day, 7 days a week]]
|-
| BPO
| [[Business process outsourcing]]
|-
| CAO
| [[Chief Accounting Officer]]
|-
|CDO
|[[Chief data officer|Chief Data Officer]]
|-
| CEO
| [[Chief Executive Officer]]
|-
| CFO
| [[Chief Financial Officer]]
|-
| CIO
| [[Chief Information Officer]], [[Chief Investment Officer]], or [[Chief Innovation Officer]]
|-
| CISO
| [[Chief Information Security Officer]]
|-
| CLO
| [[Chief Legal Officer]]
|-
| CMO
| [[Chief Marketing Officer]]
|-
| COB
| Close of business&lt;ref name="wolfson"/&gt;
|-
| COO
| [[Chief Operating Officer]]
|-
| CPO
| [[Chief People Officer]] also [[Chief procurement officer]]
|-
| CSA
| [[Customer Service Advisor]]
|-
| CTA
| Call to action&lt;ref name="wolfson"/&gt;
|-
|CRO
|[[Chief revenue officer|Chief Revenue Officer]]
|-
| CTO
| [[Chief Technical Officer]]
|-
| CSW
| [[Completed Staff Work]]
|-
| CxO
| Any chief officer(s), x being a placeholder. Chief [Placeholder] Officer.
|-
| [[Earnings before interest, taxes, depreciation, and amortization|EBITDA]]
| Earnings before interest, taxes, depreciation, and amortization
|-
| EOB
| End of the business day; for example, by 6:00 p.m. in the U.S. (same as Close of Business)
|-
| EOD
| End of day
|-
| FTE
| full-time equivalent
|-
| FY
| [[fiscal year]]
|-
| HIBBIS
| Heads in Beds, Butts in Seats (hotel industry)
|-
| HR
| [[human resources]]
|-
| ITT
| [[Invitation to tender]]
|-
| KPI
| [[Key performance indicators]]&lt;ref name="wolfson"/&gt;
|-
| MILE
| Maximum impact, little effort&lt;ref name="wolfson"/&gt;
|-
| NDA
| [[Non-disclosure agreement]]
|-
| PCP
| Previous corresponding period (Used when comparing sales over corresponding periods)
|-
| RFI
| Request for Information (about goods/services to be supplied)&lt;ref name="wolfson"/&gt;
|-
| RFP
| Request for Proposal
|-
| RFQ
| Request for Quote
|-
| RFX
| Request for information, proposal, or quotation (''x'' is a placeholder)
|-
| POS
| [[Point of Sale]]
|-
| R&amp;D
| [[Research and Development]]
|-
| RIF
| [[Reduction in Force]]
|-
| ROI
| [[Return on Investment]]
|-
| SBU
| [[Strategic Business Unit]]
|-
| SME
| [[Subject Matter Expert]] or [[Small and medium-sized enterprises|Small to Medium Enterprise]]
|-
| TCO
| [[Total Cost of Ownership]]
|-
| USP
| [[Unique Selling Proposition]]/Point
|-
| VP
| [[Vice president]]
|-
| WC
| Week Commencing
|-
| WE
| Week Ending
|-
| YoY
| Year on Year (current vs prior)
|-
| YTD
| Year to date
|-
|}

== Noun phrases ==

{| class="wikitable sortable" border="1" 
|-
! Noun phrase
! Definition
|-deser
|30,000 foot view
| Program management view
|-
|50,000 foot view
| Highest management overview
|-
|Bandwidth
| Availability&lt;ref name="wolfson"/&gt;
|-
|Benchmark
|Measuring against
|-
|Best practice
| Tried and tested methodology/process
|-
|Blue sky thinking
| Idealistic or visionary ideas, not always with practical application (source: BBC)
|-
|Bottleneck
| Where a process is held up
|-
|Cascade
| Array of possible actions to take in response to a problem: protocol
|-
|Check in the box
| Complete the task
|-
|Cross-functional
| Works in multiple directions simultaneously
|-
|Customer-centric
| The customer is the main focus
|-
|Cutting edge practices
| Up to date or new methods
|-
|[[Dashboards (management information systems)|Dashboard]]
| Collection of key indicators
|-
|Deliverable(s)
| Finished product or outcome
|-
|Downsize
| Reduce the number of employees through a lay-off
|-
|End-user perspective
| Point of view of a customer about a product or service
|-
|Evergreen
| Content that is always relevant&lt;ref name="wolfson"/&gt;
|-
|Flavour of the month
| The current popular or trending activity
|-
|[[Golden handshake]]
| Contract clause which richly rewards a key employee in the case of termination
|-
|[[Golden parachute]]
| Contract clause richly (perhaps excessively) rewarding a key executive if termination is due to corporate takeover or merger
|-
|Hard stop
| Deadline&lt;ref name="wolfson"/&gt;
|-
|Hub
| A central idea to which other ideas are linked
|-
|In the loop
| Knowing what's going on and being kept informed
|-
|In the weeds
| Immersed or entangled in details or complexities
|-
|Joined-up thinking
| Discussing the viewpoints of each organization and coming to an agreement or compromise
|-
|{{anchor|Low-hanging fruit}}Low-hanging fruit
| Tasks that have the greatest positive effect for the least effort, used when promoting new projects to show the advantages.&lt;ref name="wolfson"&gt; {{cite web
 | url = https://moneyish.com/ish/18-obnoxious-things-that-everyone-should-stop-saying-in-the-office/
 | title = 18 obnoxious things that everyone in the office should stop saying
 | author = Alisa Wolfson
 | publisher = Moneyish.com / Dow Jones &amp; Company
 | date = June 23, 2017
}} &lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|Lay-off
| Redundancies on a large scale 
|-
|[[Nesting (process)|Nesting]]
| Processes within processes
|-
|Off the shelf
| Buying in a product or service that is already completed
|-
|One button to push/Push of a button
| Reduced number of suppliers
|-
|[[Operational excellence]]
| Sustainable improvement of key performance metrics
|-
|Python
| Challenging problem&lt;ref name="wolfson"/&gt;
|-
|Raft of measures
| A collection of proposals or schemes
|-
|Rattler
| Obvious problem&lt;ref name="wolfson"/&gt;
|-
|Run it up the flagpole
| Moving a project along to the next appropriate person&lt;ref name="wolfson"/&gt;
|-
|Scalability
| A small component's ability to grow within a larger system&lt;ref name="wolfson"/&gt;
|-
|Silo (Vertical and Horizontal)
| A system, process, department, etc. that operates in isolation from others.
|-
|Silver bullet
| One solution for everything, especially vampires{{dubious|date=June 2017}}
|-
|[[Six Sigma]]
| A system for process improvement by error reduction
|-
|Stakeholders
| Group or individual affected by the outcome of a decision
|-
|Talent
| Employees
|-
|Tent pole
| The task or item most likely to delay a project or consume the most resources
|-
|Under-pinning
| The foundations of an idea, which helps another related scheme or proposal
|-
|[[Unique selling proposition]] (USP)
| Any aspect of an object that differentiates it from similar objects
|-
|Win-win solution
| Providing a product or service which makes everyone happy, particularly both buyer and seller
|-
|}

== Verb phrases ==

{| class="wikitable sortable" border="1" 
|-
! Verb phrase
! Definition
|-deser
|Action that
| Put something into practice&lt;ref name="wolfson"/&gt;
|-
|Baked in
| Something which has been "baked in" is implied to be impossible to remove.
|-
|Boil the ocean
| Undertake an impossible or impractical task &lt;ref name="wolfson"/&gt;
|-
|Buck the trend
| To follow an action against market tendencies
|-
|Build capacity
| Take actions which increase the amount of work that can be done in the future.
|-
|Circle back
| Discuss later&lt;ref name="wolfson"/&gt;
|-
|[[Circle the wagons]]
| Defensive strategy to provide time to plan or produce a better solution
|-
|Cover all directions of the compass
| Ensure the product specification covers everything
|-
|Create the storyboard
| Outline what the solution will look like
|-
|Deep dive
| Get into the detail
|-
|Drill down
|Investigate in depth &lt;ref name="wolfson"/&gt;
|-
|Have the vendor in our pocket
| Keep a vendor/contractors paid
|-
|Ideate
| Come up with ideas&lt;ref name="wolfson"/&gt;
|-
|Land and expand
| To sell a small solution and then grow it within the client's environment
|-
|Make hay
| Productive or successful in a short time&lt;ref name="wolfson"/&gt;
|-
|Moving forward
|  Making progress on an idea or scheme
|-
|Move the goal posts
| Change the criteria for success&lt;ref name="wolfson"/&gt;
|-
|Pick the low-hanging fruit
| Go (initially) for the easiest options &lt;ref name="wolfson"/&gt;
|-
|Power to the elbow
| Get additional backup information to make your case stronger
|-
|Pull the plug
| Close a venture that is losing money or has no prospects of success
|-
|Punt
| Relinquish responsibility&lt;ref name="wolfson"/&gt;
|-
|Pushing the envelope
| Going outside normal boundaries to achieve a target or goal (such as exceeding specifications)
|-
|Put this on your radar
| Consider this&lt;ref name="wolfson"/&gt;
|-
|Scrub the numbers
| Find errors&lt;ref name="wolfson"/&gt;
|-
|Sing from the same hymn sheet
| Show a united front, or everyone understanding and saying the same thing to clientele.
|-
|Table the conversation
| Reconvene at a later time&lt;ref name="wolfson"/&gt;
|-
|Test the water
| 'Put your toe' into a market to determine its temperature.
|-
|Touch base
| To meet up with a colleague to discuss progress (from baseball)
|-
|Touch base offline
| Meet and talk&lt;ref name="wolfson"/&gt;
|-
|Tranch up the workload
| Divide responsibilities&lt;ref name="wolfson"/&gt;
|-
|Trim the fat
| Cut excess budgets, remove avoidable costs &lt;ref name="wolfson"/&gt;
|-
|Unscramble that egg
| Take care of that mess&lt;ref name="wolfson"/&gt;
|-
|}

==See also==
* [[Buzzwords]]
* [[Corporate communication]]
* [[Corporate jargon]]
* [[Doublespeak]]
* [[Euphemism]]
* [[Obfuscation]]

==References==
{{reflist}}
*{{citation |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Jz_-yyHwMGcC&amp;pg=PA314|chapter=A glossary of business terms |title=Business English |year=2004 |isbn=9780764124440}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Business terms}}
[[Category:Business-related lists|Terms]]
[[Category:Wikipedia glossaries|Business]]</text>
      <sha1>0rosbpavi73xk1bit5ezb3l6qk9elkg</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Management process</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>401046</id>
    <revision>
      <id>826645039</id>
      <parentid>822293367</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-02-20T07:27:00Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Marcocapelle</username>
        <id>14965160</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>removed [[Category:Project management]]; added [[Category:Management]] using [[WP:HC|HotCat]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="1416">{{Refimprove|date=December 2009}}
'''Management process''' is a process of setting goals, [[plan]]ning and/or [[Control (management)|controlling]] the [[organizing (management)|organizing]] and leading the execution of any type of activity, such as: 
* a [[project]] ([[project management process]]) or
* a process ([[process management]] process, sometimes referred to as the process performance measurement and management system).

An [[organization]]'s [[senior management]] is responsible for carrying out its management process. However, this is not always the case for all management processes, for example, it is the responsibility of the project manager to carry out a project management process.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pmhut.com/the-simplified-project-management-process The Simplified Project Management Process] Accessed: 2010-05-02.&lt;/ref&gt;


==Steps==
'''Planning,'' it determines the objectives, evaluate the different alternatives and choose the best
'''Organizing,''' define group's functions, establish relationships and defining authority irresponsibility
'''Staffing,''' recruitment or placement and selection or training takes place for the development of  members in the firm
'''directing,''' is to give the Direction to the employes.

==See also==
*[[Business process]]
*[[Project management]]
*[[Project planning]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Management Process}}
[[Category:Management]]</text>
      <sha1>r4vueb8kr6kty58kcqkrr4fctkb9qll</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Open Options Corporation</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>19975724</id>
    <revision>
      <id>799350701</id>
      <parentid>758876187</parentid>
      <timestamp>2017-09-07T04:39:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>KolbertBot</username>
        <id>31691822</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Bot: [[User:KolbertBot|HTTP→HTTPS]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="2224">'''Open Options Corporation''' is a privately owned business strategy consulting company that specializes in applied [[game theory]] and [[business war games]] where there are multiple stakeholders who can all influence the final outcome of a particular situation.

Open Options’ original software development was funded by the [[CIA]] through a company called Waterloo Engineering Software. The software was designed to help the American government better anticipate the collapse of the Soviet Union into many different breakaway republics.&lt;ref name= "Globe and Mail"&gt; https://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20070125.rmgame0125/BNStory/specialROBmagazine/home &lt;/ref&gt; The software was based on academic research by Dr. Niall Fraser from the [[University of Waterloo]]. Dr. Fraser has written several books on game theory including Mathematical Modeling of Resolutions of Conflict&lt;ref name= "Mathematical Modeling of Resolutions"&gt;  Okada, N, K.W. Hipel, N.M. Fraser and M. Fukushima (1988). Mathematical Modeling of Resolutions of Conflict, Kyoto Japan: Gendai Sugakusha (in Japanese).&lt;/ref&gt; and Conflict Analysis: Models and Resolutions.&lt;ref name= "Conflict Analysis"&gt;  Fraser, N.M. and K.W. Hipel (1984). Conflict Analysis: Models and Resolutions. New York: North-Holland. &lt;/ref&gt;

Open Options uses a type of game theory called Ordinal Non-cooperative Game Theory which is a less well-known sub-section of game theory.&lt;ref name = "Globe and Mail" /&gt; However, this approach and proprietary software enables Open Options to analyze millions of possible outcomes.&lt;ref name = "Globe and Mail" /&gt;&lt;ref name= "Economist"&gt;http://www.economist.com/business/displaystory.cfm?story_id=9257879 &lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name= "Risk Management Magazine"&gt; http://www.rmmag.com/MGTemplate.cfm?Section=MagArchive&amp;NavMenuID=304&amp;template=/Magazine/DisplayMagazines.cfm&amp;Archive=1&amp;IssueID=212&amp;AID=2316&amp;Volume=51&amp;ShowArticle=1&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name= "CFO magazine"&gt; http://www.cfo.com/article.cfm/11700044?f=search &lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}
[https://pdx.academia.edu/nathanFlow business ideas]

==External links==
*[http://openoptions.com Company website]

[[Category:Game theory]]
[[Category:Business planning]]
[[Category:Consulting firms]]</text>
      <sha1>ryyqeo9jvh0yjvlsnsx8n1oghqs1aue</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Oxford Global Islamic Branding and Marketing Forum</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>26604528</id>
    <revision>
      <id>766849463</id>
      <parentid>722891798</parentid>
      <timestamp>2017-02-22T14:04:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bender the Bot</username>
        <id>28903366</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* About the Forum */HTTP&amp;rarr;HTTPS for [[The New York Times]]. using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="5181">{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2013}}
{{orphan|date=April 2010}}
The '''Oxford Global Islamic Branding and Marketing Forum'''  is a two-day forum that brings together over 250 business leaders, branding and marketing experts and thought leaders to discuss and understand the key issues that face the growth of the Muslim market.

==About the Forum==
According to the Pew Research Center a comprehensive demographic study (Mapping the Global Muslim Population)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=ANALYSIS 7 October 2009 |url=http://pewforum.org/docs/?DocID=450 |title=Mapping the Global Muslim Population - Pew Forum on Religion &amp; Public Life |publisher=Pewforum.org |date=2009-10-07 |accessdate=2011-11-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;   of more than 200 countries finds that there are 1.57 billion Muslims of all ages living in the world today, representing 23% of an estimated 2009 world population of 6.8 billion. Not only is the Muslim population a significant percentage of the global population but AT Kearney&lt;ref&gt;http://www.atkearney.com/images/global/pdf/AddressingMuslimMarket_S.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;  also point out that the market for sharia compliant products or services – that is products and services that confirm to Islamic Law – totals US$2trillion annually and is growing rapidly.

As Muslim countries develop, there is an expressed need to develop and market their own brands to the rest of the world. Additionally, there is massive interest amongst non-Muslim companies in how to enter and penetrate this global market, which spans many industries, including finance, food and beverage, cosmetics, healthcare, pharmaceuticals, logistics, tourism, fashion, and others.

This Forum brings Muslim and non-Muslim leaders and companies from a variety of business sectors together to discuss how to develop better trade and business relations and to learn from each other about the markets involved and to facilitate greater understanding of each other.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Miles Young, Campaign, 8 June 2007, 12:00AM |url=http://www.brandrepublic.com/InDepth/Analysis/663467/World-Islamic-branding-meets-eye/ |title=The World: More to Islamic branding than meets the eye? - Brand Republic News |publisher=Brandrepublic.com |date=2007-06-08 |accessdate=2011-11-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; This is a new and growing area of marketing and branding that has not been fully understood but is gaining interest from the business world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Story |first=Louise |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/28/business/28muslim.html?scp=1&amp;sq=Rewriting%20the%20Ad%20Rules%20for%20Muslim-Americans&amp;st=cse |title=Rewriting the Ad Rules for Muslim-Americans - New York Times |publisher=Nytimes.com |date=2007-04-28 |accessdate=2011-11-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
Islam is one religion, but within the Islamic global population there are many markets that behave differently from cultural and business perspectives and both Muslim and non-Muslim marketers seek to understand these differences effectively to address their needs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=editor |url=http://mediame.com/news/interview_opinion/roy_haddad_understanding_the_islamic_consumers |title=Roy Haddad: Understanding the Islamic Consumers |publisher=mediaME |date=2008-07-02 |accessdate=2011-11-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Role Players ==

The confirmed role players include The Honourable Dato' Sri Mohd [[Najib Tun Razak]], [[Prime Minister of Malaysia]]; H.E. [[Shaukat Aziz]], former Prime Minister of Pakistan; Lord Nazir Ahmed, Life Peer of the House of Lords of the UK Parliament; Mr Miles Young, CEO of [[Ogilvy &amp; Mather]] Worldwide; Rafi-uddin Shikoh, CEO, The Dinar Standard; Tan Sri Dato’ H. Muhammad-Ali, President &amp; CEO, Johor Corporation; Arif Zaman, Principal Consultant, Reputation Institute; Datuk Seri Farid Ridzuan, CEO, [[Media Prima]], Malaysia

Issues in Islamic Branding &amp; Marketing:
* "The Role of Muslim Nations in Rebuilding Today’s Global Economy."
* "Understanding Muslim Consumers: Are Muslims the Same the World Over? What are the Ethnographic, Demographic and Behavioural Similarities and Differences Across Global Muslim Markets ? Where is the Purchasing Power? What are the Implications for Branding and Marketing Strategies?"
* "Islamic Branding: The Next Big Thing? What are the best communications channels to reach Muslim markets? What should the media industry take into consideration?"
* "What is the role of e-business and new social networking media in Muslim communities in different Muslim countries?"
* "What are the Innovative Branding and Marketing Developments in Muslim Countries? Do ‘Western’ strategies apply?"

== Organiser ==

The organiser is the Executive Education Department of the [[Said Business School]] of [[Oxford University]].

== References ==
&lt;!--- See [[Wikipedia:Footnotes]] on how to create references using &lt;ref&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; tags which will then appear here automatically --&gt;
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
* Official Homepage of the Oxford Global Islamic Branding &amp; Marketing Forum:[http://www.sbs.oxford.edu/islamicmarketing]
* Said Business School Homepage: [http://www.sbs.ox.ac.uk]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Oxford Global Islamic Branding And Marketing Forum}}
[[Category:Business conferences]]
[[Category:Events in Oxford]]</text>
      <sha1>4b2rowxgnsb2xw2yhmvukn6in5y97kt</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Ralph Kimball</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3265765</id>
    <revision>
      <id>845643615</id>
      <parentid>835625351</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-06-13T05:19:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>202.36.133.130</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>remove crap</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="7136">{{about||the Wyoming Supreme Court judge|Ralph Kimball (judge)|the English cricketer|Ralph Kimbell}}
{{BLP sources|date=March 2014}}
{{notability|biographies|date=December 2015}}
'''Ralph Kimball''' (born 1944) is an author on the subject of [[data warehousing]] and [[business intelligence]]. He is one of the original architects of [[data warehousing]] and is known for long-term convictions that data warehouses must be designed to be understandable and fast. 
His methodology, also known as [[dimensional modeling]] or the Kimball methodology, has become the de facto standard in the area of [[decision support]].

He is the principal author of the best-selling&lt;ref name="2012-09-28_Informatica" /&gt; books ''The Data Warehouse Toolkit'',&lt;ref name="Whitehorn_2010-03-09_CW" /&gt; ''The Data Warehouse Lifecycle Toolkit'', ''The Data Warehouse ETL Toolkit'' and ''The Kimball Group Reader'', published by Wiley and Sons.

==Career==
After receiving a Ph.D.&lt;ref name="2012-09-28_Informatica" /&gt; in 1973 from [[Stanford University]] in electrical engineering (specializing in man-machine systems), Ralph joined the [[PARC (company)|Xerox Palo Alto Research Center]] (PARC). At PARC Ralph was a principal designer of the [[Xerox Star]] Workstation, the first commercial product to use mice, icons and windows.

Kimball then became vice president of applications at Metaphor Computer Systems, a [[decision support system|decision support software]] and services provider. He developed the Capsule Facility in 1982. The Capsule was a graphical programming technique which connected icons together in a logical flow, allowing a very visual style of programming for non-programmers. The Capsule was used to build reporting and analysis applications at Metaphor.

Kimball founded Red Brick Systems in 1986, serving as CEO until 1992. Red Brick Systems was acquired by Informix, which is now owned by [[IBM]].&lt;ref name="2015-12-11_IBM" /&gt; Red Brick was known for its [[relational database]] optimized for data warehousing. Their claim to fame was the use of bit-map [[Index (database)|Indexes]] in order to achieve performance gains that amounted to almost 10 times that of other Database vendors at that time.

Ralph Kimball Associates incorporated in 1992 to provide data warehouse consulting and education.

The Kimball Group, founded by Kimball,&lt;ref name="2012-09-28_Informatica" /&gt; formalized existing long-term relationships between Ralph Kimball Associates, DecisionWorks Consulting, and InfoDynamics LLC.

==Bibliography==
* {{Cite book |last=Kimball |first=Ralph |author2=Margy Ross  |title=The Data Warehouse Toolkit: The Definitive Guide to Dimensional Modeling |edition=3rd|publisher=Wiley |year=2013 |isbn=978-1-118-53080-1 }}
* {{Cite book |last=Kimball |first=Ralph |author2=Margy Ross  |title=The Kimball Group Reader |publisher=Wiley |year=2010 |isbn=978-0-470-56310-6 }}
* {{Cite book |last=Kimball |first=Ralph |author2=Margy Ross |author3=Warren Thornthwaite |author4=Joy Mundy |author5=Bob Becker  |title=The Data Warehouse Lifecycle Toolkit |edition=2nd |publisher=Wiley |year=2008 |isbn=978-0-470-14977-5 }}
* {{Cite book |last=Kimball |first=Ralph |author2=Joe Caserta  |title=The Data Warehouse ETL Toolkit |publisher=Wiley |year=2004 |isbn=0-7645-6757-8 }}
* {{Cite book |last=Kimball|first=Ralph |author2=Margy Ross  |title=The Data Warehouse Toolkit: The Complete Guide to Dimensional Modeling |edition=2nd |publisher=Wiley |year=2002 |isbn=0-471-20024-7 }}
* {{Cite book |last=Kimball |first=Ralph |author2=Richard Merz  |title=The Data Webhouse Toolkit: Building the Web-Enabled Data Warehouse |publisher=Wiley |year=2000 |isbn=0-471-37680-9 }}
* {{Cite book |last=Kimball |first=Ralph |title=The Data Warehouse Lifecycle Toolkit |publisher=Wiley |year=1998 |isbn=0-471-25547-5 |display-authors=etal}}
* {{Cite book |last=Kimball |first=Ralph |title=The Data Warehouse Toolkit |publisher=Wiley |year=1996 |isbn=978-0-471-15337-5 }}

== References ==
{{Reflist|refs=

 &lt;ref name="2015-12-11_IBM"&gt;{{cite web
 |url         = http://www.ibm.com/software/data/informix/redbrick/
 |title       = IBM Red Brick Warehouse
 |publisher   = [[IBM]]
 |date        = 2015-12-11
 |accessdate  = 2017-03-04
 |archiveurl  = https://archive.is/20151211202207/http://www-03.ibm.com/software/products/en/redbrick
 |archivedate = 2015-12-11
 |quote       = 
 |deadurl     = yes
 |df          = 
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

 &lt;ref name="2012-09-28_Informatica"&gt;{{cite web
 |url         = https://www.informatica.com/about-us/news/news-releases/2012/09/20120928-dr-ralph-kimball-and-informatica-host-big-data-best-practices-webinar.html
 |title       = Dr. Ralph Kimball and Informatica Host Big Data Best Practices Webinar Industry Leaders and Innovators Share Newly Emerging Best Practices for Big Data
 |publisher   = [[Informatica]]
 |date        = 2012-09-28
 |accessdate  = 2015-12-11
 |archiveurl  = https://www.webcitation.org/6dhhpaSNd?url=https://www.informatica.com/about-us/news/news-releases/2012/09/20120928-dr-ralph-kimball-and-informatica-host-big-data-best-practices-webinar.html
 |archivedate = 2015-12-11
 |quote       = Dr. Ralph Kimball, founder of the Kimball Group, is known worldwide as an innovator, writer, educator, speaker and consultant in the field of data warehousing. He has remained steadfast in his long-term conviction that data warehouses must be designed to be understandable and fast. Ralph's books on dimensional design techniques have become the all-time best sellers in data warehousing and he has trained more than 10,000 IT professionals around the globe. Prior to founding Kimball Group, he worked at Metaphor, founded Red Brick Systems and co-invented the Star workstation at Xerox's Palo Alto Research Center (PARC). Ralph has his Ph.D. in Electrical Engineering from Stanford University.
 |deadurl     = yes
 |df          = 
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

 &lt;ref name="Whitehorn_2010-03-09_CW"&gt;{{cite web
  | url = http://www.computerweekly.com/news/2240016833/Inmon-vs-Kimball-data-warehousing-the-debate-over-DW-architecture
  | title = Inmon vs. Kimball data warehousing: the debate over DW architecture
  | last = Whitehorn
  | first = Mark
  | authorlink =
  | publisher = [[ComputerWeekly.com]]
  | date = 2010-03-09
  | accessdate =  2015-12-11
  | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20151003080126/http://www.computerweekly.com/news/2240016833/Inmon-vs-Kimball-data-warehousing-the-debate-over-DW-architecture
  | archivedate = 2015-10-03
  | quote = Indeed, the fact that [[Bill Inmon|Inmon]] wrote a foreword for the first edition of Kimball’s book The Data Warehouse Toolkit tells us that they probably take a balanced view.
 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

}}

==External links==
* [http://www.kimballgroup.com/ Kimball Group]
* [http://www.kimballgroup.com/2004/03/differences-of-opinion/ Differences of Opinion: The Kimball bus architecture and the Corporate Information Factory]

{{Data warehouse}}

{{Authority control}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Kimball, Ralph}}
[[Category:Business intelligence]]
[[Category:Data warehousing]]
[[Category:Technical writers]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:1944 births]]
[[Category:Scientists at PARC]]</text>
      <sha1>4biamjuzi40v8jo596vk06ahwvqwrvx</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Relational contract</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>25539116</id>
    <revision>
      <id>852890772</id>
      <parentid>791102577</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-08-01T02:02:05Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ad Orientem</username>
        <id>13259281</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Removing link(s): [[Wikipedia:Articles for deletion/International Association for Contract and Commercial Management]] closed as soft delete ([[WP:XFDC|XFDcloser]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="9761">A '''relational contract''' is a [[contract]] whose effect is based upon a relationship of [[trust (social sciences)|trust]] between the parties to which it pertains.  The explicit terms of the contract are just an outline as there are implicit terms and understandings which determine the behaviour of the parties.

Relational contract theory was originally developed in the United States by the legal scholars [[Ian Roderick Macneil]] and [[Stewart Macaulay]].  According to Macneil it offered a response to the so-called “[[Death of Contract]]” school’s nihilistic argument that contract was not a fit subject for study as a whole; each different type of contract (e.g., sales, employment, negotiable instruments) could be studied individually, but not “contracts-in-gross”.&lt;ref&gt;I.R. Macneil, “Whither Contracts?” (1969) 21 ''Journal of Legal Education'' 403.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |url=http://www.ft.com/cms/s/0/cc712f1a-3134-11df-8e6f-00144feabdc0.html |publisher=Financial Times |title=Think before you tear up an unwritten contract |author=John Kay |date=March 16, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Macneil explains that this is only one of a number of possible relational theories of contracts, and accordingly renamed his own version “essential contract theory”.&lt;ref&gt;I.R. Macneil, “Contracting Worlds and Essential Contract Theory” (2000) ''[[Social &amp; Legal Studies]]'' 9, 431.&lt;/ref&gt;

Relational contract theory is characterized by a view of contracts as relations rather than as discrete transactions (which, Macneil argued,&lt;ref&gt;I.R. Macneil, “The Many Futures of Contract” (1974) 47 ''Southern California Law Review'' 691&lt;/ref&gt; traditional “classical” or "[[neo-classical contract]]" theory treats contracts as being). Thus, even a simple transaction can properly be understood as involving a wider social and economic context. For instance, if A purchases a packet of cigarettes from a shop he has never been into before and will never enter again, that seems quite discrete. However, A will almost certainly have a loyalty to a particular brand of cigarettes and expectations about quality about which he would be prepared to complain to the manufacturer, although he has no contractual privity with the manufacturer. There is also an understanding that A will pay for the cigarettes, not simply run off with them, and that if he tenders a £10 note in exchange for the cigarettes which are priced at £6, the paper money will be acceptable and change of £4 will be given. None of this is explicitly stated between the parties, whose conversation is likely limited to “20 Marlboro, please” on A’s part and “That’ll be £6, please” on the part of the retailer. Thus, even the simplest transaction has a good deal that is unstated and dependent on a wider web of social and economic relations. How far outwards into that web one needs to investigate will depend on the transaction and on the purpose for which it is being examined.&lt;ref&gt;I.R. Macneil, “Reflections on Relational Contract Theory After a Neoclassical Seminar” in H. Collins, D. Campbell and J. Wightman (Eds), ''The Implicit Dimensions of Contract'' (Hart: Oxford, 2003).&lt;/ref&gt;

Although earlier writing&lt;ref&gt;I.R. Macneil, “The Many Futures of Contract” (1974) 47 ''Southern California Law Review'' 691; I.R. Macneil, “Contracts: Adjustment of Long-Term Economic Relations Under Classical, Neoclassical and Relational Contract Law” (1978) 72 ''Northwestern University Law Review'' 340.&lt;/ref&gt;  may be taken in places to suggest that the substantive rules of contract law need to be reframed to acknowledge the relational, non-discrete nature of contracts, this has not been subsequently pursued and current scholars have argued that it is neither possible nor necessary to reform the law of contract itself to work effectively with relationally-constituted contracts.&lt;ref&gt;See, M. Eisenberg, “Why There is No Law of Relational Contracts” (2000) 94 ''Northwestern University Law Review'' 805; R. Austen-Baker, “A Relational Law of Contract?” (2004) 20 ''Journal of Contract Law'' 125.&lt;/ref&gt;

Other characteristics of relational contract theory are that “contract” is understood to cover economic exchange in general, not just contracts that would be recognized as legally enforceable agreements by courts in any given jurisdiction, that relations are mostly held together by their own internal values and wider social/economic factors, and, at least in relational theory in the Macneil mould, that exchange relations are governed by a number of norms. This last is not to say that relational contract theory is normative in nature, setting out what ought to be the case properly, but rather that there are actual observable normal characteristics or factors at play in relations. Macneil’s essential contract theory offers some 14 norms.&lt;ref&gt;See Wikipedia article [[Ian Roderick Macneil]].&lt;/ref&gt;

The English contracts scholar Richard Austen-Baker has more recently proposed an alternative version of relational contract theory, called “comprehensive contract theory”, which posits four “comprehensive contract norms” in place of Macneil’s 14, though Austen-Baker does not deny the validity of Macneil’s norms as a complex tool of analysis.&lt;ref&gt;R. Austen-Baker, “Comprehensive Contract Theory: A Four-Norm Model of Contract Relations” (2009) 25 ''Journal of Contract Law'' 216.&lt;/ref&gt;  The Japanese scholar Takashi Uchida has proposed a version of relational contract theory inspired by Macneil, relating it to the Japanese situation.&lt;ref&gt;See, e.g.,  T. Uchida, “The New Development of Contract Law and General Clauses – A Japanese Perspective” in The Organizing Committee (Eds), ''Proceedings of the Symposium: Japanese and Dutch Laws Compared'' (University of Tokyo Centre for Comparative Law and Politics Institute of Comparative Law: Tokyo, 1993).&lt;/ref&gt; Other notable contributions to relational contract theory have been made by Stewart Macaulay (U.S.), Lisa Bernstein (U.S.), [[David Campbell (legal academic)|David Campbell]] (England) and John Wightman (England).

Recent research from the International Association for Contract and Commercial Management, the [[University of Tennessee]] and [http://www.lindahl.se/en/home/ Lindahl law firm] takes the relational contracting theories expressed by Macneil, Macaulay and others and makes them relevant for contracting practitioners trying to craft strategic, collaborative relationships with their procurement and outsourced business partners.&lt;ref&gt;"Unpacking Relational Contracts: The Practitioner's Go-To Guide for Understanding Relational Contracts"[http://www.vestedway.com/vested-library/] 2016|Vested Way|accessed 26 October 2016&lt;/ref&gt;
The white paper, &lt;ref&gt;“Unpacking Relational Contracting”&lt;/ref&gt; outlines basic tenets that are foundational to relational contracting, including: communication, risk allocation, problem solving, no-blame culture, joint working, gain and pain sharing, mutual objectives, performance measurement and continuous improvement.
The Unpacking Relational Contracting white paper also describes a five-step process for developing a relational contract:
# Focus on the relationship, not the deal. This step is designed to help build the trust necessary to focus on the relationship. It includes ensuring alignment within the organization and using a process for choosing a partner that considers relational competencies in addition to service offerings, quality levels, etc.
# Establish a Partnership instead of Arms-Length Relationship. This step is designed to explore and lay the foundation of trust, transparency and compatibility between the parties.
# Embed Social Norms in the Relationship. This step is designed helps the parties jointly discover and formally agree to six guiding principles: reciprocity, autonomy, honesty, loyalty, equity, integrity.  
# Avoid and Mitigate Risks by Alignment of Interests. This step lays the foundation for continuously aligning interests, beginning agreement on a shared vision and strategic objectives for the partnership, specifying what joint success and value looks like. 
# Create a Fair and Flexible Framework. Establish a governance framework for continuous relationship management. The parties agree upon the contract clauses that are necessary to establish the more specific rules of the relationship, all of them aligned with the guiding principles.

==Examples of relational contracts==
===Construction examples===
* Integrated Form of Agreement (IFoA) (USA) - developed for Sutter Health projects in California and used by some other healthcare providers
* ConsensusDocs 300 (USA) - a derivative of IFoA
* AIA C191-2009 Standard Form Multi-Party Agreement for IPD (USA)
* AIA C199-2010 Standard Form of Agreement Between Single Purpose Entity and Contractor for Integrated Project Delivery
* PPC2000 International (UK)
* Alliancing Agreement (Australia) - not yet a standard form but moving in that direction
* Integrated Project Delivery Agreement (Profit Deferred Until Final Completion)(USA)
* U.S Department of Energy - transformation of a former weapons facility to a wildlife refuge&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Vitasek|first=Kate, et. al.,|title=Vested: How P&amp;G, McDonald's, and Microsoft are Redefining Winning in Business Relationships|year=2012|publisher=Palgrave Macmillan|location=New York|isbn=0230341705|edition=1st}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [https://www2.iaccm.com/resources/?id=9348 FFG Enterprise]: a collaboration underpinned by a relational contract between the Royal Australian Navy, Defense Industry, and the Capability, Acquisition and Sustainment Group (CASG)

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Relational contract}}
[[Category:Business law]]
[[Category:Contract law]]</text>
      <sha1>gjg0m5xfgw31q2xg1lemyka8m9ynl9m</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>SAS (software)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>990677</id>
    <revision>
      <id>869246051</id>
      <parentid>865895608</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-11-17T10:32:45Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>49.197.5.59</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* References */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="40963">{{About|the software suite||SAS (disambiguation)}}
{{Infobox software
| name                   = SAS
| logo                   = স্যাস লোগো.png
| screenshot             = SAS 9 on Microsoft Windows.png
| caption                = SAS 9 on Microsoft Windows
| developer              = [[SAS Institute]]
| programming language   = [[C (programming language)|C]]
| released               = {{start date and age|1976}}
| latest release version = 9.4
| latest release date    = {{Start date and age|2013|07|10}}
| operating system       = [[Microsoft Windows|Windows]], [[IBM mainframe]], [[Unix]]/[[Linux]], [[OpenVMS|OpenVMS Alpha]]
| genre                  = [[Numerical analysis]]
| license                = [[Proprietary software|Proprietary]]
| website                = {{URL|www.sas.com/en_us/home.html}}
}}

'''SAS''' (previously "'''Statistical Analysis System'''")&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.sas.com/en_us/company-information.html#history|title=About SAS|last=|first=|date=|website=|accessdate=5 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; is a software suite developed by [[SAS Institute]] for advanced analytics, [[multivariate analyses]], [[business intelligence]], [[data management]], and [[predictive analytics]].

SAS was developed at [[North Carolina State University]] from 1966 until 1976, when SAS Institute was incorporated. SAS was further developed in the 1980s and 1990s with the addition of new statistical procedures, additional components and the introduction of [[JMP (statistical software)|JMP]]. A point-and-click interface was added in version 9 in 2004. A [[social media analytics]] product was added in 2010.

==Technical overview and terminology==
SAS is a software suite that can mine, alter, manage and retrieve data from a variety of sources and perform statistical analysis on it.&lt;ref name="encycl"/&gt; SAS provides a graphical point-and-click user interface for non-technical users and more advanced options through the [[SAS language]].&lt;ref name="encycl"&gt;
{{Cite journal | title = Encyclopedia of Research Design Encyclopedia of research design | doi = 10.4135/9781412961288 | year = 2010 | isbn = 9781412961271 | pmid =  | pmc = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

SAS programs have DATA steps, which retrieve and manipulate data, and PROC steps, which analyze the data.&lt;ref name="court"/&gt; Each step consists of a series of statements.&lt;ref name="DelwicheSlaughter2012"&gt;
{{cite book
| author1=Lora D. Delwiche
| author2=Susan J. Slaughter
| title=The Little SAS Book: A Primer : a Programming Approach
| url=https://books.google.com/books?id=WtZZ6sYA2_QC&amp;pg=PA6|year=2012
| publisher=SAS Institute
| isbn=978-1-61290-400-9
| pages=6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The DATA step has executable statements that result in the software taking an action, and declarative statements that provide instructions to read a data set or alter the data's appearance.&lt;ref name="court"/&gt; The DATA step has two phases: compilation and execution. In the compilation phase, declarative statements are processed and syntax errors are identified. Afterwards, the execution phase processes each executable statement sequentially.&lt;ref name="Li2013"&gt;
{{cite book
| author=Arthur Li
| title=Handbook of SAS DATA Step Programming
| url=https://books.google.com/books?id=kBL_aEB6RX0C&amp;pg=PA149
| date=10 April 2013
| publisher=CRC Press
| isbn=978-1-4665-5238-8|page=149}}&lt;/ref&gt; Data sets are organized into tables with rows called "observations" and columns called "variables". Additionally, each piece of data has a descriptor and a value.&lt;ref name="court"&gt;
{{cite court
| litigants =SAS Institute Inc. and World Programming Limited
| court =England and Wales High Court (Chancery Division)
| date =July 23, 2010
| url=http://www.bailii.org/ew/cases/EWHC/Ch/2010/1829.html#para36 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
| first =Debbie
| last =Buck
| title =A Hands-On Introduction to SAS DATA Step Programming
| publisher =SAS Institute
| location =SUGI 30
| url =http://www2.sas.com/proceedings/sugi30/134-30.pdf
| accessdate =October 2, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The PROC step consists of PROC statements that call upon named procedures. Procedures perform analysis and reporting on data sets to produce statistics, analyses, and graphics. There are more than 300 procedures and each one contains a substantial body of programming and statistical work.&lt;ref name="court"/&gt; PROC statements can also display results, sort data or perform other operations.&lt;ref name="DelwicheSlaughter2012"/&gt;

SAS macros are pieces of code or variables that are coded once and referenced to perform repetitive tasks.&lt;ref name="BassSolutions2007"&gt;
{{cite book
| author1=N. Jyoti Bass
| author2=K. Madhavi Lata &amp; Kogent Solutions
| title=Base Sas Programming Black Book, 2007 Ed
| url=https://books.google.com/books?id=o9nVu8Xsd6kC&amp;pg=PA365
| date=1 September 2007
| publisher=Dreamtech Press
| isbn=978-81-7722-769-7
| pages=365–}}&lt;/ref&gt;

SAS data can be published in HTML, PDF, Excel and other formats using the Output Delivery System, which was first introduced in 2007.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal
| last =Tolbert
| first =William
| title =How to Win Friends and Influence People with the SAS Output Delivery System
| journal =Clinical Medicine &amp; Research
| volume =8
| issue =3–4
| pages =189–190
| date =December 1, 2010
| url =http://www.clinmedres.org/content/8/3-4/189.3
| accessdate =October 2, 2013
| doi =10.3121/cmr.2010.943.c-c1-04 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The SAS Enterprise Guide is SAS's point-and-click interface. It generates code to manipulate data or perform analysis automatically and does not require SAS programming experience to use.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal
| last =Der
| first =G.
| author2=B. S. Everittt
| title =Basic Statistics using SAS Enterprise Guide
| journal =Journal of the Royal Statistical Society, Series A
| volume =172
| issue =2
| pages =530
| date =March 10, 2009
| doi =10.1111/j.1467-985X.2009.00588_2.x }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The SAS software suite has more than 200&lt;ref name="Schermerhorn2011"&gt;{{cite book|author=John R. Schermerhorn|title=Exploring Management|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=qNVP2L6iKi0C&amp;pg=SL3-PA22|date=11 October 2011|publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons|isbn=978-0-470-87821-7|pages=3}}&lt;/ref&gt; components&lt;ref name="berk"&gt;
{{cite web
| publisher=University of California, Berkeley
| title=An Introduction to the SAS System
| first=Phil|last=Spector
| url=https://www.stat.berkeley.edu/classes/s100/sas.pdf
| format=PDF
| archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131012065352/http://www.stat.berkeley.edu/classes/s100/sas.pdf
| archivedate=October 12, 2013
| accessdate=October 4, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
| url=http://www.nesug.org/Proceedings/nesug12/ma/ma10.pdf
| title=Determine what SAS Version and Components are available
| first=David
| last=Chapman
| publisher=NESUG
| format=PDF
| year=2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some of the SAS components include:&lt;ref name="encycl"/&gt;&lt;ref name="berk"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite journal | last1 = Hallahan | first1 = C. | title = Data Analysis Using SAS | doi = 10.1177/0049124195023003006 | journal = Sociological Methods &amp; Research | volume = 23 | issue = 3 | pages = 373–391 | year = 1995 | pmid =  | pmc = }}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{columns-list|colwidth=30em|
* Base SAS – Basic procedures and data management
* SAS/STAT – Statistical analysis
* SAS/GRAPH – Graphics and presentation
* SAS/OR – Operations research
* SAS/ETS – [[Econometrics]] and [[Time Series Analysis]]
* SAS/IML – Interactive matrix language
* SAS/AF – Applications facility
* SAS/QC – Quality control
* SAS/INSIGHT – [[Data mining]]
* SAS/PH – [[Clinical trial]] analysis
* Enterprise Miner – data mining
* Enterprise Guide - GUI based code editor &amp; project manager
* SAS EBI - Suite of [[Business Intelligence]] Applications 
* SAS Grid Manager - Manager of SAS grid computing environment
}}

== History ==

===Origins===
The development of SAS began in 1966 after [[North Carolina State University]] re-hired [[Anthony James Barr|Anthony Barr]]&lt;ref name="NourseGreenberg1978"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Nourse|first1=E. Shepley|last2=Greenberg|first2=Bernard G.|last3=Cox|first3=Gertrude M.|last4=Mason|first4=David D.|last5=Grizzle|first5=James E.|last6=Johnson|first6=Norman L.|last7=Jones|first7=Lyle V.|last8=Monroe|first8=John|last9=Simons|first9=Gordon D.|title=Statistical Training and Research: The University of North Carolina System|journal=International Statistical Review / Revue Internationale de Statistique|volume=46|issue=2|year=1978|pages=171|issn=0306-7734|doi=10.2307/1402812|jstor=1402812}}&lt;/ref&gt; to program his analysis of variance and regression software so that it would run on [[IBM System/360]] computers.&lt;ref name="AgrestiMeng2012"&gt;{{cite book|author1=Alan Agresti|author2=Xiao-Li Meng|title=Strength in Numbers: The Rising of Academic Statistics Departments in the U. S.: The Rising of Academic Statistics Departments in the U.S.|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=kPGJUiUCJZkC&amp;pg=PA177|date=2 November 2012|publisher=Springer|isbn=978-1-4614-3649-2|pages=177}}&lt;/ref&gt; The project was funded by the [[National Institute of Health]]&lt;ref name="fda"/&gt; and was originally intended to analyze agricultural data&lt;ref name="berk"/&gt;&lt;ref name="“little"&gt;{{cite news|title=Little-known software giant to raise its profile|first=Emery|last=Dalesio|url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?nid=1916&amp;dat=20010505&amp;id=nPpIAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=oAUNAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=3476,727402|date=May 5, 2001|publisher=Associated Press|accessdate=April 8, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; to improve crop yields.&lt;ref name="seventyeight"&gt;{{cite news|first=David|last=Kaplan|newspaper=Fortune|url=http://money.cnn.com/2010/01/21/technology/sas_best_companies.fortune/|title=SAS: A new no. 1 best employer|date=January 22, 2010|accessdate=April 8, 2014|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20111129010236/http://money.cnn.com/2010/01/21/technology/sas_best_companies.fortune/|archivedate=November 29, 2011|df=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Barr was joined by student [[James Goodnight]], who developed the software's statistical routines, and the two became project leaders.&lt;ref name="NourseGreenberg1978"/&gt;&lt;ref name="AgrestiMeng2012"/&gt;&lt;ref name="timeline"/&gt; In 1968, Barr and Goodnight integrated new [[multiple regression]] and [[analysis of variance]] routines.&lt;ref name="Attr76"&gt;{{cite journal|first=Anthony|last=Barr|author2=James Goodnight |title=The SAS Staff|year=1976|quote=SAS 72 and SAS 76 are attributed to Barr, Goodnight, Service, Perkins, and Helwig}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;(Barr &amp; Goodnight et al. 1979:front matter) Attribution of the development of various parts of the system to Barr, Goodnight, and Sall.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1972, after issuing the first release of SAS, the project lost its funding.&lt;ref name="fda"&gt;{{citation|title=SAS Institute FDA Intellectual Partnership for Efficient Regulated Research Data Archival and Analyses|url=http://www.fda.gov/ohrms/dockets/dockets/00n0001/ts00016.pdf|publisher=Presented at Duke University|date=April 12, 2000|accessdate=September 28, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to Goodnight, this was because NIH only wanted to fund projects with medical applications.&lt;ref name="intervieww"&gt;{{citation|title=Oral History Interview with Jim Goodnight|date=July 22, 1999|url=http://docsouth.unc.edu/sohp/I-0073/excerpts/excerpt_976.html|accessdate=April 8, 2014|publisher=Oral Histories of the American South}}&lt;/ref&gt; Goodnight continued teaching at the university for a salary of $1 and access to mainframe computers for use with the project,&lt;ref name="fda"/&gt; until it was funded by the [[University Statisticians of the Southern Experiment Stations]] the following year.&lt;ref name="AgrestiMeng2012"/&gt;&lt;ref name="intervieww"/&gt; [[John Sall]] joined the project in 1973 and contributed to the software's econometrics, time series, and matrix algebra. Another early participant, Caroll G. Perkins, contributed to SAS' early programming. Jolayne W. Service and Jane T. Helwig created SAS' first documentation.&lt;ref name="Attr76"/&gt;

The first versions of SAS were named after the year in which they were released.&lt;ref name="expert"&gt;{{cite web
| title=History of SAS version
| url=http://www.globalstatements.com/sas/differences/
| publisher=Global Statements|first=Rick|last=Aster
| accessdate=October 4, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1971, SAS 71 was published as a limited release.&lt;ref name="encycl"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
| first=Anthony|last=Barr |author2=James Goodnight |author3=James Howard
| url=http://www.worldcat.org/title/statistical-analysis-system/oclc/5728643
| publisher=North Carolina State University|year=1971
| title=Statistical analysis system
| accessdate=October 3, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was used only on IBM mainframes and had the main elements of SAS programming, such as the DATA step and the most common procedures in the PROC step.&lt;ref name="expert"/&gt; The following year a full version was released as SAS 72, which introduced the MERGE statement and added features for handling missing data or combining data sets.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
| last=Service
| first=Jolayne
| title=A User's Guide to the Statistical Analysis System
| publisher=North Carolina State University
| year=1972
| url=http://www.worldcatlibraries.org/oclc/1325510}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1976, Barr, Goodnight, Sall, and Helwig removed the project from North Carolina State and incorporated it into [[SAS Institute|SAS Institute, Inc.]]&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite news
| first=Mary
| last=Shacklett
| date=September 5, 2013
| url=http://www.techrepublic.com/blog/big-data-analytics/see-if-the-r-language-fits-in-your-big-data-toolkit/
| publisher=The New Republic|accessdate=October 3, 2013
| title=See if the R language fits in your big data toolkit}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Development===
SAS was re-designed in SAS 76 with an [[open architecture]] that allowed for [[compilers]] and procedures. The INPUT and INFILE statements were improved so they could read most data formats used by IBM mainframes. Generating reports was also added through the PUT and FILE statements. The ability to analyze [[general linear model]]s was also added&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book
| last=Barr
| first=Anthony
| author2=James Goodnight
| author3=James Sall
| author4=John Helwig
| author5=Jane T
| title=SAS Programmer's Guide, 1979 Edition
| publisher=SAS Institute, Inc.
| year=1979
| url=http://www.worldcatlibraries.org/oclc/4984363
| oclc=4984363}}&lt;/ref&gt; as was the FORMAT procedure, which allowed developers to customize the appearance of data.&lt;ref name="expert"/&gt; In 1979, SAS 79 added support for the [[Conversational Monitor System|CMS operating system]] and introduced the DATASETS procedure. Three years later, SAS 82 introduced an early macro language and the APPEND procedure.&lt;ref name="expert"/&gt;

SAS version 4 had limited features, but made SAS more accessible. Version 5 introduced a complete macro language, array subscripts, and a full-screen interactive user interface called Display Manager.&lt;ref name="expert"/&gt; In 1985, SAS was rewritten in the [[C programming language]]. This allowed for the SAS' Multivendor Architecture that allows the software to run on [[UNIX]], [[MS-DOS]], and [[Windows]]. It was previously written in [[PL/I]], [[Fortran]], and [[assembly language]].&lt;ref name="timeline"/&gt;&lt;ref name="expert"/&gt;

In the 1980s and 1990s, SAS released a number of components to complement Base SAS. SAS/GRAPH, which produces graphics, was released in 1980, as well as the SAS/ETS component, which supports econometric and time series analysis. A component intended for pharmaceutical users, SAS/PH-Clinical, was released in the 1990s. The [[Food and Drug Administration]] standardized on SAS/PH-Clinical for new drug applications in 2002.&lt;ref name="timeline"&gt;
{{cite news
| url=http://www.wral.com/business/story/9211429/
| title=SAS corporate timeline|date=March 3, 2011
| accessdate=October 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Vertical products like SAS Financial Management and SAS Human Capital Management (then called CFO Vision and HR Vision respectively) were also introduced.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
| url=http://www.sas.com/company/about/history.html#s1=5
| title=SAS history
| publisher=SAS Institute
| accessdate=October 4, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[JMP (statistical software)|JMP]] was developed by SAS co-founder [[John Sall]] and a team of developers to take advantage of the graphical user interface introduced in the 1984 [[Apple Macintosh]]&lt;ref name="CoxGaudard2009"&gt;
{{cite book
| author1=Ian Cox|author2=Marie A. Gaudard
| author3=Philip J. Ramsey |author4=Mia L. Stephens |author5=Leo Wright
| title=Visual Six Sigma: Making Data Analysis Lean
| url=https://books.google.com/books?id=xdg9nkBFh1UC&amp;pg=PA23
| accessdate=16 November 2012|date=21 December 2009
| publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons
| isbn=978-0-470-50691-2
| pages=23–}}&lt;/ref&gt; and shipped for the first time in 1989.&lt;ref name="CoxGaudard2009"/&gt; Updated versions of JMP were released continuously after 2002 with the most recent release being from 2016.&lt;ref name="jmpone"&gt;
{{cite news
| url=http://www.jmp.com/landing/foreword_pdf/JMPForeward_72dpi.pdf
| title=Growing up|pp=5
| accessdate=October 4, 2013
| newspaper=JMP Forward
| publisher=JMP}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="jumptwo"&gt;
{{cite news
| first=John
| last=Saul
| newspaper=JMPer Cable
| url=http://www.jmp.com/about/newsletters/jmpercable/pdf/26_winter_2010.pdf
| title=JMP is 20 Years Old
| date=Winter 2010
| accessdate=October 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite news
| url=http://www.google.com/translate?hl=en&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;sl=auto&amp;tl=en&amp;u=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.diarioti.com%2Fnoticia%2FSAS_lanza_JMP_8_para_Mac%2F24733
| title=Launches SAS JMP 8 for Mac and Linux
| date=April 11, 2009
| accessdate=December 30, 2012
| newspaper=Ti Journal}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
| title=New Features in JMP 9
| url=http://www.jmp.com/support/downloads/pdf/jmp9/jmp9_new_features.pdf|publisher=JMP
| accessdate=December 30, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite news
| first=Adriian
| url=http://www.drdobbs.com/tools/228200027?queryText=SAS%2BJMP
| last=Bridgewater|newspaper=Dr. Dobbs Journal
| title=JMP Genomics 5: Data Visualization &amp; Exploration|date=November 3, 2010
| accessdate=May 31, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
| url=http://www.pharmasug.org/proceedings/2012/DG/PharmaSUG-2012-DG01.pdf
| work=PharmaSUG 2012
| title=Proficiency in JMP Visualization
| first=Charles
| last=Shipp
| author2=Kirk Paul Lafler
| accessdate=December 30, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="thirtyeight"&gt;
{{cite news
| first=James
| last=Taylor
| publisher=JTonEDM
| title=First Look – JMP Pro
| date=August 10, 2011
| accessdate=May 31, 2012
| url=http://jtonedm.com/2011/08/10/first-look-jmp-pro/}}&lt;/ref&gt;

SAS version 6 was used throughout the 1990s and was available on a wider range of operating systems, including [[Macintosh]], [[OS/2]], [[Silicon Graphics]], and [[Primos]]. SAS introduced new features through dot-releases. From 6.06 to 6.09, a user interface based on the windows paradigm was introduced and support for SQL &lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
| first=Kirk Paul
| last=Lafler
| title=PROC SQL: Beyond the Basics Using SAS, Second Edition
| url=https://www.sas.com/store/books/categories/usage-and-reference/proc-sql-beyond-the-basics-using-sas-second-edition/prodBK_62432_en.html
| publisher=SAS Institute
| isbn=978-1-61290-027-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; was added.&lt;ref name="expert"/&gt; Version 7 introduced the Output Delivery System (ODS) and an improved text editor. ODS was improved upon in successive releases. For example, more output options were added in version 8. The number of operating systems that were supported was reduced to [[UNIX]], [[Windows]] and [[z/OS]], and [[Linux]] was added.&lt;ref name="expert"/&gt;&lt;ref name="supported systems"&gt;
{{cite web
| url=http://support.sas.com/supportos/list
| title=Supported Operating Systems
| publisher=SAS Institute
| accessdate=October 6, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; SAS version 8 and SAS Enterprise Miner were released in 1999.&lt;ref name="timeline"/&gt;

===Recent history===
In 2002, the Text Miner software was introduced. Text Miner [[text mining|analyzes text data]] like emails for patterns in Business Intelligence applications.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|first=Emery|last=Dalesio|title=Text Miner program to bolster business intelligence|url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?nid=1734&amp;dat=20020205&amp;id=ljUgAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=GFMEAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=4836,3215963|date=February 5, 2002|accessdate=April 8, 2014|publisher=Associated Press}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2004, SAS Version 9.0 was released, which was dubbed "Project Mercury" and was designed to make SAS accessible to a broader range of business users.&lt;ref name="sixtyfour"&gt;
{{cite news
| first=Dave
| last=Steven
| publisher=Pennsylvania State University
| url=http://css.its.psu.edu/news/nlsu02/sas.html
| title=SAS is Starting to Look Even Better...
| date=July 29, 2002
| accessdate=October 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="sixtyfive"&gt;
{{cite news
| first=Rick
| last=Whiting
| newspaper=InformationWeek
| url=http://informationweek.com/news/18700087?queryText=SAS+announced
| title=SAS Extends Business Intelligence to the Masses
| date=March 31, 2004
| accessdate=October 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Version 9.0 added custom user interfaces based on the user's role and established the point-and-click user interface of SAS Enterprise Guide as the software's primary [[graphical user interface]] (GUI).&lt;ref name="sixtyfour"/&gt; The [[Customer Relationship Management]] (CRM) features were improved in 2004 with SAS Interaction Management.&lt;ref name="sixtythree"&gt;
{{cite news
| first=Dennis
| last=Callaghan
| newspaper=eWeek
| url=http://www.eweek.com/c/a/Finance-IT/SAS-to-Add-to-Analytical-CRM-Arsenal/
| title=SAS to Add to Analytical CRM Arsenal
| date=September 26, 2002
| accessdate=October 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2008 SAS announced Project Unity, designed to integrate data quality, data integration and master data management.&lt;ref name="sixtysix"&gt;
{{cite news
| first=Antone
| last=Gonsalves
| newspaper=InformationWeek
| url=http://informationweek.com/news/software/bi/211100027?queryText=SAS+announced
| title=SAS, DataFlux Unveil 'Project Unity'
| date=October 10, 2008
| accessdate=October 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

SAS [[SAS Institute lawsuit with World Programming|sued World Programming]], the developers of a competing implementation, [[World Programming System]], alleging that they had infringed SAS's copyright in part by implementing the same functionality. This case was referred from the United Kingdom's [[High Court of Justice]] to the [[European Court of Justice]] on 11 August 2010.&lt;ref name="ecj reference"&gt;
{{cite web
| url=http://curia.europa.eu/juris/document/document.jsf?docid=82474&amp;doclang=en&amp;mode=&amp;part=1
| title=Reference for a preliminary ruling from High Court of Justice (Chancery Division) (England and Wales) made on 11 August 2010 – SAS Institute Inc. v World Programming Ltd
| publisher=European Court of Justice
| accessdate=May 19, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; In May 2012, the [[European Court of Justice]] ruled in favor of World Programming, finding that "the functionality of a computer program and the programming language cannot be protected by copyright."&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
| url=http://curia.europa.eu/jcms/upload/docs/application/pdf/2012-05/cp120053en.pdf
| title=The functionality of a computer program and the programming language cannot be protected by copyright
| publisher=European Court of Justice
| accessdate=May 19, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A free version was introduced for students in 2010.&lt;ref name="fortyeight"&gt;{{cite news|first=Quentin|last=Hardy|newspaper=Forbes|url=https://www.forbes.com/sites/quentinhardy/2011/06/09/sas-ibms-bad-culture-how-well-win/|title=SAS-We Spurned IBM, Now to Win|date=June 9, 2011|accessdate=October 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; SAS Social Media Analytics, a tool for social media monitoring, engagement and [[sentiment analysis]], was also released that year.&lt;ref name="twentyseven"&gt;
{{cite news
| first=Paul
| last=Greenberg
| publisher=ZDNet
| url=http://www.zdnet.com/blog/crm/the-crm-watchlist-part-ii-the-usual-suspects/2419?tag=mantle_skin;content
| title=The CRM Watchlist Part II: The Usual Suspects
| date=December 31, 2010
| accessdate=October 4, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="ninetyfour"/&gt; SAS Rapid Predictive Modeler (RPM), which creates basic analytical models using [[Microsoft Excel]], was introduced that same year.&lt;ref name="ninetyfour"&gt;
{{cite web
| publisher=UCLA Academic Technology Services
| url=http://www.ats.ucla.edu/stat/sas/seminars/sas_macros_introduction/default.htm
| title=Computing Seminars: Introduction to SAS Macro Language
| accessdate=October 4, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="sixtyseven"&gt;
{{cite news
| first=Cindi
| last=Howson
| newspaper=InformationWeek
| url=http://informationweek.com/blog/software/228900553?queryText=SAS+announced
| title=SAS Takes Predictive Analytics Mainstream|date=September 7, 2010
| accessdate=October 4, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; JMP 9 in 2010 added a new interface for using the [[R (programming language)|R programming language]] from JMP and an add-in for Excel.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=New Features in JMP 9|url=http://www.jmp.com/support/downloads/pdf/jmp9/jmp9_new_features.pdf|publisher=JMP|accessdate=December 30, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|first=Adriian|url=http://www.drdobbs.com/tools/228200027?queryText=SAS%2BJMP|last=Bridgewater|newspaper=Dr. Dobbs Journal|title=JMP Genomics 5: Data Visualization &amp; Exploration|date=November 3, 2010|accessdate=May 31, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The following year, a [[High Performance Computing]] appliance was made available in a partnership with [[Teradata]] and [[EMC Greenplum]].&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite news
| first=Nicole
| last=Laskowski
| publisher=SearchBusinessAnalytics
| url=http://searchbusinessanalytics.techtarget.com/news/2240102699/SAS-ups-big-data-ante-with-high-performance-computing-platform
| title=SAS ups 'big data' ante with high-performance computing platform
| date=October 26, 2011
| accessdate=October 4, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
| first=Madan
| last=Sheina
|author2=Surya Mukherjee
 | publisher=Ovum
| url=http://ovum.com/2011/10/17/sas-adds-in-memory-to-high-performance-computing/
| title=SAS adds in-memory to high-performance computing
| date=October 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2011, the company released Enterprise Miner 7.1.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite news
| first=James
| last=Taylor
| title=First Look – SAS Enterprise Miner 7.1
| url=http://jtonedm.com/2011/11/11/first-look-sas-enterprise-miner-7-1/
| date=November 11, 2011
| accessdate=October 4, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The company introduced 27 data management products from October 2013 to October 2014 and updates to 160 others.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=SAS expands cloud analytics business|first=Nestor|last=Arellano|date=October 22, 2014|url=http://www.itworldcanada.com/article/sas-expands-cloud-analytics-business/98450#ixzz3IzvMFJ9l|newspaper=IT World Canada|accessdate=November 13, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the 2015 SAS Global Forum, it announced several new products that were specialized for different industries, as well as new training software.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=SAS enlarges its palette for big data analysis|first=Joab|last=Jackson|date=April 27, 2015|url=http://www.itworld.com/article/2915374/sas-enlarges-its-palette-for-big-data-analysis.html|publisher=IT World|accessdate=May 22, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Releases date ===
SAS had many releases since 1972.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://blogs.sas.com/content/iml/2013/08/02/how-old-is-your-version-of-sas-release-dates-for-sas-software.html|title=How old is your version of SAS? Release dates for SAS software|work=The DO Loop|access-date=2018-03-27|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since release 9.3, SAS/STAT has its own release numbering.
{| class="wikitable"
|+
!Release
!Date
!Comment
|-
|72
|January 1972
|
|-
|76
|July 1976
|
|-
|79.5
|April 1981
|
|-
|82.4
|January 1983
|
|-
|4.06
|March 1984
|
|-
|5.03
|July 1986
|
|-
|6.01
|January 1985
|PC-DOS
|-
|6.03
|March 1988
|
|-
|6.06
|March 1990
|
|-
|6.07
|April 1991
|
|-
|6.08
|March 1993
|
|-
|6.09
|October 1993
|
|-
|6.10
|October 1994
|
|-
|6.11
|October 1995
|
|-
|6.12
|November 1996
|
|-
|7.0
|October 1998
|
|-
|8.0
|November 1999
|
|-
|8.1
|July 2000
|
|-
|8.2
|March 2001
|
|-
|9.0
|October 2002
|
|-
|9.1
|December 2003
|
|-
|9.1.3
|August 2004
|
|-
|9.2
|March 2008
|STAT 9.2
|-
|9.2m2
|April 2010
|STAT 9.22
|-
|9.3
|July 2011
|STAT 9.3
|-
|9.3m2
|August 2012
|STAT 12.1
|-
|9.4
|July 2013
|STAT 12.3
|-
|9.4m1
|December 2013
|STAT 13.1
|-
|9.4m2
|August 2014
|STAT 13.2
|-
|9.4m3
|July 2015
|STAT 14.1
|-
|9.4m4
|November 2016
|STAT 14.2
|-
|9.4m5
|September 2017
|STAT 14.3
|}

==Software products==
As of 2011 SAS's largest set of products is its line for [[customer intelligence]]. Numerous SAS modules for web, social media and marketing analytics may be used to profile customers and prospects, predict their behaviors and manage and optimize communications.&lt;ref name="thirtyeight" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|date=May 11, 2004|newspaper=InformationWeek|first=Rick|last=Whiting|url= http://www.informationweek.com/sas-ships-customer-intelligence-app/d/d-id/1025026?|title=SAS Ships Customer-Intelligence App|accessdate=January 7, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; SAS also provides the SAS Fraud Framework. The framework's primary functionality is to monitor transactions across different applications, networks and partners and use analytics to identify anomalies that are indicative of fraud.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Social network analysis, predictive coding enlisted to fight fraud|newspaper=Government Computer News|date=May 10, 2013|accessdate=December 11, 2013|url=http://gcn.com/Articles/2013/05/10/Social-media-analysis-predictive-coding-enlisted-to-fight-fraud.aspx?Page=3|first=Rutrell|last=Yasin}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.oregonlive.com/finance/index.ssf/2013/08/what_to_do_with_that_false_pos.html|newspaper=The Oregonian|title=Credit card blocked? Get used to false positive fraud alerts for now|first=Brent|last=Hunsberger|date=August 23, 2013|accessdate=December 11, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=IRS, States Call on IBM, LexisNexis, SAS to Fight Tax Fraud|first=Reed|last=Albergotti|date=July 22, 2013|url= https://online.wsj.com/news/articles/SB10001424127887324144304578619811891715262|newspaper=The Wall Street Journal}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.insurancenetworking.com/news/business_intelligence_analytics_cloud_computing_fraud_insurance_technology-12069-1.html|newspaper=Insurance Networking News|date=March 25, 2009|first=Bill|last=Kenealy|accessdate=December 11, 2013|title=Assessing Business Intelligence}}&lt;/ref&gt; SAS Enterprise GRC (Governance, Risk and Compliance) provides risk modeling, scenario analysis and other functions&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=SAS Upgrades GRC Software Quicker Compliance|url=http://www.information-management.com/news/SAS-GRC-compliance-software-Forrester-McClean-10022461-1.html|publisher=Information Management|date=May 10, 2012|first=Justin|last=Stephani}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.protiviti.com/en-US/Documents/About-Us/The-Forrester-Wave-Enterprise-Governance-Risk-and-Compliance-Platforms-Q4-2011.pdf|date=November 30, 2011|title=The Forrester Wave™: Enterprise, Governance, Risk, And Compliance Platforms, Q4 2011|first= Chris|last=McClean|accessdate=December 12, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; in order to manage and visualize risk, compliance and corporate policies.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|url=http://www.gleanster.com/#/solution/sas-for-governance-risk-and-compliance|title=Solution Overview|publisher=Gleanster|accessdate=December 12, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; There is also a SAS Enterprise Risk Management product-set designed primarily for banks and financial services organizations.&lt;ref name="Editor"&gt;{{cite book|author=Hui Pan, Editor|title=Iraq Telecom Monthly Newsletter November 2009|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=vTDCtLEo5UcC&amp;pg=PA5|publisher=Information Gatekeepers Inc|pages=5–|id=GGKEY:ZPZ8BD13DR8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

SAS' products for monitoring and managing the operations of IT systems are collectively referred to as SAS IT Management Solutions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=SAS Launches Suite Of Solutions For IT|publisher=ITManagementNews|date=September 22, 2004|accessdate=December 12, 2013|url=http://archive.itmanagementnews.com/itmanagementnews-54-20040922SASLaunchesSuiteofSolutionsforIT.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; SAS collects data from various IT assets on performance and utilization, then creates reports and analyses.&lt;ref name="CokinsSchubert2010"&gt;{{cite book|author1=Gary Cokins|author2=Karl D. Schubert|author3=Michael H. Hugos |author4=Randy Betancourt |author5=Alyssa Farrell |author6=Bill Flemming |author7=Jonathan Hujsak|title=CIO Best Practices: Enabling Strategic Value With Information Technology|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=vjqSNRhEnQcC&amp;pg=PA64|date=24 September 2010|publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons|isbn=978-0-470-91255-3|pages=64–}}&lt;/ref&gt; SAS' Performance Management products consolidate and provide graphical displays for [[Performance indicator|key performance indicators]] (KPIs) at the employee, department and organizational level.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|url=http://www.nesug.org/proceedings/nesug02/et/et004.pdf|title=Using SAS Strategically: A Case Study|first=Timothy|last=Brown|publisher=NESUG|accessdate=December 12, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Product Review SAS SPM Strategic Performance Management|url=http://www.fsn.co.uk/channel_bi_bpm_cpm/pr_sas_spm_strategic_performance_management|date=October 8, 2006|accessdate=December 12, 2013|publisher=FSN}}&lt;/ref&gt; The SAS Supply Chain Intelligence product suite is offered for supply chain needs, such as forecasting product demand, managing distribution and inventory and optimizing pricing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=SAS to Extend Its Supply Chain Offerings|first=Dennis|last=Callaghan|url=http://www.eweek.com/c/a/Channel/SAS-to-Extend-Its-Supply-Chain-Offerings/#sthash.DcJjCKou.dpuf|newspaper=eWeek|accessdate=December 12, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; There is also a "SAS for Sustainability Management" set of software to forecast environmental, social and economic effects and identify causal relationships between operations and an impact on the environment or ecosystem.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Software for sustainability management unveiled|date=May 5, 2008|pp=41|first=Kang|last=Li|newspaper=New Straits Times}}&lt;/ref&gt;

SAS has product sets for specific industries, such as government, retail, telecommunications and aerospace and for marketing optimization or [[high-performance computing]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.sas.com/products/|title=Products &amp; Solutions Index|publisher=SAS|accessdate=December 12, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Comparison to other products===
{{See also|Comparison of statistical packages}}
In a 2005 article for the ''[[Journal of Marriage and Family]]'' comparing statistical packages from SAS and its competitors [[Stata]] and [[SPSS]], Alan C. Acock wrote that SAS programs provide "extraordinary range of data analysis and data management tasks," but were [[Usability|difficult to use]] and learn.&lt;ref name="Acock"/&gt; SPSS and Stata, meanwhile, were both easier to learn (with better documentation) but had less capable analytic abilities, though these could be expanded with paid (in SPSS) or free (in Stata) add-ons. Acock concluded that SAS was best for [[power user]]s, while occasional users would benefit most from SPSS and Stata.&lt;ref name="Acock"&gt;{{cite journal|pages=1093–1095|title=SAS, Stata, SPSS: A Comparison |journal=Journal of Marriage and Family |doi=10.1111/j.1741-3737.2005.00196.x|volume=67|issue=4 |date=November 2005 |url=http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/j.1741-3737.2005.00196.x/full | last=Acock |first=Alan C}}&lt;/ref&gt; A comparison by the [[University of California, Los Angeles]], gave similar results.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ats.ucla.edu/stat/mult_pkg/compare_packages.htm |title=Compare Packages |publisher=University of California, Los Angeles |accessdate=12 January 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Competitors such as [[Revolution Analytics]] and [[Alpine Data Labs]] advertise their products as considerably cheaper than SAS'. In a 2011 comparison, Doug Henschen of ''[[InformationWeek]]'' found that start-up fees for the three are similar, though he admitted that the starting fees were not necessarily the best basis for comparison.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.informationweek.com/software/information-management/low-cost-options-for-predictive-analytics-challenge-sas-ibm/d/d-id/1099191?page_number=1 |title=Low-Cost Options For Predictive Analytics Challenge SAS, IBM|first=Dough |last=Henschen |work=InformationWeek|date=July 26, 2011 |accessdate=January 12, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; SAS' business model is not weighted as heavily on initial fees for its programs, instead focusing on revenue from annual subscription fees.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=SAS' revenue up 12% in 2011|work=The News &amp; Observer, |location= Raleigh, North Carolina |date=January 20, 2012 |url=http://www.newsobserver.com/2012/01/20/1790587/sas-revenue-up-12-in-2011.html|last=Ranii|first=David |accessdate=January 12, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="SoftBus"&gt;{{cite web|last=Turchin|first=Brian|title=SAS Profile -- Going Its Own Way|url=http://www.cabnr.unr.edu/gf/apst650/sassoftbusiness.pdf|publisher=Software Business Online}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Adoption==
According to IDC, SAS is the largest market-share holder in "advanced analytics" with 35.4 percent of the market as of 2013.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.clickz.com/clickz/column/2353618/just-how-big-is-the-big-data-market |title=Just How Big Is the Big Data Market? |publisher=ClickZ |accessdate=7 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is the fifth largest market-share holder for [[business intelligence|business intelligence (BI)]] software with a 6.9% share&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
| title=Worldwide Business Analytics Software 2013–2017 Forecast and 2012 Vendor Shares
| url=http://idcdocserv.com/241689e_sas
| first=Dan
| last=Vesset |author2=David Schubmehl |author3=Brian McDonough |author4=Mary Wardley
| publisher=IDC
| date=June 2013
| accessdate=October 2, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the largest independent vendor. It competes in the BI market against conglomerates, such as [[SAP BusinessObjects]], [[IBM Cognos]], [[SPSS Modeler]], [[Oracle Hyperion]], and [[Power BI|Microsoft BI]].&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
| url=http://www.bi-verdict.com/fileadmin/FreeAnalyses/consolidations.htm
| title=Consolidations in the BI industry
| date=March 7, 2008
| last=Pendse
| first=Nigel
| work=The OLAP Report}}&lt;/ref&gt; SAS has been named in the Gartner Leader's Quadrant for Data Integration Tool and for Business Intelligence and Analytical Platforms.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
| title=Magic Quadrant for Business Intelligence and Analytics Platforms
| date=February 5, 2013
| publisher=Gartner
| url=http://www.gartner.com/technology/reprints.do?id=1-1DZLPEP&amp;ct=130207&amp;st=sb
| accessdate=October 1, 2013
| first=Kurt
| last=Schlegel |author2=Rita Sallam |author3=Daniel Yuen |author4=Joao Tapadinhas}}&lt;/ref&gt;
A study published in 2011 in ''[[BMC Health Services Research]]'' found that SAS was used in 42.6 percent of data analyses in health service research, based on a sample of 1,139 articles drawn from three journals.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | last1 = Dembe | first1 = A. E. | last2 = Partridge | first2 = J. S. | last3 = Geist | first3 = L. C. | title = Statistical software applications used in health services research: Analysis of published studies in the U.S | doi = 10.1186/1472-6963-11-252 | journal = BMC Health Services Research | volume = 11 | pages = 252 | year = 2011 | pmid =  21977990| pmc =3205033 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Comparison of numerical analysis software]]
* [[Comparison of OLAP Servers]]
* [[JMP (statistical software)]], also from [[SAS Institute Inc.]]
* [[SAS language]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
* {{Cite journal
| last1=Greenberg
| first1=Bernard G.
| last2=Cox
| first2=Gertrude M.
| authorlink2=Gertrude Mary Cox
| last3=Mason
| first3=David D.
| last4=Grizzle
| first4=James E.
| last5=Johnson
| first5=Norman L.
| last6=Jones
| first6=Lyle V.
| last7=Monroe
| first7=John
| last8=Simmons
| first8=Gordon D., Jr.
| editor=Nourse, E. Shepley
| journal=International Statistical Review
| title=Statistical Training and Research: The University of North Carolina System
|volume=46
| pages=171–207
| year=1978
| jstor=1402812
| issue=2
| doi=10.2307/1402812
| postscript=&lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to "." for the cite to end in a ".", as necessary. --&gt;{{inconsistent citations}} }}

== External links ==
{{Wikiquote}}
{{Wikibooks|SAS}}
* [http://www.sas.com SAS homepage]
* [https://books.google.com/books?id=a0Fc9dJby7EC&amp;pg=PA321&amp;dq=sas+%22library+engine%22+%22remote+library+services%22&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=pmZNUsnbI6SHygHt4oHYAQ&amp;ved=0CEsQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=Glossary&amp;f=false A Glossary of SAS terminology]
* [http://www.sascommunity.org/wiki/Main_Page The SAS customer community Wiki]
* [[Wikiversity:Data Analysis using the SAS Language]]
{{Statistical software}}
{{Good article}}

[[Category:4GL]]
[[Category:Articles with example code]]
[[Category:Business intelligence]]
[[Category:C software]]
[[Category:Data mining and machine learning software]]
[[Category:Data warehousing]]
[[Category:Extract, transform, load tools]]
[[Category:Mathematical optimization software]]
[[Category:Numerical software]]
[[Category:Proprietary commercial software for Linux]]
[[Category:Proprietary cross-platform software]]
[[Category:Science software for Linux]]</text>
      <sha1>8mkcyyrcmtekpx0iztiddrjut178vsl</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Sales outsourcing</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6874024</id>
    <revision>
      <id>851067910</id>
      <parentid>848597898</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-07-19T20:52:09Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Grayfell</username>
        <id>6603956</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Revert. Please find something more reliable than a vague, promotional press release.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="13230">'''Sales outsourcing''' is a way for companies to attract increased, high volumes of sales for their products or services by using a third party. The company typically uses outsourcing companies to improve sales volumes without links to the sales teams that carry out those campaigns. The company that undertakes the outsourcing will normally be paid based on the results they are able to generate, and therefore creates a mutually beneficial situation for both client and the outsourcing company. 

== Background ==
Full 'sales outsourcing' is observed when companies have an external third party [[sales]] force. It is differentiated from [[Value-added re seller|value added reselling]] or [[Distributor (business)|distribution]] in that the [[business model]] can be based on shared risk, although there are models where the outsourcer is paid for all of their activity - just as with a hired [[direct sales]] force, but the outsourcer provides rapidity, flexibility and experience. 
Other names for sales outsourcing include 'indirect sales' and 'channel sales'.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Anderson|first=E|title=Outsourcing the sales function: The real cost of field sales|year=2005|publisher=Thomson/South-western|location=Mason, Ohio|author2=Trickle }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Full sales outsourcing is different from [[telemarketing]] in that it requires direct recruitment of sales personnel with specific backgrounds for each sales campaign. Usually the sales executives will be part of a team that may include telemarketing, [[marketing]], tools systems and methodologies as well as [[sales management]].

Sales [[outsourcing]] firms provide [[accountability]] regarding all sales results and activities while representing the brand of the client. For the end-customer, it usually appears as if the sales team sold the product themselves rather than the sales outsourcing firm. The outsourcing firm is, in essence, an extension of the client but is responsible for all operations associated with direct sales activities, often receiving sales engineering and initial product/service [[training]] support from the client.

== Purpose of indirect sales ==
The sole purpose of a contract sales organization is to provide sales resource to its clients, without taking title to their products.  Sales outsourcing providers include [[manufacturers' representative]]s, contract sales organizations, sales agents or sales outsourcing consultants. One way of organising the sales effort, especially when product delivery is erratic, is to replace or supplement internal resources with [[wikt:function|functionality]] and expertise brought in from contract sales organisations.

Sales outsourcing is quite different from large-scale service outsourcing, which has its advantages but also requires pro-active contract and relationship management.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Anderson|first=E|title=Outsourcing the sales function: The real cost of field sales|year=2005|publisher=Thomson/South-western|location=Mason, Ohio|author2=Trinkle }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Novick|first=H. J.|title=Selling through independent reps|year=2000|publisher=AMACOM|location=New York, NY}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In addition to full sales outsourcing, many partial models are observed, particularly in large firms.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Rogers|first=B|title=An exploratory study of the make-or-buy decision in pharmaceutical sales|journal=Journal of Medical Marketing|year=2009|volume=9|issue=1|pages=11–20|doi=10.1057/jmm.2008.32}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Typical outsourced activities ==
A variety of sales activities may be outsourced such as:
*Outsourcing part of the sales process, e.g. lead qualification or lead nurturing
*Outsourcing management of particular [[customer]] segments, e.g. niche segments, geographies or sectors that are difficult to reach or are culturally very different
*Outsourcing of sales of particular [[Product line|product]] or service lines (e.g. parts, maintenance), or product-related activities such as product launches

Any of the following may also be considered as partial sales outsourcing or sales out-tasking:
*Integrating [[Independent contractor|contractors]] into in-house sales teams for coverage of long-term absences such as [[maternity leave]], or general vacancy management
*Syndicated sales – where the contracted salesperson presents complementary products from different companies on a single call to a customer

== Advantages ==

Sales outsourcing is expected to be cheaper than the fully loaded cost of employing salespeople, but calculating the cost comparison over time is far from straightforward. Nevertheless, replacing fixed costs with variable costs is attractive to budget-holders.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Rogers|first=B|title=An exploratory study of the make-or-buy decision in pharmaceutical sales|journal=Journal of Medical Marketing|year=2009|volume=9|issue=1|pages=11–20|doi=10.1057/jmm.2008.32}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, unlike many forms of outsourcing, the advantages of sales outsourcing does not often come from saving costs but rather increasing [[revenue]] or providing speed of response or flexibility.

The [[business case]] for sales outsourcing should also include consideration of the cost of controlling the contract.  Difficulty in measuring the link between sales activity and sales performance leads to a preference for employed salespeople.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Krafft|first=M |author2=Albers, S. |author3=Lal, R.|title=Relative Explanatory Power of Agency Theory and Transaction Cost Analysis in German Salesforces|journal=International Journal of Research in Marketing|year=2004|volume=21|issue=3|pages=265–283|doi=10.1016/j.ijresmar.2003.11.001}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the issues internally are often the same and the internal hire has many other corporate "distractions" that do not occur with external resources.

Companies may also choose sales outsourcing as a means of accessing the best sales skills.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Anderson|first=E|title=Outsourcing the sales function: The real cost of field sales|year=2005|publisher=Thomson/South-western|location=Mason, Ohio|author2=Trinkle }}&lt;/ref&gt; Although the [[pejorative]] term “rent-a-rep” is still used, there is some evidence that contractors are perceived as good performers against qualitative as well as quantitative performance criteria.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Anderson|first=E|title=Outsourcing the sales function: The real cost of field sales|year=2005|publisher=Thomson/South-western|location=Mason, Ohio|author2=Trinkle }}&lt;/ref&gt; Even so, the reputational risk of third parties handling customer relationships has been observed as a factor restricting sales outsourcing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Weiss|first=A M |author2=Anderson E |author3=MacInnis D J|title=Reputation Management as a Motivation for Sales Structure Decisions|journal=Journal of Marketing|year=1999|volume=63|pages=74–89|doi=10.2307/1251975}}&lt;/ref&gt; One could argue that an employee is often using a company to gain 2–3 years salary and experience whereas a sales outsourcing firm would usually be looking at a long term contract even though the staff may change during that time. So the aims of an outsourcer can be closely aligned with the aims and objectives of the contracting company.

A recent study has highlighted flexibility as an important driver for outsourcing sales.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Rogers|first=B|title=An exploratory study of the make-or-buy decision in pharmaceutical sales|journal=Journal of Medical Marketing|year=2009|volume=9|issue=1|pages=11–20|doi=10.1057/jmm.2008.32}}&lt;/ref&gt; Uncertain business environments accentuate the need to turn sales resource on and off quickly. Industries and companies undergoing rapid change may need to avoid hiring and firing costs and risks.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Downey|first=J. M.|title=Risks of outsourcing - applying risk management to staffing methods|journal=Facilities|year=1995|volume=13|series=9/10|pages=38–44|doi=10.1108/02632779510095617}}&lt;/ref&gt; Contract sales organizations can absorb employment risk, enabling their clients to respond to short-term opportunities or competitor activity (see [[Lean startup#Philosophy|Lean startup]]). However, an outsourcer may build in more of a premium to the rate or commission if excessive flexibility is required on a contract.

Contract sales organizations are growing in volume and influence, able to provide both tactical activity and long-term strategic support to their clients.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Rogers|first=B|title=Contract sales organizations (CSOs): making the transition from tactical resource to strategic partnering|journal=Journal of Medical Marketing|year=2008|volume=8|series=1|pages=39–47|doi=10.1057/palgrave.jmm.5050119}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.salespartnerships.com/resources/articles/contract-pharmaceutical-sales-pharma-landscape|title=Contract Pharmaceutical Sales: The Changing Pharma Landscape|date=2017-09-06|work=Sales Partnerships|access-date=2017-10-17|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Speed of response is seen as a key reason to use an outsourcer. If a company was looking to enter a market it may take several months to recruit the local manager which then takes several months to find an office and build a team. With an outsourcer, a full working team can oftentimes be operational within a matter of days or weeks.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|last=Poulter|first=Julian|title=Selling People Ltd|newspaper=Sales outsourcing alternatives|date=2005-05-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Sales outsourcing can also be used as a [[market entry strategy]] and avoids [[permanent establishment]] risk.

==Indirect sales growth rate==
The experience of many organizations over the past several years demonstrates that indirect channels can be critical to expanding market coverage. This has been particularly true in the [[electronics]], [[communications]] and [[high tech]] sectors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Chugg|first=Justin|title=What is a Master Agent?|url=http://www.telarus.com/why-telarus.php|publisher=Telecom Channel News|accessdate=10 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, the indirect channel now accounts for 66 percent of overall technology sales, up from 53 percent in 1997.

==Examples of indirect sales companies==
Some examples of communications companies who employ indirect sales forces to their internal sales efforts include:  [[Airespring|AireSpring]], [[AT&amp;T]], [[Comcast]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Oborn|first=Patrick|title=Comcast Solution Provider Program|url=http://www.telarus.com/carrier-information/comcast-business.html|publisher=Telecom Channel Association|accessdate=4 February 2013|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130128124010/http://www.telarus.com/carrier-information/comcast-business.html|archivedate=28 January 2013|df=}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[EarthLink|Earthlink Business]], [[Integra Telecom]], [[Level 3 Communications]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Holverson|first=Austin|title=Level 3 Debuts New Channel Partner Program; Introduces Tiered Structure and Enhanced Support Resources|url=http://www.telarus.com/industry/level-3-debuts-new-channel-partner-program;-introduces-tiered-structure-and-enhanced-support-resources.html|accessdate=4 February 2013|newspaper=Telecom Channel Updates|date=4 February 2013|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130407082959/http://www.telarus.com/industry/level-3-debuts-new-channel-partner-program;-introduces-tiered-structure-and-enhanced-support-resources.html|archivedate=7 April 2013|df=}}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Time Warner Cable]], [[TelePacific Communications|TelePacific]], [[tw telecom]], [[XO Communications]], and [[Windstream]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Chugg|first=Justin|title=Carriers in the Channel|url=http://www.telarus.com/carriers.html|publisher=Telecom Channel Updates|accessdate=6 March 2012|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120226073857/http://www.telarus.com/carriers.html|archivedate=26 February 2012|df=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some top sales agencies who sell voice and data services for these carriers include [[Telarus]], based in [[Salt Lake City, Utah]], Intelisys, based in [[Petaluma, California]], and Telecom Brokerage Inc (TBI), based in [[Chicago|Chicago, Illinois]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Henderson|first=Khali|title=Comcast Agent Program|url=http://www.telarus.com/carrier-information/comcast-business.html|accessdate=14 March 2011|newspaper=Channel Partners|date=14 March 2011|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110320204929/http://www.telarus.com/carrier-information/comcast-business.html|archivedate=20 March 2011|df=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Chugg|first=Justin|title=Comcast Business Services Enters Into Master Agent Agreement with Telarus|url=http://www.telarus.com/news/comcast-business-services-enters-into-master-agent-agreement-with-telarus.html|accessdate=14 March 2011|newspaper=Telarus Industry News Briefs|date=14 March 2011|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110321221607/http://www.telarus.com/news/comcast-business-services-enters-into-master-agent-agreement-with-telarus.html|archivedate=21 March 2011|df=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}

[[Category:Sales]]
[[Category:Business terms]]
[[Category:International business]]
[[Category:Offshoring]]
[[Category:Outsourcing]]
[[Category:Telecommuting]]</text>
      <sha1>pq5esgezs7qswroii1oyp1c8mqh9r2a</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Single customer view</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>37040021</id>
    <revision>
      <id>868631324</id>
      <parentid>867703122</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-11-13T13:23:12Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>GermanJoe</username>
        <id>12935443</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 867703122 by [[Special:Contributions/Szymongrzesiak|Szymongrzesiak]] ([[User talk:Szymongrzesiak|talk]]) spam</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="3411">A '''single customer view''' is an [[Aggregate (data warehouse)|aggregated]], consistent and holistic&lt;ref name="Experian"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.edq.com/globalassets/uk/product-brochures/single-customer-view-guide.pdf |title=See the benefits of a Single Customer View |publisher=Experian}}&lt;/ref&gt; representation of the [[data (computing)|data]] held by an organisation about its customers&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.experian.co.uk/assets/about-us/white-papers/single-customer-view-whitepaper.pdf |title=Exploiting the Single Customer View to Maximise the Value of Customer Relationships|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ardentisys.com/stories/streamlining-customer-data|title=Streamlining Customer Data|website=www.ardentisys.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; that can be viewed in one place, such as a single page.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180404073146/https://spotlessdata.com/blog/data-driven-marketing|title=Data-Driven Marketing|website=spotlessdata.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; The advantage to an organisation of attaining this unified view comes from the ability it gives to analyse past behaviour in order to better target and personalise future customer interactions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.atominsight.com/about-us/blog/single-customer-view-essential|title=Why a single customer view is essential|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; A single customer view is also considered especially relevant where organisations engage with customers through [[multichannel marketing]], since customers expect those interactions to reflect a consistent understanding of their history and preferences.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://econsultancy.com/uk/blog/9612-the-impact-of-a-single-customer-view-on-consumer-behaviour-infographic|title=The impact of a single customer view on consumer behaviour: infographic|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, some commentators have challenged the idea that a single view of customers across an entire organisation is either natural or meaningful, proposing that the priority should instead be consistency between the multiple views that arise in different contexts.

Where representations of a customer are held in more than one [[data set]], achieving a single customer view can be difficult: firstly because customer identity must be traceable between the records held in those systems, and secondly because anomalies or discrepancies in the customer data must be [[data cleansing|data cleansed]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.atominsight.com/about-us/blog/single-customer-view-hard|title=Why building a single customer view isn’t as easy as you might think|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; As such, the acquisition by an organisation of a single customer view is one potential outcome of successful [[master data management]]. Since 31 December, 2010, maintaining a single customer view, and submitting it within 72 hours, has become mandatory for [[financial institution]]s in the [[United Kingdom]] due to new rules introduced by the [[Financial Services Compensation Scheme]].&lt;ref name="Experian"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.fscs.org.uk/industry/single-customer-view/|title=Deposit Guarantee Scheme - Customer Review -FSCS|website=www.fscs.org.uk}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Data warehouse]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Identity management]]
[[Category:Business intelligence]]
[[Category:Data management]]
[[Category:Data warehousing]]
[[Category:Information technology management]]</text>
      <sha1>k0hhdp8i847sl5fmwr12ctxk0j3s5yg</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
