<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.33.0-wmf.4</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Federal Geographic Data Committee</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>13348166</id>
    <revision>
      <id>822781646</id>
      <parentid>717649416</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-01-28T13:06:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>OwenBlacker</username>
        <id>62026</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* top */ [[Template:Official URL]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="2614">{{refimprove|date=August 2010}}
{{Infobox Government agency
|agency_name     = Federal Geographic Data Committee
|nativename      =
|nativename_a    =
|nativename_r    =
|logo            = US-FederalGeographicDataCommittee-Logo.svg
|logo_width      = 220px
|logo_caption    =
|seal            =
|seal_width      =
|seal_caption    =
|formed          = 1990
|preceding1      =
|preceding2      =
|dissolved       =
|superseding     =
|jurisdiction    =
|headquarters    = [[United States Geological Survey|USGS]] National Center&lt;br/&gt;[[Reston, Virginia]]
|employees       =
|budget          =
|minister1_name  =
|minister1_pfo   =
|minister2_name  =
|minister2_pfo   =
|chief1_name     = [[Sally Jewel]]
|chief1_position = Chairman
|chief2_name     = [[Jeffrey Zients]]
|chief2_position = Vice-Chair
|parent_agency   =
|child1_agency   =
|child2_agency   =
|website         = {{Official URL}}
|footnotes       =
}}
The '''Federal Geographic Data Committee''' (FGDC) is a United States government committee which promotes the coordinated development, use, sharing, and dissemination of geospatial data on a national basis. Its 32 members are representatives from the [[Executive Office of the President]], and [[United States Cabinet|Cabinet]] level and independent Federal agencies. The Secretary of the [[Department of the Interior]] chairs the FGDC, with the Deputy Director for Management, [[Office of Management and Budget]] (OMB) as Vice-Chair.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fgdc.gov/index.html Federal Geographic Data Committee] Retrieved 2010-08-24.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Services==
The FGDC coordinates the sharing of geographic data, maps, and online services through an online portal, ''geodata.gov'', that searches metadata held within the [[OMB Circular A-16|NSDI]] Clearinghouse Network.&lt;ref&gt;Data &amp; Services. [http://www.fgdc.gov/index.html Federal Geographic Data Committee] Retrieved 2010-08-24.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Member Compliance==
On July 23, 2009, the Energy and Mineral Resources Subcommittee of the House Natural Resources Committee held an oversight hearing on federal geospatial data management. Rep. [[John Sarbanes]] of Maryland quoted a U.S. General Accounting Office (GAO) report from his briefing material saying that only 4 of the FGDC member agencies were in compliance.&lt;ref&gt;Will Craig (Fall 2009). ''Governance of the NSDI''.
[http://www.esri.com/news/arcnews/fall09articles/governance-of-nsdi.html ArcNews Online] Retrieved 2010-08-24.&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Geocodes]]
[[Category:United States federal boards, commissions, and committees]]

{{geography-stub}}
{{cartography-stub}}
{{US-gov-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>n2yuaiuhwh2q177hg337590y1ha6yqp</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Geography of aging</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>53452291</id>
    <revision>
      <id>844667992</id>
      <parentid>839877734</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-06-06T09:48:05Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Narky Blert</username>
        <id>22041646</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Link to DAB page removed (everyday word)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="7745">'''Geography of aging''' or '''gerontological geography''' is an emerging field of knowledge of [[Human Geography]] that analyzes the socio-spatial implications of [[aging]] of the [[population]] from the understanding of the relationships between the [[Social environment|physical-social environment]] and the [[elderly]], at different scales, micro (City, region, country), etc.

Since the 1970s in a number of developed countries such as the [[United States]], [[Canada]], the [[United Kingdom]], [[Germany]], [[Sweden]], [[France]], [[Spain]], [[Australia]], [[New Zealand]] and [[Japan]], there have been increasing studies focusing on the understanding of spatial patterns of [[aging population]], as well as aspects related to residential changes and provision of health and social services. Among the geographers of aging is S. Harper, who identified the phenomenon of aging associated with the social construction of old age and the processes of residential mobility of this group to the urban periphery, mainly nursing homes and sheltered housing.

The contribution of geographers of aging, such as Graham D. Rowles, SM. Golant, S. Harper, G. Laws, are contributing to environmental gerontology by understanding the environmental aspects of [[gerontology]] in developed and developing countries. Also in Spain, some geographers, such as Gloria Fernández-Mayoralas, Fermina Rojo-Pérez and Vicente Rodríguez-Rodríguez, have made outstanding contributions to the study of residential strategies, access to health services, and, in general, quality of Life of the elderly, as well as the impacts of Northern European retirees on the Costa del Sol (Spain).

In [[Latin America]] and [[Spain]], Diego Sánchez-González has shed light on the deepening of issues such as the physical-built and [[social environment]] and the [[quality of life]] of the [[elderly]]; the importance of the [[natural environment]] (therapeutic [[natural landscape]]) on active and [[healthy aging]] in the place; residential strategies for the maintenance of the elderly in the communities; the socio-environmental [[vulnerability]] of the elderly in the face of [[climate change]]; as well as issues related to the attachment to the place (identity and [[public space]]); elderly people with [[disabilities]] and [[social exclusion]]; [[leisure]] and [[tourism]] of elderly; and the [[planning]] of gerontological and geriatric services.

== References ==

* Abellán García, A., (1999), “Movilidad residencial y género entre las personas de edad: una aproximación a las estrategias residenciales en Madrid”, Documents d’anàlisi geogràfica, núm. 34, pp. 143-159.
* Andrews, Gavin J.; Phillips, David R. (2005). Ageing and Place: Perspectives, Policy, Practice. Routledge.
* Escudero, JM., (2003), “Los viejos en su casa, en su ciudad”, Scripta Nova. Revista electrónica de geografía y ciencias sociales, vol. VII, núm. 146 (203), Universidad de Barcelona, Barcelona.
* Eyles, J., (2004-, “The geography of everyday life”, in D. Gregory y R. Walford (eds): Horizons in human geography, London, MacMillan, pp. 102-117.
* García Ballesteros, A., Ortiz-Álvarez, M.I., y Gómez Escobar, M.C. (2003), “El envejecimiento de las poblaciones: los casos de España y México”, Anales de Geografía de la Universidad Complutense, N° 23, pp. 75-102.
* Golant, SM., (2002), “The housing problems of the future elderly population”. Commission on Affordable Housing and Health Facility Needs for seniors in the 21st Century (ed.): A quiet crisis in America: A report to Congress. Washington, DC: US Government Printing Office, pp. 189-370.
* Golant, SM. y Salmon, JR., (2004), “The unequal availability of affordable assisted living units in Florida’s Counties”, Journal of Applied Gerontology, Dec., vol. 23, pp. 349-369.
* Hanson, S. y Pratt, G., (1992), “Dynamic dependencies: A geographic investigation of local labour markets”, Economic Geography, vol. 68, núm. 4, October, pp. 373-405.
* Harper, S. y Laws, G., (1995), “Rethinking the geography of ageing”, Progress in Human Geography, núm. 19, SAGE Publications, London, pp. 199-221.
* Katz, C., and J. Monk, (eds.) (1993). Full circles. London: Routledge.
* Laws, G. (1994). Aging, contested meanings, and the built environment. Environment and Planning A, 26:1787–802.
* López Jiménez, J.J. (1993), El proceso de envejecimiento urbano y sus implicaciones en el municipio de Madrid. Tesis doctoral, Universidad Complutense, Madrid.
* Peet, JR. y Rowles, GD., (1974), “Geographical aspects of aging”, Geographical Review, vol. LXIV, núm. 2, The American Geographical Society of Nueva York, Nueva York, pp. 287-289.
* Phillips, D. et al., (2005), "The Impacts of Dwelling Conditions on Older Persons' Psychological Well-being in Hong Kong: The Mediating Role of Residential Satisfaction", Social Science &amp; Medicine, 60, 12, June 2005, pp. 2785-2797.
* Puga González, MD. y Abellán García, A., (2007), “Las escalas territoriales del envejecimiento”, Semata: Ciencias sociais e humanidades, núm. 18, pp. 121-141.
* Rodríguez, V. et al., (2003), “Envejecimiento y salud: diez años de investigación en el CSIC”, en Revista Multidisciplinar de Gerontología, vol. 13, nº 1, Nexus, Barcelona, pp. 43-46.
* Rojo, F., Fernández-Mayoralas, G., Pozo, E., (2000), “Envejecer en casa: los predictores de la satisfacción con la casa, el barrio y el vecindario como componentes de la calidad de vida de los mayores en Madrid”, Revista Multidisciplinar de Gerontología, 10, 4, pp. 222-233.
* Rowles, Graham D. (1978). Prisoners of space? Exploring the geographical experience of older people. Boulder, C., Westview Press.
* Rowles, Graham D.; Chaudhury, Habib (2005). Home and identity in late life: international perspectives. Nueva York: Springer Publishing Company.
* Rowles, Graham D.; Bernard, Miriam (2012). Environmental Gerontology: Making Meaningful Places in Old Age. Nueva York: Springer Publishing Company.
* Sánchez-González, D. (2005). The situation of older people in the city of Granada. Geographical Survey. Granada: Universidad de Granada. p. 2089. {{ISBN|978-84-338-3570-3}}.
* Sánchez-González, D. (2009). «Environmental context and spatial experience of aging in place: the case of Granada». Papeles de Población 15 (60): 175-213. ISSN 1405-7425.
* Sánchez-González, D. (2011). Geografía del envejecimiento y sus implicaciones en Gerontología. Contribuciones geográficas a la Gerontología Ambiental y el envejecimiento de la población. Saarbrücken: Editorial Académica Española-Lambert Academic Publishing. p. 264. {{ISBN|978-3-8443-4692-3}}.
* Sánchez-González, D. (2015): "Physical-social environments and aging population from environmental gerontology and geography. Socio-spatial implications in Latin America", Revista de Geografía Norte Grande, Nº 60, Mayo 2015, pp. 97-114
* Sánchez-González, D.; Rodríguez-Rodríguez, V. (2016). Environmental Gerontology in Europe and Latin America. Policies and perspectives on environment and aging. New York: Springer Publishing Company. p. 306. {{ISBN|978-3-319-21418-4}}.
* Smith, GC., (1998), “Residential separation and patterns of interaction between elderly parents and their adult children”. Progress in Human Geography, Jun, vol. 22, pp. 368-384.
* Stewart, JE., (2003), “Geographic Information Systems in Community-Based Gerontological Research and Practice”, Journal of Applied Gerontology, vol. 22, nº 1, pp. 134-151.
* Warnes, AM., (1990), “Geographical questions in gerontology: needed directions for research”, Progress in Human Geography, núm. 14, SAGE Publications, London, pp. 24-56.

[[Category:Geography]]
[[Category:Ageing]]</text>
      <sha1>dxr4229tv0cb6pap58m8njr34nhb1hq</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Geotagging</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1870398</id>
    <revision>
      <id>864267234</id>
      <parentid>849248396</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-10-16T05:15:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>DocWatson42</username>
        <id>38455</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* External links */ Added a bullet.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="24188">{{selfref|For information on geotagging content on Wikipedia, see [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Geographical coordinates]].}}
[[Image:Geotagging gThumb.png|thumb|Geotag information in a [[JPEG]] photo, shown by the software [[gThumb]]]]
[[File:Geotag Stamp.jpg|thumb|Geotag information stamped onto a JPEG photo by the software GPStamper]]
[[Image:Solmeta N2 auf Nikon D5000 Rueckansicht.JPG|thumb|Geotagger "Solmeta N2" for [[Nikon D5000]] DSLR]]

'''Geotagging''' or '''GeoTagging''', is the process of adding geographical identification [[metadata]] to various media such as a [[geotagged photograph]] or video, websites, SMS messages, QR Codes&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://qrd.by |title=Geo Tagged QR Codes |accessdate=2011-10-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; or [[RSS (file format)|RSS]] feeds and is a form of [[geospatial metadata]]. This data usually consists of [[geographic coordinate system|latitude and longitude coordinates]], though they can also include [[altitude]], [[Bearing (navigation)|bearing]], distance, accuracy data, and place names, and perhaps a [[time stamp]].

Geotagging can help users find a wide variety of location-specific information from a device. For instance, someone can find images taken near a given location by entering latitude and longitude coordinates into a suitable image [[search engine]]. Geotagging-enabled information services can also potentially be used to find location-based news, websites, or other resources.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.mywire.com/pubs/AP/2008/01/18/5437214?extID=10051 |title= GPS adds dimension to online photos |author=Anick Jesdanun, AP |date=2008-01-18 |accessdate=2008-01-19}}&lt;!-- this has a dead URL --&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;  Geotagging can tell users the location of the content of a given picture or other media or the [[Perspective (visual)|point of view]], and conversely on some media platforms show media relevant to a given location.

The related term [[geocoding]] refers to the process of taking non-coordinate based geographical identifiers, such as a street address, and finding associated [[geographic coordinates]] (or vice versa for [[reverse geocoding]]).  Such techniques can be used together with geotagging to provide alternative search techniques.

==Popular examples==
Geotagging has become a popular feature on several social media platforms, such as Facebook and Instagram.

[[Facebook]] users can geotag photos that can be added to the  page of the location they are tagging. Users may also use a feature that allows them to find nearby Facebook friends, by generating a list of people according to the location tracker in their mobile devices.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://techcrunch.com/2012/06/24/friendshake-facebooks-new-mobile-feature-for-finding-people-nearby-and-a-highlight-killer/ |title= Facebook’s New Mobile Feature For Finding People Around You |accessdate=2016-04-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Instagram]] uses a map feature that allows users to geotag photos. The map layout pin points specific photos that the user has taken on a world map.

==Geotagging techniques==
The geographical location data used in geotagging will, in almost every case, be derived from the [[global positioning system]], and based on a [[latitude]]/[[longitude]]-coordinate system that presents each location on the earth from 180° west through 180° east along the [[Equator]] and 90° north through 90° south along the [[prime meridian]].{{Citation needed|date=August 2014}}

===Geotagging photos===
{{main|Geotagged photograph}}
There are two main options for geotagging photos; capturing GPS information at the time the photo is taken or "attaching" the photograph to a map after the picture is taken.

In order to capture GPS data at the time the photograph is captured, the user must have a camera with built in GPS or a standalone GPS along with a digital camera. Because of the requirement for wireless service providers in United States to supply more precise location information for 911 calls by September 11, 2012,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.fcc.gov/cgb/consumerfacts/wireless911srvc.html |title=Wireless 911 Services |accessdate=2010-07-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; more and more cell phones have built-in GPS chips.  Most smart phones already use a GPS chip along with built-in cameras to allow users to automatically geotag photos. Others may have the GPS chip and camera but do not have internal software needed to embed the GPS information within the picture. A few digital cameras also have built-on or built-in GPS that allow for automatic geotagging.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.fireflyarticles.com/photography/photographers-have-several-camera-options-for-geotagging-pictures-with-gps-points-22.html|title=Photographers Have Several Camera Options for Geotagging Pictures with GPS Points}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Devices use GPS, A-GPS or both. [[Assisted GPS|A-GPS]] can be faster getting an initial fix if within range of a cell phone tower, and may work better inside buildings. Traditional GPS does not need cell phone towers and uses standard GPS signals outside of urban areas. Traditional GPS tends to use more battery power. Almost any digital camera can be coupled with a stand-alone GPS and post processed with photo mapping software, to write the location information to the image's [[exif]] header.

===GPS formats===
GPS coordinates may be represented in text in a number of ways, with more or fewer [[decimal]]s:
{| class="wikitable"
|-
! Template
! Description
! Example
|-
| [-]d.d, [-]d.d
| Decimal degrees with negative numbers for South and West.
| 12.3456, -98.7654
|-
| d° m.m′ &lt;nowiki&gt;{N|S}&lt;/nowiki&gt;, d° m.m′ &lt;nowiki&gt;{E|W}&lt;/nowiki&gt;
| Degrees and decimal minutes with N, S, E or W suffix for North, South, East, West
| 12° 20.736′ N, 98°&amp;nbsp;45.924′&amp;nbsp;W
|-
| &lt;nowiki&gt;{N|S}&lt;/nowiki&gt; d° m.m′ &lt;nowiki&gt;{E|W}&lt;/nowiki&gt; d° m.m′
| Degrees and decimal minutes with N, S, E or W prefix for North, South, East, West
| N 12° 20.736′, W&amp;nbsp;98°&amp;nbsp;45.924′
|-
| d° m' s" &lt;nowiki&gt;{N|S}&lt;/nowiki&gt;, d° m' s" &lt;nowiki&gt;{E|W}&lt;/nowiki&gt;
| Degrees, minutes and seconds with N, S, E or W suffix for North, South, East, West
| 12° 20' 44" N, 98°&amp;nbsp;45'&amp;nbsp;55"&amp;nbsp;W
|-
| &lt;nowiki&gt;{N|S}&lt;/nowiki&gt; d° m' s", &lt;nowiki&gt;{E|W}&lt;/nowiki&gt; d° m' s"
| Degrees, minutes and seconds with N, S, E or W prefix for North, South, East, West
| N 12° 20' 44", W&amp;nbsp;98°&amp;nbsp;45'&amp;nbsp;55"
|}

==Geotagging standards in electronic file formats==

===Photographs===
With photos stored in [[JPEG]], [[TIFF]] and many other file formats, the geotag information, storing camera location and sometimes heading, is typically embedded in the [[metadata]], stored in [[Exchangeable image file format]] (Exif) or [[Extensible Metadata Platform]] (XMP) format. These data are not visible in the picture itself but are read and written by special programs and most [[digital camera]]s and modern [[Image scanner|scanners]].  Latitude and longitude are stored in units of degrees with decimals.&lt;ref&gt;In this format, a positively signed coordinate indicates Northern or Eastern hemisphere, while negative sign indicates Southern or Western hemisphere.&lt;/ref&gt;  This geotag information can be read by many programs, such as the [[cross-platform]] [[open source]] [[ExifTool]]. An example readout for a photo might look like:

 &lt;code&gt;GPS Latitude                    : 57 deg 38' 56.83" N&lt;/code&gt;
 &lt;code&gt;GPS Longitude                   : 10 deg 24' 26.79" E&lt;/code&gt;
 &lt;code&gt;GPS Position                    : 57 deg 38' 56.83" N, 10 deg 24' 26.79" E&lt;/code&gt;

or the same coordinates could also be presented as decimal degrees:

 &lt;code&gt;GPS&lt;/code&gt;
 &lt;code&gt;GPS Longitude                   : 10.40744&lt;/code&gt;
 &lt;code&gt;GPS Position                    : 57.64911 10.40744&lt;/code&gt;

When stored in Exif, the coordinates are represented as a series of rational numbers in the GPS sub-IFD.  Here is a hexadecimal dump of the relevant section of the Exif metadata (with [[Endianness|big-endian]] byte order):

 &lt;code&gt;+ [GPS directory with 5 entries]&lt;/code&gt;
 &lt;code&gt;| 0)  GPSVersionID = 2 2 0 0&lt;/code&gt;
 &lt;code&gt;|     - Tag 0x0000 (4 bytes, int8u[4]):&lt;/code&gt;
 &lt;code&gt;|         dump: 02 02 00 00&lt;/code&gt;
 &lt;code&gt;| 1)  GPSLatitudeRef = N&lt;/code&gt;
 &lt;code&gt;|     - Tag 0x0001 (2 bytes, string[2]):&lt;/code&gt;
 &lt;code&gt;|         dump: 4e 00  [ASCII "N\0"]&lt;/code&gt;
 &lt;code&gt;| 2)  GPSLatitude = 57 38 56.83 (57/1 38/1 5683/100)&lt;/code&gt;
 &lt;code&gt;|     - Tag 0x0002 (24 bytes, rational64u[3]):&lt;/code&gt;
 &lt;code&gt;|         dump: 00 00 00 39 00 00 00 01 00 00 00 26 00 00 00 01&lt;/code&gt;
 &lt;code&gt;|         dump: 00 00 16 33 00 00 00 64&lt;/code&gt;
 &lt;code&gt;| 3)  GPSLongitudeRef = W&lt;/code&gt;
 &lt;code&gt;|     - Tag 0x0003 (2 bytes, string[2]):&lt;/code&gt;
 &lt;code&gt;|         dump: 57 00  [ASCII "W\0"]&lt;/code&gt;
 &lt;code&gt;| 4)  GPSLongitude = 10 24 26.79 (10/1 24/1 2679/100)&lt;/code&gt;
 &lt;code&gt;|     - Tag 0x0004 (24 bytes, rational64u[3]):&lt;/code&gt;
 &lt;code&gt;|         dump: 00 00 00 0a 00 00 00 01 00 00 00 18 00 00 00 01&lt;/code&gt;
 &lt;code&gt;|         dump: 00 00 0a 77 00 00 00 64&lt;/code&gt;

=== Remote sensing data ===
In the field of [[remote sensing]] the geotagging goal is to store coordinates of every pixel in the image. One approach is used with the [[orthophoto]]s where we store coordinates of four corners and all the other pixels can be georeferenced by [[interpolation]]. The four corners are stored using [[GeoTIFF]] or [[World file]] standards. [[Hyperspectral imaging|Hyperspectral images]] take a different approach defining a separate file of the same spatial dimensions as the image where [[latitude]] and [[longitude]] of each pixel are stored as two 2D layers in so called ''Input geometry data'' (IGM) files,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=ENVI Classic Tutorial: Georeferencing Images Using Input Geometry|url=http://www.exelisvis.com/portals/0/pdfs/envi/Georef_Input_Geometry.pdf|publisher=[[Exelis]]|accessdate=29 April 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; also known as GEO files.

===Audio/video files===
Audio/video files can be geotagged via: metadata, audio encoding, overlay, or with companion files.  Metadata records the geospatial data in the encoded video file to be decoded for later analysis. One of the standards used with [[unmanned aerial vehicle]] is '''[[:File:MISB_Standard_0601.pdf|MISB Standard 0601]]''' which allows geocoding of corner points and horizon lines in individual video frames.&lt;ref&gt;[[:File:MISB Standard 0601.pdf|MISB Standard 0601]]&lt;/ref&gt; Audio encoding involves a process of converting gps data into audio data such as modem squawk. Overlay involves overlaying GPS data as text on the recorded video.  Companion files are separate data files which correspond to respective audio/video files.  Companion files are typically found in the .KML and .GPX data formats.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ruggedvid.com/geospatial/|title=Airborne Geospatial Video Recorders, Cameras, and Systems|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;   For audio and video files which use the [[Vorbis comment|vorbiscomment]] metadata format (including [[Opus (audio codec)|Opus]], [[Ogg Vorbis]], [[FLAC]], [[Speex]], and [[Ogg Theora]]), there is a proposed GEO LOCATION&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://wiki.xiph.org/VorbisComment#Geo_Location_fields|title=VorbisComment – XiphWiki|website=wiki.xiph.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; field which can be used. Like all vorbiscomments, it is plain text, and it takes the form:

&lt;code&gt;GEO_LOCATION=(decimal latitude);(decimal longitude);([optional]elevation in meters)&lt;/code&gt;

for example:

&lt;code&gt;GEO_LOCATION=35.1592;-98.4422;410&lt;/code&gt;

===SMS messages===
The [[GeoSMS]] standard works by embedding one or more [[Geo URI|'geo' URI]]s in the body of an SMS, for example:

:&lt;code&gt;I'm at the pub geo:-37.801631,144.980294;u=16&lt;/code&gt;

===DNS entries===
{{main|LOC record}}
RFC 1876 defines a means for expressing location information in the [[Domain Name System]]. LOC resources records can specify the latitude, longitude, altitude, precision of the location, and the physical size of on entity attached to an IP address. However, in practice not all IP addresses have such a record, so it is more common to use [[geolocation]] services to find the physical location of an IP address.

===HTML pages===

====ICBM method====
{{main|ICBM address}}
The GeoURL&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://geourl.org/add.html |title=Adding yourself to GeoURL |accessdate=2008-07-30 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080515145826/http://geourl.org/add.html |archivedate=2008-05-15 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt; method requires the [[ICBM address|ICBM]] tag&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://tools.ietf.org/id/draft-daviel-html-geo-tag-08.txt| title=Geographic registration of HTML documents |author=The Internet Engineering Task Force |accessdate=2008-07-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; (plus optional [[Dublin Core]] metadata), which is used to geotag standard web pages in [[HTML]] format:

&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="html"&gt;
 &lt;meta name="ICBM" content="50.167958, -97.133185"&gt;
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

The similar Geo Tag format allows the addition of placename and region tags:

&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="html"&gt;
 &lt;meta name="geo.position" content="50.167958;-97.133185"&gt;
 &lt;meta name="geo.placename" content="Rockwood Rural Municipality, Manitoba, Canada"&gt;
 &lt;meta name="geo.region" content="ca-mb"&gt;
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

====RDF feeds====
The [[Resource Description Framework|RDF]] method is defined by W3 Group and presents the information in RDF tags:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/ |title=Basic Geo (WGS84 lat/long) Vocabulary |author=W3C Semantic Web Interest Group |accessdate=2008-07-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="xml"&gt;
&lt;rdf:RDF xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
         xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"&gt;
  &lt;geo:Point&gt;
  &lt;geo:lat&gt;55.701&lt;/geo:lat&gt;
  &lt;geo:long&gt;12.552&lt;/geo:long&gt;
  &lt;/geo:Point&gt;
&lt;/rdf:RDF&gt;
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

====Microformat====
The [[Geo (microformat)|Geo microformat]] allows coordinates within HyperText Markup Language pages to be marked up in such a way that they can be "discovered" by software tools. Example:

&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="html"&gt;
 &lt;span class="geo"&gt;
    &lt;span class="latitude"&gt;50.167958&lt;/span&gt;;
    &lt;span class="longitude"&gt;-97.133185&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

A proposal has been developed&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Geo Extension Straw-Man Proposal | url=http://microformats.org/wiki/geo-extension-strawman | accessdate=2007-12-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; to extend Geo to cover other bodies, such as [[Mars]] and the [[Moon]].

An example is the [[Flickr]] photo-sharing Web site, which provides geographic data for any [[geotagged photo]] in all of the above-mentioned formats.

===Geotagging in tag-based systems===
No industry standards exist, however there are a variety of techniques for adding geographical identification metadata to an information resource. One convention, established by the website [[Geobloggers]] and used by more and more sites, e.g. photo sharing sites [[Panoramio]] and [[Flickr]], and the social bookmarking site [[del.icio.us]], enables content to be found via a location search. Such sites allow users to add metadata to an information resource via a set of so-called ''machine tags'' (see [[folksonomy]]).

 &lt;code&gt;geotagged&lt;/code&gt;
 &lt;code&gt;geo:lat=57.64911&lt;/code&gt;
 &lt;code&gt;geo:lon=10.40744&lt;/code&gt;

This describes the geographic coordinates of a particular location in terms of [[latitude]] (geo:lat) and [[longitude]] (geo:lon). These are expressed in decimal degrees in the [[WGS84]] [[datum (geodesy)|datum]], which has become something of a default geodetic datum with the advent of [[GPS]].{{Citation needed|date=November 2007}}

Using three tags works within the constraint of having tags that can only be single 'words'. Identifying geotagged information resources on sites like [[Flickr]] and [[del.icio.us]] is done by searching for the 'geotagged' tag, since the tags beginning 'geo:lat=' and 'geo:lon=' are necessarily very variable.

Another option is to tag with a [[Geohash]]:

 &lt;code&gt;geo:hash=u4pruydqqvj&lt;/code&gt;

A further convention proposed by [[FlickrFly]] adds tags to specify the suggested viewing angle and range when the geotagged location is viewed in [[Google Earth]]:

 &lt;code&gt;ge:head=225.00&lt;/code&gt;
 &lt;code&gt;ge:tilt=45.00&lt;/code&gt;
 &lt;code&gt;ge:range=560.00&lt;/code&gt;

These three tags would indicate that the camera is pointed heading 225° (south west), has a 45° tilt and is 560 metres from the subject.

Where the above methods are in use, their coordinates may differ from those specified by the photo's internal Exif data, for example because of a correction or a difference between the camera's location and the subject's.

In order to integrate geotags in social media and enhance text readability or oral use, the concept of 'meetag' or tag-to-meet has been proposed. Differing from hashtag construction, meetag includes the geolocation information after an underscore. A meetag is therefore a word or an unspaced phrase prefixed with an underscore ("_"). Words in messages on microblogging and social networking services may be tagged by putting "_" before them, either as they appear in a sentence, (e.g. "There is a concert going _montreuxjazzfestival", "the world wide web was invented _cern _geneve", ...) or appended to it.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://meet.ag |title=Web page for the 'meetag standard' proposition |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140714201304/http://meet.ag/ |archivedate=2014-07-14 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Geoblogging===
Geoblogging attaches specific geographic location information to [[blog]] entries via ''geotags''. Searching a list of blogs and pictures tagged using geotag technology allows users to select areas of specific interest to them on interactive maps.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.everytrail.com/view_trip.php?trip_id=294109 |title=Example of pictures with geotag, using mobile phone}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The progression of [[GPS]] technology, along with the development of various online applications, has fueled the popularity of such tagged blogging, {{Citation needed|date=January 2008}} and the combination of [[GPS Phone]]s and [[GSM localization]], has led to the [[moblog]]ging, where blog posts are tagged with exact position of the user.  [[Real-time geotagging]] relays automatically geotagged media such as photos or video to be published and shared immediately.

For better integration and readability of geotags into blog texts, the [[meetag]] syntax has been proposed, which transforms any word, sentence, or precise geolocalization coordinates prefixed with an underscore into a 'meetag'. It not only lets one express a precise location but also takes in account dynamically changing geolocations.

===Wikipedia article geosearching apps===
{{Cleanup|date=July 2011}}
One of the first attempts to initiate the geotagging aspect of searching and locating articles seems to be the now-inoperative site Wikinear.com, launched in 2008, which showed the user Wikipedia pages that are geographically closest to one's current location.&lt;ref&gt;Willison, Simon. (2008). "[http://simonwillison.net/2008/Mar/22/wikinear/ Wininear.com, OAuth and Fire Eagle]", SimonWillison.net, Mar 22 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

The 2009 app [[Cyclopedia (iPhone application)|Cyclopedia]] works relatively well showing geotagged Wikipedia articles located within several miles of ones location, integrated with a street-view mode, and 360-degree mode.

The app Respotter Wiki, launched in 2009, claims to feature Wikipedia searching via a map, also allowing users to interact with people around them, via messaging and reviews, etc. The app, in its current function, however, seems to give only geotagged photo results.

As of 2017, the [[:de:Wikipedia:WikiProjekt_Georeferenzierung/Hauptseite/Wikipedia-World/en|Wikipedia-World Project]] provides a [https://tools.wmflabs.org/wp-world/karte.php?la=en simple map search tool] which can display tagged articles near to a particular location, as well as a variety of more sophisticated tools integrated with external mapping services.

==Dangers of geotagging==
Following a scientific study&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.usenix.org/events/hotsec10/tech/full_papers/Friedland.pdf |title=G. Friedland, R. Sommer: "Cybercasing the Joint: On the Privacy Implications of Geo-Tagging", 5th Usenix Hot Topics in Security Workshop (HotSec2010), Washington DC, August 2010. |format=PDF |date= |accessdate=2013-12-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; and several demonstrative websites,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pleaserobme.com|title=Please Rob Me|website=www.pleaserobme.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.icanstalku.com |title=icanstalku.com |publisher=icanstalku.com |date= |accessdate=2013-12-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; a discussion on the privacy implications of geotagging has raised public attention.&lt;ref&gt;{{YouTube|N2vARzvWxwY|NBC Action News Smartphone pictures pose privacy risk}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Heussner, Ki Mae, [http://abcnews.go.com/Technology/celebrity-stalking-online-photos-give-location/story?id=11162352 "Celebrities' Photos, Videos May Reveal Location"], ''ABC News'', July 16, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.newscientist.com/article/dn19160-geotags-reveals-celeb-secrets.html Geo-tags reveal celeb secrets], 12 July 2010, by Jim Giles, New Scientist&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2010/08/12/technology/personaltech/12basics.html?_r=2 |title=Web Photos That Reveal Secrets Such As Where You Live / "MythBusters" host inadvertently reveals his home address on Twitter |publisher=Nytimes.com |date= |accessdate=2013-12-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; In particular, the automatic embedding of geotags in pictures taken with smartphones is often ignored by cell-phone users. As a result, people are often not aware that the photos they publish on the Internet have been geotagged. Many celebrities reportedly gave away their home location without knowing it. According to the study, a significant number of for-sale advertisements on [[Craigslist]], that were otherwise anonymized, contained geotags, thereby revealing the location of high-valued goods—sometimes in combination with clear hints to the absence of the offerer at certain times. Publishing photos and other media tagged with exact geolocation on the Internet allows random people to track an individual's location and correlate it with other information. Therefore, criminals could find out when homes are empty because their inhabitants posted geotagged and timestamped information both about their home address and their vacation residence. These dangers can be avoided by removing geotags with a [[metadata removal tool]] for photos before publishing them on the [[Internet]].&lt;ref&gt;For instance, [http://www.superutils.com/products/exifcleaner/ ExifCleaner] and [http://www.steelbytes.com/?mid=30 JPEG &amp; PNG Stripper]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;iPhone-App [https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/imetaphoto/id549115463 iMetaPhoto]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2007, four [[United States Army]] [[AH-64 Apache#United States Army|Apache helicopters]] were destroyed on the ground by Iraqi insurgent mortar fire; the insurgents had made use of embedded coordinates in web-published photographs (geotagging) taken of the helicopters by soldiers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.army.mil/article/75165/Geotagging_poses_security_risks |title=Geotagging poses security risks |publisher=Army.mil |date= |accessdate=2013-12-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Another newly realised danger of geotagging is the location information provided to criminal gangs and poachers on the whereabouts of often endangered animals. This can effectively make tourists scouts for these poachers, so geotagging should be turned off when photographing these animals.

==See also==
&lt;!-- New links in alphabetical order please --&gt;
*[[Geocaching]]
*[[Geographic information system]] (GIS)
*[[Georeference]]
*[[Geomessaging]]
*[[GeoRSS]]
*[[Geotagged photograph]]
*[[GeoURI]]
*[[Supranet]]
*[[Tag (metadata)|Tagging]]
*[[Toponym Resolution]]

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

== Further reading ==
* {{Cite journal|first1=Jiebo|last1=Luo|first2=Dhiraj|last2=Joshi|first3=Jie|last3=Yu|first4=Andrew|last4=Gallagher|title=Geotagging in multimedia and computer vision—a survey|journal=Multimedia Tools and Applications|volume=51|issue=1|pages=187–211|doi=10.1007/s11042-010-0623-y|publisher=Springer}}

==External links==
* {{commonscatinline}}

{{Web syndication}}

[[Category:Geographic data and information]]
[[Category:Geocodes]]
[[Category:Global Positioning System]]</text>
      <sha1>121o3qegaw885orozzae3eupei14vg2</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Gordon Cullen</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9357204</id>
    <revision>
      <id>868890930</id>
      <parentid>844739849</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-11-15T03:07:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Atchom</username>
        <id>85952</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>clean up</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="6750">{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2012}}
{{Use British English|date=June 2012}}
'''Thomas Gordon Cullen''' (9 August 1914 – 11 August 1994) was an influential British [[architect]] and urban designer who was a key motivator in the [[Townscape]] movement. He is best known for the book ''Townscape'', first published in 1961.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://lccn.loc.gov/61016682|title=Library of Congress LCCN Permalink 61016682|website=Lccn.loc.gov|accessdate=3 February 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; Later editions of ''Townscape '' were published under the title ''The Concise Townscape''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://lccn.loc.gov/73161799 |archive-url=https://archive.is/20120710185037/http://lccn.loc.gov/73161799 |dead-url=yes |archive-date=2012-07-10 |title=Library of Congress LCCN Permalink 73161799 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Biography==
{{Refimprove section|date=February 2014}}
Cullen was born in [[Calverley]], Pudsey, near [[Leeds]], Yorkshire, England. He studied architecture at the [[University of Westminster|Royal Polytechnic Institution]], the present day University of Westminster, and subsequently worked as a draughtsman in various architects' offices including that of [[Berthold Lubetkin]] and [[Tecton]], but he never qualified or practised as an architect.

[[File:ScannedImage-7.jpg|thumb|right|alt=A drawing by Gordon Cullen showing his use of perspective|A drawing of Cullen's showing use of perspective.]]
Between 1944 and 1946 he worked in the planning office of the Development and Welfare Department in [[Barbados]], as his poor eyesight meant that he was unfit to serve in the British armed forces. He later returned to London and joined the ''[[Architectural Review]]'' journal, first as a draughtsman and then as a writer on planning policies. There he produced a large number of influential editorials and case studies on the theory of planning and the design of towns. Many improvements in the urban and rural environment in Britain during the 1950s and 1960s. He was also involved in the [[Festival of Britain]] in 1951. One of the few large scale Cullen works on public display is the mural in the foyer of the [[Erno Goldfinger]] designed [[Greenside School|Greenside Primary School]] in west London, completed in 1953.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.greenside.lbhf.sch.uk/ourschool |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2015-09-24 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150925113131/http://www.greenside.lbhf.sch.uk/ourschool |archivedate=25 September 2015 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; His 1958 ceramic mural in Coventry, depicting the history of the City and its post-war regeneration, is on a much grander scale though now relocated away from its original central location.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.c20society.org.uk/murals-campaign/11-gordon-cullen-ceramic-tile-mural-1958/|title=11 Gordon Cullen, Ceramic Tile Mural, 1958 — The Twentieth Century Society|website=C20society.org.uk|accessdate=3 February 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

His techniques consisted largely of sketchy drawings that conveyed a particularly clear understanding of his ideas, and these had a considerable influence on subsequent architectural illustration styles. He also illustrated several books by other various authors, before writing his own book - based on the idea of Townscape - in 1961. '''The Concise Townscape''' has subsequently been republished around 15 times, proving to be one of the most popular books on Urban Design in the 20th Century.

In 1956 Cullen became a freelance writer and consultant and, in the years immediately following he advised the cities of [[Liverpool]] and [[Peterborough]] on their reconstruction and redevelopment plans. In 1960 he was invited to [[India]] to advise on the planning aspects of the [[Ford Foundation]]'s work in [[New Delhi]] and [[Calcutta]] and so in 1962 he and his family lived in India for 6 months while he worked on the projects. Later, his work included planning advice to the city of [[Glasgow]] and during the 1980s the [[London Docklands Development Corporation]].

For a while Cullen teamed up with a student, David Price, and they formed an architectural firm together - Price &amp; Cullen. They won a competition in London in the 1980s and together designed and oversaw the building of the [[Swedish Quays]] housing development in Docklands. They worked together until 1990 as Price's first child was born and because Cullen's health was deteriorating. Price died in 2009 at the age of 53.

Cullen lived in the small village of [[Wraysbury]] (Berkshire) from 1958 until his death, aged 80, on 11 August 1994, following a serious stroke. After his passing, David Gosling and [[Norman Foster, Baron Foster of Thames Bank|Norman Foster]] collected various examples of his work and put them together in the book "Visions of Urban Design".

== Awards ==
In 1972 he was elected Honorary Fellow of the [[RIBA]]. In 1975 he was awarded with an [[Royal Designers for Industry|RDI]] for illustration and Townscape. The following year he was awarded a medal from [[The American Institute of Architects]]. In 1978 he was appointed a [[Commander of the Order of the British Empire|CBE]] for his contribution to architecture from [[Elizabeth II of the United Kingdom]].

==See also==
* [[Townscape]]
* [[LDDC]]
* [[Reg Ward]]
* [[Modern Architecture]]

==References==
;Citations
{{Reflist}}
;Sources
* David Gosling and Foster Norman. ''Gordon Cullen: Visions of Urban Design.'' Academy Editions, 1996. {{ISBN|1-85490-435-3}}
* Gordon Cullen. ''Townscape.'' Reinhold Pub. Corp., 1961. LC control #3 .C8
*8077783464 Gordon Cullen. ''The Concise Townscape''. {{ISBN|0-7506-2018-8}}

==External links==
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20081219132252/http://swedishquays.co.uk/ The website containing information on the competition won by both Cullen and Price.] The housing development is situated in [[London Docklands|Docklands]] on the [[River Thames|Thames]].
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20090111114833/http://swedishquays.co.uk/swedishquays/ A page from the website above showing the plaque dedicated to the architects].
*[http://arts.brighton.ac.uk/collections/design-archives/resources/rdis-at-britain-can-make-it,-1946/gordon-cullen Royal Designers for Industry &amp; Britain Can Make It]

==Gallery==
&lt;gallery mode="packed"&gt;
Greenside Primary School Erno Goldfinger 02.jpg|Partial view of the mural at [[Greenside School]]
Greenside Primary School Erno Goldfinger 03.jpg|Partial view of the mural at [[Greenside School]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Cullen, George}}
[[Category:1914 births]]
[[Category:1994 deaths]]
[[Category:British urban planners]]
[[Category:Landscape]]
[[Category:English landscape architects]]
[[Category:People from Pudsey]]
[[Category:Urban theorists]]
[[Category:Urban designers]]</text>
      <sha1>3vh0x9wuf45biovtx8zmfz6bbczuutc</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Heading (navigation)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>41677283</id>
    <revision>
      <id>854289333</id>
      <parentid>853739304</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-08-10T07:33:48Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Rodney Baggins</username>
        <id>32975992</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* top */ ce lead to match [[Course (navigation)]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="1102">{{unreferenced|date=January 2014}}
[[File:Wind drift.png|thumb|This navigation triangle shows the aircraft's ''heading'' towards point B (HDG), and its ''course'' towards C (TR). The drift angle, in red, is due to the wind, green.]]
In [[navigation]], the '''heading''' of a vessel or aircraft is the [[Points of the compass|compass direction]] in which the craft's bow or nose is pointed. This may not necessarily be the direction that the vehicle actually travels, which is known as its ''[[Course (navigation)|course]]'' or ''track''. Any difference between the heading and course is due to the motion of the underlying medium, the air or water, or other effects like [[skid (aerodynamic)|skidding]] or [[Slip (aerodynamic)|slipping]]. The difference is known as the ''drift'', and can be determined by the ''[[navigational triangle]]''.

== Notation ==
Heading is typically based on compass directions, so 0° (or 360°) indicates a direction toward true North, 90° indicates a direction toward true East, 180° is true South, and 270° is true West.

{{transport-stub}}



[[Category:Navigation]]</text>
      <sha1>k38e7cv00l5oc91jh91brnps4r902mp</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Index of gardening articles</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4277031</id>
    <revision>
      <id>846645609</id>
      <parentid>846214449</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-06-20T02:02:51Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Plantdrew</username>
        <id>14423536</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>not in botany navbox</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="4417">{{Main|Gardening}}
{{see also|Category:Gardening lists}}

This is a '''list of gardening topics.'''

{{AlphanumericTOC
| align=center
| nobreak=
| numbers=
| references=
| externallinks=
| top=
}}

==A==
[[Aesthetics]]
- [[African Violet Society of America]]
- [[Allotment (gardening)|Allotment]]
- [[Aquascaping]]
- [[Arboretum]]
- [[Architectural theory]]

==B==
[[Bonsai]]
- [[Botanical gardens]]

==C==
[[California native plants]]
- [[Chelsea Flower Show]]
- [[Community garden]]
- [[Companion planting]]
- [[Compost]]
- [[Composting]]
- [[Historic garden conservation|Conservation]]

==D==
[[Design]]

==E==
[[English garden]]
- [[Environmental design]]
- [[:Category:Environmental design|Category: Environmental design]]

==F==
[[Flowerbed]]
- [[Fountains]]
- [[French intensive gardening]]
- [[French landscape garden]]

==G==
[[Garden]]
- [[Garden designer]]
- [[:Category:Garden plants|Garden plants]]
- [[Gardener]]
- [[Gardening]]
- [[Garden buildings]]
- [[:Category:Garden features|Garden features]]
- [[Garden|List of gardens in fiction]]
- [[Garden tool]]
- [[Garden Gnome Liberation Front]]
- [[Garden à la française]]
- [[Gardens of the French Renaissance]]
- [[Gardens of Versailles]]
- [[:Category:Gardens by country|Gardens by country]]
- [[:Category:Gardens in Spain|Gardens in Spain]]
- [[Giardino all'italiana]]					
- [[Grandi Giardini Italiani]]
- [[Growbag]]
- [[Guerrilla gardening]]

==H==
[[History of gardening]]
- [[History of gardens]]
- [[History of landscape architecture]]
- [[hedge (barrier)|Hedge]]
- [[Herbaceous border]]
- [[Home economics]]
- [[Horticulture]]
- [[:Category:Horticulture and gardening|Horticulture and gardening]]

==I==
[[Invasive species]]
- [[Italian Renaissance garden]]

==J==
[[Japanese garden]]
- [[Japanese rock garden]]

==L==
[[:Category:Landscape architecture|Landscape architecture categories]]
- [[:Category:Landscape design history|Landscape design history categories]]
- [[:Category:Landscape gardens|Landscape gardens categories]]
- [[:Category:Landscape or garden designers|Landscape or garden designers categories]]
- [[:Category:Landscape|Landscape categories]]
- [[:Category:Lists of plants|Lists of plants categories]]
- [[History of gardening|List of notable historical gardens]]
- [[Land Arts of the American West]]
- [[Landscape architecture]]
- [[Landscape design]]
- [[Landscape detailing]]
- [[Landscape garden]]
- [[Landscape manager]]
- [[Landscape products]]
- [[Lawn]]
- [[Lawnmower]]
- [[List of botanical gardens in Italy]]
- [[List of botanical gardens in the United States]]
- [[List of Chinese gardens]]
- [[List of garden and horticulture books]]
- [[List of garden features]]
- [[List of garden plants]]
- [[List of gardens in Italy]]
- [[List of invasive species in North America]]
- [[List of organic gardening and farming topics]]
- [[List of professional gardeners]]
- [[Local food]]

==M==

==N==
[[Native plant gardening]]
- [[Natural landscaping]]
- [[Nature]] and [[Culture]]
- [[Never Ending Gardens]]
- [[No-dig gardening]]

==O==
[[Organic gardening]]
- [[Arboreta]]

==P==
[[Patio garden]]
- [[Pergola]]
- [[Parterre]]
- [[Permaculture]]
- [[:Category:Plant common names|Plant common names]]
- [[Plant community]]
- [[Planting design]]
- [[Flower pot]]
- [[Pruning]]

==R==
[[Rain gardens]]
- [[Raised bed gardening]]
- [[Remarkable Gardens of France]]
- [[:Category:Renaissance gardens|Renaissance gardens]]
- [[Rock garden]]
- [[Roof garden]]
- [[Roman garden]]

==S==
[[Sculpture garden]]
- [[Sheet mulching]]
- [[Shrub]]
- [[Spanish garden]]
- [[Spanish gardens]]
- [[Square foot gardening]]
- [[Statuary]]
- [[Sustainable art]]
- [[Sustainable design]]
- [[Sustainability]]

==T==
[[Terrace (gardening)|terrace]]
- [[Topiary]]
- [[Tree]]
- [[Tropical garden]]
- [[:Category:Types of garden|Types of garden]]

==V==
[[Vegetable farming]]

==W==
[[Water garden]]
- [[Water garden|water feature]]
- [[Wildlife corridor]]
- [[Wildlife garden]]

==X==
[[Xeriscaping]]

==Z==
[[Zen garden]]

==See also==
* [[List of organic gardening and farming topics]]
* [[List of garden plants]]
* [[List of professional gardeners]]

{{Horticulture and Gardening}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Gardening topics}}
[[Category:Landscape design history|History of Landscape design]]
[[Category:Gardening lists]]
[[Category:Horticulture and gardening]]
[[Category:Landscape]]
[[Category:Nature-related lists]]
[[Category:Wikipedia indexes]]</text>
      <sha1>b5ktnveoproxik1fhk6se2wk022wxti</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>José Antonio Sosa</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>53091648</id>
    <revision>
      <id>846524346</id>
      <parentid>845034259</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-06-19T08:48:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>KolbertBot</username>
        <id>31691822</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Bot: [[User:KolbertBot|HTTP→HTTPS]] (v485)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="19609">{{Infobox writer 
| name         = José Antonio Sosa
| image        = Profesor José Antonio Sosa Díaz-Saavedra.jpg
| caption       = José Antonio Sosa Diaz-Saavedra
| birth_date    = {{birth date and age|df=y|1957|5|8}}
| birth_place   = [[Gran Canaria]], [[Canary Islands]], [[Spain]]
| occupation   = [[Architect]], [[University Professor]]
| nationality  = [[Spain|Spanish]]
| movement     = 
| awards =  
}}

''' José Antonio Sosa''' (born 8 May 1957, [[Las Palmas]]) is a Spanish [[architect]], [[university professor]] and [[researcher]]. He is a member of the [[Royal Spanish Academy]].

== Early life and education ==
José Antonio Sosa Díaz-Saavedra was brought up in a family with an interest in art and history, especially in relation to the Canary Islands. As a result, he was encouraged to study architecture, graduating from the [[Superior Technical School of Architecture of Madrid]] in 1981. In 1994, he earned a [[Ph.D]] at the School of Architecture, [[University of Las Palmas de Gran Canaria]].

== Teaching ==

After completing his doctoral studies, he obtained the chair of Architectural Projects in the Department of Graphic Expression and Architectural Projects of the EALPGC, School of Architecture of Las Palmas de Gran Canaria, where he has been since 1983.

In the year 2000 he was "[[Visiting Scholar]]" and taught in the Department of Architecture, belonging to the Graduate School of Design, [[Harvard University]], he has also participated as a jury in several universities among which is the [[ETH Zurich|Swiss Federal Institute of Technology, ETH]] (Studio Basel).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url=http://arc.miami.edu/news/alonso-and-sosa-to-lecture-on-confluences-friday-april-1 |title=Alonso and Sosa to Lecture On Confluences Friday, April 1— On Confluences|publisher=University of Miami, School of Architecture |date= |archive-date=8 May 2014 |accessdate= 25 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2015 he joined the University Institute of Intelligent Systems and Numerical Applications in Engineering of the ULPGC, [[University of Las Palmas de Gran Canaria]].

== Main architecture contributions ==
José Antonio Sosa has been the main proponent of modern architectural development in the early twentieth century in the Canary Islands and Spain, promoting its place in the history of urban and cultural heritage. As a result, he was appointed a member of the Royal Spanish Academy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url=http://www2.ulpgc.es/hege/almacen/download/3/3767/20030714_C7_01.pdf |title= Un libro reivindica el valor de la arquitectura canaria entre 1925 y 1965 |publisher= ulpgc.es|date= |archive-date= 14 July 2007 |accessdate= 5 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title= «Guía de Arquitectura de España 1920-2000» |author=Anton Capitel |publisher= Tanais|isbn=9788449601026|date=2000 |archive-date= 10 March 2000 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=  «Guía de Arquitectura  Española 1929-1996» |author=Carlos Flores |publisher= Actar |isbn=84-920718-9-3 |date=1996 |archive-date= 23 September 1996 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title= "Diccionario Metapolis de Arquitectura" |author=Xavier Guell, Manuel Gausa Avanzada |publisher= Actar|isbn=9788495273932|date=2002 |archive-date= 8 October 2002 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1996 Professor Sosa joined his studio to [[Magüi González]] creating the Nred Arquitectos Group, where several projects stand out: the City of Justice (New Law Courts Headquarters) and the rehabilitation of the Town Halls (Town Hall Houses) of Las Palmas de Gran Canaria.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url=https://divisare.com/projects/254876-jose-antonio-sosa-magui-gonzalez-miguel-santiago-nred-arquitectos-roland-halbe-law-courts-complex|title= JOSÉ ANTONIO SOSA + MAGÜI GONZÁLEZ + MIGUEL SANTIAGO, NRED ARQUITECTOS LAW COURTS COMPLEX |publisher= divisare.com |date= |archive-date= 24 March 2014 |accessdate= 5 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url= http://www.nred-arquitectos.eu/esp/principal.php?web=jose|title= Nred Arquitectos, Jose Antonio sosa, Judicial City Las Palmas de Gran Canaria.|publisher= nred-arquitectos.eu |date= |archive-date=|accessdate= 6 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url= http://www.archdaily.co/co/02-353306/ciudad-de-la-justicia-magui-gonzalez-jose-antonio-sosa-miguel-santiago|title= City of Justice / Magüi González, José Antonio Sosa, Miguel Santiago|publisher= archdaily.co |date= |archive-date=|accessdate= 6 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url= http://www.nred-arquitectos.eu/esp/proyectosjose.php|title= Obras y proyectos / José Antonio Sosa|publisher= nred-arquitectos.eu |date= |archive-date=|accessdate= 6 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url= http://www.nred-arquitectos.eu/esp/curriculumjose.php|title= Nred Arquitectos,Curriculum José Antonio Sosa|publisher= nred-arquitectos.eu |date= |archive-date=|accessdate= 6 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url= http://www.buscalibre.com.ar/libro-magui-gonzalez-jose-antonio-sosa/9788461138517/p/4332129|title= Magui Gonzalez + José Antonio Sosa, Autor: Manuel Gausa|publisher= buscalibre.com.ar |date= |archive-date=|accessdate= 6 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url= http://www.archilovers.com/jose-antonio-sosa/|title= Jose Antonio Sosa,Law Courts Complex|publisher= archilovers.com|date= 2013|archive-date= 12 June 2013 |accessdate= 5 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Since 2011, he has founded a new studio for [[architecture]] and [[urban planning]] together with Evelyn Alonso Rohner.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url=http://www.alonso-sosa.com/|title=Alonso + Sosa Studio, Jose Antonio Sosa and Evelyn Alonso Rohner, Alonso + Sosa Architects |publisher= |date= |archive-date=|accessdate= 25 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2015 José Antonio Sosa is the managing editor of the Arquiatesis editorial line for the publication and publication of theses and research works in architecture.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url=http://fundacion.arquia.es/concursos/tesis/AcercaDe|title=Arquia tesis acerca de|publisher= Arquia Tesis|date= |archive-date=|accessdate= 8 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Individual and Collective exhibitions ===

Sosa, has participated in the following exhibitions:
&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url= http://www.siani.es/Jose%20Antonio%20Diaz%20Saavedra.html|title= JOSE ANTONIO SOSA|publisher= SIANI, University Institute of Intelligent Systems and Numeric Applications in Engineering|date= |archive-date=|accessdate= 25 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*1997 "Hard &amp; Soft" Eight Floor Gallery, (New York), USA
*2003 "One is always Two", Professional Architects Association (Tenerife), Spain
*2003 "Spaces for intimacy" Hall los Aljibes (Lanzarote), Spain 
*2004 "DakÁrt Biennial" (Dakar), Senegal
*2005 "Sao Paulo Architecture Biennial", Brazil.
*2005 "Architecture for Justice" COAC. (Madrid), Spain
*2007 "Individual exhibition": Nred Architects, Literary Cabinet. (Las Palmas), Spain
*2007 "Regeneration Strategy", Nacional Library. (Pekín), China
*2007 "Refabricating City "Shenzhen &amp; Hong Kong, Biennial of Urban Planning and Architecture. (Hong Kong), China
*2007 "Xisi Bei street". (Beijing), China &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url= http://www.orgnets.net/bdm_rrr/|title= Interpretation of China Space - Renovate Restorate Renew |publisher= Exhibition of a Conceptual Design for New Xisi Bei Street, Beijing |date= |archive-date=8 May 2014 |accessdate= 25 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*2008 "Gallery AEDES". (Berlin), Germany &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url= http://www.aedes-arc.de/cms/aedes/de/programm?id=373843|title= NRED ARCHITECTS, GRAN CANARIA,MAGÜI GONZÁLEZ UND JOSÉ ANTONIO SOSA, abstract natures |publisher= Aedes, Architectum Forum |date= |archive-date=|accessdate= 25 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url= http://www.abc.es/hemeroteca/historico-23-10-2008/abc/Canarias/la-arquitectura-canaria-llega-a-berlin_91765356009.html|title= La Arquitectura Canaria llega a Berlín|publisher= abc.es, hemeroteca |date= |archive-date=|accessdate= 8 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*2008" Sustainable Building. (Melbourne), Australia
*2007-2009 "Biennial of Art, Architecture and landscape of Canarias". (Las Palmas), Spain
*2009 "Object Art" Manuel Ojeda Gallery. (Las Palmas), Spain 
*2010-2011 "A city called Spain". (Athens-Moscow), Greece-Russia
*2015-2016 Exhibition at the MAXXI (Museo Nazionale delle Arti del XXI Secolo in Rome), Italy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url= http://canariasenhora.com/#!/workshop-internacional-de-arquitectura-en-el-caam|title=Workshop' internacional de arquitectura en el CAAM|publisher=canariasenhora.com|date= |archive-date=|accessdate= 6 June 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*2017 "In process". Exhibition of architectural models by Alonso-Sosa in the Saro León Gallery. (Las Palmas), Spain.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url=http://semanaarquitectura2017.arquitectosgrancanaria.es/exposicion_enproceso/|title=Exposición ‘En proceso’ de Alonso + Sosa arquitectos|publisher=semanaarquitectura2017.arquitectosgrancanaria.es|date= |archive-date=|accessdate= 6 June 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Acknowledgments ===

==== Royal Academy Member ====
* Admission of José Antonio Sosa Díaz-Saavedra into the Real Academia de Bellas Artes de Canarias of San Miguel Arcangel  (Royal Canarian Academy of Fine Arts of St. Michael Archángel.), 2014.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=|url=http://cultura.arquitectosgrancanaria.es/2014/05/05/140505_jasosa_racba/|title= Ingreso de José Antonio Sosa Díaz-Saavedra en la RACBA, Real Academia Canaria de Bellas Artes, 2014 |publisher= Royal Academy of Fine Arts of Canary Islands , Royal Spanish Academy |date= |archive-date=8 May 2014 |accessdate= 25 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Awards ====
Professor Sosa has been awarded in the following competitions:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=|url=https://www.ulpgc.es/noticia/sosadiaz_07052014/|title= El Catedrático José Antonio Sosa Díaz-Saavedra, numerario de la Real Academia de Bellas Artes|publisher= ULPGC |date= |archive-date=8 May 2014 |accessdate= 8 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*2006 First prize, The Venegas Public Square and Underground Car Park
*2005 First prize, Puerto del Rosario Waterfront
*2005 First prize, La Regenta Art Center
*2004 First prize, the City of Justice (New Law Courts Headquarter) in Las Palmas.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=|title= Nred arquitectos &amp; Santiago, Ciudad de la Justicia en Las Palmas|publisher= AV Monografías| number=165-166 |date= 10 May 2014 |issn=0213-487X}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*2002 First prize, The Rehabilitation (building restoration) of the Town Hall Las Palmas, Gran Canaria 
*1997 First prize, The Rehabilitation (building restoration) of the Literary Cabinet "Design and Ideas"
*2008 Third prize,The Madrid. Slaughterhouse
*2008 First prize, Rehabilitation, Consistorial Houses of the Palmas de Gran Canaria (Melbourne Sustainable Building)
*2008 First Accésit, For Architectural Renovation (building restoration) of the Old Tabakalera in Donostia-San Sebastián
*2012 First prize, Railway Station of Playa del Inglés
*2013 Second prize, Station-20, Sophia, Bulgaria
*2016 First prize, A House in a Garden, Gran Canaria

== Buildings  ==

Some of them are:&lt;ref&gt;«Catálogo Exposición Nred arquitectos».SOSA, José Antonio; GONZÁLEZ, Maria Luisa; MUÑOZ, Clara; ABALOS, Iñaki; GAUSA,Manuel. Gobierno de Canarias, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

*2003 Loyola`s Foundation Administrative building, Spain
*2003 The Elongated House. (Gran Canaria), Spain (In collaboration with Miguel Santiago),
*2004 The Hidden House. (Gran Canaria), Spain 
*2008 Rehabilitación (building restoration) Town Hall of (Las Palmas), Spain (In collaboration with Magüi González)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url= http://www.nred-arquitectos.eu/esp/proyectojose/135|title= Rehabilitation of Consistorial Houses, 1rst Prize, Melbourne Sustainable Building 2008|date= |archive-date= 8 April 2016 |accessdate= 26 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*2010 Black Pavilion. (Las Palmas),  Spain  
*2010 Art Center, La Regenta. (Las Palmas), Spain 
*2011 The Z House. (Gran Canaria), Spain&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url= http://www.archdaily.com/499220/z-house-jose-antonio-sosa|title= Z House - Jose Antonio Sosa |publisher= archdaily|date= |archive-date=24 Apr 2014 |accessdate= 26 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url= http://www.nred-arquitectos.eu/esp/proyectojose/3|title= Casa Z, Jose Antonio Sosa |publisher= nred-arquitectos.eu|date= |archive-date=24 Apr 2014 |accessdate= 6 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*2011 Station-20. (Sophia), Bulgaria
*2012 Railway Station of Playa del Inglés. (Las Palmas), Spain   
*2012 The City of Justice,"New Law Courts Headquarter". (Las Palmas), Spain. (Jointly with Magüi González y Miguel Santiago)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url= http://arquiscopio.com/los-nuevos-juzgados-de-gran-canaria/|title=Los nuevos Juzgados de Gran Canaria
|publisher= arquiscopio.com|date= 2013|archive-date= 14 June 2013 |accessdate= 8 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*2012 Central Library of Helsinki, Finland (Jointly with Evelyn Alonso Rohner)
*2014 Philologicum of Munich, Germany (Jointly with Evelyn Alonso Rohner)
*2014 The Loft Apartment, emblematic house intervention and renewal. (Las Palmas), Spain (Jointly with Evelyn Alonso Rohner).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url= http://www.archilovers.com/projects/128876/the-loft-boutique-apartment.html|title=The Loft Boutique Apartment|date= 2014|archive-date= 6 October 2014 |accessdate= 4 June 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*2014 Total building rehabilitation Buganvilla Apartments. (Gran Canaria), Spain. (Jointly with Evelyn Alonso Rohner).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url= http://www.coolhuntercanarias.com/trips-travel/-2015/09/14/apartamentos-buganvilla-el-limite-es-el-mar/|title=Hotel Buganvilla: El límite es el mar|date= 2015|archive-date= 14 September 2015 |accessdate= 4 June 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*2015-16 Industrial building renewal,  Group Volkswagen franchisee “Majuelos” La Laguna, Tenerife , Spain. (Jointly with Evelyn Alonso Rohner)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url= https://www.motor2000.net/noticia.php?N=11504|title=Domingo Alonso inaugura unas vanguardistas instalaciones en Tenerife|date= 2017|archive-date= 7 June 2017 |accessdate= 4 June 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*2016-17 Rehabilitation of the Industrial and Commercial Building “La Loza” (Las Palmas), Spain. (Jointly with Evelyn Alonso Rohner).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url=https://www.academia.edu/35179915/171005_libro_COMPLETO_Saro_León.pdf|title= "En proceso", alonso and sosa arquitectos|date= 2017|archive-date= 27 October 2017 |accessdate= 4 June 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Publications ==

=== Books ===

Sosa has published the following texts:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url= http://www.todostuslibros.com/autor/sosa-diaz-saavedra-jose-antonio|title= Ten titles to "Sosa Diaz Saavedra Jose Antonio |publisher= todostuslibros.com|date= |archive-date=24 Apr 2014 |accessdate= 8 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* ''En Proceso'', José Antonio Sosa, Evelyn Alonso, David Alemán, Vidania Báez, Álvaro del Amo, Carlos Marrero, 2017 {{ISBN|978-84-697-5304-0}}
* Confluences. José Antonio Sosa, Magūi González, Miguel Santiago, Evelyn Alonso, Author: Ana Maria Torres, Publisher: Cinisello Balsamo, Milano Silvana,2015, {{ISBN|9788836630189}} 
* Paisajes de Encuentro. José Antonio Sosa,2007 {{ISBN|978-84-7947-432-4}}
* Redes. José Antonio Sosa,2007 {{ISBN|978-84-611-6387-8}}
* Corralejo. José Antonio Sosa,2007 {{ISBN|978-84-614-2065-0}}
* NRED Arquitectos, Compilación. José Antonio Sosa,  Maria L. Gonzalez, Graham Thomson,Clara Jiménez, Publisher: Literary Cabinet of Las Palmas, 2006 {{ISBN|978-84-611-3851-7}}
* Cultivo. José Antonio Sosa, Eva Alfonso, Hector Sanchez 2005 {{ISBN|978-84-7931-043-1}}
* Hibridaciones. José Antonio Sosa, Eva Alfonso, Hector Sanchez 2005 {{ISBN|978-84-7931-042-4}}
* Aprendiendo del Territorio. José Antonio Sosa, Pedro Nicolas Romera, 2004 {{ISBN|978-84-609-0777-0}}
*Arquitectura Moderna y Turismo: 1925-1965: Proceedings IV Congreso DOCOMOMO Iberian Foundation, José Antonio Sosa Díaz-Saavedra, Carmen Jordá Such, Nuno Portas, DOCOMOMO Iberian Foundation of Valencia, 2003 {{ISBN|84-609-2997-3}}
*La Casa del Marino, Las Palmas de Gran Canaria, 1958-1964: José Antonio Sosa, Miguel Martín-Fernández, Colegio de Arquitectos de Almería, 2002. {{ISBN|84-921038-8-4}}
*Contextualismo y Abstracción. Interrelaciones entre suelo, paisaje y arquitectura,1994 {{ISBN|84-606-2613-X}}

=== Articles ===

Among them are:
&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url= https://dialnet.unirioja.es/servlet/autor?codigo=1975737|title= José Antonio Sosa Díaz-Saavedra, Periodo de publicación recogido 1984 - 2015 |publisher= dialnet.unirioja.es|date= |archive-date= 11 August 2015 |accessdate= 8 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*Introspecciones Elocuentes. José Antonio Sosa Díaz-Saavedra Annals of the Royal Canarian Academy of Fine Arts of San Miguel Arcángel..: RACBA, ISSN 2174-1484, Nº. 8, 2015, págs. 165-168
*Naturalezas Abstractas. José Antonio Sosa Díaz-Saavedra, Annals of the Royal Canarian Academy of Fine Arts of San Miguel Arcángel.: RACBA, ISSN 2174-1484, Nº. 7, 2014, págs. 143-152
*Armazones. José Antonio Sosa Díaz-Saavedra, Transfer, ISSN 1695-1778, Nº. 5, 2003, pág. 107
*Condiciones de Contorno. Official Magazine, Colegio de Arquitectos de Madrid (COAM), ISSN 0004-2706, Nº. 345, 2006, págs.
*Espacios sin Sombra. José Antonio Sosa Díaz-Saavedra, Official Magazine, Colegio de Arquitectos de Madrid (COAM), ISSN 0004-2706, Nº. 330, 2003, págs. 48-5
*Una Nube en una Jaula, (La Maison Suspendu). José Antonio Sosa Díaz-Saavedra y, Paul Nelson Official Magazine, Colegio de Arquitectos de Madrid (COAM), ISSN 0004-2706, Nº. 328, 2002, págs. 20-27
*Capó y Envolventes. José Antonio Sosa Díaz-Saavedra y Magüi González, Basa, ISSN 0213-0653, Nº. 24, 2001, págs. 138-145
*Coello de Portugal en Canarias. José Antonio Sosa Díaz-Saavedra, Basa, ISSN 0213-0653, Nº. 22, 2000, págs. 20-41
*Constructores de Ambientes. del mat-building a la lava programática, José Antonio Sosa Díaz-Saavedra Quaderns 220, 1998
*Vacío: deriva y captura. José Antonio Sosa Díaz-Saavedra y Magüi González, Basa, ISSN 0213-0653, Nº. 19, 1996, págs. 68-71
*El Cabildo Racionalista de Gran Canaria "Alejandro de la Sota" y el proyecto para su ampliación. José Antonio Sosa Díaz-Saavedra, Magui González, Official Magazine, Colegio de Arquitectos de Madrid (COAM), ISSN 0004-2706, Nº. 300, 1994, págs. 42-48
*El Paisaje como Premisa de Proyecto en el Movimiento Moderno. José Antonio Sosa Díaz-Saavedra, Félix J. Bordes Caballero), Basa, ISSN 0213-0653, Nº. 16, 1994, págs. 98-103
*Doce Apartamentos en Playa del Inglés. Playa del Inglés "Gran Canaria", José Antonio Sosa Díaz-Saavedra y Francisco Campos, Basa, ISSN 0213-0653, Nº. 10, 1989, págs. 98-101
* Ideas y Obras. José Antonio Sosa Díaz-Saavedra, Basa, ISSN 0213-0653, Nº. 2, 1984 (Book dedicated to: Eduardo Westerdahl), págs. 33-36

== References==
{{Reflist}}

{{authority control}}

==External links==
* [http://www.siani.es/Jose%20Antonio%20Diaz%20Saavedra.html SIANI]
* [http://www.english.ulpgc.es/ University of Las Palmas de Gran Canaria]
* [https://www.ulpgc.es/noticia/sosadiaz_07052014 El Catedrático José Antonio Sosa Díaz-Saavedra, numerario de la Real Academia de Bellas Artes]
* [https://www.alonso-sosa.com/ Alonso &amp; Sosa Architects]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Sosa, Jose Antonio}}
[[Category:1957 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:People from Las Palmas]]
[[Category:Spanish architects]]
[[Category:Modernist architects]]
[[Category:Modernist architecture]]
[[Category:Members of the Royal Spanish Academy]]
[[Category:Urban planners]]
[[Category:Urban designers]]
[[Category:Landscape]]
[[Category:Landscape architecture]]</text>
      <sha1>84g6fqwuerhzimffb8m7fmqlq7c1bo4</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Land rehabilitation</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>469799</id>
    <revision>
      <id>830995332</id>
      <parentid>830992936</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-03-18T03:37:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bahudhara</username>
        <id>12215099</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Reverted to revision 829578367 by [[Special:Contributions/Klbrain|Klbrain]] ([[User talk:Klbrain|talk]]): Rvv. ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="5099">{{more footnotes|date=May 2012}}
[[Image:Wetland restoration in Australia.jpg|250px|right|thumb|Recently constructed wetland regeneration in Australia, on a site previously used for agriculture.]]
[[File:Regenerated habitat for superb parrot on the abandoned Boroowa railway line.JPG|250px|right|thumb|Regenerated habitat for the [[superb parrot]] on the abandoned Boroowa railway line]]
'''Land rehabilitation''' is the process of returning the land in a given area to some degree of its former state, after some process ([[industry]], [[natural disaster]]s, etc.) has resulted in its damage. Many [[project]]s and [[Subdivision (land)|development]]s will result in the land becoming [[environmental degradation|degraded]], for example [[mining]], [[farming]] and [[forestry]].

==Mine rehabilitation==
Modern mine rehabilitation aims to minimize and mitigate the [[Environmental effects of mining|environmental effects of modern mining]], which may in the case of [[open pit]] mining involve movement of significant volumes of rock. Rehabilitation management is an ongoing process, often resulting in open pit mines being backfilled.

After mining finishes, the mine area must undergo rehabilitation. 
* [[Waste dump]]s are contoured to flatten them out, to further stabilize them against [[erosion]].
* If the ore contains [[sulfides]] it is usually covered with a layer of [[clay]] to prevent access of [[rain]] and [[oxygen]] from the [[air]], which can [[Oxidation|oxidize]] the sulfides to produce [[sulfuric acid]].
* [[Landfill]]s are covered with [[topsoil]], and [[vegetation]] is planted to help consolidate the material.
* Dumps are usually fenced off to prevent [[livestock]] denuding them of vegetation.
* The open pit is then surrounded with a fence, to prevent access, and it generally eventually fills up with [[groundwater]].
* [[Tailings]] [[dam]]s are left to [[evaporate]], then covered with waste rock, clay if need be, and [[soil]], which is planted to stabilize it.

For underground mines, rehabilitation is not always a significant problem or cost. This is because of the higher grade of the [[ore]] and lower volumes of waste rock and tailings. In some situations, [[Stoping (mining method)|stope]]s are backfilled with [[concrete]] [[slurry]] using waste, so that minimal waste is left at surface.

The removal of [[Physical plant|plant]] and [[infrastructure]] is not always part of a rehabilitation programme, as many old mine plants have [[cultural heritage]] and [[cultural]] value. Often in [[gold]] mines, rehabilitation is performed by scavenger operations which treat the soil within the plant area for spilled gold using modified [[placer mining]] [[gravity]] collection plants.

Also possible is that the section of the mine that is below ground, is kept and used to provide heating, water and/or methane. Heat extraction can be done using heat exchangers, that convey the heat to a nearby city (hence making it be used for [[district heating]] purposes.&lt;ref&gt;[http://warmopweg.nl/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/Lokale-warmte-initiatieven-en-de-rol-van-burgercollectieven-in-de-warmtemarkt.pdf MijnWater BV recovering heat from abandoned mines]&lt;/ref&gt;
Water can be harvested from the mine as well (mines are often filled with water once the mine has been shut down and the pumps no longer operate). Methane is also often present in the mine shafts, in small quantities (often around 0,1%). This can still be recovered though with specialised systems.&lt;ref&gt;The West Cliff Collier Power Plant has successfully been able to recover methane from ventilation shafts of mines&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.globalmethane.org/documents/events_all_20101208_mattus.pdf Ventilation Air Methane]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The Blue Economy By Gunter Pauli&lt;/ref&gt; An added advantage of recovering the methane finally is that the methane does not come into the atmosphere, and so does not contribute to global warming.

==See also==
* [[Land restoration]]
* [[Forest restoration]], [[Reforestation]]
* [[Prairie restoration]]
* [[Restoration ecology]]
* [[Environmental remediation]]
* [[Holistic management]]
* [[Mine reclamation]]
* [[Soil salinity control]] - rehabilitation of salinized soils
* [[Watertable control]] - rehabilitation of waterlogged soils
* [[Land reclamation]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* Rehabilitation of waterlogged and saline soils: [http://www.waterlog.info], free downloads of software and articles on land drainage.
* [http://www.biorecycleaustralia.com/forest.html Bio Recycle]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20060711185930/http://www.sydneywater.com.au/EnsuringTheFuture/Biosolids/ Sydney Water BioSolids]
*[http://www.eemp.org EEMP] - a non-profit 501 (c) 3 organization dedicated to communicate the lessons of rehabilitation and restoration through media around the world.

[[Category:Construction]]
[[Category:Environmental issues with soil]]
[[Category:Economic geology]]
[[Category:Landscape]]
[[Category:Land management]]
[[Category:Ecological restoration]]

[[da:Naturgenopretning]]
[[et:Rekultiveerimine]]
[[fr:Renaturation]]
[[pl:Renaturyzacja]]</text>
      <sha1>5b5ni55urwb8scdir5coh77xj252kpm</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>List of explorations</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9502</id>
    <revision>
      <id>836216365</id>
      <parentid>805480649</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-04-13T11:40:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Onel5969</username>
        <id>10951369</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Disambiguating links to [[European exploration of Australia]] (link changed to [[European maritime exploration of Australia]]) using [[User:Qwertyytrewqqwerty/DisamAssist|DisamAssist]].</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="5795">Some of the most important '''[[exploration]]s''' of [[Complex society|State Societies]], in chronological order:

&lt;!-- table --&gt;
{| class="wikitable"
|-
! Exploration
! When
! Who ([[Exploration|explorer]])
|-
| Northwest [[Africa]]n coast ([[West Africa]])
|  about 500 BC
| [[Hanno the Navigator]]
|-
| The [[Mediterranean Sea]]
| 5th century BC
| [[Himilco the Navigator]]
|-
| Around western [[Europe]] to [[Thule (myth)|Thule]] Island
|  about 330 BC  
| [[Pytheas]] of Marseilles
|-
| [[Greenland]]
| 900
| [[Gunnbjörn Ulfsson]]
|-
| [[Americas]] ([[North America]])
| 999
| [[Leif Ericson]]
|-
| [[Brazil]] ([[South America]]) - ''controversial''
| c. 14th century CE
| [[Abu Bakr II]]
|-
| [[Sahelian kingdoms]]
| 1351-1354
| [[Ibn Battuta]]
|-
| Great permanent wind wheel of [[Volta do Mar]], the [[North Atlantic Gyre]]. Recognition of the [[Sargasso Sea]], [[Madeira]], [[Azores]] and [[West Africa|West African]] coast. [[Cape Verde]]
| 1427-1460
| Several navigators: Portuguese or serving Portugal, most under the sponsorship of [[Henry the Navigator]]
|-
| [[Congo River]], [[Angola]] and [[Namibia]]
| 1482-1485
| [[Diogo Cão]]
|-
| [[South Africa]]. Connected the [[Atlantic]] to the [[Indian Ocean]]. [[South Atlantic]]'' [[Volta do Mar]]'' winds
| 1482-1485
| [[Bartolomeu Dias]]
|-
| [[Caribbean]], [[Venezuela]] ([[South America]]) and [[Central America]]. Use and development of the North Atlantic [[Volta do Mar|routes]]
| 1493-1502
| [[Christopher Columbus]]
|-
| [[Atlantic Ocean]] ([[Volta do Mar|outer routes]]) and [[Indian Ocean]], ''Sea route to [[India]]'' ([[Europe]] to [[Asia]])
| 1497-1499
| [[Vasco da Gama]]
|-
| [[Brazil]], South Atlantic [[Volta do Mar]], Indian Ocean, [[Madagascar]], gate of the [[Red Sea]] ([[Bab-el-Mandeb]] Strait); [[India]]. Voyage that united [[Europe]], [[Americas]], [[Africa]] and [[Asia]]
| 1500-1501
| [[Pedro Álvares Cabral]] and [[Diogo Dias]], among others
|-
| [[Timor]], [[Moluccas]] ([[Australasia]] - Pacific Ocean)
| 1512-1513
| [[António de Abreu]] and [[Francisco Serrão]]
|-
| [[Circumnavigation]] of the Globe. Connection from the Atlantic to the [[Pacific Ocean]] (America to Asia)
| 1519-1522
| [[Ferdinand Magellan]] and [[Juan Sebastián Elcano]]
|-
| [[Mexico]]
| 1519-1521
| [[Hernán Cortés]]
|-
| Brazil, [[Paraguay]], [[Bolivia]] and east of the [[Inca]] Empire
| 1525-1527
| [[Aleixo Garcia]]
|-
| Traveled across the Southwest of [[North America]] (Completely)
| 1528
| [[Álvar Núñez Cabeza de Vaca]]
|-
| [[Peru]], [[Inca]] Empire and [[Ecuador]]
| 1531-1534
| [[Francisco Pizarro]]
|-
| [[Ecuador]] and Brazil. Length of the [[Amazon river]]
| 1531-1534
| [[Francisco de Orellana]]
|-
| [[Canada]], [[Saint Lawrence River]]
| 1534-1542
| [[Jacques Cartier]]
|-
| [[Colombia]], [[Spanish conquest of the Muisca|Conquest of the Muisca]]
| 1536-1537
| [[Gonzalo Jiménez de Quesada]]
|-
| [[Pacific Ocean]]'s [[Volta do Mar]] (Asia to America)
| 1564-1565
| [[Andrés de Urdaneta]]
|-
| [[Galápagos Islands]], [[Rapa Nui]]
| c. 1480
| [[Topa Inca Yupanqui|Tupaq Inka Yupanki]]. 1594-1597&lt;br&gt;Rediscovered by the Spanish
|-	
| [[North]], [[Canada]] ([[Hudson Bay]]) 
| 1574-1631 	
| [[Henry Hudson]]
|-
| [[North]]
| 1594-1597 
| [[Willem Barents]]
|-
| [[Siberia]] and Pacific coast.
| 1649-1641 
| [[Ivan Yuryevich Moskvitin]]
|-
| [[Oceania]]
| 1642-1643 
| [[Abel Tasman]]
|-
| Brazil (Circumnavigation), Paraguay, Bolivia and Peru. Connected the [[Río de la Plata Basin|River Plate Basin]] to the [[Andes]] and to the mouth of the [[Amazon River]]
| 1648-1651 
| [[António Raposo Tavares]]
|-
| [[Oceania]]
| 1768-1779 
| [[James Cook]]
|-
| North [[Pacific]], western [[Alaska]], Far East Eurasian Coast
| 1771
| [[Moric Benovsky]] 
|-
| [[Hawaiian Islands]]
| By c. 800
| [[Hawaiʻiloa]] (mythical)
|-
| [[Central America]] and [[Latin America]]
| 1799-1803
| [[Alexander von Humboldt]]
|-
| [[Indigenous peoples of the Northwest Plateau|Northwest Plateau of North America]]
| 1804-1806
| [[Lewis and Clark Expedition]]
|-
| The [[North Magnetic Pole]]
| 1831-06-01
| [[James Clark Ross]]
|-
| [[Australia (continent)|Australia]]
| c. 1640
| [[Makassan contact with Australia|Makassar People]] before. Explored by Abel Tasman
|-
| Interior of Africa
| 1851-1873
| [[David Livingstone]]
|-
| The [[Burke and Wills expedition]] (Central Australia)
| 1860-1861
| [[Robert O'Hara Burke]] and [[William John Wills]]
|-
| Exploration of the Zambeze river region, Central Africa, Angola, Mozambique, Zambia, Zaire
| 1877
| [[Serpa Pinto]]
|-
| The [[Northern Sea Route]]
| 1878
| [[Adolf Erik Nordenskiöld]]
|-
| The [[South Magnetic Pole]]
| January 16, 1909
| [[Douglas Mawson]], [[Edgeworth David]], and [[Alistair Mackay]]
|-
| The [[North Pole]]
| April 6, 1909
| [[Robert Peary]]
|-
| The [[South Pole]]
| December 14, 1911
| [[Roald Amundsen]]
|-
| The [[South Pole]]
| January 17, 1912
| [[Robert Falcon Scott]]
|-
| [[Mount Everest]] Summit
| May 29, 1953
| Sir [[Edmund Hillary]] and [[Tenzing Norgay]]
|-
| The [[Moon]]
| July 20, 1969
| [[Neil Armstrong]], [[Michael Collins (astronaut)|Michael Collins]], and [[Buzz Aldrin]] (''[[Apollo 11]]'')
|-
| [[Mars]]
| 1960 to present
| [[NASA]] and other [[space agency]] exploration robots 
|}

==See also==
* [[Age of Discovery]]
* [[European maritime exploration of Australia|Exploration of Australia]]
* [[List of lost expeditions]]
* [[List of Russian explorers]]
* [[Exploration of the High Alps]]
* [[Portugal in the period of discoveries]]
* [[Chronology of European exploration of Asia]]

{{DEFAULTSORT:List Of Explorations}}
[[Category:Exploration|*Explorations]]
[[Category:History-related lists|Explorations]]

[[bs:Istraživanja]]
[[de:Entdeckungsreise]]
[[es:Cronología de las exploraciones]]
[[hr:Zemljopisna otkrića]]</text>
      <sha1>n0heb31avxra9e4ulbvpbnv063sbphd</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>List of international prime ministerial trips made by Jacinda Ardern</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>55792911</id>
    <revision>
      <id>869270901</id>
      <parentid>869190348</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-11-17T15:07:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>2607:FEA8:20DF:F26B:2CCC:6A3B:316A:F8FE</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* 2018 */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="14710">{{Use dmy dates|date=March 2018}}
{{Use New Zealand English|date=March 2018}}
[[File:Ardern travels.svg|thumb|right|261px|Map of international trips made by Jacinda Ardern as prime minister
{{legend|#a1a7ef|1 visit}}
&lt;!-- {{legend|#737ce8|2 visits}} --&gt;
{{legend|#4f5ae3|3 visits}}
&lt;!--{{legend|#2533dd|4 visits}}
{{legend|#1a25ac|5 visits}}
{{legend|#111976|6 visits}}
{{legend|#050725|7 or more visits}}--&gt;
{{legend|#000000|New Zealand}}]]
This is a '''list of international prime ministerial trips made by Jacinda Ardern''', the [[List of Prime Ministers of New Zealand|40th]] [[Prime Minister of New Zealand|Prime Minister]] of New Zealand. {{As of|November 2018}}, [[Jacinda Ardern]] has made eight international trips to twelve sovereign countries and two [[associated state]]s of New Zealand, since her premiership began on 26 October 2017.

== Summary ==
{| class="wikitable" style="margin: 1em auto 1em auto"
|-
! scope="col"| Number of visits
! scope="col"| Country
|-
!scope="row"| 3
| {{flatlist|
*[[Australia]]
}}
|-
!scope="row"| 1
| {{flatlist|
*[[Cook Islands]]&lt;ref group="note" name="AS"/&gt;
*[[France]]
*[[Germany]]
*[[Nauru]]
*[[Niue]]&lt;ref group="note" name="AS"/&gt;
*[[Philippines]]
*[[Papua New Guinea]]
*[[Samoa]]
*[[Singapore]]
*[[Tonga]]
*[[United Kingdom]]
*[[United States]]
*[[Vietnam]]
}}
|}

== 2017 ==
{| class="wikitable sortable" border="1" style="margin: 1em auto 1em auto"
|-
!scope="col" style="width: 12%;"|Country
!scope="col" style="width: 18%;"|Locations
!scope="col" style="width: 12%;"|Dates
!scope="col" style="width: 58%;" class="unsortable"|Details
|-
!scope="row"| {{flag|Australia}}
| [[Sydney]]
| {{sort|1|5 November}}
|Ardern met Prime Minister [[Malcolm Turnbull]].&lt;ref name="McGowan"&gt;{{cite web |last1=McGowan |first1=Michael |title=Warm relations as Turnbull and Ardern stow differences in chilly bin|url=https://www.theguardian.com/australia-news/2017/nov/05/warm-relations-as-turnbull-and-ardern-stow-differences-in-chilly-bin|work=[[The Guardian]] |accessdate=25 November 2017|date=5 November 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
!scope="row"|{{flag|Vietnam}} 
| {{flatlist|
*[[Hanoi]]
*[[Ho Chi Minh City]]
*[[Da Nang]]
}}
| {{sort|2|9–11 November}}
|Ardern attended the [[2017 APEC Summit]] and met with Vietnamese President [[Trần Đại Quang]] and Prime Minister [[Nguyễn Xuân Phúc]], Japanese Prime Minister [[Shinzō Abe]] and Malaysian Prime Minister [[Najib Razak]]. &lt;ref name="Small"&gt;{{cite web |last1=Small|first1=Vernon |title=PM Jacinda Ardern appears to be in fine form despite Apec's frenetic pace|url=https://www.stuff.co.nz/national/politics/98782687/pm-jacinda-ardern-appears-to-be-in-fine-form-despite-apecs-frenetic-pace|website=[[Stuff.co.nz]]|accessdate=25 November 2017|date=10 November 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
!scope="row"| {{flag|Philippines}}
| {{flatlist|
*[[Manila]]
*[[Pasay]]
}}
| {{sort|3|12–14 November}}
|Ardern attended the [[2017 ASEAN Summits|31st ASEAN Summit]] and the [[Twelfth East Asia Summit]] and met with Filipino President [[Rodrigo Duterte]], Canadian Prime Minister [[Justin Trudeau]] and Indian Prime Minister [[Narendra Modi]]. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Jacinda Ardern meets President of the Philippines|url=http://www.nzherald.co.nz/national-video/news/video.cfm?c_id=1503075&amp;gal_cid=1503075&amp;gallery_id=184712 |work=[[The New Zealand Herald]] |accessdate=25 November 2017|date=15 November 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|}

== 2018 ==
{| class="wikitable sortable" border="1" style="margin: 1em auto 1em auto"
|-
!scope="col" style="width: 12%;"|Country
!scope="col" style="width: 18%;"|Locations
!scope="col" style="width: 12%;"|Dates
!scope="col" style="width: 58%;" class="unsortable"|Details
|-
!scope="row"| {{flag|Australia}}
| [[Sydney]]
| {{sort|1|1–2 March}}
| Ardern met Prime Minister [[Malcolm Turnbull]] to discuss [[Closer Economic Relations]] and spoke at the Australia–New Zealand Leadership Forum.&lt;ref group="note"&gt;{{cite press release |url=https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/joint-statement-hon-malcolm-turnbull-and-rt-hon-jacinda-ardern |title=Joint statement by the Hon Malcolm Turnbull and Rt Hon Jacinda Ardern |date=2 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.radionz.co.nz/news/political/351587/pm-angling-for-business-deal-in-australia |title=PM angling for business deal in Australia |first=Chris |last=Bramwell |date=1 March 2018 |publisher=[[Radio New Zealand]] |accessdate=2 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
!scope="row"| {{flag|Samoa}}
| {{flatlist|
*[[Apia]]
*[[Magiagi Tai]]
}}
| {{sort|2|5–6 March}}
| Ardern met Prime Minister [[Tuilaepa Aiono Sailele Malielegaoi]]. Visited [[National University of Samoa]] and [[Robert Louis Stevenson]] Museum.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Henry |last=Cooke |url=https://www.stuff.co.nz/national/politics/101995813/jacinda-arderns-island-honeymoon-with-samoa-comes-with-big-promises |title=Jacinda Ardern's island honeymoon with Samoa comes with big promises |publisher=[[Stuff.co.nz]] |date=5 March 2018 |accessdate=6 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
!scope="row"| {{flag|Niue}}&lt;ref group="note" name="AS"&gt;The [[Cook Islands]] and [[Niue]] are [[associated state]]s of New Zealand.&lt;/ref&gt;
| [[Alofi]]
| {{sort|3|6 March}}
| Ardern met her father and New Zealand High Commissioner [[Ross Ardern]]. Discussed economic and environmental sustainability with Prime Minister [[Toke Talagi]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.radionz.co.nz/news/political/351887/pm-s-pacific-island-trip-becomes-a-family-reunion |title=PM's Pacific Island trip becomes a family reunion |publisher=[[Radio New Zealand]] |date=6 March 2018 |accessdate=6 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=https://nz.news.yahoo.com/family-affair-ardern-niue-150046933--spt.html |title=Family affair for Ardern in Niue |first=Boris |last=Jancic |work=Newswire |publisher=[[Yahoo!]] |date=6 March 2018 |accessdate=6 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
!scope="row"| {{flag|Tonga}}
| [[Nuku'alofa]]
| {{sort|4|6–8 March}}
|Ardern met with Prime Minister [[ʻAkilisi Pōhiva]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.stuff.co.nz/national/politics/102039953/prime-minister-jacinda-ardern-arrives-in-a-turbulent-tonga |title=Prime Minister Jacinda Ardern arrives in a turbulent Tonga |first=Henry |last=Cooke |publisher=Stuff.co.nz |date=6 March 2018 |accessdate=7 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.radionz.co.nz/international/pacific-news/351971/new-zealand-pm-in-tonga |title=New Zealand PM in Tonga |publisher=Radio New Zealand |date=7 March 2018 |accessdate=7 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
!scope="row"| {{flag|Cook Islands}}&lt;ref group="note" name="AS"/&gt;
| [[Rarotonga]]
| {{sort|5|8 March}}
| Ardern met with Prime Minister [[Henry Puna]] and discussed pension portability.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.stuff.co.nz/national/politics/102082994/PM-Jacinda-Ardern-announces-pension-portability-for-Cook-Islanders-Tokeulauns-and-Niueans |title=PM Jacinda Ardern announces pension portability for Cook Islanders, Tokeulauns and Niueans |first=Henry |last=Cooke |publisher=Stuff.co.nz |date=8 March 2018 |accessdate=8 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; Later that day changes were announced to make it easier for residents of the [[Realm of New Zealand]] to access New Zealand superannuation payments.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.radionz.co.nz/international/pacific-news/352085/easier-access-to-nz-pension-for-realm-countries |title=Easier access to NZ pension for Realm countries |publisher=Radio New Zealand |date=8 March 2018 |accessdate=9 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
!scope="row"| {{flag|Australia}}
| [[Gold Coast, Queensland|Gold Coast]]
| {{sort|6|13–14 April}}
| Ardern met with Team New Zealand's medal winners and watched the [[Hockey at the 2018 Commonwealth Games – Women's tournament|women's hockey final]] at the [[2018 Commonwealth Games|Commonwealth Games]].&lt;ref name="grateful"&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.radionz.co.nz/news/political/354947/i-am-grateful-that-her-majesty-is-taking-the-time-to-meet-me |title=Prime Minister Jacinda Ardern to meet the Queen in London next week |publisher=Radio New Zealand |date=13 April 2018 |accessdate=15 April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.nzherald.co.nz/sport/news/article.cfm?c_id=4&amp;objectid=12032673 |title=Hockey: Black Sticks women claim first ever Commonwealth Games gold |first=Andrew |last=Alderson |work=The New Zealand Herald |date=14 April 2018 |accessdate=14 April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
!scope="row"| {{flag|France}}
|[[Paris]]
|{{sort|7|16 April}}
|Ardern met President [[Emmanuel Macron]] to discuss climate change,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.nzherald.co.nz/nz/news/article.cfm?c_id=1&amp;objectid=12033655 |title=Ardern, Trudeau and Macron: The young guns share Paris in the springtime |work=The New Zealand Herald |date=16 April 2018 |accessdate=17 April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; the [[2018 bombing of Damascus and Homs]] and trade, after which Macron declared support for a European Union–New Zealand Free Trade Agreement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.radionz.co.nz/news/national/355258/france-supports-nz-eu-trade-negotiations |title=France supports NZ-EU trade negotiations |publisher=Radio New Zealand |date=16 April 2018 |accessdate=17 April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ardern also discussed the [[CPTPP]] with Canadian Prime Minister [[Justin Trudeau]] and spoke about climate change at [[Sciences Po]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.radionz.co.nz/news/political/355269/ardern-hails-trade-vision-france-s-macron-to-visit-nz |title=Ardern hails trade 'vision', France's Macron to visit NZ |publisher=Radio New Zealand |first=Craig |last=McCulloch |date=17 April 2018 |accessdate=17 April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.nzherald.co.nz/nz/news/article.cfm?c_id=1&amp;objectid=12033811 |title=PM Jacinda Ardern speaks about climate change after meeting with French president Emmanuel Macron in Paris |date=17 April 2018 |accessdate=17 April 2018 |work=The New Zealand Herald |first=Claire |last=Trevett}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
!scope="row"|{{flag|Germany}}
|[[Berlin]]
|{{sort|8|17 April}}
|Ardern met with Chancellor [[Angela Merkel]] and discussed trade which included Merkel's support of a Free Trade Agreement between New Zealand and the European Union, [[Brexit]] the ongoing tensions with Russia, the Syrian bombings, climate change and co-operation over science and space. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.radionz.co.nz/news/political/355348/merkel-ardern-discuss-threats-to-world-order |title=Merkel, Ardern discuss threats to world order |first=Craig |last=McCulloch |publisher=Radio New Zealand |date=18 April 2018 |accessdate=18 April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
!scope="row"| {{flag|United Kingdom}}
|[[London]]
|{{sort|9|17–21 April}}
&lt;ref&gt;https://www.stuff.co.nz/national/politics/103194073/jacinda-ardern-to-meet-british-pm-prince-charles&lt;/ref&gt;
|Ardern met with [[Charles, Prince of Wales]] and [[Camilla, Duchess of Cornwall]]. Then met with British Prime Minister [[Theresa May]] where discussions about Russia dominated the meeting. Also attended a Town Hall debate with Canadian Prime Minister [[Justin Trudeau]], hosted by London Mayor [[Sadiq Khan]] and a [[Five Eyes]] meeting with Prime Minister May, Trudeau and Turnbull to receive an intelligence briefing. The following day Ardern attended the [[Commonwealth Heads of Government Meeting 2018]] and met with [[Elizabeth II]]. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.stuff.co.nz/national/politics/103004525/jacinda-ardern-and-justin-trudeau-in-london-town-hall-event |title=Jacinda Ardern and Justin Trudeau in London town hall event |first=Laura |last=Walters |publisher=Stuff.co.nz |date=11 April 2018 |accessdate=11 April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
!scope="row"| {{flag|Nauru}}
|
|{{sort|10|5 September}}
|Ardern attended the [[Pacific Islands Forum]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.stuff.co.nz/world/south-pacific/106858635/pm-jacinda-ardern-leader-steals-limelight-in-nauru |title=PM Jacinda Ardern leader steals limelight in Nauru |first=Nick |last=Perry |publisher=[[Stuff.co.nz]] |date=5 September 2018 |}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
!scope="row"| {{flag|United States}}
|[[New York City]]
| {{sort|10|24–28 September}}
|Ardern delivered a keynote speech at the Social Good Summit, met with [[UNICEF]] Executive Director [[Henrietta Fore]] and [[United Nations]] Secretary General [[Antonio Guterres]]. She then made a keynote speech at the opening of Climate Week, made a statement at the Nelson Mandela Peace Summit Opening Plenary, held bilateral meetings with Colombian President [[Iván Márquez]], Irish Prime Minister [[Leo Varadkar]], Austrian Chancellor [[Sebastian Kurz]] and Spanish Prime Minister [[Pedro Sánchez (politician)|Pedro Sánchez]] and attended US President [[Donald Trump]]’s reception for heads of delegation. Thereafter Ardern spoke at the Global Planet Summit, the [[Bloomberg Global Business Forum]] and held a tri-lateral meeting with Canadian Prime Minister [[Justin Trudeau]] and Chilean President [[Sebastián Piñera]]. The following day Ardern spoke at a meeting on the Prevention and Control of Non-Communicable Diseases, made a speech at the International Conference on Sustainable Development, attended the inaugural meeting of the Carbon Nutrality Coalition and delivered New Zealand's national statement at the [[Seventy-third session of the United Nations General Assembly]]. 
|-
!scope="row"| {{flag|Singapore}}
|[[Singapore]]
| {{sort|11|13–17 November}}
|Ardern attended the 33rd [[ASEAN Summit]] and the [[Thirteenth East Asia Summit]] and held bilateral meetings with Burmese State Counsellor [[Aung San Suu Kyi]], Australian Prime Minister [[Scott Morrison]], Chinese Premier [[Li Keqiang]], Singaporean Prime Minister [[Lee Hsien Loong]], Japanese Prime Minister [[Shinzō Abe]] and Malaysian Prime Minister [[Mahathir Mohamad]]. &lt;ref name="Walters"&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.newsroom.co.nz/2018/11/12/318701/great-power-rivalry-on-the-agenda |title=Great power rivalry on the agenda |first=Laura |last=Walters |date=12 November 2018 |work=[[Newsroom (website)|Newsroom]] |accessdate=13 November 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
!scope="row"| {{flag|Papua New Guinea}}
|[[Port Moresby]]
| {{sort|12|17–19 November}}
|Ardern attended the [[APEC Papua New Guinea 2018|2018 APEC Summit]].&lt;ref name="Walters"/&gt;
|}

==See also==
*[[Foreign relations of New Zealand]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|group="note"}}

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

{{Jacinda Ardern}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Ardern, Jacinda, International prime ministerial trips made by }}
[[Category:Jacinda Ardern|International prime ministerial trips]]
[[Category:2017 in international relations]]
[[Category:Diplomatic visits by heads of government]]
[[Category:Foreign relations of New Zealand]]
[[Category:Geography-related lists]]
[[Category:Lists of diplomatic trips]]
[[Category:New Zealand diplomacy-related lists]]
[[Category:2018 in international relations]]</text>
      <sha1>7x7zx41xify9q3b8vcxikwtpqpzu212</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>List of towns and cities with 100,000 or more inhabitants/cityname: Z</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>11486275</id>
    <revision>
      <id>866992711</id>
      <parentid>859519682</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-11-02T22:36:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>JalenFolf</username>
        <id>4052843</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Template transclusion</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="2652">{{City 100000|type=cityname|Z}}
{{City 100000 index}}

=={{small|List of cities beginning with letter}} Z==
[[File:Chromos i Zagrebtower.jpg|right|thumb|250px|[[Zagreb]], [[Croatia]]]]
{| class="wikitable sortable" border="1"
|-
! City
! Country
|-
| [[Zaanstad]]
| {{NLD}}
|-
| [[Zabol]]
| {{IRN}}
|-
| [[Zabrze]]
| {{POL}}
|-
| [[Zacatecas, Zacatecas|Zacatecas]]
| {{MEX}}
|-
| [[Zagazig]]
| {{EGY}}
|-
| [[Zagreb]]
| {{HRV}}
|-
| [[Zahedan]]
| {{IRN}}
|-
| [[Zama, Kanagawa|Zama]]
| {{JPN}}
|-
| [[Zamboanga City]]
| {{PHL}}
|-
| [[Zamora, Michoacán|Zamora de Hidalgo]]
| {{MEX}}
|-
| [[Zanjan, Iran|Zanjan]]
| {{IRN}}
|-
| [[Zanzibar City]]
| {{TZA}}
|-
| [[Zaoyang]]
| {{CHN}}
|-
| [[Zaozhuang]]
| {{CHN}}
|-
| [[Zapopan]]
| {{MEX}}
|-
| [[Zaporizhia]]
| {{UKR}}
|-
| [[Zaragoza]]
| {{ESP}}
|-
| [[Zaria]]
| {{NGA}}
|-
| [[Zarqa]]
| {{JOR}}
|-
| [[Zelenograd]]
| {{RUS}}
|-
| [[Zenica]]
| {{BIH}}
|-
| [[Zhalantun]]
| {{CHN}}
|-
| [[Zhangjiagang]]
| {{CHN}}
|-
| [[Zhangjiajie]]
| {{CHN}}
|-
| [[Zhangjiakou]]
| {{CHN}}
|-
| [[Zhangshu]]
| {{CHN}}
|-
| [[Zhangye]]
| {{CHN}}
|-
| [[Zhangzhou]]
| {{CHN}}
|-
| [[Zhanjiang]]
| {{CHN}}
|-
| [[Zhaodong]]
| {{CHN}}
|-
| [[Zhaoqing]]
| {{CHN}}
|-
| [[Zhaotong]]
| {{CHN}}
|-
| [[Zheleznodorozhny, Moscow Oblast|Zheleznodorozhny]]
| {{RUS}}
|-
| [[Zhengzhou]]
| {{CHN}}
|-
| [[Zhenjiang]]
| {{CHN}}
|-
| [[Zhongshan]]
| {{CHN}}
|-
| [[Zhoukou]]
| {{CHN}}
|-
| [[Zhoushan]]
| {{CHN}}
|-
| [[Zhucheng]]
| {{CHN}}
|-
| [[Zhuhai]]
| {{CHN}}
|-
| [[Zhuji]]
| {{CHN}}
|-
| [[Zhukovsky, Moscow Oblast|Zhukovsky]]
| {{RUS}}
|-
| [[Zhumadian]]
| {{CHN}}
|-
| [[Zhuozhou]]
| {{CHN}}
|-
| [[Zhuzhou]]
| {{CHN}}
|-
| [[Zhytomyr]]
| {{UKR}}
|-
| [[Zibo]]
| {{CHN}}
|-
| [[Zielona Góra]]
| {{POL}}
|-
| [[Zigong]]
| {{CHN}}
|-
| [[Ziguinchor]]
| {{SEN}}
|-
| [[Zinder]]
| {{NER}}
|-
| [[Zixing]]
| {{CHN}}
|-
| [[Zlatoust]]
| {{RUS}}
|-
| [[Zoetermeer]]
| {{NLD}}
|-
| [[Zrenjanin]]
| {{SRB}}
|-
| [[Zunyi]]
| {{CHN}}
|-
| [[Zürich]]
| {{CHE}}
|-
| [[Zuwarah]]
| {{LBY}}
|-
| [[Zwolle]]
| {{NLD}}
|}

==See also==
* [[World largest cities]]

==References==
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20090228180315/http://unstats.un.org/unsd/demographic/sconcerns/densurb/urban.aspx Population of capital cities and cities of 100,000 and more inhabitants] United Nations Statistics Division, accessed 24 August 2006

{{DEFAULTSORT:List Of Towns And Cities With 100,000 Or More Inhabitants Cityname: Z}}
[[Category:Geography-related lists|Towns and cities with 100,000 or more inhabitants]]
[[Category:Lists of towns and cities with 100,000 or more inhabitants|100,000 or more inhabitants]]

[[lt:Pasaulio šalių didmiesčiai]]</text>
      <sha1>rqwklpam6cl63l0s6bakaxeqkkxrcjd</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Nautical measured mile</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>32374980</id>
    <revision>
      <id>732170736</id>
      <parentid>720539465</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-07-30T03:19:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>OmniBot</username>
        <id>27920258</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>did [[WP:AWB/GF|general fixes]] if needed, replaced: See Also → See also</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="1815">[[File:Admiralty Distance Poles at St Abb's Head - geograph.org.uk - 1552719.jpg|thumb|right|Admiralty Distance Poles at [[St Abb's Head]].]]
{{wiktionary|measured mile}}
A '''nautical measured mile''' is a [[nautical mile]] which is marked by two pairs of towers. A mile is measure by sailing on a given [[bearing (navigation)|bearing]] and lining up the pairs of towers.  The start of the mile is recorded when the first pair of towers line up and the end of the mile recorded when the second pair line up.

To accurately measure performance ships must make at least four to six runs in both directions to allow for the wind and tide.    
                 
There are several nautical measured miles around the British Isles:
* Between [[Talland|Talland Bay]] and Hannafore, [[Looe#West Looe|West Looe]], [[Cornwall]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title= Nautical Measured Mile Markers|publisher=Polperro village website|url=http://www.polperro.org/measuredmile.html|author=Tony White|date=March 2003|accessdate=11 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* At [[Skelmorlie]], [[North Ayrshire]], [[Scotland]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Skelmorlie Measured Mile|publisher=Kintyre on Record|author=Dee Kay|date=February 21, 2009|accessdate=11 July 2011|url=http://www.kintyreonrecord.co.uk/articles.php?article_id=151}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* There are four Admiralty Distance Poles at [[St Abb's Head]], [[Berwickshire]], [[Scotland]].&lt;ref name="SS"&gt;{{cite web|title=Measured Miles|publisher=Secret Scotland|accessdate=11 July 2011|url=http://www.secretscotland.org.uk/index.php/Secrets/MeasuredMiles}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* There are two consecutive miles on the [[Isle of Arran]], [[Scotland]] between [[Sannox|South Sannox]] and Corloch.&lt;ref name="SS"/&gt;

==See also==
*[[Navigation transit markers]]

==References==
&lt;references /&gt;

[[Category:Navigation]]


{{Water-transport-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>jie7k1v4y94afnmnnkatp89iiyl6bk6</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Nightscape</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>52744449</id>
    <revision>
      <id>853697411</id>
      <parentid>823004857</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-08-06T12:23:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>2hark</username>
        <id>34359519</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="644">A '''nightscape''' or '''night view''' is the visible features of an area of [[landscape]] as viewed at [[night]].&lt;ref name="New Oxford American Dictionary"&gt;''New Oxford American Dictionary''&lt;/ref&gt;
{{multiple image
 | align     = right
 | direction = horizontal
 | image1    = Hong Kong Night view.jpg
 | width1    = 150
 | caption1  =Nightscape of [[Victoria Harbour]] from [[Victoria Peak]], [[Hong Kong]]
 | image2    = Monaco - Port en décembre.jpg
 | width2    = 150
 | caption2  = A night view in [[Monaco]]
}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==

[[Category:Landscape]]
[[Category:Landscape architecture]]
[[Category:Night]]</text>
      <sha1>1zjb8cjiowhl2ubjn0wbnnz524n5jdj</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Plane table</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>12978962</id>
    <revision>
      <id>857089415</id>
      <parentid>853941104</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-08-29T14:02:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Dougsim</username>
        <id>1457274</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>added image</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="4738">{{for|the mountain|Plane Table}}
A '''plane table''' ('''plain table''' prior to 1830)&lt;ref name=gturner/&gt; is a device used in [[surveying]] and related disciplines to provide a solid and level surface on which to make field drawings, charts and maps.  The early use of the name ''plain table'' reflected its simplicity and plainness rather than its flatness.&lt;ref name=kiely/&gt;

==History==
[[File:US Army Corps of Engineers Map Making, World War I.jpg|thumb|Using a plane table]]
The earliest mention of a plane table dates to 1551 in Abel Foullon's ''"Usage et description de l'holomètre"'', published in Paris.&lt;ref name=aturner&gt;Turner, Anthony, ''Early Scientific Instruments, Europe 1400-1800'', Sotheby's Publishing, 1987, {{ISBN|0-85667-319-6}}.  page 81&lt;/ref&gt;  However, since Foullon's description was of a complete, fully developed instrument, it must have been invented earlier.&lt;ref name=kiely/&gt;

A brief description was also added to the 1591 edition of Digge's ''Pantometria''.&lt;ref name=aturner/&gt;  The first mention of the device in English was by [[Cyprian Lucar]] in 1590.&lt;ref name=gturner&gt;Turner, Gerard L'E., ''Scientific Instruments 1500-1900, An Introduction'', [[University of California Press]], 1998 {{ISBN|0-85667-491-5}}.  This is an updated version of his earlier ''Antique Scientific Instruments'' Blandford Press Ltd. 1980, {{ISBN|0-7137-1068-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some have credited Johann Richter, also known as [[Johannes Praetorius]],&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=rmrGS9s-KewC&amp;pg=PA200&amp;lpg=PA200&amp;dq=johannes+%22plane+table%22&amp;source=web&amp;ots=BM1Ad8syAu&amp;sig=XHgQ7YZ8GZY___o6hqfhuTvD_pQ  Vai, Gian Battista, Caldwell, W. G. E. ''The Origins of Geology in Italy''] Google books online copy&lt;/ref&gt; a [[Nuremberg]] mathematician, in 1610&lt;ref name="laussedat"&gt;Laussedat, Amié, ''Recherches sur les instruments, les méthodes et le dessin topographiques'', Paris, 1898-1902, two volumes&lt;/ref&gt; with the first plane table, but this appears to be incorrect.

The plane table became a popular instrument for [[surveying]].&lt;ref name=kiely&gt;Kiely, Edmond, ''Surveying Instruments: Their history and classroom use'', Bureau of Publications, Teachers College, Columbia University, 1947. page 228&lt;/ref&gt;  Its use was widely taught.  Some considered it a substandard instrument compared to other devices such as the [[theodolite]], since it was relatively easy to use.&lt;ref name=gturner/&gt;  By allowing the use of graphical methods rather than mathematical calculations, it could be used by those with less education than other instruments. The addition of a camera to the plane table, as was done from 1890 by [[Sebastian Finsterwalder]] in conjunction with a [[phototheodolite]], established photogrammetry in spatial and temporal surveying.

==Plane table construction==
[[File:Plane table cgs00426.jpg|thumb|300px|A plane table cutaway.&lt;br&gt;  This shows a plane table with part of the surface of the table cut away to show the mounting on the tripod.  The mount allows the table to be levelled.  On the table, the [[alidade]] with telescopic sight is seen]]A plane table consists of a smooth table surface mounted on a sturdy base.  The connection between the table top and the base permits one to level  the table precisely, using [[bubble level]]s, in a horizontal plane.  The base, a tripod, is designed to support the table over a specific point on land.  By adjusting the length of the legs, one can bring the table level regardless of the roughness of the terrain. 

==Use of a plane table==
In use, a plane table is set over a point and brought to precise horizontal level.  A drawing sheet is attached to the surface and an [[alidade]] is used to sight objects of interest.  The alidade, in modern examples of the instrument a [[ruler|rule]] with a [[telescopic sight]], can then be used to construct a line on the drawing that is in the direction of the object of interest.

By using the alidade as a surveying level, information on the topography of the site can be directly recorded on the drawing as elevations.  Distances to the objects can be measured directly or by the use of [[stadia mark]]s in the telescope of the alidade.

==References==
{{reflist}}

*Raymond Davis, Francis Foote, Joe Kelly, ''Surveying, Theory and Practice'', [[McGraw-Hill]] Book Company, 1966 LC 64-66263

==External links==
*[http://americanhistory.si.edu/collections/surveying/enlarge.cfm?recordnumber=764357 Telescopic Plane Table Alidade] in the collection of the Smithsonian National Museum of American History.  This image shows the [[bubble level]]s on the base.
* http://www.sciencemuseum.org.uk/objects/surveying/1933-7.aspx

[[Category:Measuring instruments]]
[[Category:Surveying]]
[[Category:Historical scientific instruments]]</text>
      <sha1>hv0u9m57rucz0d333bnabyurafjcu10</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Political geography</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1845092</id>
    <revision>
      <id>859528428</id>
      <parentid>859528416</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-09-14T16:21:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ClueBot NG</username>
        <id>13286072</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverting possible vandalism by [[Special:Contribs/167.128.17.56|167.128.17.56]] to version by Adog16. [[WP:CBFP|Report False Positive?]] Thanks, [[WP:CBNG|ClueBot NG]]. (3473920) (Bot)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="12643">{{About|the discipline|the journal|Political Geography (journal)}}
{{More footnotes|date=March 2018}}
'''Political geography''' is concerned with the study of both the spatially uneven outcomes of [[politics|political]] processes and the ways in which political processes are themselves affected by spatial structures. Conventionally, for the purposes of analysis, political geography adopts a three-scale structure with the study of [[State (polity)|the state]] at the centre, the study of [[international relations]] (or [[geopolitics]]) above it, and the study of localities below it. The primary concerns of the subdiscipline can be summarized as the inter-relationships between people, state, and territory.

== History ==

The British geographer [[Halford Mackinder]] was also heavily influenced by environmental determinism and in developing his concept of the 'geographical pivot of history'  or the [[The Geographical Pivot of History|Heartland Theory]] (in 1904) he argued that the era of sea power was coming to an end and that land based powers were in the ascendant, and, in particular, that whoever controlled the heartland of 'Euro-Asia' would control the world.  This theory involved concepts diametrically opposed to the ideas of [[Alfred Thayer Mahan]] about the significance of ''sea power'' in world conflict.  The heartland theory hypothesized the possibility of a huge empire being created which didn't need to use coastal or transoceanic transport to supply its [[military–industrial complex]], and that this empire could not be defeated by the rest of the world allied against it.  This perspective proved influential throughout the period of the [[Cold War]], underpinning military thinking about the creation of [[buffer state]]s between East and West in central Europe.

The heartland theory depicted a world divided into a ''Heartland'' (Eastern Europe/Western Russia); ''World Island'' (Eurasia and Africa); ''Peripheral Islands'' (British Isles, Japan, Indonesia and Australia) and ''New World'' (The Americas). Mackinder argued that whoever controlled the Heartland would have control of the world. He used these ideas to politically influence events such as the [[Treaty of Versailles]], where buffer states were created between the [[USSR]] and [[Germany]], to prevent either of them controlling the Heartland.  At the same time, Ratzel was creating a theory of states based around the concepts of Lebensraum and [[Social Darwinism]].  He argued that states were analogous to 'organisms' that needed sufficient room in which to live.  Both of these writers created the idea of a political and geographical [[science]], with an [[Objectivity (journalism)|objective]] view of the world.  Prior to [[World War II]] political geography was concerned largely with these issues of global power struggles and influencing state policy, and the above theories were taken on board by German geopoliticians (see [[Geopolitik]]) such as [[Karl Haushofer]] who - perhaps inadvertently - greatly influenced [[Nazism|Nazi]] political theory, which was a form of politics seen to be legitimated by such 'scientific' theories.

The close association with environmental determinism and the freezing of political boundaries during the Cold War led to a significant decline in the perceived importance of political geography, which was described by Brian Berry in 1968 as a 'moribund backwater'.  Although at this time in most other areas of human geography new approaches, including quantitative spatial science, behavioural studies, and structural Marxism, were invigorating academic research these were largely ignored by political geographers whose main point of reference remained the regional approach.  As a result, most of the political geography texts produced during this period were descriptive, and it was not until 1976 that Richard Muir could argue that political geography was no longer a dead duck, but could in fact be a phoenix.

== Areas of study ==
[[File:13.8 scharf.png|thumb|right|The [[Brandenburg Gate]] of the [[Berlin Wall]] in 1961.]]

From the late-1970s onwards, political geography has undergone a renaissance, and could fairly be described as one of the most dynamic of the sub-disciplines today. The revival was underpinned by the launch of the journal ''Political Geography Quarterly'' (and its expansion to bi-monthly production as ''Political Geography''). In part this growth has been associated with the adoption by political geographers of the approaches taken up earlier in other areas of human geography, for example, [[Ron J. Johnston]]'s (1979) work on electoral geography relied heavily on the adoption of quantitative spatial science, Robert Sack's (1986) work on territoriality was based on the behavioural approach, [[Henry Bakis]] (1987) showed the impact of information and telecommunications networks on political geography, and Peter Taylor's (e.g. 2007) work on World Systems Theory owed much to developments within structural Marxism.  However, the recent growth in vitality and importance of this sub-discipline is also related to the changes in the world as a result of the end of the Cold War.  With the emergence of a new world order (which as yet, is only poorly defined) and the development of new research agendas, such as the more recent focus on social movements and political struggles, going beyond the study of nationalism with its explicit territorial basis. There has also been increasing interest in the geography of green politics (see, for example, David Pepper's (1996) work), including the geopolitics of environmental protest, and in the capacity of our existing state apparatus and wider political institutions, to address any contemporary and future environmental problems competently.

Political geography has extended the scope of traditional political science approaches by acknowledging that the exercise of power is not restricted to states and bureaucracies, but is part of everyday life.  This has resulted in the concerns of political geography increasingly overlapping with those of other human geography sub-disciplines such as economic geography, and, particularly, with those of social and cultural geography in relation to the study of the politics of place (see, for example, the books by David Harvey (1996) and Joe Painter (1995)).  Although contemporary political geography maintains many of its traditional concerns (see below) the multi-disciplinary expansion into related areas is part of a general process within human geography which involves the blurring of boundaries between formerly discrete areas of study, and through which the discipline as a whole is enriched&lt;ref&gt;Simandan D. 2011. Kinds of environments—a framework for reflecting on the possible contours of a better world. The Canadian Geographer/Le Géographe canadien, 55(3), pp. 383-386.  https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1541-0064.2010.00334.x &lt;/ref&gt;.

In particular, contemporary political geography often considers:
* How and why states are organized into regional groupings, both formally (e.g. the [[European Union]]) and informally (e.g. the [[Third World]])
* The relationship between states and former colonies, and how these are propagated over time, for example through [[neo-colonialism]]
* The relationship between a [[government]] and its people
* The relationships between states including international trades and treaties
* The functions, demarcations and policing of boundaries
* How [[imagined geographies]] have political implications
* The influence of political power on geographical space
* The political implications of modern media (e.g. radio, TV, ICT, Internet, social networks)
* The study of election results (electoral geography)

===Critical political geography===
{{See also|Critical geopolitics}}

Critical political geography is mainly concerned with the criticism of traditional political geographies vis-a-vis modern trends.  As with much of the move towards 'Critical geographies', the arguments have drawn largely from [[postmodern]], [[post structural]] and [[postcolonial]] theories&lt;ref&gt;Simandan D. 2010. Beware of contingency. Environment and planning. D: Society and Space, 28(3), pp. 388-396. https://doi.org/10.1068/d2310&lt;/ref&gt;.  Examples include:
* [[Feminist geography]], which argues for recognition of the power relations as [[patriarchal]] and attempts to theorise alternative conceptions of [[Personal identity|identity]] and [[identity politics]]&lt;ref&gt;Sharp, J., 2007. Geography and gender: Finding feminist political geographies. Progress in Human Geography, 31(3), pp.381-387.&lt;/ref&gt;. Alongside related concerns such as [[Queer theory]] and [[Youth studies]]
* [[Postcolonial]] theories which recognise the [[Imperialistic]], universalising nature of much political geography, especially in [[Development geography]]&lt;ref&gt;Robinson, J., 2003. Political geography in a postcolonial context. Political Geography, 22(6), pp.647-651.&lt;/ref&gt;.
* [[Environmental justice]] which addresses the fair treatment and meaningful involvement of all people regardless of race, color, or income with respect to the development, implementation, and enforcement of environmental laws, regulations, and policies.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Environmental Justice and Environmentalism: The Social Justice Challenge to the Environmental Movement|last=|first=|publisher=The MIT Press|year=2007|isbn=0262195526|location=|pages=29}}&lt;/ref&gt; In other words, it is a human right for all people to share equally in the benefits bestowed by a healthy environment.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Environmental Justice Reader: Politics, Poetics, &amp; Pedagogy|last=|first=|publisher=The University of Arizona Press|year=2002|isbn=0816522065|location=|pages=4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable political geographers==

{{div col|colwidth=30em}}
* [[John A. Agnew]]
* [[Simon Dalby]]
* [[Klaus Dodds]]
* [[Derek Gregory]]
* [[Richard Hartshorne]]
* [[Karl Haushofer]]
* [[Ron J. Johnston]]
* [[Reece Jones (geographer)|Reece Jones]]
* [[Cindi Katz]]
* [[Peter Kropotkin]]
* [[Yves Lacoste]]
* [[Halford Mackinder]]
* [[Doreen Massey (geographer)|Doreen Massey]]
* [[Gearóid Ó Tuathail]]
* [[Joe Painter]]
* [[Friedrich Ratzel]]
* [[Ellen Churchill Semple]]
* [[Peter J. Taylor]]
{{div col end}}

== See also ==
*[[List of geography topics]]
*[[List of countries]]
*[[List of reference tables#Geography and places|Geography reference tables]]

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==References==
* Bakis H (1987) ''Géopolitique de l'information'' Presses Universitaires de France, Paris
* Harvey D  (1996) ''Justice, nature and the geography of difference''  Oxford: Blackwell {{ISBN|1-55786-680-5}}
* Johnston RJ (1979) ''Political, electoral and spatial systems''  Oxford: Clarendon Press {{ISBN|0-19-874072-7}}
* Painter J (1995) ''Politics, geography and 'political geography': a critical perspective''  London: Arnold {{ISBN|0-340-56735-X}}
* Pepper D (1996) ''Modern environmentalism''  London: Routledge {{ISBN|0-415-05744-2}}
* Ratzel F (1897) ''Politische Geographie'', Munich, Oldenbourg 
* Sack RD (1986) ''Human territoriality: its theory and history''  Cambridge: Cambridge University Press {{ISBN|0-521-26614-9}}

== Further reading ==
* Agnew J (1997) ''Political geography: a reader''  London: Arnold {{ISBN|0-470-23655-8}}
* Bakis H (1995) ‘Communication and Political Geography in a Changing World’ ''Revue Internationale de Science Politique'' 16 (3) pp219–311 - http://ips.sagepub.com/content/16/3.toc
* Buleon P (1992) 'The state of political geography in France in the 1970s and 1980s' ''Progress in Human Geography'' 16 (1) pp24–40
* Claval P (1978) ''Espace et pouvoir'', Paris, Presses Universitaires de France 
* Cox KR, Low M &amp; Robinson J (2008) ''Handbook of Political Geography'' London: Sage 
* Sanguin A-L &amp; Prevelakis G (1996), 'Jean Gottmann (1915-1994), un pionnier de la géographie politique', ''[[Annales de Géographie]]'', 105, 587. pp73–78
* Short JR (1993) ''An introduction to political geography - 2nd edn.''  London: Routledge {{ISBN|0-415-08226-9}}
* Spykman NJ (1944) ''The Geography of the Peace'' New York: Harcourt, Brace and Co.
* Sutton I (1991) 'The Political Geography of Indian Country' ''American Indian Culture and Research Journal'' 15(2) pp1–169.
* Taylor PJ &amp; Flint C (2007) ''Political geography: world-economy, nation-state and locality''  Harlow: Pearson Education Lim. {{ISBN|0-13-196012-1}}

==External links==
*{{commons category-inline}}

{{Navboxes
|list=
{{Geography topics}}
{{Human geography}}
}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Political geography| ]]
[[Category:Branches of geography]]
[[Category:Human geography]]</text>
      <sha1>td16ao56haposot6g3v5wcmobayanoh</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Softscape</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>12321263</id>
    <revision>
      <id>820053312</id>
      <parentid>763869170</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-01-12T20:36:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Moral edits</username>
        <id>32633109</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>{{Horticulture-stub}}</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="1184">{{unreferenced|date=July 2012}}
'''Softscape''' refers to the live [[horticulture|horticultural]] elements of a [[landscape]]. Softscaping can include, flowers, plants, shrubs, trees, flower beds, and duties like weed/nuisance management, grading, planting, mowing, trimming, aerating, spraying, and digging for everything from plants and shrubs , to flower beds. Wheel barrows and manual tools like rakes, shovels, picks, and gas power tools are commonly used. This is a term that has been popularized in recent pop culture (2006 onwards) on television shows such as [[Home &amp; Garden Television]]. The purpose of softscape is to lend character to the landscaping, create an aura, ambience, and reflect the sensibilities of the inhabitants. 

The term softscape stands in contrast to [[hardscape]] which represents inanimate objects of a landscape such as : pavers, stones, rocks,planter boxes, arbors , water feature as well as structures  of wood and natural stone and concrete, like: retaining walls, patios, fences and decks, pergolas, stairs, Etc

== See also ==
* [[Landscape]]
* [[Hardscape]]

[[Category:Horticulture and gardening]]
[[Category:Landscape]]
{{Horticulture-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>8nqreo5it1d78wwxzzh7z8fxyzhj4zl</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Spatial analysis</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3190431</id>
    <revision>
      <id>868092547</id>
      <parentid>867714580</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-11-09T23:16:23Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>74.93.189.81</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>This is directly sourced from a journal article, reflects bias, and is not sufficiently proven in the stub.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="58530">{{short description|Formal techniques which study entities using their topological, geometric, or geographic properties}}
[[Image:Snow-cholera-map.jpg|thumb|right|300px|Map by Dr. [[John Snow (physician)|John Snow]] of [[London]], showing [[cluster (epidemiology)|cluster]]s of cholera cases in the [[1854 Broad Street cholera outbreak]]. This was one of the first uses of map-based spatial analysis.]] '''Spatial analysis''' or '''spatial statistics''' includes any of the formal [[Scientific technique|techniques]]  which study entities using their [[topological]], [[geometric]], or [[geographic]] properties. Spatial analysis includes a variety of techniques, many still in their early development, using different analytic approaches and applied in fields as diverse as [[astronomy]], with its studies of the placement of galaxies in the [[cosmos]], to chip fabrication engineering, with its use of "place and route" [[algorithm]]s to build complex wiring structures. In a more restricted sense, spatial analysis is the technique applied to structures at the human scale, most notably in the analysis of [[geographic data]].

Complex issues arise in spatial analysis, many of which are neither clearly defined nor completely resolved, but form the basis for current research. The most fundamental of these is the problem of defining the spatial location of the entities being studied.

Classification of the techniques of spatial analysis is difficult because of the large number of different fields of research involved, the different fundamental approaches which can be chosen, and the many forms the data can take.

== History of spatial analysis ==
Spatial analysis can perhaps be considered{{according to|date=February 2018}} to have arisen with early attempts at [[cartography]] and [[surveying]] but many fields have contributed to its rise in modern form. [[Biology]] contributed through [[botany|botanical]] studies of global plant distributions and local plant locations, [[ethology|ethological]] studies of animal movement, [[landscape ecology|landscape ecological]] studies of vegetation blocks, [[ecology|ecological]] studies of spatial population dynamics, and the study of [[biogeography]]. [[Epidemiology]] contributed with early work on disease mapping, notably [[John Snow (physician)|John Snow]]'s work of mapping an outbreak of cholera, with research on mapping the spread of disease and with location studies for health care delivery. [[Statistics]] has contributed greatly through work in spatial statistics. [[Economics]] has contributed notably through [[spatial econometrics]]. [[Geographic information system]] is currently a major contributor due to the importance of geographic software in the modern analytic toolbox. [[Remote sensing]] has contributed extensively in morphometric and clustering analysis. [[Computer science]] has contributed extensively through the study of algorithms, notably in [[computational geometry]]. [[Mathematics]] continues to provide the fundamental tools for analysis and to reveal the complexity of the spatial realm, for example, with recent work on [[fractals]] and [[scale invariance]]. [[Scientific modelling]] provides a useful framework for new approaches.

== Fundamental issues in spatial analysis ==
Spatial analysis confronts many fundamental issues in the definition of its objects of study, in the construction of the analytic operations to be used, in the use of computers for analysis, in the limitations and particularities of the analyses which are known, and in the presentation of analytic results. Many of these issues are active subjects of modern research.

Common errors often arise in spatial analysis, some due to the mathematics of space, some due to the particular ways data are presented spatially, some due to the tools which are available. Census data, because it protects individual privacy by aggregating data into local units, raises a number of statistical issues. The fractal nature of coastline makes precise measurements of its length difficult if not impossible. A computer software fitting straight lines to the curve of a coastline, can easily calculate the lengths of the lines which it defines. However these straight lines may have no inherent meaning in the real world, as was shown for the [[How Long Is the Coast of Britain? Statistical Self-Similarity and Fractional Dimension|coastline of Britain]].

These problems represent a challenge in spatial analysis because of the power of maps as media of presentation. When results are presented as maps, the presentation combines spatial data which are generally accurate with analytic results which may be inaccurate, leading to an impression that analytic results are more accurate than the data would indicate.&lt;ref&gt;Mark Monmonier ''How to Lie with Maps'' University of Chicago Press, 1996.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Spatial characterization ===
[[File:Bubonic plague-en.svg|thumb|240px|Spread of bubonic plague in medieval Europe.{{citation needed|date=February 2013}} The colors indicate the spatial distribution of plague outbreaks over time.]]The definition of the spatial presence of an entity constrains the possible analysis which can be applied to that entity and influences the final conclusions that can be reached. While this property is fundamentally true of all [[analysis]], it is particularly important in spatial analysis because the tools to define and study entities favor specific characterizations of the entities being studied. Statistical techniques favor the spatial definition of objects as points because there are very few statistical techniques which operate directly on line, area, or volume elements. Computer tools favor the spatial definition of objects as homogeneous and separate elements because of the limited number of [[database]] elements and computational structures available, and the ease with which these primitive structures can be created.

=== Spatial dependency or auto-correlation ===
{{see also|Spatial association}}
Spatial dependency is the co-variation of properties within geographic space: characteristics at proximal locations appear to be correlated, either positively or negatively. Spatial dependency leads to the spatial [[autocorrelation]] problem in statistics since, like temporal autocorrelation, this violates standard statistical techniques that assume independence among observations. For example, [[Regression analysis|regression]] analyses that do not compensate for spatial dependency can have unstable parameter estimates and yield unreliable significance tests. Spatial regression models (see below) capture these relationships and do not suffer from these weaknesses. It is also appropriate to view spatial dependency as a source of information rather than something to be corrected.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Knegt | first1 = De | last2 = Coughenour | first2 = M.B. | last3 = Skidmore | first3 = A.K. | last4 = Heitkönig | first4 = I.M.A. | last5 = Knox | first5 = N.M. | last6 = Slotow | first6 = R. | last7 = Prins | first7 = H.H.T. | year = 2010 | title = Spatial autocorrelation and the scaling of species–environment relationships | journal = Ecology | volume = 91 | issue = 8| pages = 2455–2465 | doi = 10.1890/09-1359.1 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Locational effects also manifest as spatial [[heterogeneity]], or the apparent variation in a process with respect to location in geographic space. Unless a space is uniform and boundless, every location will have some degree of uniqueness relative to the other locations. This affects the spatial dependency relations and therefore the spatial process. Spatial heterogeneity means that overall parameters estimated for the entire system may not adequately describe the process at any given location.

=== Scaling ===
Spatial [[measurement]] scale is a persistent issue in spatial analysis; more detail is available at the [[modifiable areal unit problem]] (MAUP) topic entry. Landscape ecologists developed a series of [[scale invariant]] metrics for aspects of ecology that are [[fractal]] in nature.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Halley|first=J. M.|last2=Hartley|first2=S.|last3=Kallimanis|first3=A. S.|last4=Kunin|first4=W. E.|last5=Lennon|first5=J. J.|last6=Sgardelis|first6=S. P.|date=2004-03-01|title=Uses and abuses of fractal methodology in ecology|journal=Ecology Letters|language=en|volume=7|issue=3|pages=254–271|doi=10.1111/j.1461-0248.2004.00568.x|issn=1461-0248}}&lt;/ref&gt; In more general terms, no scale independent method of [[analysis]] is widely agreed upon for spatial statistics.

=== Sampling ===
Spatial [[Sampling (statistics)|sampling]] involves determining a limited number of locations in geographic space for faithfully measuring phenomena that are subject to dependency and heterogeneity. {{Citation needed|date=December 2010}} Dependency suggests that since one location can predict the value of another location, we do not need observations in both places.  But heterogeneity suggests that this relation can change across space, and therefore we cannot trust an observed degree of dependency beyond a region that may be small.  Basic spatial sampling schemes include random, clustered and systematic. These basic schemes can be applied at multiple levels in a designated spatial hierarchy (e.g., urban area, city, neighborhood). It is also possible to exploit ancillary data, for example, using property values as a guide in a spatial sampling scheme to measure educational attainment and income.  Spatial models such as autocorrelation statistics, regression and interpolation (see below) can also dictate sample design.{{Citation needed|date=December 2010}}

=== Common errors in spatial analysis ===
The fundamental issues in spatial analysis lead to numerous problems in analysis including bias, distortion and outright errors in the conclusions reached. These issues are often interlinked but various attempts have been made to separate out particular issues from each other.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Ocaña-Riola | first1 = R | year = 2010 | title = Common errors in disease mapping | journal = Geospatial Health | volume = 4 | issue = 2| pages = 139–154 | pmid = 20503184 | doi=10.4081/gh.2010.196}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Length ====
In a paper by [[Benoit Mandelbrot]] on the [[How Long Is the Coast of Britain? Statistical Self-Similarity and Fractional Dimension|coastline of Britain]] it was shown that it is inherently nonsensical to discuss certain spatial concepts despite an inherent presumption of the validity of the concept. Lengths in ecology depend directly on the scale at which they are measured and experienced. So while surveyors commonly measure the length of a river, this length only has meaning in the context of the relevance of the measuring technique to the question under study.
&lt;gallery perRow="3"&gt;
Image:britain-fractal-coastline-200km.png|Britain measured using a long yardstick
Image:britain-fractal-coastline-100km.png|Britain measured using a medium yardstick
Image:britain-fractal-coastline-50km.png|Britain measured using a short yardstick
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==== Locational fallacy ====
The locational fallacy refers to error due to the particular spatial characterization chosen for the elements of study, in particular choice of placement for the spatial presence of the element.

Spatial characterizations may be simplistic or even wrong. Studies of humans often reduce the spatial existence of humans to a single point, for instance their home address. This can easily lead to poor analysis, for example, when considering disease transmission which can happen at work or at school and therefore far from the home.

The spatial characterization may implicitly limit the subject of study. For example, the spatial analysis of crime data has recently become popular but these studies can only describe the particular kinds of crime which can be described spatially. This leads to many maps of assault but not to any maps of embezzlement with political consequences in the conceptualization of crime and the design of policies to address the issue.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Understanding Spatial Fallacies|url=https://www.e-education.psu.edu/sgam/node/214|website=The Learner's Guide to Geospatial Analysis|publisher=Penn State Department of Geography|accessdate=27 April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Atomic fallacy ====
This describes errors due to treating elements as separate 'atoms' outside of their spatial context. The fallacy is about transferring individual conclusions to spatial units.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=Integrating scale in remote sensing and GIS |last=Quattrochi |first=Dale A |isbn=9781482218268|oclc=973767077|date=2016-02-01 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Ecological fallacy ====
The [[ecological fallacy]] describes errors due to performing analyses on aggregate data when trying to reach conclusions on the individual units. {{Citation needed|date=December 2010}} Errors occur in part from spatial aggregation.  For example, a [[pixel]] represents the average surface temperatures within an area.  Ecological fallacy would be to assume that all points within the area have the same temperature. This topic is closely related to the [[modifiable areal unit problem]].

=== Solutions to the fundamental issues ===

==== Geographic space ====
[[File:Manhattan distance.svg|thumb|200px|Manhattan distance versus Euclidean distance: The red, blue, and yellow lines have the same length (12) in both Euclidean and taxicab geometry. In Euclidean geometry, the green line has length 6×{{radic|2}}&amp;nbsp;≈&amp;nbsp;8.48, and is the unique shortest path. In taxicab geometry, the green line's length is still 12, making it no shorter than any other path shown.]]A mathematical space exists whenever we have a set of observations and quantitative measures of their attributes. For example, we can represent individuals' incomes or years of education within a coordinate system where the location of each individual can be specified with respect to both dimensions. The distance between individuals within this space is a quantitative measure of their differences with respect to income and education. However, in spatial analysis, we are concerned with specific types of mathematical spaces, namely, geographic space. In geographic space, the observations correspond to locations in a spatial measurement framework that capture their proximity in the real world. The locations in a spatial measurement framework often represent locations on the surface of the Earth, but this is not strictly necessary. A spatial measurement framework can also capture proximity with respect to, say, interstellar space or within a biological entity such as a liver. The fundamental tenet is [[Tobler's first law of geography|Tobler's First Law of Geography]]: if the interrelation between entities increases with proximity in the real world, then representation in geographic space and assessment using spatial analysis techniques are appropriate.

The [[Euclidean distance]] between locations often represents their proximity, although this is only one possibility. There are an infinite number of distances in addition to Euclidean that can support quantitative analysis. For example, "Manhattan" (or "[[Taxicab geometry|Taxicab]]") distances where movement is restricted to paths parallel to the axes can be more meaningful than Euclidean distances in urban settings. In addition to distances, other geographic relationships such as connectivity''' (e.g., the existence or degree of shared borders) and direction''' can also influence the relationships among entities. It is also possible to compute minimal cost paths across a cost surface; for example, this can represent proximity among locations when travel must occur across rugged terrain.

== Types of spatial analysis ==
&lt;blockquote&gt;
 Spatial data comes in many varieties and it is not easy to
 arrive at a system of classification that is simultaneously
 exclusive, exhaustive, imaginative, and satisfying.
                             -- G. Upton &amp; B. Fingelton&lt;ref name="Upton+:1985"&gt;Graham J. Upton &amp; Bernard Fingelton: '''Spatial Data Analysis by Example Volume 1: Point Pattern and Quantitative Data''' John Wiley &amp; Sons, New York. 1985.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

=== Spatial data analysis ===
Urban and Regional Studies deal with large tables of spatial data obtained from censuses and surveys. It is necessary to simplify the huge amount of detailed information in order to extract the main trends. Multivariable analysis (or [[Factor analysis]], FA) allows a change of variables, transforming the many variables of the census, usually correlated between themselves, into fewer independent "Factors" or "Principal Components" which are, actually, the [[Eigenvalues and eigenvectors|eigenvectors]] of the data correlation matrix weighted by the inverse of their eigenvalues. This change of variables has two main advantages:
# Since information is concentrated on the first new factors, it is possible to keep only a few of them while losing only a small amount of information; mapping them produces fewer and more significant maps 
# The factors, actually the eigenvectors, are orthogonal by construction, i.e. not correlated. In most cases, the dominant factor (with the largest eigenvalue) is the Social Component, separating rich and poor in the city. Since factors are not-correlated, other smaller processes than social status, which would have remained hidden otherwise, appear on the second, third, … factors.

Factor analysis depends on measuring distances between observations : the choice of a significant metric is crucial. The Euclidean metric (Principal Component Analysis), the Chi-Square distance (Correspondence Analysis) or the Generalized Mahalanobis distance (Discriminant Analysis ) are among the more widely used.&lt;ref&gt;Harman H H (1960) ''Modern Factor Analysis'', University of Chicago Press&lt;/ref&gt; More complicated models, using communalities or rotations have been proposed.&lt;ref&gt;Rummel R J (1970) ''Applied Factor Analysis''. Evanston, ILL: Northwestern University Press.&lt;/ref&gt;

Using multivariate methods in spatial analysis began really in the 1950s (although some examples go back to the beginning of the century) and culminated in the 1970s, with the increasing power and accessibility of computers. Already in 1948, in a seminal publication, two sociologists, Bell and Shevky,&lt;ref&gt;Bell W &amp; E Shevky (1955) ''Social Area Analysis'', Stanford University Press&lt;/ref&gt; had shown that most city populations in the USA and in the world could be represented with three independent factors : 1- the « socio-economic status » opposing rich and poor districts and distributed in sectors running along highways from the city center, 2- the « life cycle », i.e. the age structure of households, distributed in concentric circles, and 3-  « race and ethnicity », identifying patches of migrants located within the city. In 1961, in a groundbreaking study, British geographers used FA to classify British towns.&lt;ref&gt;Moser C A &amp; W Scott (1961) ''British Towns ; A Statistical Study of their Social and Economic Differences'', Oliver &amp; Boyd, London.&lt;/ref&gt; Brian J Berry, at the University of Chicago, and his students made a wide use of the method,&lt;ref&gt;Berry B J &amp; F Horton (1971) ''Geographic Perspectives on Urban Systems'', John Wiley, N-Y.&lt;/ref&gt; applying it to most important cities in the world and exhibiting common social structures.&lt;ref&gt;Berry B J &amp; K B Smith eds (1972) ''City Classification Handbook : Methods and Applications'', John Wiley, N-Y.&lt;/ref&gt; 
The use of Factor Analysis in Geography, made so easy by modern computers, has been very wide but not always very wise.&lt;ref&gt;Ciceri M-F (1974) ''Méthodes d’analyse multivariée dans la géographie anglo-saxonne'', Université de Paris-1 ; free download on http://www-ohp.univ-paris1.fr&lt;/ref&gt;

Since the vectors extracted are determined by the data matrix, it is not possible to compare factors obtained from different censuses. A solution consists in fusing together several census matrices in a unique table which, then, may be analyzed. This, however, assumes that the definition of the variables has not changed over time and produces very large tables, difficult to manage. A better solution, proposed by psychometricians,&lt;ref&gt;Tucker L R (1964) « The extension of Factor Analysis to three-dimensional matrices », in  Frederiksen N &amp; H Gulliksen eds, ''Contributions to Mathematical Psychology'', Holt, Rinehart and Winston, NY.&lt;/ref&gt; groups the data in a « cubic matrix », with three entries (for instance, locations, variables, time periods). A Three-Way Factor Analysis produces then three groups of factors related by a small cubic « core matrix ».&lt;ref&gt;R. Coppi &amp; S. Bolasco, eds. (1989), ''Multiway data analysis'', Elsevier, Amsterdam.&lt;/ref&gt; This method, which exhibits data evolution over time, has not been widely used in geography.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Cant | first1 = R.G. | year = 1971 | title =  Changes in the location of manufacturing in New Zealand 1957-1968: An application of three-mode factor analysis | journal = New Zealand Geographer | volume = 27 | issue = | pages = 38–55 | doi=10.1111/j.1745-7939.1971.tb00636.x}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Los Angeles,&lt;ref&gt;Marchand B (1986) ''The Emergence of Los Angeles, 1940-1970'', Pion Ltd, London&lt;/ref&gt; however, it has exhibited the role, traditionally ignored, of Downtown as an organizing center for the whole city during several decades.

=== Spatial autocorrelation ===
Spatial [[autocorrelation]] statistics measure and analyze the degree of dependency among observations in a geographic space.  Classic spatial autocorrelation statistics include [[Moran's I|Moran's &lt;math&gt;I&lt;/math&gt;]], [[Geary's C|Geary's &lt;math&gt;C&lt;/math&gt;]], [[Getis's G|Getis's]] &lt;math&gt;G&lt;/math&gt; and the [[standard deviational ellipse]]. These statistics require measuring a spatial weights matrix that reflects the intensity of the geographic relationship between observations in a neighborhood, e.g., the distances between neighbors, the lengths of shared border, or whether they fall into a specified directional class such as "west". Classic spatial autocorrelation statistics compare the spatial weights to the covariance relationship at pairs of locations. Spatial autocorrelation that is more positive than expected from random indicate the clustering of similar values across geographic space, while significant negative spatial autocorrelation indicates that neighboring values are more dissimilar than expected by chance, suggesting a spatial pattern similar to a chess board.

Spatial autocorrelation statistics such as Moran's &lt;math&gt;I&lt;/math&gt; and Geary's &lt;math&gt;C&lt;/math&gt; are global in the sense that they estimate the overall degree of spatial autocorrelation for a dataset.  The possibility of spatial heterogeneity suggests that the estimated degree of autocorrelation may vary significantly across geographic space. '''Local spatial autocorrelation statistics''' provide estimates disaggregated to the level of the spatial analysis units, allowing assessment of the dependency relationships across space. &lt;math&gt;G&lt;/math&gt; statistics compare neighborhoods to a global average and identify local regions of strong autocorrelation.  Local versions of the &lt;math&gt;I&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;C&lt;/math&gt; statistics are also available.

=== Spatial stratified heterogeneity ===
Spatial stratified heterogeneity, referring to the within-strata variance less than the between strata-variance, is ubiquitous in ecological phenomena, such as ecological zones and many ecological variables.  Spatial stratified heterogeneity of an attribute can be measured by geographical detector ''q''-statistic:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Wang | first1 = JF | last2 = Zhang | first2 = TL | last3 = Fu | first3 = BJ | year = 2016 | title = A measure of spatial stratified heterogeneity | journal = Ecological Indicators | volume = 67 | issue = | pages = 250–256 | doi=10.1016/j.ecolind.2016.02.052}}&lt;/ref&gt;
                              &lt;math&gt; q = 1 - \frac{1}{N\sigma^2}\sum_{h=1}^LN_h\sigma_h^2  &lt;/math&gt;
where a population is partitioned into ''h'' = 1, ..., ''L'' strata; ''N'' stands for the size of the population, σ&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; stands for variance of the attribute. The value of ''q'' is within [0, 1], 0 indicates no spatial stratified heterogeneity, 1 indicates perfect spatial stratified heterogeneity.The value of ''q'' indicates the percent of the variance of an attribute explained by the stratification.The ''q'' follows a noncentral ''F'' probability density function.

[[File:Q-fig2.jpg|frame|center|A hand map with different spatial patterns. Note: ''p'' is the probability of ''q''-statistic; * denotes statistical significant at level 0.05, ** for 0.001, *** for smaller than 10&lt;sup&gt;−3&lt;/sup&gt;;(D) subscripts 1, 2, 3 of ''q'' and ''p'' denotes the strata Z1+Z2 with Z3, Z1 with Z2+Z3, and Z1 and Z2 and Z3 individually, respectively; (E) subscripts 1 and 2 of ''q'' and ''p'' denotes the strata Z1+Z2 with Z3+Z4, and Z1+Z3 with Z2+Z4, respectively.]]

=== Spatial interpolation ===
[[Spatial interpolation]] methods estimate the variables at unobserved locations in geographic space based on the values at observed locations.  Basic methods include [[inverse distance weighting]]: this attenuates the variable with decreasing proximity from the observed location.  [[Kriging]] is a more sophisticated method that interpolates across space according to a spatial lag relationship that has both systematic and random components.  This can accommodate a wide range of spatial relationships for the hidden values between observed locations.  Kriging provides optimal estimates given the hypothesized lag relationship, and error estimates can be mapped to determine if spatial patterns exist.

=== Spatial regression ===
{{See also|Local regression|Regression-Kriging}}

Spatial regression methods capture spatial dependency in [[regression analysis]], avoiding statistical problems such as unstable parameters and unreliable significance tests, as well as providing information on spatial relationships among the variables involved.  The estimated spatial relationships can be used on spatial and spatio-temporal predictions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Song|first=Yongze|author2=Yong Ge|title=Spatial distribution estimation of malaria in northern China and its scenarios in 2020, 2030, 2040 and 2050|journal=Malaria Journal|volume=15|issue=1|pages=345|doi=10.1186/s12936-016-1395-2|pmid=27387921|pmc=4936159|year=2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Depending on the specific technique, spatial dependency can enter the regression model as relationships between the independent variables and the dependent, between the dependent variables and a spatial lag of itself, or in the error terms.  '''Geographically weighted regression''' (GWR) is a local version of spatial regression that generates parameters disaggregated by the spatial units of analysis.&lt;ref name="Fotheringham1998"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Fotheringham | first1 = A. S. | last2 = Charlton | first2 = M. E. | last3 = Brunsdon | first3 = C. | year = 1998 | title = Geographically weighted regression: a natural evolution of the expansion method for spatial data analysis | journal = Environment and Planning A | volume = 30 | issue = 11| pages = 1905–1927 | doi = 10.1068/a301905 | url = http://eprints.maynoothuniversity.ie/6102/1/MC_gwr%201998.pdf | type = Submitted manuscript }}&lt;/ref&gt;  This allows assessment of the spatial heterogeneity in the estimated relationships between the independent and dependent variables. The use of [[Bayesian hierarchical modeling]]&lt;ref name="Banerjee2014"&gt;{{Citation | last = Banerjee | first = Sudipto | last2 = Carlin | first2 = Bradley P. | last3 = Gelfand | first3 = Alan E. | date = 2014 | title = Hierarchical Modeling and Analysis for Spatial Data, Second Edition | series = Monographs on Statistics and Applied Probability | publisher = Chapman and Hall/CRC | edition = 2nd | isbn = 9781439819173}}&lt;/ref&gt; in conjunction with [[Markov Chain Monte Carlo]] (MCMC) methods have recently shown to be effective in modeling complex relationships using Poisson-Gamma-CAR, Poisson-lognormal-SAR, or Overdispersed logit models. 
Spatial stochastic processes, such as [[Gaussian processes]] are also increasingly being deployed in spatial regression analysis. Model-based versions of GWR, known as spatially varying coefficient models have been applied to conduct Bayesian inference.&lt;ref name="Banerjee2014"/&gt; Spatial stochastic process can become computationally effective and scalable Gaussian process models, such as Gaussian Predictive Processes&lt;ref name="Banerjee2008"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Banerjee | first1 = Sudipto | last2 = Gelfand | first2 = Alan E. | last3 = Finley | first3 = Andrew O. | last4 = Sang | first4 = Huiyan | year = 2008 | title = Gaussian predictive process models for large spatial datasets | journal = Journal of the Royal Statistical Society, Series B | volume = 70 | issue = 4| pages = 825–848 | doi = 10.1111/j.1467-9868.2008.00663.x| pmid = 19750209 | pmc = 2741335 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  and Nearest Neighbor Gaussian Processes (NNGP).&lt;ref name="Banerjee2016"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Datta | first1 = Abhirup | last2 = Banerjee | first2 = Sudipto | last4 = Gelfand | first4 = Alan E. | last3 = Finley | first3 = Andrew O. | year = 2016 | title = Hierarchical Nearest Neighbor Gaussian Process Models for Large Geostatistical Datasets | journal = Journal of the American Statistical Association | volume = 111| issue = 514| pages =  800–812| doi = 10.1080/01621459.2015.1044091| pmid = 29720777 | pmc = 5927603 | arxiv = 1406.7343}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Spatial interaction ===
Spatial interaction or "[[gravity model]]s" estimate the flow of people, material or information between locations in geographic space.  Factors can include origin propulsive variables such as the number of commuters in residential areas, destination attractiveness variables such as the amount of office space in employment areas, and proximity relationships between the locations measured in terms such as driving distance or travel time.  In addition, the topological, or [[Geospatial topology|connective]], relationships between areas must be identified, particularly considering the often conflicting relationship between distance and topology; for example, two spatially close neighborhoods may not display any significant interaction if they are separated by a highway. After specifying the functional forms of these relationships, the analyst can estimate model parameters using observed flow data and standard estimation techniques such as ordinary least squares or maximum likelihood. Competing destinations versions of spatial interaction models include the proximity among the destinations (or origins) in addition to the origin-destination proximity; this captures the effects of destination (origin) clustering on flows. Computational methods such as [[artificial neural networks]] can also estimate spatial interaction relationships among locations and can handle noisy and qualitative data.{{Citation needed|date=August 2014}}

=== Simulation and modeling ===
Spatial interaction models are aggregate and top-down: they specify an overall governing relationship for flow between locations.  This characteristic is also shared by urban models such as those based on mathematical programming, flows among economic sectors, or bid-rent theory.  An alternative modeling perspective is to represent the system at the highest possible level of disaggregation and study the bottom-up emergence of complex patterns and relationships from behavior and interactions at the individual level. {{Citation needed|date=December 2010}}

[[Complex adaptive systems]] theory as applied to spatial analysis suggests that simple interactions among proximal entities can lead to intricate, persistent and functional spatial entities at aggregate levels.  Two fundamentally spatial simulation methods are cellular automata and agent-based modeling. [[Cellular automata]] modeling imposes a fixed spatial framework such as grid cells and specifies rules that dictate the state of a cell based on the states of its neighboring cells.  As time progresses, spatial patterns emerge as cells change states based on their neighbors; this alters the conditions for future time periods.  For example, cells can represent locations in an urban area and their states can be different types of land use.  Patterns that can emerge from the simple interactions of local land uses include office districts and urban sprawl. [[Agent-based model]]ing uses software entities (agents) that have purposeful behavior (goals) and can react, interact and modify their environment while seeking their objectives.  Unlike the cells in cellular automata, simulysts can allow agents to be mobile with respect to space.  For example, one could model traffic flow and dynamics using agents representing individual vehicles that try to minimize travel time between specified origins and destinations.  While pursuing minimal travel times, the agents must avoid collisions with other vehicles also seeking to minimize their travel times.  Cellular automata and agent-based modeling are complementary modeling strategies.  They can be integrated into a common geographic automata system where some agents are fixed while others are mobile.

Calibration plays a pivotal role in both CA and ABM simulation and modelling approaches. Initial approaches to CA proposed robust calibration approaches based on stochastic, Monte Carlo methods.&lt;ref name="Silva"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Silva|first1=E. A.|last2=Clarke|first2=K.C.|title=Calibration of the SLEUTH urban growth model for Lisbon and Porto, Portugal|journal=Computers, Environment and Urban Systems|date=2002|volume=26|issue=6|pages=525–552|doi=10.1016/S0198-9715(01)00014-X }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Silva_EPS"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Silva|first1=E A|title=Complexity, emergence and cellular urban models: lessons learned from applying SLEUTH to two Portuguese metropolitan areas|journal=European Planning Studies|date=2003|volume=13|issue=1|pages=93–115|doi=10.1080/0965431042000312424}}&lt;/ref&gt; ABM approaches rely on agents' decision rules (in many cases extracted from qualitative research base methods such as questionnaires).&lt;ref name="silva3"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Liu and Silva|title=Examining the dynamics of the interaction between the development of creative industries and urban spatial structure by agent-based modelling: A case study of Nanjing, China|journal=Urban Studies|date=2017|volume=65|issue=5|pages=113–125|doi=10.1177/0042098016686493 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Recent Machine Learning Algorithms calibrate using training sets, for instance in order to understand the qualities of the built environment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Liu|first1=Lun|last2=Silva|first2=Elisabete A.|last3=Wu|first3=Chunyang|last4=Wang|first4=Hui|title=A machine learning-based method for the large-scale evaluation of the qualities of the urban environment|journal=Computers Environment and Urban Systems|date=2017|volume=65|pages=113–125|doi=10.1016/j.compenvurbsys.2017.06.003 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Multiple-point geostatistics (MPS) ===
Spatial analysis of a conceptual geological model is the main purpose of any MPS algorithm. The method analyzes the spatial statistics of the geological model, called the training image, and generates realizations of the phenomena that honor those input multiple-point statistics.

A recent MPS algorithm used to accomplish this task is the pattern-based method by Honarkhah.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Honarkhah | first1 = M | last2 = Caers | first2 = J | year = 2010 | title = Stochastic Simulation of Patterns Using Distance-Based Pattern Modeling | doi = 10.1007/s11004-010-9276-7 | journal = Mathematical Geosciences | volume = 42 | issue = 5| pages = 487–517 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In this method, a distance-based approach is employed to analyze the patterns in the training image. This allows the reproduction of the multiple-point statistics, and the complex geometrical features of the training image. Each output of the MPS algorithm is a realization that represents a random field. Together, several realizations may be used to quantify spatial uncertainty.

One of the recent methods is presented by Tahmasebi et al.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Tahmasebi | first1 = P. | last2 = Hezarkhani | first2 = A. | last3 = Sahimi | first3 = M. | year = 2012 | title = Multiple-point geostatistical modeling based on the cross-correlation functions | journal = Computational Geosciences | volume = 16 | issue = 3| pages = 779–79742 | doi=10.1007/s10596-012-9287-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; uses a cross-correlation function to improve the spatial pattern reproduction. They call their MPS simulation method as the CCSIM algorithm. This method is able to quantify the spatial connectivity, variability and uncertainty. Furthermore, the method is not sensitive to any type of data and is able to simulate both categorical and continuous scenarios. CCSIM algorithm is able to be used for any stationary, non-stationary and multivariate systems and it can provide high quality visual appeal model.,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Tahmasebi |first=P. |last2=Sahimi |first2=M. |year=2015 |doi=10.1103/PhysRevE.91.032401 |pmid=25871117 |title=Reconstruction of nonstationary disordered materials and media: Watershed transform and cross-correlation function |journal=Physical Review E |volume=91 |issue=3|pages=032401 |bibcode=2015PhRvE..91c2401T }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Tahmasebi |first=P. |last2=Sahimi |first2=M. |year=2015 |title=Geostatistical Simulation and Reconstruction of Porous Media by a Cross-Correlation Function and Integration of Hard and Soft Data |doi=10.1007/s11242-015-0471-3 |journal=Transport in Porous Media |volume=107 |issue=3| pages=871–905}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Geospatial analysis ==
[[File:Jubilee Campus MMB «24 Nottingham Geospatial Building.jpg|thumb|The Nottingham Geospatial Building on the [[University of Nottingham]]'s [[Jubilee Campus]].]]
'''Geospatial analysis''', or just '''spatial analysis''',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Graduate Program in Spatial Analysis|url=http://www.ryerson.ca/graduate/programs/spatial/index.html|website=Ryerson University|publisher=Ryerson University|accessdate=17 December 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; is an approach to applying [[statistical analysis]] and other analytic techniques to data which has a geographical or spatial aspect &lt;ref&gt;Hemakumara, GPTS, &amp; Rainis, Ruslan. (2015). Geo-statistical modeling to evaluate the socio-economic impacts of households in the context of low-lying areas conversion in Colombo metropolitan region-Sri Lanka. Paper presented at the AIP Conference Proceedings.&lt;/ref&gt;. Such analysis would typically employ software capable of rendering maps processing spatial data, and applying [[Scientific modelling|analytical]] methods to terrestrial or [[geographic]] datasets, including the use of [[geographic information system]]s and [[geomatics]].&lt;ref&gt;geospatial. Collins English Dictionary - Complete &amp; Unabridged 11th Edition. Retrieved 5tth August 2012 from CollinsDictionary.com website:
http://www.collinsdictionary.com/dictionary/english/geospatial&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Dictionary.com's 21st Century Lexicon Copyright © 2003-2010 Dictionary.com, LLC  http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/geospatial&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.receiver.vodafone.com/the-geospatial-web The geospatial web – blending physical and virtual spaces.] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20111002151826/http://www.receiver.vodafone.com/the-geospatial-web |date=2011-10-02 }}, Arno Scharl in receiver magazine, Autumn 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Geographical information system usage ===
[[Geographic information system]]s (GIS) — a large domain that provides a variety of capabilities designed to capture, store, manipulate, analyze, manage, and present all types of geographical data — utilizes geospatial analysis in a variety of contexts, operations and applications.

==== Basic applications ====
Geospatial analysis, using [[GIS]], was developed for problems in the environmental and life sciences, in particular [[ecology]], [[geology]] and [[epidemiology]]. It has extended to almost all industries including defense, intelligence, utilities, Natural Resources (i.e. Oil and Gas, Forestry ... etc.), social sciences, medicine and [[Public Safety]] (i.e. emergency management and criminology), disaster risk reduction and management (DRRM), and climate change adaptation (CCA). Spatial statistics typically result primarily from observation rather than experimentation.

==== Basic operations ====
Vector-based [[GIS]] is typically related to operations such as map overlay (combining two or more maps or map layers according to predefined rules), simple buffering (identifying regions of a map within a specified distance of one or more features, such as towns, roads or rivers) and similar basic operations. This reflects (and is reflected in) the use of the term spatial analysis within the Open Geospatial Consortium ([[Open Geospatial Consortium|OGC]]) “simple feature specifications”. For raster-based GIS, widely used in the environmental sciences and remote sensing, this typically means a range of actions applied to the grid cells of one or more maps (or images) often involving filtering and/or algebraic operations (map algebra). These techniques involve processing one or more raster layers according to simple rules resulting in a new map layer, for example replacing each cell value with some combination of its neighbours’ values, or computing the sum or difference of specific attribute values for each grid cell in two matching raster datasets. Descriptive statistics, such as cell counts, means, variances, maxima, minima, cumulative values, frequencies and a number of other measures and distance computations are also often included in this generic term [[spatial analysis]]. Spatial analysis includes a large variety of statistical techniques (descriptive, [[Exploratory data analysis|exploratory]], and explanatory [[statistics]]) that apply to data that vary spatially and which can vary over time. Some more advanced statistical techniques include Getis-ord Gi* or Anselin Local Moran's I which are used to determine clustering patterns of spatially referenced data.

==== Advanced operations ====
Geospatial analysis goes beyond 2D and 3D mapping operations and spatial statistics. It includes: 
* Surface analysis — in particular analysing the properties of physical surfaces, such as [[gradient]], [[aspect (geography)|aspect]] and [[visibility]], and analysing surface-like data “fields”;
* Network analysis — examining the properties of natural and man-made networks in order to understand the behaviour of flows within and around such networks; and locational analysis. GIS-based network analysis may be used to address a wide range of practical problems such as route selection and facility location (core topics in the field of [[operations research]], and problems involving flows such as those found in [[hydrology]] and transportation research. In many instances location problems relate to networks and as such are addressed with tools designed for this purpose, but in others existing networks may have little or no relevance or may be impractical to incorporate within the modeling process. Problems that are not specifically network constrained, such as new road or pipeline routing, regional warehouse location, mobile phone mast positioning or the selection of rural community health care sites, may be effectively analysed (at least initially) without reference to existing physical networks. Locational analysis "in the plane" is also applicable where suitable network datasets are not available, or are too large or expensive to be utilised, or where the location algorithm is very complex or involves the examination or simulation of a very large number of alternative configurations.
* [[Geovisualization]] — the creation and manipulation of images, maps, diagrams, charts, 3D views and their associated tabular datasets. GIS packages increasingly provide a range of such tools, providing static or rotating views, draping images over 2.5D surface representations, providing animations and fly-throughs, dynamic linking and brushing and spatio-temporal visualisations. This latter class of tools is the least developed, reflecting in part the limited range of suitable compatible datasets and the limited set of analytical methods available, although this picture is changing rapidly. All these facilities augment the core tools utilised in spatial analysis throughout the analytical process (exploration of data, identification of patterns and relationships, construction of models, and communication of results)

==== Mobile Geospatial Computing ====
Traditionally geospatial computing has been performed primarily on personal computers (PCs) or servers. Due to the increasing capabilities of mobile devices, however, geospatial computing in mobile devices is a fast-growing trend.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Chen|first1=Ruizhi|last2=Guinness|first2=Robert E.|title=Geospatial Computing in Mobile Devices|date=2014|publisher=Artech House|location=Norwood, MA|isbn=978-1-60807-565-2|pages=228|edition=1st|url=http://www.artechhouse.com/International/Books/Geospatial-Computing-in-Mobile-Devices-2159.aspx|accessdate=1 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; The portable nature of these devices, as well as the presence of useful sensors, such as Global Navigation Satellite System (GNSS) receivers and barometric pressure sensors, make them useful for capturing and processing geospatial information in the field. In addition to the local processing of geospatial information on mobile devices, another growing trend is cloud-based geospatial computing. In this architecture, data can be collected in the field using mobile devices and then transmitted to cloud-based servers for further processing and ultimate storage. In a similar manner, geospatial information can be made available to connected mobile devices via the cloud, allowing access to vast databases of geospatial information anywhere where a wireless data connection is available.

=== Geographic information science and spatial analysis ===
{{further information|Geographic information systems#Spatial analysis}}
'''[[Geographic information systems]]''' (GIS) and the underlying [[geographic information science]] that advances these technologies have a strong influence on spatial analysis.  The increasing ability to capture and handle geographic data means that spatial analysis is occurring within increasingly data-rich environments.  Geographic data capture systems include remotely sensed imagery, environmental monitoring systems such as intelligent transportation systems, and location-aware technologies such as mobile devices that can report location in near-real time.  GIS provide platforms for managing these data, computing spatial relationships such as distance, connectivity and directional relationships between spatial units, and visualizing both the raw data and spatial analytic results within a cartographic context.
[[Image:Minard.png|thumb|300px|This flow map of Napoleon's ill-fated march on Moscow is an early and celebrated example of geovisualization. It shows the army's direction as it traveled, the places the troops passed through, the size of the army as troops died from hunger and wounds, and the freezing temperatures they experienced.]]

==== Content ====
*Spatial location: Transfer positioning information of space objects with the help of space coordinate system. Projection transformation theory is the foundation of spatial object representation.
*Spatial distribution: the similar spatial object groups positioning information, including distribution, trends, contrast etc..
*Spatial form: the geometric shape of the spatial objects
*Spatial space: the space objects' approaching degree
*Spatial relationship: relationship between spatial objects, including topological, orientation, similarity, etc..

'''[[Geovisualization]]''' (GVis) combines scientific visualization with [[digital cartography]] to support the exploration and analysis of geographic data and information, including the results of spatial analysis or simulation. GVis leverages the human orientation towards visual information processing in the exploration, analysis and communication of geographic data and information.  In contrast with traditional cartography, GVis is typically three- or four-dimensional (the latter including time) and user-interactive.

'''Geographic knowledge discovery''' (GKD) is the human-centered process of applying efficient computational tools for exploring massive [[spatial database]]s. GKD includes geographic [[data mining]], but also encompasses related activities such as data selection, data cleaning and pre-processing, and interpretation of results. GVis can also serve a central role in the GKD process.  GKD is based on the premise that massive databases contain interesting (valid, novel, useful and understandable) patterns that standard analytical techniques cannot find.  GKD can serve as a hypothesis-generating process for spatial analysis, producing tentative patterns and relationships that should be confirmed using spatial analytical techniques.

'''[[Spatial decision support system]]s''' (SDSS) take existing spatial data and use a variety of mathematical models to make projections into the future. This allows urban and regional planners to test intervention decisions prior to implementation.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=González|first=Ainhoa|last2=Donnelly|first2=Alison|last3=Jones|first3=Mike|last4=Chrysoulakis|first4=Nektarios|last5=Lopes|first5=Myriam|year=2012|title=A decision-support system for sustainable urban metabolism in Europe|doi=10.1016/j.eiar.2012.06.007|journal=Environmental Impact Assessment Review|volume=38|pages=109–119}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
;General topics
{{div col|colwidth=18em}}
* [[Cartography]]
* [[Complete spatial randomness]]
* [[GeoComputation]]
* [[Geospatial intelligence]]
* [[Geospatial predictive modeling]]
* [[DE-9IM|Dimensionally Extended nine-Intersection Model]]  (DE-9IM)
* [[Geographic information science]]
* [[Mathematical statistics]]
* [[Modifiable areal unit problem]]
* [[Spatial autocorrelation]]
* [[Spatial relation]]
* [[List of spatial analysis software]]
{{div col end}}


;Specific applications
{{div col|colwidth=18em}}
* [[Geographic information systems]]
* [[Geodemographic segmentation]]
* [[Visibility analysis]]
* [[Fuzzy architectural spatial analysis]]
* [[Suitability analysis]]
* [[Extrapolation domain analysis]]
* [[Geoinformatics]]
* [[Boundary problem (in spatial analysis)]]
* [[Spatial epidemiology]]
* [[Spatial econometrics]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
{{Further reading cleanup|date=June 2014}}
* Abler, R., J. Adams, and P. Gould (1971) ''Spatial Organization&amp;ndash;The Geographer's View of the World'', Englewood Cliffs, NJ: Prentice-Hall.
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20110919052807/http://www.drs.wisc.edu/documents/articles/curtis/cesoc977/Anselin1995.pdf Anselin, L. (1995) "Local indicators of spatial association – LISA". ''Geographical Analysis'', 27, 93&amp;ndash;115].
* {{cite book|author1=Awange, Joseph|author2=Paláncz, Béla|year=2016|title=Geospatial Algebraic Computations, Theory and Applications, Third Edition|location=New York|publisher=Springer|isbn=978-3319254630}}
* {{Citation | last = Banerjee | first = Sudipto | last2 = Carlin | first2 = Bradley P. | last3 = Gelfand | first3 = Alan E. | date = 2014 | title = Hierarchical Modeling and Analysis for Spatial Data, Second Edition | series = Monographs on Statistics and Applied Probability | publisher = Chapman and Hall/CRC | edition = 2nd | isbn = 9781439819173}}
* Benenson, I. and P. M. Torrens. (2004). ''Geosimulation: Automata-Based Modeling of Urban Phenomena.'' Wiley.
* Fotheringham, A. S., C. Brunsdon and M. Charlton (2000) ''Quantitative Geography: Perspectives on Spatial Data Analysis'', Sage.
* Fotheringham, A. S. and M. E. O'Kelly (1989) ''Spatial Interaction Models: Formulations and Applications'', Kluwer Academic
* {{cite journal | last1 = Fotheringham | first1 = A. S. | last2 = Rogerson | first2 = P. A. | year = 1993 | title = GIS and spatial analytical problems | journal = International Journal of Geographical Information Systems | volume = 7 | issue = | pages = 3–19 | doi=10.1080/02693799308901936}}
* {{cite journal | last1 = Goodchild | first1 = M. F. | year = 1987 | title = A spatial analytical perspective on geographical information systems | journal = International Journal of Geographical Information Systems | volume = 1 | issue = 4| pages = 327–44 | doi=10.1080/02693798708927820}}
* [[Alan MacEachren|MacEachren, A. M.]] and D. R. F. Taylor (eds.) (1994) ''Visualization in Modern Cartography'', Pergamon.
* Levine, N. (2010).  ''CrimeStat: A Spatial Statistics Program for the Analysis of Crime Incident Locations''. Version 3.3. Ned Levine &amp; Associates, Houston, TX and the National Institute of Justice, Washington, DC. Ch. 1-17 + 2 update chapters [http://www.icpsr.umich.edu/CrimeStat]
* {{cite journal | last1 = Miller | first1 = H. J. | year = 2004 | title = Tobler's First Law and spatial analysis | journal = Annals of the Association of American Geographers | volume = 94 | issue = 2| pages = 284–289 | doi=10.1111/j.1467-8306.2004.09402005.x}}
* Miller, H. J. and J. Han (eds.) (2001) ''Geographic Data Mining and Knowledge Discovery'', Taylor and Francis.
* O'Sullivan, D. and D. Unwin (2002) ''Geographic Information Analysis'', Wiley.
* {{cite journal | last1 = Parker | first1 = D. C. | authorlink3 = Marco A. Janssen | last2 = Manson | first2 = S. M. | last3 = Janssen | first3 = M.A. | last4 = Hoffmann | first4 = M. J. | last5 = Deadman | first5 = P. | year = 2003 | title = Multi-agent systems for the simulation of land-use and land-cover change: A review | journal = Annals of the Association of American Geographers | volume = 93 | issue = 2| pages = 314–337 | doi=10.1111/1467-8306.9302004| citeseerx = 10.1.1.109.1825 }}
* {{cite journal | last1 = White | first1 = R. | last2 = Engelen | first2 = G. | year = 1997 | title = Cellular automata as the basis of integrated dynamic regional modelling | journal = Environment and Planning B: Planning and Design | volume = 24 | issue = 2| pages = 235–246 | doi=10.1068/b240235}}
* {{cite book
|author1=Scheldeman, X.  |author2=van Zonneveld, M.   
 |lastauthoramp=yes |year=2010  
|title= Training Manual on Spatial Analysis of Plant Diversity and Distribution
|publisher= Bioversity International 
|url=  http://www.bioversityinternational.org/index.php?id=244&amp;tx_news_pi1%5Bnews%5D=1256&amp;cHash=110ef499ad0d2d17abb48849909f1356}}
* Fisher MM, Leung Y (2001) Geocomputational Modelling: techniques and applications. Springer Verlag, Berlin
* {{cite journal | last1 = Fotheringham | first1 = S | last2 = Clarke | first2 = G | last3 = Abrahart | first3 = B | year = 1997 | title = Geocomputation and GIS | journal = Transactions in GIS | volume = 2 | issue = 3| pages = 199–200 | doi=10.1111/j.1467-9671.1997.tb00010.x}}
* Openshaw S and Abrahart RJ (2000) GeoComputation. CRC Press
* Diappi Lidia (2004) Evolving Cities: Geocomputation in Territorial Planning. Ashgate, England
* Longley PA, Brooks SM, McDonnell R, Macmillan B (1998), Geocomputation, a primer. John Wiley and Sons, Chichester
* {{cite journal | last1 = Ehlen | first1 = J | last2 = Caldwell | first2 = DR | last3 = Harding | first3 = S | year = 2002 | title = GeoComputation: what is it? | journal = Comput Environ and Urban Syst | volume = 26 | issue = 4| pages = 257–265 | doi=10.1016/s0198-9715(01)00047-3}}
* {{cite journal | last1 = Gahegan | first1 = M | year = 1999 | title = What is Geocomputation? | journal = Transaction in GIS | volume = 3 | issue = 3| pages = 203–206 | doi=10.1111/1467-9671.00017}}
* Murgante B., Borruso G., Lapucci A. (2009) "Geocomputation and Urban Planning" ''Studies in Computational Intelligence'', Vol. 176. Springer-Verlag, Berlin.
*{{cite journal |doi=10.1080/02723638.2015.1096118 |title=Spatial metrics to study urban patterns in growing and shrinking cities |journal=Urban Geography |volume=37 |issue=2 |pages=246–271 |year=2016 |last1=Reis |first1=José P. |last2=Silva |first2=Elisabete A. |last3=Pinho |first3=Paulo }}
*{{cite journal |doi=10.1016/S1470-160X(02)00052-3 |title=Modelling indicators and indices of landscape complexity: An approach using G.I.S |journal=Ecological Indicators |volume=2 |pages=17–25 |year=2002 |last1=Papadimitriou |first1=F. }}
* Fischer M., Leung Y. (2010) "GeoComputational Modelling: Techniques and Applications" Advances in Spatial Science. Springer-Verlag, Berlin.
* Murgante B., Borruso G., Lapucci A. (2011) "Geocomputation, Sustainability and Environmental Planning" ''Studies in Computational Intelligence'', Vol. 348. Springer-Verlag, Berlin.
* {{cite journal | last1 = Tahmasebi | first1 = P. | last2 = Hezarkhani | first2 = A. | last3 = Sahimi | first3 = M. | year = 2012 | title = Multiple-point geostatistical modeling based on the cross-correlation functions | journal = Computational Geosciences | volume = 16 | issue = 3| pages = 779–79742 | doi=10.1007/s10596-012-9287-1}}
*{{cite journal |doi=10.13140/2.1.1560.2247 |title=European Spatial Structure |last1=Geza |first1=Tóth |last2=Áron |first2=Kincses |last3=Zoltán |first3=Nagy |url=http://rgdoi.net/10.13140/2.1.1560.2247 |year=2014 |publisher=LAP LAMBERT Academic Publishing }}

==External links==
{{Commonscat|Spatial data analysis}}
* [https://sites.google.com/site/commissionofica/ ICA Commission on Geospatial Analysis and Modeling]
* [http://www.ai-geostats.org/ An educational resource about spatial statistics and geostatistics]
* [http://www.spatialanalysisonline.com/ A comprehensive guide to principles, techniques &amp; software tools]
* [http://sasi.group.shef.ac.uk/ Social and Spatial Inequalities]
* [http://www.ncgia.ucsb.edu/ National Center for Geographic Information and Analysis (NCGIA)]
*[http://www.icaci.org International Cartographic Association (ICA)], the world body for mapping and GIScience professionals

{{Visualization}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Spatial Analysis}}
[[Category:Cartography]]
[[Category:Geographic data and information]]
[[Category:Geography]]
[[Category:Geostatistics]]
[[Category:Mathematical and quantitative methods (economics)]]
[[Category:Spatial data analysis| ]]
[[Category:Statistical data types]]</text>
      <sha1>1rcvl03igqmp5cnuldzd164yb7io8mb</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Survey stakes</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>13219832</id>
    <revision>
      <id>666344598</id>
      <parentid>626613456</parentid>
      <timestamp>2015-06-10T14:49:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>87.190.243.142</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>adding link</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="1491">{{multiple issues|
{{Underlinked|date=September 2014}}
{{unreferenced|date=December 2007}}
}}

Control of alignment and grade during [[construction]] is established through the use of '''survey stakes'''. Stakes are generally made of wood in different sizes. Based on the use of the stake they are called ''alignment stakes, offset stakes, grade stakes, and slope stakes''.

Survey stakes are markers surveyors use in surveying projects to prepare job sites, mark out property boundaries, and provide information about claims on natural resources like timber and minerals. They can be made from wood, metal, plastic, and other materials and typically come in a range of sizes and colors for different purposes. Sources can include surveying and construction suppliers, and people can also make or order their own for custom applications.

A survey stake is typically small, with a pointed end to make it easy to drive into the earth. It may be color-coded or have a space for people to write information on the stake. Surveyors use stakes when assessing sites to mark out boundaries, record data, and convey information to other people. On a job site, for example, survey stakes indicate where it is necessary to [[backfill]] with soil to raise the elevation, or to cut soil away to lower it. Stakes can also provide information about slope and grading for people getting a job site ready for construction.

[[Category:Construction terminology]]
[[Category:Surveying]]


{{engineering-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>ffb7pnwi5c1tv9ybv8z4e8e861j839l</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Table (landform)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>18062821</id>
    <revision>
      <id>868008469</id>
      <parentid>849099284</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-11-09T11:39:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>J 1982</username>
        <id>777667</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="1628">{{Notability|date=March 2009}}
{{redirect|Table hill|the Marilyn of England|Table Hill}}
{{redirect|Table mountain||Table Mountain (disambiguation)}}
{{redirect-distinguish|Tableland|Tablelands (disambiguation)}}
[[File:Over Monument Valley, Navajo Nation.jpg|thumb|right|A [[mesa]] in [[Monument Valley]] in [[Navajo Nation]].]]
[[File:HarQatum.jpg|thumb|right|Har Qatum, a [[Mesa]] located on the southern edge of [[Makhtesh Ramon]], [[Israel]].]]
A '''table''' or '''tableland''' is a [[butte]], flank of a mountain, or [[mountain]], that has a flat [[summit|top]].  

This landform has numerous names in addition to "table", including:
*[[Tuya]]
*[[Tepui]]
*[[Mesa]]
*[[Potrero (landform)|Potrero]]
*[[Butte]]
*[[Plateau]]
*[[Fluvial terrace|Terrace]]
*Table
**Table hill
**Table-topped hill
**Table mountain
**Tableland

==Description==
The term "flat" is relative when speaking of tables, and often the naming or identification of a table (or table hill or mountain) is based on the appearance of the terrain feature from a distance or from below it.  An example is [[Mesa Verde National Park|Mesa Verde, Colorado]], where the "flat top" of the mountain is both rolling terrain and cut by numerous deep canyons and arroyos, but whose rims appear quite flat from almost all directions, terminating in cliffs.

==See also==
{{Portal|Geography}}
*[[Plateau]] - ''syn: Tablelands''
{{-}}

{{Earth's landforms|state=collapsed}}
{{Physical geography topics}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Table (Landform)}}
[[Category:Tables (landform)| ]]
[[Category:Landforms]]
[[Category:Mountains]]
[[Category:Geography terminology]]


{{Topography-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>epevq6qg0r3usobs8uiafbmvh7ufoav</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Theodolite</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>248860</id>
    <revision>
      <id>867639492</id>
      <parentid>865802704</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-11-07T01:20:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>LouisAlain</username>
        <id>14909828</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>direct link to new article</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="22779">{{anchor|Non-Transit|Transit|Seconds|Optical}}
[[File:SovietTheodolite.jpg|thumb|A direct readout  theodolite, manufactured in the Soviet Union in 1958 and used for topographic surveying]]

A '''theodolite''' {{IPAc-en|θ|iː|ˈ|ɒ|d|ə|l|aɪ|t}} is a precision optical instrument for measuring [[angle]]s between designated visible points in the [[horizontal and vertical]] planes. The traditional use has been for [[surveying|land surveying]], but they are also used extensively for [[Construction|building and infrastructure construction]], and some specialized applications such as [[meteorology]] and [[rocket launch]]ing.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |title=Double Theodolite Pibal Evaluation by Computer |first=Norman |last=Thyer |date=March 1962 |journal=Journal of Applied Meteorology and Climatology |volume=1 |issue=1 |pages=66–68 |publisher=American Meteorological Society |doi=10.1175/1520-0450(1962)001&lt;0066:DTPEBC&gt;2.0.CO;2 }}&lt;/ref&gt; 

It consists of a moveable [[telescope]] mounted so it can rotate around horizontal and vertical [[Cartesian coordinate system|axes]] and provide angular readouts. These indicate the orientation of the telescope, and are used to relate the first point sighted through the telescope to subsequent sightings of other points from the same theodolite position. These angles can be measured with great accuracy, typically to [[milliradian]] or [[Minute and second of arc|seconds of arc]]. From these readings a plan can be drawn, or objects can be positioned in accordance with an existing plan. The modern theodolite has evolved into what is known as a [[total station]] where angles and distances are measured electronically, and are read directly to computer memory.   

In a transit theodolite, the telescope is short enough to rotate through the [[zenith]], otherwise for non-transit instruments vertical (or altitude), rotation is restricted to a limited arc. 

The [[optical level]] is sometimes mistaken for a theodolite, but it does not measure vertical angles, and is used only for [[levelling]] on a [[horizontal plane]].

== Principles of operation ==
[[File:theodolite vermeer.svg|thumb|The axes and circles of a theodolite]]
[[File:Optical Theodolite.jpg|thumb|Diagram of an optical readout theodolite]]
===Preparation for making sightings===
{{main|Temporary adjustments of theodolites}}
Temporary adjustments are a set of operations necessary in order to make a theodolite ready for taking observations at a station. These include its setting up, centering, leveling up and elimination of parallax, and are achieved in four steps:

* Setting up - fixing the theodolite onto a tripod along with approximate levelling and centering over the station mark. 
* Centering - bringing the vertical axis of theodolite immediately over station mark using a centering plate also known as a [[tribrach (instrument)|tribrach]].
* Levelling - leveling of the base of the instrument to make the vertical axis vertical usually with an in-built bubble-level.
* Focusing - removing [[parallax]] error by proper focusing of objective and eye-piece. The eye-piece only requires adjustment once at a station. The objective will be re-focused for each subsequent sightings from this station because of the different distances to the target.

===Sightings===
Sightings are taken by the surveyor, who adjusts the telescope's vertical and horizontal angular orientation so the [[cross-hairs]] align with the desired sighting point. Both angles are read either from exposed or internal scales and recorded. The next object is then sighted and recorded without moving the position of the instrument and tripod.

The earliest angular readouts were from open [[vernier scale]]s directly visible to the eye. Gradually these scales were enclosed for physical protection, and finally became an indirect optical readout, with convoluted light paths to bring them to a convenient place on the instrument for viewing. The modern digital theodolites have electronic displays.

=== Errors in measurement ===
'''Index error -''' The angles in the vertical axis should read 90[[degree (angle)|°]] (100 [[grad (angle)|grad]]) when the sight axis is horizontal, or 270° (300 grad) when the instrument is transited. Half of the difference between the two positions is called the "index error". This can only be checked on transit instruments.

'''Horizontal axis error''' - The horizontal and vertical axes of a theodolite must be perpendicular; if not then a "horizontal axis error" exists. This can be tested by aligning the tubular spirit bubble parallel to a line between two footscrews and setting the bubble central. A horizontal axis error is present if the bubble runs off central when the tubular spirit bubble is reversed (turned through 180°). To adjust, the operator removes 1/2 the amount the bubble has run off using the adjusting screw, then re-level, test and refine the adjustment.

'''Collimation error -''' The optical axis of the telescope, must also be perpendicular to the horizontal axis. If not, then a "collimation error" exists.

Index error, horizontal-axis error ('trunnion-axis error') and collimation error are regularly determined by [[calibration]] and are removed by mechanical adjustment. Their existence is taken into account in the choice of measurement procedure in order to eliminate their effect on the measurement results of the theodolite.

== {{anchor|Half|Simple|Plain}}History ==
[[File:Universaltheodolit.14Zoll.Pistor&amp;Martins.Berlin.1851.jpg|thumb|A theodolite of 1851, showing the open construction, and the altitude and azimuth scales which are read directly.]]
[[Image:Sectioned_theodolite.jpg|thumb|Sectioned theodolite showing the complex light paths for optical readout, and the enclosed construction.]]

The term ''diopter'' was sometimes used in old texts as a synonym for theodolite.&lt;ref&gt;''The Compact Edition of the Oxford English Dictionary'', Oxford University Press, 1971 - see entry for ''diopter''&lt;/ref&gt; This derives from an older astronomical instrument called a [[dioptra]].

Prior to the theodolite, instruments such as the [[Groma surveying|groma]], [[geometric square]] and various other graduated circles (see [[circumferentor]]) and semicircles (see [[graphometer]]) were used to obtain either vertical or horizontal angle measurements. It was only a matter of time before someone put two measuring devices into a single instrument that could measure both angles simultaneously. [[Gregorius Reisch]] showed such an instrument in the appendix of his book ''Margarita Philosophica'', which he published in [[Strasbourg|Strasburg]] in 1512.&lt;ref name="daumas"&gt;Daumas, Maurice, ''Scientific Instruments of the Seventeenth and Eighteenth Centuries and Their Makers'', Portman Books, London 1989 {{ISBN|978-0-7134-0727-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was described in the appendix by [[Martin Waldseemüller]], a German [[topographer]] and [[cartographer]], who made the device in the same year.&lt;ref name="geomaticaonline"/&gt; Waldseemüller called his instrument the ''polimetrum''.&lt;ref name="mills"&gt;Mills, John FitzMaurice, ''Encyclopedia of Antique Scientific Instruments'', Aurum Press, London, 1983, {{ISBN|0-906053-40-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The first occurrence of the word "theodolite" is found in the [[surveying]] textbook ''A geometric practice named Pantometria'' (1571) by [[Leonard Digges (scientist)|Leonard Digges]], which was published posthumously by his son, Thomas Digges.&lt;ref name="daumas"/&gt; The [[etymology]] of the word is unknown. The first part of the [[New Latin]] ''theo-delitus'' might stem from the [[Greek language|Greek]] ''[[wikt:θεάομαι|θεᾶσθαι]]'', "to behold or look attentively upon"&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.searchgodsword.org/lex/grk/view.cgi?number=2300 Theaomai - Greek Lexicon&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; or ''[[wikt:θέω|θεῖν]]'' "to run",&lt;ref name="Wordnik"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wordnik.com/words/theodolite/etymologies|title=Wordnik|work=Wordnik.com|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150402191341/https://www.wordnik.com/words/theodolite/etymologies|archivedate=2015-04-02|df=}}&lt;/ref&gt; but the second part is more puzzling and is often attributed to an unscholarly variation of one of the following Greek words: ''[[wikt:δῆλος|δῆλος]]'', meaning "evident" or "clear",&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.languagehat.com/archives/001935.php|title=languagehat.com :   THEODOLITE.|work=languagehat.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.takeourword.com/Issue016.html|title=Take Our Word For It Issue 16|work=takeourword.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; or ''[[wikt:δολιχός|δολιχός]]'' "long", or ''[[wikt:δοῦλος|δοῦλος]]'' "slave", or an unattested Neolatin compound combining ''[[wikt:ὁδός|ὁδός]]'' "way" and ''[[wikt:λιτός|λιτός]]'' "plain".&lt;ref name="Wordnik"/&gt; It has been also suggested that ''-delitus'' is a variation of the Latin [[supine]] ''[[wikt:deletus|deletus]]'', in the sense of "crossed out".&lt;ref name="Wordnik"/&gt;

There is some confusion about the instrument to which the name was originally applied. Some identify the early theodolite as an [[azimuth]] instrument only, while others specify it as an [[altazimuth mount|altazimuth]] instrument. In Digges's book, the name "theodolite" described an instrument for measuring horizontal angles only. He also described an instrument that measured both altitude and azimuth, which he called a ''topographicall instrument'' {{sic}}.&lt;ref name="turnerEIM"&gt;Turner, Gerard L'E., ''Elizabethan Instrument Makers: The Origins of the London Trade in Precision Instrument Making'', Oxford University Press, 2000, {{ISBN|978-0-19-856566-6}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thus the name originally applied only to the azimuth instrument and only later became associated with the altazimuth instrument. The 1728 ''[[Cyclopaedia, or an Universal Dictionary of Arts and Sciences|Cyclopaedia]]'' compares "[[graphometer]]" to "half-theodolite".&lt;ref&gt;''[[Cyclopaedia, or an Universal Dictionary of Arts and Sciences|Cyclopaedia]]'', vol. 2 p. 50 for "Semi-Circle"&lt;/ref&gt; Even as late as the 19th century, the instrument for measuring horizontal angles only was called a ''simple theodolite'' and the altazimuth instrument, the ''plain theodolite''.&lt;ref name="turner"/&gt;

The first instrument more like a true theodolite was likely the one built by [[Joshua Habermel]] ([[Erasmus Habermehl]]) in Germany in 1576, complete with compass and tripod.&lt;ref name="geomaticaonline"&gt;[http://www.geomatica.it/strumenti_antichi/estratto.htm Geomatica Online] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071113052943/http://geomatica.it/strumenti_antichi/estratto.htm |date=2007-11-13 }} Colombo, Luigi, Selvini, Attilio, ''Sintesi di una storia degli strumenti per la misura topografica''&lt;/ref&gt;

The earliest altazimuth instruments consisted of a base graduated with a full circle at the [[wikt:limb#Etymology 2|limb]] and a vertical angle measuring device, most often a semicircle. An [[alidade]] on the base was used to sight an object for horizontal angle measurement, and a second alidade was mounted on the vertical semicircle. Later instruments had a single alidade on the vertical semicircle and the entire semicircle was mounted so as to be used to indicate horizontal angles directly. Eventually, the simple, open-sight alidade was replaced with a sighting [[telescope]]. This was first done by [[Jonathan Sisson]] in 1725.&lt;ref name="turner"/&gt;

The theodolite became a modern, accurate instrument in 1787, with the introduction of [[Jesse Ramsden]]'s famous [[Ramsden theodolite|great theodolite]], which he created using a very accurate [[dividing engine]] of his own design.&lt;ref name="turner"&gt;Turner, Gerard L'E. ''Nineteenth Century Scientific Instruments'', Sotheby Publications, 1983, {{ISBN|0-85667-170-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; The demand could not be met by foreign theodolites owing to their inadequate precision, hence all instruments meeting high precision requirements were made in England. Despite the many German instrument builders at the turn of the century, there were no usable German theodolites available. A transition was brought about by Breithaupt and the symbiosis of Utzschneider, Reichenbach and Fraunhofer.&lt;ref&gt;Ralf Kern: Wissenschaftliche Instrumente in ihrer Zeit/Band 4: Perfektion von Optik und Mechanik. Cologne, 2010, pp. 349–360.&lt;/ref&gt;
As technology progressed, in the 1840s, the vertical partial circle was replaced with a full circle, and both vertical and horizontal circles were finely graduated. This was the ''transit theodolite''. Theodolites were later adapted to a wider variety of mountings and uses. In the 1870s, an interesting waterborne version of the theodolite (using a pendulum device to counteract wave movement) was invented by [[Edward Samuel Ritchie]].&lt;ref&gt;American Academy of Arts and Sciences, ''Proceedings of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences'', Vol. XXIII, May 1895 - May 1896, Boston: University Press, John Wilson and Son (1896), pp. 359–360&lt;/ref&gt; It was used by the U.S. Navy to take the first precision surveys of American harbors on the Atlantic and Gulf coasts.&lt;ref&gt;American Academy, pp. 359–360&lt;/ref&gt;

In the early part of the 20th century, [[Heinrich Wild]] produced theodolites that became popular with surveyors. His Wild T2, T3, and A1 instruments were made for many years, and he would go on to develop the DK1, DKM1, DM2, DKM2, and DKM3 for Kern Aarau company. With continuing refinements, instruments steadily evolved into the modern theodolite used by surveyors today.

=== Operation in surveying ===
{{main|Triangulation (surveying)}}
[[Image:theb1982.jpg|thumb|right|150px|[[U.S. National Geodetic Survey]] technicians observing with a 0.2 [[arcsecond]] (≈ 0.001 [[Milliradian|mrad]] or 1 µrad) resolution Wild T3 theodolite mounted on an observing stand. Photo was taken during an Arctic field party (c. 1950).]]

[[Triangulation (surveying)|Triangulation]], as invented by [[Gemma Frisius]] around 1533, consists of making such direction plots of the surrounding landscape from two separate standpoints. The two graphing papers are superimposed, providing a scale model of the landscape, or rather the targets in it. The true scale can be obtained by measuring one distance both in the real terrain and in the graphical representation.

Modern triangulation as, e.g., practised by [[Willebrord Snell|Snellius]], is the same procedure executed by numerical means. Photogrammetric block adjustment of stereo pairs of aerial photographs is a modern, three-dimensional variant.

In the late 1780s, [[Jesse Ramsden]], a Yorkshireman from [[Halifax, West Yorkshire|Halifax]], England who had developed the [[dividing engine]] for dividing angular scales accurately to within a second of arc (≈ 0.0048 [[Milliradian|mrad]] or 4.8 µrad), was commissioned to build a new instrument for the British [[Ordnance Survey]]. The [[Ramsden theodolite]] was used over the next few years to map the whole of southern [[Kingdom of Great Britain|Britain]] by triangulation.

In network measurement, the use of forced centering speeds up operations while maintaining the highest precision. The theodolite or the target can be rapidly removed from, or socketed into, the forced centering plate with sub-millimeter precision. Nowadays [[GPS]] antennas used for [[geodetic positioning]] use a similar mounting system. The height of the reference point of the theodolite—or the target—above the ground [[benchmark (surveying)|benchmark]] must be measured precisely.

===Transit theodolite===
The term '''transit theodolite''', or '''transit''' for short, refers to a type of theodolite that was developed in the early 19th century. It was popular with American railroad engineers pushing west, and it replaced the [[railroad compass]], [[sextant]] and [[Octant (instrument)|octant]]. It features a vertical circle which is graduated through the full 360 degrees and a telescope that could "flip over" ("transit the scope").  By reversing the telescope and at the same time rotating the instrument through 180 degrees about the vertical axis, the instrument can be used in 'plate-left' or 'plate-right' modes ('plate' refers to the vertical protractor circle).  By measuring the same horizontal and vertical angles in these two modes and then averaging the results, centering and collimating errors in the instrument can be eliminated. Some transit instruments are capable of reading angles directly to thirty arc-seconds (≈ 0.15 [[Milliradian|mrad]]). Modern theodolites are usually of the transit-theodolite design, but engraved plates have been replaced with glass plates designed to be read with [[light-emitting diodes]] and computer circuitry, greatly improving accuracy.

== {{anchor|Pibal}}Use with weather balloons ==
There is a long history of theodolite use in measuring winds aloft, by using specially-manufactured theodolites to track the horizontal and vertical angles of special weather balloons called ''[[ceiling balloon]]s'' or ''pilot balloons'' (''pibal''). Early attempts at this were made in the opening years of the nineteenth century, but the instruments and procedures weren't fully developed until a hundred years later. This method was extensively used in World War II and thereafter, and was gradually replaced by radio and GPS measuring systems from the 1980s onward.

The pibal theodolite uses a prism to bend the optical path by 90 degrees so the operator's eye position does not change as the elevation is changed through a complete 180 degrees. The theodolite is typically mounted on a rugged steel stand, set up so it is level and pointed north, with the altitude and azimuth scales reading zero degrees. A balloon is released in front of the theodolite, and its position is precisely tracked, usually once a minute. The balloons are carefully constructed and filled, so their rate of ascent can be known fairly accurately in advance. Mathematical calculations on time, rate of ascent, azimuth and angular altitude can produce good estimates of wind speed and direction at various altitudes.&lt;ref name="Brenner"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.csulb.edu/~mbrenner/balloon.htm |title=Pilot Weather Balloon (Pibal) Optical Theodolites |last=Brenner |first=Martin |work=Martin Brenner's Pilot Balloon Resources |publisher=California State University, Long Beach |date=2009-11-25 |accessdate=2014-07-25 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== {{anchor|Electronic}}Modern electronic theodolites ==
[[Image:Teodolit nikon 520.jpg|thumb|150px|A typical modern electronic theodolite: [[Nikon]] DTM-520]]
In modern electronic theodolites, the readout of the horizontal and vertical circles is usually done with a [[rotary encoder]]. These produce signals indicating the altitude and azimuth of the telescope which are fed to a microprocessor. [[Charge-coupled device|CCD]] sensors have been added to the [[focal plane]] of the [[telescope]] allowing both auto-targeting and the automated measurement of residual target offset. All this is implemented in embedded software of the processor.

Many modern theodolites are equipped with integrated electro-optical distance measuring devices, generally [[infrared]] based, allowing the measurement in one step of complete three-dimensional [[vector (geometry)|vector]]s—albeit in instrument-defined polar co-ordinates, which can then be transformed to a pre-existing co-ordinate system in the area by means of a sufficient number of [[control point (surveying)|control point]]s. This technique is called a [[resection (orientation)|resection]] solution or [[free station position surveying]] and is widely used in mapping surveying.

Such instruments are "intelligent" theodolites called self-registering [[Tacheometry|tacheometers]] or colloquially "[[total station]]s", and perform all the necessary angular and distance calculations, and the results or raw data can be downloaded to external processors, such as ruggedized [[laptops]], [[Personal digital assistant|PDA]]s or [[programmable calculator]]s&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=The End of An Era - On the genesis, life and death of the HP 48 | first=Joseph V. | last=Paiva | date=2004-10-01 | website=Point of Beginning (PoB) | publisher=BNP Media | url=http://www.pobonline.com/articles/85345-the-end-of-an-era | accessdate=2015-10-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Gyrotheodolites ==
{{Main|gyrotheodolite}}
A '''gyrotheodolite''' is used when the north-south reference bearing of the meridian is required in the absence of astronomical star sights. This occurs mainly in the underground mining industry and in tunnel engineering. For example, where a conduit must pass under a river, a vertical shaft on each side of the river might be connected by a horizontal tunnel. A gyrotheodolite can be operated at the surface and then again at the foot of the shafts to identify the directions needed to tunnel between the base of the two shafts. Unlike an artificial horizon or inertial navigation system, a gyrotheodolite cannot be relocated while it is operating. It must be restarted again at each site.

The gyrotheodolite comprises a normal theodolite with an attachment that contains a gyroscope mounted so as to sense rotation of the Earth and from that the alignment of the meridian. The meridian is the plane that contains both the axis of the Earth's rotation and the observer. The intersection of the meridian plane with the horizontal contains the true north-south geographic reference bearing required. The gyrotheodolite is usually referred to as being able to determine or find true north.

A gyrotheodolite will function at the equator and in both the northern and southern hemispheres. The meridian is undefined at the geographic poles. A gyrotheodolite cannot be used at the poles where the Earth's axis is precisely perpendicular to the horizontal axis of the spinner, indeed it is not normally used within about 15 degrees of the pole because the east-west component of the Earth's rotation is insufficient to obtain reliable results. When available, astronomical star sights are able to give the meridian bearing to better than one hundred times the accuracy of the gyrotheodolite. Where this extra precision is not required, the gyrotheodolite is able to produce a result quickly without the need for night observations.

== See also ==
* [[Cinetheodolite]]
* [[Dumpy level]]
* [[Inclinometer]]
* [[LIDAR]]
* [[Macrometer]]
* [[Plane table]]
* [[Rankine's method]]
* [[Survey camp]]
* [[Temporary adjustments of theodolite]]

== Manufacturers ==
* [[Leica Geosystems]]
* [[Sokkia]]
* [[Topcon]]
* [[Trimble (company)]]

== References ==
{{Commons category|Theodolites}}
{{reflist}}

{{Measuring and alignment tools}}

[[Category:Geodesy]]
[[Category:Inclinometers]]
[[Category:Optical devices]]
[[Category:Surveying instruments]]
[[Category:Surveying]]</text>
      <sha1>975ajkq579qex9flub2ew9dwsguxhz5</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
