<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.33.0-wmf.4</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Activism industry</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>302468</id>
    <redirect title="Activism" />
    <revision>
      <id>784009772</id>
      <parentid>556682625</parentid>
      <timestamp>2017-06-05T23:47:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Tom.Reding</username>
        <id>9784415</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>+{{Redirect category shell}} using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="222">#REDIRECT [[Activism#Activism industry]]

{{Redirect category shell|1=
{{R from merge}}
{{R to section}}
}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Activism Industry}}
[[Category:Activism]]
[[Category:Community organizing]]
[[Category:Industries]]</text>
      <sha1>jr1j6wsasmiy3q6v893h3qbvrsfzu2z</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Advisor Group</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>17434798</id>
    <revision>
      <id>860578105</id>
      <parentid>856650413</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-09-21T16:43:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Chris the speller</username>
        <id>525927</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* top */[[WP:AWB/T|typo(s) fixed]]: the U.S.A. → the US</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="1096">'''Advisor Group''' is an Independent Broker-Dealer as of May 2016 as the result of AIG's sale of Advisor Group to Lightyear Capital LLC, a private equity firm specializing in financial services investing, and PSP Investments. With its headquarters in Phoenix, Arizona, it is one of the largest network of independent [[broker-dealer]]s in the US, with over 6,000 registered representatives, many of whom are also [[investment advisor]]s.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.financial-planning.com/asset/article/574571/joby-gruber-out-aig.html?pg= Joby Gruber Out at AIG - Articles - Financial Planning&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; There are four separate broker-dealers that constitute Advisor Group: SagePoint Financial based in [[Phoenix, AZ]]; Royal Alliance in New Jersey; FSC Securities Corporation located in [[Atlanta, GA]]; and Woodbury Financial Services located in [[Oakdale, MN]].

The CEO of Advisor Group is Jamie Price and the chairman is Valerie Brown.

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.advisorgroup.com]

[[Category:Business]]
{{improve categories|date=August 2018}}</text>
      <sha1>cr7yxj3ow6l0osrus3p0l4x0si4giqv</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Agricultural machinery industry</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>44511538</id>
    <revision>
      <id>862497134</id>
      <parentid>831387054</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-10-04T19:23:23Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rescuing 1 sources and tagging 0 as dead. #IABot (v2.0beta9)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="22083">[[File:MacDon M150 windrower with D60-D draper.jpg|thumb|280px|[[AFBF]] 2011 exhibition, Atlanta, Georgia, USA.]]
The '''agricultural machinery industry''' or '''agricultural engineering industry''' is the part of the [[industry]], that produces and maintain [[tractor]]s, [[agricultural machinery]] and agricultural implements. This branch is considered to be part of the [[machinery industry]].

== History ==
:''See also history of [[Agricultural machinery#History|Agricultural machinery]] and [[Mechanised agriculture#History|Mechanised agriculture]]''

=== 19th century ===
The agricultural machinery industry emerged in Britain and the United States in the 19th century. Until then the common tools of farming were the [[plough]] and the sickle.&lt;ref name="RCG 1992"&gt;R.C. Gifford. ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=G6JkSfrmbF8C&amp;pg=PA7 Agricultural Engineering in Development: Concepts and principles].'' 1992. p. 7-8&lt;/ref&gt; These iron agricultural implements were often made by [[blacksmiths]] in the local village, who regularly also acted as [[farrier]]. In the first part of the 19th century some of the early agricultural machine manufacturers arose from these blacksmith workshops,&lt;ref name="JHM94"&gt;Jan H. Maas (1994) ''De Nederlandse agrosector: geografie en dynamiek'' p.177&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Gifford (1992, p. 9) even stated that "nearly all farm machinery manufacturers today can be trace their beginnings to a blacksmith."&lt;/ref&gt; such as [[John Deere]] who started up with the production of ploughs in series in the 1840s. 
[[File:Great Exhibition, Agricutlural Implements 2, HF Talbot, 1851.jpg|thumb|Agricultural Implements, 1851.]]
Other companies arose from the introduction of horse drawn [[reaper|reaping]], which replaced the type of [[Scythe|hand reaper]] in use since biblical times.&lt;ref name="RCG 1992"/&gt; A company as the [[International Harvester|McCormick]] started up with building these kind of harvesting machines around the 1840s. And another origin of agricultural industry was the introduction of combined harvesting, threshing and cleaning in the 1830s.&lt;ref name="RCG 1992"/&gt; The [[Case Corporation]] for example started building those in 1842 as the Racine Threshing Machine Works. Until early 20th century most of those machinery were powered by horses.&lt;ref name="RCG 1992"/&gt;

Mid 19th century the portable steam-powered [[ploughing engine|plowing engine]]s were introduced. They were used in pairs, placed on either side of a field to haul a plow back and forth between them using a wire cable. These [[portable engine]]s were also used to power threshing machines, mills and pumps.&lt;ref name="RCG 1992"/&gt; The portable steam engines were produced by specific agricultural machinery maker, such as [[Ransomes, Sims &amp; Jefferies]] who had started as brass and iron-founder making casting ploughshares late 18th century.

Late 19th century in Britain more companies such as [[Richard Garrett &amp; Sons]] and [[Mann’s Patent Steam Cart and Wagon Company]] developed [[steam tractor]]s for direct ploughing, but the heavy, wet soil of England meant that these designs were less economical than a team of horses. In the United States, where soil conditions permitted, steam tractors were used to direct-haul plows. Steam-powered agricultural engines remained in use well into the 20th century until reliable internal combustion engines had been developed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.livinghistoryfarm.org/farminginthe30s/machines_04.html|title=Tractors in the 1930s}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Collins (1987) recalled that the impact of the agricultural machinery industry in the 19th century was still limited. He stated : "prior the third quarter of the nineteenth century the impact of machinery in agriculture was slight compared with that in manufacturing industry. Some operations such as barn work and hay and corn harvesting had been largely mechanized by 1880 but, up to the Second World War, many were still performed by hand labour and large numbers of workers were still required for seasonal tasks such as hop- and fruit-picking and vegetable cultivations."&lt;ref&gt;Collins, Edward JT. "[http://www.bahs.org.uk/AGHR/ARTICLES/35n1a4.pdf The rationality of'surplus' agricultural labour: mechanization in English agriculture in the nineteenth century]." The Agricultural History Review (1987): 36-46.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== 20th century ===
In the beginning of the 20th century in the UK the Agricultural machinery industry "although composed of many hundreds of firms, was dominated by a few large ones, chiefly in the eastern counties of England. The total output of the industry was estimated to be worth 6.5 million pounds in 1913, or about 5 percent of the total value of the output of the mechanical engineering industry at the first Census of Production in 1907."&lt;ref&gt;Dewey, Peter. "The British Agricultural Machinery Industry, 1914-1939: Boom, Crisis, and Response." ''Agricultural History'' (1995): 298-313.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Fotothek df roe-neg 0006016 027 IFA-Traktor mit Anbauwechselpflug.jpg|thumb|Agricultural exhibitions, 1951]]
In the first decennia the [[internal combustion engine]]; first the [[petrol engine]], and later [[diesel engine]]s; became the main source of [[power (physics)|power]] for the next generation of tractors. Early companies expanded into the tractor business, such as [[John Deere]] which bought the [[Waterloo Gasoline Engine Company]] in 1918, which manufactured the popular [[Waterloo Boy]] tractor. In the 1930s new technologies as rubber ties and hydrologics were introduced in tractors and other farm machinery.&lt;ref&gt;Gifford (1992, p. 8)&lt;/ref&gt; The diesel engines also contributed to the development of the self-propelled, combined harvester and thresher, or [[combine harvester]] (also shortened to 'combine'). Instead of cutting the grain stalks and transporting them to a stationary threshing machine, these combines cut, threshed, and separated the grain while moving continuously through the field.

In the second part of the 20th century the production of agricultural machinery in development countries rose rapidly. In the 1960s a country as the UK exported more than 60% of its production to Western Europe, Australia, USA, Canada and South Africa, and main manufacturers started production plants abroad. Another trend was the increased concentration among manufacturers. In the 1970s in the UK six companies supplied 75% of the total output.&lt;ref&gt;Keith Cowling, David Metcalf, A. J. Rayner. (1973) ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=cKjYBAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA128 Resource Structure of Agriculture: An Economic Analysis],'' p. 127-8&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;See also: World bank (1954) ''[http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1954/06/1554374/western-europe-tractor-agricultural-machinery-industry Western Europe - Tractor and agricultural machinery industry].''&lt;/ref&gt;

The further mechanization of agriculture in the 20th century made possible by the agricultural machinery industry had a huge impact of the economic structure of society. In the developed countries the total labour force engaged in agriculture dropped from about 75% in 1800 to less than 5% late 20th century.&lt;ref name="G 92 p.9"&gt;Gifford (1992, p. 9)&lt;/ref&gt; In developing countries, in late 20th century still 75% of all land "was farmed with only hand-tools and draught-animal technology."&lt;ref&gt;Gifford (1992, p. 10)&lt;/ref&gt; In Turkey still 48% and in India 66.5% of the labor were working in agriculture, according to the [[Food and Agriculture Organization|FAO]] Production Yearbook 1990.&lt;ref name="G 92 p.9"/&gt;

=== 21st century ===
A 2013 report by the [[VDMA]] gave the following preview of the current developments in the agricultural machinery industry:
:"''The general trends in society, agriculture and technology allow conclusions about the future requirements profile for agricultural machinery... The depicted dominating topics for the agricultural sector are
:* ''Precision &amp; automation''
:* ''Efficiency &amp; user friendliness''
:* ''Communication &amp; networking''
:''These topics are today already central components of the specifications for new developments...''"&lt;ref&gt;[[VDMA]].  ''[http://www.vdma.org/documents/105903/842491/VDMA%20Market%20Perspectives%202014.pdf/9a9a7bef-4bb5-4d11-891e-934998177005 Agricultural Machinery November 2013 : Market Perspectives 2014]{{dead link|date=October 2016 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }},'' 2013-14. p. 5&lt;/ref&gt;

== Agricultural machinery ==
{{Main|Agricultural machinery|List of agricultural machinery}}
The agricultural machinery industry produces [[agricultural machinery]], machinery used in the operation of agricultural areas and farms. Main types are:&lt;ref name="AA 2012"&gt;Ade Asefeso (2012). ''CEO Guide to Doing Business in Australia,'' p. 54&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Tractor]]s and power.
* Machinery for  [[tillage]] or soil cultivation.
* Machinery for [[planting]], [[sowing|seeding]], [[fertilizing]], [[pest control]], [[irrigation]].
* Machinery for [[harvesting]], [[haymaking]], and post-harvest, such as produce sorters, and machinery for loading
* Machinery for milking
* Other agricultural machinery, for example grinder mixers, wool presses and [[windmill]]s.&lt;ref name="AA 2012"/&gt;
In developed countries overall the largest segment of agricultural equipment sales is tractors.&lt;ref name="AA 2012"/&gt;

== Agricultural machinery manufacturers ==
Agricultural machinery manufacturers exist in sizes from small and medium business to multinationals. James &amp; Akrasanee (1988) stipulated that those forms have different production management, and can be classified into three groups:
:* ''The first group consists of those workshops with limited and simple equipment. Despite their flexibility, the production management system is very rare in this case.''
:* ''The second group includes those with certain degrees of division of labour within the plant. They do organize some plant layout, but not in a fully systematic manner.''
:* ''The last group constitutes those with clear production lines and division of labour.''&lt;ref&gt;Kenneth James, Narongchai Akrasanee. ''Small and Medium Business Improvement in the ASEAN Region: Production Management.'' Institute of Southeast Asian Studies, 1 dec. 1988&lt;/ref&gt;

The two largest agricultural machinery manufacturers worldwide based on revenue (in 2012):&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.statista.com/statistics/257347/leading-machinery-manufacturers-worldwide/ The leading machinery manufacturers worldwide in 2012, based on revenue]. Accessed 25.11.2014.&lt;/ref&gt; 
* [[John Deere]] : $37.79 billion revenues and employing 67,000 people worldwide in 2013. Its workforce has increased significantly in the past decennia from 43.000 in 2002 to 67.000 in 2013.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.statista.com/statistics/278010/john-deere-number-of-employees-since-2002/ Number of employees of John Deere (Deere &amp; Company) from 2002 to 2013]. Accessed 25.11.2014.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[CNH Global]] : $19.4 billion revenues and employing 33.800 people worldwide in 2013.

In the United States the revenue of tractor &amp; agricultural machinery manufacturing sector increased from about 35 billion U.S. dollars in 2009 to 42 billion U.S. dollars in 2014.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.statista.com/statistics/291882/revenue-of-tractor-and-agricultural-machinery-manufacturing-in-the-us/ Revenue of tractor &amp; agricultural machinery manufacturing (NAICS 33311) in the United States from 2009 to 2014 (in billion U.S. dollars)]. Accessed 25.11.2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Agricultural machinery associations ==
Some of the more important agricultural machinery associations are:

* Agricultural Engineers Association (AEA): British trade association which represents manufacturers and importers of agricultural machinery and outdoor equipment.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aea.uk.com/about-the-aea About the AEA. Accessed 27.11.2014.]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Agrievolution: global network of agricultural machinery associations. &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.agrievolution.com/ Agrevolution website] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150810063122/http://www.agrievolution.com/ |date=August 10, 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Association of Equipment Manufacturers (AEM): American association which represents manufacturers of agricultural machinery. &lt;ref&gt;[https://www.aem.org/ AEM website]&lt;/ref&gt; 
* CEMA: European association representing the agricultural machinery industry in Europe. &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cema-agri.org/ CEMA website]&lt;/ref&gt;
* VDMA Agricultural Machinery Association: German manufacturers' association which represents manufacturers of agricultural machinery. &lt;ref&gt;[http://lt.vdma.org/en/home VDMA website]&lt;/ref&gt;
* ANSEMAT Association of agricultural machinery manufacturers in Spain. &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ansemat.org/ ANSEMAT website]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Global agricultural machinery industry ==
According to the [[CEMA (European agricultural machinery)|CEMA]], the European association representing the European agricultural machinery industry, Europe was the largest producer of agricultural machinery globally in 2013:&lt;ref name="CEMA 2014"&gt;[[CEMA (European agricultural machinery)|CEMA]]. ''[http://cema-agri.org/publication/2013-another-strong-year-european-agricultural-machinery-industry 2013 another strong year for the European agricultural machinery industry].'' February 2014. Accessed 26.11.2014&lt;/ref&gt; 
* Europe produced 31% of the global production
* North America produced 26.5% of the global production, 
* China produced 26.5% of the global production, and
* The remaining 16% is produced elsewhere. 
In total, the production of agricultural machinery worldwide in 2013 generated about 95 billion euros,&lt;ref name="CEMA 2014"/&gt; based on a report ''Agricultural Machinery November 2013 : Market Perspectives 2014''&lt;ref&gt;VDMA. ''[http://www.vdma.org/documents/105903/842491/VDMA%20Market%20Perspectives%202014.pdf/9a9a7bef-4bb5-4d11-891e-934998177005 Agricultural Machinery November 2013 : Market Perspectives 2014]{{dead link|date=October 2016 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }},'' 2013-14. p. 25&lt;/ref&gt; by the [[VDMA]], a German engineering association. Another recent statistic mentioned, that the agricultural machinery industry in 2010 generated worldwide about $56 billion.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.reportlinker.com/ci02002/Agricultural-Machinery.html Agricultural Machinery Industry Market Research &amp; Statistics]. Accessed 25.11.2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Agricultural machinery industry in Asia ===
Yuan'en (2007) stated, that the "Chinese government has attached great importance to agriculture, rural areas and farmers, made a series of policies that favorite to the farmers, added the financial subsidy to the agriculture, especially constituted the subsidy policies for the farmers on their agricultural machinery purchasing."&lt;ref&gt;Yuan’en, Gao, and Machinery Manufacturers. "Agricultural Machinery Industry in China." ''Chinese Association of Manufacturers of Agricultural Machinery'' (2007).&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2013-2014 report acknowledged that "China's agricultural machinery industry has achieved rapid development, the gross output value of agricultural machinery exceeded RMB 300 billion, total power of agricultural machinery surpassed 1 billion kilowatts, and the integrated mechanization level of agricultural crops exceeded 50%, demonstrating that China has entered into a mechanized production-oriented period.... Tractors and harvesting machinery are the most important agricultural machinery products in China, with annual output of 2.25 million units and 1.114 million units in 2012 separately...'' &lt;ref&gt;Global and Chinese Agricultural Machinery Industry Report, 2013-2014,'' December 2013. Summary ( [http://www.researchandmarkets.com/research/sqdz96/global_and online). Accessed 25.11.2014.]&lt;/ref&gt;

Gyanendra (2006) recalled, that "the early agricultural mechanization in [[India]] was greatly influenced by the technological development in England. Irrigation pumps, tillage equipment, chaff cutters, tractors and threshers were gradually introduced for farm mechanization. The high yielding varieties with assured irrigation and higher rate of application of fertilizers gave higher returns that enabled farmers to adopt mechanization inputs, especially after Green revolution in 1960s."&lt;ref&gt;Singh, Gyanendra. "[http://agricoop.nic.in/Farm%20Mech.%20PDF/05024-09.pdf Agricultural Machinery Industry in India (Manufacturing, marketing and mechanization promotion)] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130318191654/http://agricoop.nic.in/Farm%20Mech.%20PDF/05024-09.pdf |date=March 18, 2013 }}." ''Status of Farm Mechanization in India'' (2006).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;See also: Singh, Sukhpal. "[http://www.iimahd.ernet.in/users/webrequest/files/cmareports/3AgriculturalMachineryIndustry.pdf Agricultural Machinery Industry in India: A Study of Growth, Market Structure, and Business Strategies] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150924033614/http://www.iimahd.ernet.in/users/webrequest/files/cmareports/3AgriculturalMachineryIndustry.pdf |date=2015-09-24 }}." (2009).&lt;/ref&gt;

The Turkish Ministry of Economy (2011) explained that "Turkey is one of the few countries of the world which is self-sufficient in food. At present Turkey is the largest producer and exporter of agricultural products in the Near East and North Africa... The agricultural machinery industry is {{sic|comprised |hide=y|of}} about 1000 manufacturers countrywide.... Companies manufacturing agricultural machinery and equipment except tractors are mostly small and medium size companies. The sector employs about 15,000 workers... The value of agricultural machinery and spare parts and agricultural tractors and trailers exports was US$ 313 million in 2009."&lt;ref&gt;Turkish Ministry of Economy (2011), "[http://blog.tcp.gov.tr/index.php/2011/06/agricultural-machinery-industry-in-turkey-2/ Agricultural Machinery Industry in Turkey] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141205083750/http://blog.tcp.gov.tr/index.php/2011/06/agricultural-machinery-industry-in-turkey-2/ |date=December 5, 2014 }}" at ''blog.tcp.gov.tr,'' 01.06.2011. Accessed 28.11.2014&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!--
=== Agricultural machinery industry in Africa ===
=== Agricultural machinery industry in Australia ===
--&gt;

=== Agricultural machinery industry in Europe ===
With a volume of 28 billion euros (2014) agricultural machinery production in the European Union (EU) represented 28 per cent of world total according to VDMA. Out of the EU total, the share of Germany is 27 per cent, followed by Italy (17 per cent) and France (14 per cent). All leading international manufacturers have several production sites on the European continent, and their products from these factories in general are destined for the high end customers who yield for efficiency and accuracy on the fields. 

The EU production of tractors was 187,000 units, correspondent to a value of 9.4 billion euros (2014). Outside the EU, a major production site for tractors is the Minsk Tractor Works (Belarus) with a high market share in the neighbouring countries, especially within the Commonwealth of Independent States. The leading countries for tractor production in the EU are Germany and Italy (with John Deere, Case New Holland, AGCO and Same Deutz-Fahr being the major brands). Germany is also the major place for the manufacturing of harvesting, spraying, fertilizing and seeding equipment. Italy and France have a primary position for soil working machines and transportation vehicles. The majority of the agricultural machinery companies are small and medium-sized and family owned. 

One third of the EU production is destined to markets outside the union, mainly to the Eastern European markets, but also to North America and, increasingly, to Asia.  

After a peak in 2003 and 29 billion euros of turnover, the sector experienced an economic downturn in 2014/2015. The strategy of the European industry is to keep its leading technological position and to diversify its market presence into the high potential regions (e.g. Asia).                 

=== Agricultural machinery industry in North America ===
The AEM (2014) stated that "U.S. domestic sales of agricultural machinery and equipment rose from about $20 billion in 1999 to $38 billion in 2012. Since 1998 and through 2012, U.S. exports of agricultural equipment have grown relatively quickly, more than doubling from about $4 billion to $8.7 billion.&lt;ref&gt;AEM (2014) ''[http://www.aem.org/MarketInfo/MarketIntel/WhitePapers/EconomicFootprint-AgriculturalEquipmentIndustry/Files/AEM_Economic_Whitepaper.pdf The Economic Footprint of the Agricultural Equipment Industry] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141205044016/http://www.aem.org/MarketInfo/MarketIntel/WhitePapers/EconomicFootprint-AgriculturalEquipmentIndustry/Files/AEM_Economic_Whitepaper.pdf |date=December 5, 2014 }}.'' Whitepaper.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Agricultural machinery industry in South America ===
Graciela summarized (2008) that "the agricultural machinery industry in [[Argentina]] depends for growth on higher exports and further progress towards internationalization, which are strategic goals for the largest firms. Given the dynamism of global demand for this type of machinery, the conclusion is that the sector can increase its sales in export markets, where some of its products are competing well."&lt;ref&gt;García, Graciela. "[http://www.cepal.org/cgi-bin/getProd.asp?xml=/revista/noticias/articuloCEPAL/3/35763/P35763.xml&amp;xsl=/revista/tpl-i/p39f.xsl&amp;base=/revista/tpl-i/top-bottom.xsl The agricultural machinery industry in Argentina: from restructuring to internationalization?]." CEPAL Review 96 (2008).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;See also: Barletta, F. (2012), "[http://www.ungs.edu.ar/piec/wp-content/uploads/2012/10/The-agricultural-machinery-industry-in-Argentine.pdf The agricultural machinery industry in Argentina: innovative behavior and export performance."]&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[:Category:Agricultural machinery manufacturers]]
* [[Agribusiness]]
* [[Agriculture]]
* [[Agricultural engineering]]
* [[Mechanised agriculture]]

== References ==
{{reflist|2}}

== External links ==
* {{commonscat-inline|Agricultural machine manufacturers}}

[[Category:Agricultural machinery manufacturers| ]]
[[Category:Industries]]</text>
      <sha1>r3crn183ctr1ghwxzgyz1bufx88ybrj</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Arms industry</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>608296</id>
    <revision>
      <id>865472337</id>
      <parentid>865471937</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-10-24T05:02:07Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>93.86.220.156</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>PMC's do not belong to this article. It is arms industry article.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="28657">[[File:MunitionsWorkersToronto.jpg|thumb|right|Workers assemble Browning-Inglis Hi-Power pistols at the John Inglis munitions plant, Canada, April 1944]]
{{war}}

The '''arms industry''', also known as the '''defense industry''' or the '''arms trade''', is a global [[industry classification|industry]] responsible for the [[manufacturing]] and sales of [[weapon]]s and [[military technology]]. It consists of a [[commerce|commercial]] [[industry]] involved in the [[research and development]], [[engineering]], production, and servicing of [[military]] material, equipment, and facilities. Arms-producing companies, also referred to as  '''arms dealers''', '''defence contractors''', or as the '''military industry''', produce arms for the [[armed forces]] of [[State (polity)|states]] and civilians. Departments of government also operate in the arms industry, buying and selling weapons, munitions and other military items. An [[arsenal]] is a place where arms and ammunition are made, maintained and repaired, stored, or issued, in any combination, whether privately or publicly owned. Products include [[gun]]s, [[artillery]], [[ammunition]], [[missile]]s, [[military aircraft]], [[military vehicle]]s, [[Naval ship|ship]]s, [[electronics|electronic systems]], [[night vision devices]], [[holographic weapon sight]]s, [[laser rangefinder]]s, [[laser sight]]s, [[hand grenades]], [[landmines]] and more. The arms industry also provides other logistical and operational support.

[[Stockholm International Peace Research Institute]] (SIPRI) estimated that 2012 military expenditures were roughly $1.8 trillion.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sipri.org/yearbook/2013/03 SIPRI Yearbook 2013]. www.sipri.org. Retrieved on 2016-04-29.&lt;/ref&gt; This represents a relative decline from 1990 when military expenditures made up 4% of world GDP. Part of the money goes to the procurement of military hardware and services from the military industry. The combined arms sales of the top 100 largest arms-producing companies amounted to an estimated $395 billion in 2012 according to SIPRI.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sipriyearbook.org/view/9780198712596/sipri-9780198712596-chapter-5-div1-6.xml# Stockholm International Peace Research Institute]. Sipri.org. Retrieved on 2012-05-09.&lt;/ref&gt; In 2004 over $30 billion were spent in the international arms trade (a figure that excludes domestic sales of arms).&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/business/4238644.stm Arms trade key statistics]. BBC News (2005-09-15). Retrieved on 2012-05-09.&lt;/ref&gt; According to SIPRI, the volume of international transfers of major weapons in 2010–14 was 16 per cent higher than in 2005–2009. The five biggest exporters in 2010–2014 were the United States, Russia, China, Germany and France, and the five biggest importers were India, Saudi Arabia, China, the United Arab Emirates and Pakistan.&lt;ref name="auto"&gt;{{cite web|title= Trends in International Arms Transfer, 2014|url= https://books.sipri.org/product_info?c_product_id=495|website= www.sipri.org|publisher=Stockholm International Peace Research Institute|accessdate= 18 March 2015|ref= SIPRI Fact Sheet, March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many [[industrialized countries]] have a domestic arms-industry to supply their own military forces. Some countries also have a substantial legal or illegal domestic trade in weapons for use by its citizens, primarily for self-defence, hunting or sporting purposes. [[Small arms trade|Illegal trade in small arms]] occurs in many countries and regions affected by [[political instability]]. The [[Small Arms Survey]] estimates that 875 million small arms circulate worldwide, produced by more than 1,000 companies from nearly 100 countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.smallarmssurvey.org/weapons-and-markets.html|title= Small Arms Survey&amp;nbsp;— Weapons and Markets- 875m small arms worldwide, value of authorized trade is more than $8.5b|date= 8 December 2014|publisher= |accessdate= 26 March 2015}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

Contracts to supply a given country's military are awarded by governments, making arms contracts of substantial political importance. The link between politics and the arms trade can result in the development of what [[President of the United States|U.S. President]] [[Dwight D. Eisenhower]] described as a [[military-industrial complex]], where the armed forces, commerce, and politics become closely linked, similarly to the [[European multilateral defence procurement]]. Various corporations, some publicly held, others private, bid for these contracts, which are often worth many billions of dollars. Sometimes, as with the contract for the international [[Joint Strike Fighter program|Joint Strike Fighter]], a competitive tendering process takes place, with the decision made on the merits of the designs submitted by the companies involved. Other times, no bidding or competition takes place.

[[File:Mercedes Benz Unimog Turkey exhibition side.JPG|thumb|right|[[Unimog]] truck at the [[International Defence Industry Fair]] (IDEF) in 2007]]

==History==
{{further information|Military production during World War II}}
[[File:Ministry of Information First World War Official Collection Q30035.jpg|thumb|upright=1.35|Painting shells in a shell filling factory during [[World War I]].]]

During the [[early modern period]], France, United Kingdom, Netherlands and some states in Germany became self-sufficient in arms production, with diffusion and migration of skilled workers to more peripheral countries such as Portugal and Russia.

The modern arms industry emerged in the second half of the nineteenth century as a product of the creation and expansion of the first large [[military-industrial complex|military-industrial]] companies. As smaller countries (and even newly industrializing countries like Russia and Japan) could no longer produce cutting-edge military equipment with their indigenous resources and capacity, they increasingly began to contract the manufacture of military equipment, such as [[battleship]]s, [[artillery|artillery pieces]] and [[rifle]]s to foreign firms.

In 1854, the [[British government]] awarded a contract to the [[Elswick Ordnance Company]] of industrialist [[William Armstrong, 1st Baron Armstrong|William Armstrong]] for the supply of his latest breech loading rifled artillery pieces. This galvanised the private sector into weapons production, with the surplus being increasingly exported to foreign countries. Armstrong became one of the first international arms dealers, selling his weapon systems to governments across the world from Brazil to Japan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.williamarmstrong.info/about-the-man|title=William George Armstrong (1810–1900)}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1884, he opened a shipyard at [[Elswick Ordnance Company|Elswick]] to specialise in warship production—at the time, it was the only factory in the world that could build a battleship and arm it completely.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Dougan, David |year=1970 |title=The Great Gun-Maker: The Story of Lord Armstrong|publisher=Sandhill Press Ltd. |isbn=0-946098-23-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; The factory produced warships for many navies, including the [[Imperial Japanese Navy]]. Several Armstrong cruisers played an important role in defeating the Russian fleet at the [[Battle of Tsushima]] in 1905.

In the American Civil War in 1861 the north had a distinct advantage over the south as it relied on using the breech-loading rifle against the muskets of the south. This began the transition to industrially produced mechanised weapons such as the Gatling gun.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title = Defense Industries - Military History - Oxford Bibliographies - obo|url = http://www.oxfordbibliographies.com/view/document/obo-9780199791279/obo-9780199791279-0036.xml|website = www.oxfordbibliographies.com|accessdate = 2015-11-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

This industrial innovation in the defence industry was adopted by [[Prussia]] in 1866 &amp; 1870-71 in its defeat of Austria and France respectively. By this time the machine gun had begun entering into the militaries. The first example of its effectiveness was in 1899 during the [[Boer war|Boer War]] and in 1905 during the [[Russo-Japanese War]]. However, Germany were leaders in innovation of weapons and used this innovation nearly defeating the allies in [[World War I]].

In 1885, France decided to capitalize on this increasingly lucrative form of trade and repealed its ban on weapon exports. The regulatory framework for the period up to the [[First World War]] was characterized by a [[laissez-faire]] policy that placed little obstruction in the way of weapons exports. Due to the carnage of World War I, arms traders began to be regarded with odium as "merchants of death" and were accused of having instigated and perpetuated the war in order to maximise their profits from arms sales. An inquiry into these allegations in Britain failed to find evidence to support them. However, the sea change in attitude about war more generally meant that governments began to control and regulate the trade themselves.
[[File:Ministry of Information First World War Official Collection Q30049.jpg|thumb|Stacks of shells in the shell filling factory at Chilwell during World War I.]]
The volume of the arms trade greatly increased during the 20th century, and it began to be used as a political tool, especially during the [[Cold War]] where the United States and the USSR supplied weapons to their proxies across the world, particularly [[Third World|third world countries]] (see [[Nixon Doctrine]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=uvGRBE1QxBUC&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s|title=The International Arms Trade|author1=Stohl, Rachel |author2=Grillot, Suzette |year=2013|publisher=Wiley Press|accessdate=2013-02-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Sectors==
[[File:AK47.jpg|thumb|right|upright=1.35|The [[AK-47|AK]] series of weapons have been produced in greater numbers than any other [[firearm]] and have been used in conflicts all over the world.]]

===Land-based weapon===
This category includes everything from [[SALW|light arms]] to [[heavy artillery]], and the majority of producers are small. Many are located in third world countries. International trade in [[handgun]]s, [[machine gun]]s, [[tanks]], [[armored personnel carrier]]s, and other relatively inexpensive weapons is substantial. There is relatively little regulation at the international level, and as a result, many weapons fall into the hands of organized crime, rebel forces, terrorists, or regimes under sanctions.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fpa.org/newsletter_info2584/newsletter_info.htm |title=International Defense Industry |accessdate=2007-05-20 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110726062433/http://www.fpa.org/newsletter_info2584/newsletter_info.htm |archivedate=2011-07-26 |df= }}. www.fpa.org&lt;/ref&gt;

====Small arms====
{{main article|Small arms trade}}
The [[Control Arms Campaign]], founded by [[Amnesty International]], [[Oxfam]], and the [[IANSA (NGO)|International Action Network on Small Arms]], estimated in 2003 that there are over 639 million small arms in circulation, and that over 1,135 companies based in more than 98 different countries manufacture small arms as well as their various components and ammunition.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
 |url=http://controlarms.org/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2011/02/Shattered-lives-the-case-for-tough-international-arms-control.pdf 
 |title=Shattered Lives – the case for tough international arms control 
 |author1=Debbie Hillier 
 |author2=Brian Wood 
 |publisher=Control Arms Campaign 
 |accessdate=2009-03-28 
 |year=2003 
 |format=PDF 
 |page=19 
 |deadurl=yes 
 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110723081459/http://controlarms.org/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2011/02/Shattered-lives-the-case-for-tough-international-arms-control.pdf 
 |archivedate=2011-07-23 
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

===Aerospace systems===
[[File:MDD T-45 assembly line c1988.jpeg|thumb|A [[T-45 Goshawk]] on the assembly line at [[McDonnell Douglas]].]]
{{Main article|Aerospace manufacturer}}
Encompassing military aircraft (both land-based and [[naval aviation]]), conventional missiles, and [[military satellites]], this is the most technologically advanced sector of the market. It is also the least competitive from an economic standpoint, with a handful of companies dominating the entire market. The top clients and major producers are virtually all located in the [[western world]] and Russia, with the United States easily in first place. Prominent aerospace firms include [[Rolls Royce plc|Rolls Royce]], [[BAE]], [[Dassault Aviation]], [[Sukhoi]], [[Mikoyan]], [[EADS]], [[Leonardo S.p.A.|Leonardo]], [[Thales Group]], [[Lockheed Martin]],  [[Northrop Grumman]] and [[Boeing]]. There are also several [[multinational corporation|multinational]] consortia mostly involved in the manufacturing of [[fighter jet]]s, such as the [[Eurofighter]]. The largest military contract in history, signed in October 2001, involved the development of the [[Joint Strike Fighter]].&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt;

===Naval systems===
Some of the world's [[great power]]s maintain substantial [[naval force]]s to provide a global presence, with the largest nations possessing [[aircraft carrier]]s, [[nuclear submarine]]s and advanced [[Anti-aircraft warfare|anti-air defense systems]]. The vast majority of military ships are conventionally powered, but some are [[nuclear marine propulsion|nuclear-powered]]. There is also a large global market in second-hand naval vessels, generally purchased by [[developing countries]] from [[Western world|Western]] governments.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt;

== Cybersecurity industry ==
{{main article|Computer security}}
The cybersecurity industry is becoming the most important defence industry as cyber attacks are being deemed as one of the greatest risk to defence in the next ten years as cited by the NATO review in 2013.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.nato.int/docu/review/2013/Industry/EN/index.htm|title = NATO review|date = |accessdate = |website = |publisher = }}&lt;/ref&gt; Therefore, high levels of investment has been placed in the cybersecurity industry to produce new software to protect the ever-growing transition to digitally run hardware. For the military industry it is vital that protections are used for systems used for reconnaissance, surveillance and intelligence gathering. However, to protect the cyber world from attacks there are advanced cyber protection strategies used such as content, cloud and wireless security. These can be intertwined to form several secure layers.

Nevertheless, cyber attacks and cyber attackers have become more advanced in their field using techniques such as Dynamic Trojan Horse Network (DTHN) Internet Worm, [[Zero-Day Attack]], and Stealth Bot. As a result, the cybersecurity industry has had to improve the defence technologies to remove any vulnerability to cyber attacks using systems such as the Security of Information (SIM), Next-Generation Firewalls (NGFWs) and [[DDoS]] techniques.

As the threat to computers grows, the demand for cyber protection will rise, resulting in the growth of the cybersecurity industry. It is expected that the industry will be dominated by the defence and homeland security agencies that will make up 40% of the industry.&lt;ref name="auto1"&gt;{{cite web|title = Cyber security for the defence industry {{!}} Cyber Security Review|url = http://www.cybersecurity-review.com/industry-perspective/cyber-security-for-the-defence-industry|website = www.cybersecurity-review.com|accessdate = 2015-11-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==International arms transfers==
According to research institute, [[SIPRI]], the volume of international transfers of major weapons in 2010–14 was 16 per cent higher than in 2005–2009. The five biggest exporters in 2010–14 were the United States, the United Kingdom, Russia, China and France, and the five biggest importers were India, Saudi Arabia, China, the United Arab Emirates (UAE) and Pakistan. The flow of arms to Africa, the Americas, Asia and Oceania, and the Middle East increased significantly between 2005–2009 and 2010–14, while there was a notable decrease in the flow to Europe.&lt;ref name="auto"/&gt;

SIPRI has identified 60 countries as exporters of major weapons in 2010–14. The top 5 exporters during the period were responsible for almost 74 per cent of all arms exports. The composition of the five largest exporters of arms changed between 2005–2009 and 2010–14: while the United States and Russia remained by far the largest exporters, China narrowly, but notably, replaced Germany as the third largest exporter as Germany slid down to 6th place. The top 5 exported 14 per cent more arms in 2010–14 than the top 5 in 2005–2009.&lt;ref name="auto"/&gt;

In 2010–14, 153 countries (about three-quarters of all countries) imported major weapons. The top 5 recipients accounted for 33 per cent of the total arms imports during the period (see table 2). India, China and the UAE were among the top 5 importers in both 2005–2009 and 2010–14. Asia and Oceania accounted for nearly half of imports in 2010–14, followed by the Middle East, Europe, the Americas and Africa (see figure 3). SIPRI also identified seven groups of rebel forces as importers of major weapons in 2010–14, but none of them accounted for more than 0.02 per cent of total deliveries.&lt;ref name="auto"/&gt;

==World's largest arms exporters== &lt;!--linked from [[Template:Lists of countries]]--&gt;
Units are in Trend Indicator Values expressed as millions of [[US dollar|U.S. dollar]]s at 1990s prices. These numbers may not represent real financial flows as prices for the underlying arms can be as low as zero in the case of military aid. The following are estimates from  [[SIPRI|Stockholm International Peace Research Institute]].&lt;ref name="SIPRI armstrade"&gt;[http://armstrade.sipri.org/armstrade/page/toplist.php Top List TIV Tables-SIPRI]. Armstrade.sipri.org. Retrieved on 2012-05-09.&lt;/ref&gt;
{| class="wikitable sortable"
|-
!2012–2016&lt;br/&gt;Rank
!Supplier

!data-sort-type="number"|Arms Exp
|-
|1	||{{USA}}|| 47,169
|-
|2	||{{RUS}}|| 33,186
|-
|3	||{{CHN}}|| 9,132
|-
|4	||{{FRA}}|| 8,564
|-
|5	||{{DEU}}|| 7,946
|-
|6	||{{UK}}|| 6,586
|-
|7	||{{ESP}}|| 3,958
|-
|8	||{{ITA}}|| 3,823
|-
|9	||{{UKR}}|| 3,677
|-
|10	||{{ISR}}|| 3,233
|}

[[File:Sgraffite marchand d' Armes.jpg|thumb|upright=1.35|[[Sgraffito]] at the Lambert Sevart weapons factory, in [[Liège|Liege]] (Belgium) (early 20th Century).]]

Please note that rankings for exporters below a billion dollars are less meaningful, as they can be swayed by single contracts. A much more accurate picture of export volume, free from yearly fluctuations, is presented by 5-year moving averages.

Next to SIPRI there are several other sources that provide data on international transfers of arms. These include national reports by national governments about arms exports, the UN register on conventional arms and an annual publication by the [[US Congressional Research Service|U.S. Congressional Research Service]] that includes data on arms exports to developing countries as compiled by [[US intelligence|U.S. intelligence]] agencies. A list of such sources can be found at the SIPRI website.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sipri.org/contents/armstrad/ armstrad — www.sipri.org] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20050520090124/http://www.sipri.org/contents/armstrad/ |date=May 20, 2005 }}. Sipri.org. Retrieved on 2012-05-09.&lt;/ref&gt; Due to the different methodologies and definitions used different sources often provide significantly different data. 

=== World’s biggest postwar arms exporter===
SIPRI uses the "trend-indicator values" (TIV). These are based on the known unit production costs of weapons and represent the transfer of military resources rather than the financial value of the transfer.&lt;ref&gt;[http://delano.lu/d/detail/news/worlds-biggest-postwar-arms-exporters/172983]&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class="wikitable sortable"
|-
!1950–2017&lt;br/&gt;Rank
!Supplier

!data-sort-type="number"|Arms Exp&lt;br&gt;(in billion TIV)
|-
|1	||{{USA}}|| 673,010
|-
|2	||{{RUS}}|| 588,150
|-
|3	||{{UK}}|| 140,380
|-
|4	||{{FRA}}|| 120,700
|-
|5	||{{DEU}}|| 85,980
|-
|6	||{{CHN}}|| 53,090
|-
|7	||{{ITA}}|| 32,270
|-
|8	||{{CZE}}|| 31,250
|-
|9	||{{NED}}|| 24,010
|-
|10	||{{ISR}}|| 16,790
|}

==World's largest arms importers == &lt;!--linked from [[Template:Lists of countries]]--&gt;
Units are in Trend Indicator Values expressed as millions of [[US dollar|U.S. dollar]]s at 1990s prices. These numbers may not represent real financial flows as prices for the underlying arms can be as low as zero in the case of military aid.&lt;ref name="SIPRI armstrade"/&gt;  
{| class="wikitable sortable"
|-
!2012–2016&lt;br/&gt;rank
!Recipient
!data-sort-type="number"|Arms imp
|-
|1||{{IND}}||18,239 
|-
|2||{{KSA}}||11,689
|-
|3||{{UAE}}||6,593
|-
|4||{{CHN}}||6,381
|-
|5||{{AUS}}||5,636
|-
|5||{{ALG}}||5,312
|-
|7||{{TUR}}||4,721
|-
|8||{{IRQ}}||4,598
|-
|9||{{PAK}}||4,494
|-
|10||{{VNM}}||4,273
|}

Please note that arms import rankings fluctuate heavily as countries enter and exit wars. Export data tend to be less volatile as exporters tend to be more technologically advanced and have stable production flows. 5-year moving averages present a much more accurate picture of import volume, free from yearly fluctuations.

==List of major weapon manufacturers==
{{main article|List of modern armament manufacturers|List of defense contractors}}


[[File:Biggest arms sales 2013.png|upright=1.35|thumb|right|Share of arms sales by country. Source is provided by [[SIPRI]].&lt;ref name="sipri.org"&gt;http://www.sipri.org/research/armaments/production/recent-trends-in-arms-industry&lt;/ref&gt;]]
{{further information|Companies by arms sales}}

This is a list of the world's largest arms manufacturers and other military service companies who profit the most from the [[War economy]], their origin is shown as well. The information is based on a list published by the [[Stockholm International Peace Research Institute]] for 2015.&lt;ref name="sipri.org"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sipri.org/research/armaments/production/recent-trends-in-arms-industry/Fact%20Sheet%20Top100%202013.pdf |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2014-12-16 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20141226134428/http://www.sipri.org/research/armaments/production/recent-trends-in-arms-industry/Fact%20Sheet%20Top100%202013.pdf |archivedate=2014-12-26 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://en.europeonline-magazine.eu/western-firms-dominate-global-arms-sales_368142.html|title=EUROPE ONLINE|work=europeonline-magazine.eu|accessdate=30 November 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.defensenews.com/article/20141215/DEFREG/312150016/SIPRI-Releases-Top-100-Defense-Company-Data|title=SIPRI Releases Top 100 Defense Company Data|work=Defense News|accessdate=26 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.sipri.org/sites/default/files/The-SIPRI-Top-100-2015.pdf|title=The SIPRI Top 100 Arms-Producing and Military Services Companies, 2015 |last=|first=|date=|website= |access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The list provided by the SIPRI excludes companies based in China.

{| class="wikitable sortable"
|-
!Rank!!Company!!Country!!Arms sales (US$ m.)!!Total sales (US$ m.)!!Arms sales as a % of total sales!!Total profit (US$ m.)!!Total employment
|-
|1||[[Lockheed Martin]]||{{USA}}||36,440||46,132||79||3,605||126,000
|-
|2||[[Boeing]]||{{USA}}||27,960||96,114||29||5,176||161,400
|-
|3||[[BAE Systems]]||{{UK}}||25,510||27,355||93||1,456||82,500
|-
|4||[[Raytheon]]||{{USA}}||21,780||23,247||94||2,067||61,000
|-
|5||[[Northrop Grumman]]||{{USA}}||20,060||19,683||86||1,990||65,000
|-
|6||[[General Dynamics]]||{{USA}}||19,240||31,469||61||2,965||99,900
|-
|7||[[Airbus]]||{{EU}}||12,860||71,476||18||2,992||136,570
|-
|8||[[United Technologies Corporation]]||{{USA}}||9,500||61,047||16||4,356||197,200
|-
|9||[[Leonardo S.p.A.]]||{{ITA}}||9,300||14,412||65||584||47,160
|-
|10||[[L3 Technologies]]||{{USA}}||8,770||10,466||84||282||38,000
|}

==Arms control==
{{main article|Arms control}}
Arms control refers to international restrictions upon the development, production, stockpiling, proliferation and usage of small arms, conventional weapons, and [[Weapon of mass destruction|weapons of mass destruction]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=What Is Arms Control? |url=http://usforeignpolicy.about.com/od/defense/a/what-is-arms-control.htm |work=About.com, US Foreign Policy |publisher=The New York Times Company |accessdate=13 May 2012 |author=Barry Kolodkin |format=Article}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is typically exercised through the use of [[diplomacy]], which seeks to persuade [[government]]s to accept such limitations through agreements and [[Treaty|treaties]], although it may also be forced upon non-consenting governments.

===Notable international arms control treaties===
[[File:Global weapons sales 1950-2006.jpg|thumb|Global weapons sales from 1950-2006]]
*[[Geneva Protocol]] on chemical and biological weapons, 1925
*[[Outer Space Treaty]], signed and entered into force 1967
*[[Biological Weapons Convention]], signed 1972, entered into force 1975
*[[Missile Technology Control Regime]] (MTCR), 1987
*[[Chemical Weapons Convention]], signed 1993, entered into force 1997
*[[Ottawa Treaty]] on anti-personnel land mines, signed 1997, entered into force 1999
*[[START treaty (2010)|New START Treaty]], signed by Russia and the United States in April 2010, entered into force in February 2011
*[[Arms Trade Treaty]], concluded in 2013, entered into force on 24 December 2014.&lt;ref&gt;Delgado, Andrea. Explainer: What is the Arms Trade Treaty, 23, Feb, 2015, https://theconversation.com/explainer-what-is-the-arms-trade-treaty-37673&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{columns-list|colwidth=22em|
*[[Arms race]]
*[[Arms control]]
*[[Arms deal (disambiguation)]]
*[[Arms embargo]]
*[[Arms trafficking]]
*[[Cyber-arms industry]]
*[[Disarmament]]
*[[Guns versus butter model]]
*[[History of military technology]]
*[[List of chemical arms control agreements]]
*[[List of United States defense contractors]]
*[[List of most-produced firearms]]
*[[Military Keynesianism]]
*[[Naval conference (disambiguation)]]
*[[Nuclear disarmament]]
*[[Offset agreement]]
*[[Peace and conflict studies]]
*[[Peace dividend]]
*[[Permanent war economy]]
*[[Private military company]]
*[[Small Arms and Light Weapons]] (SALW)
*[[Small arms trade]]
*[[Torture trade]]
*[[United Nations Office for Disarmament Affairs]]
}}

==References==
{{Reflist|35em}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Military industries and wartime industrial production}}
* [http://www.amnestyusa.org/our-work/issues/military-police-and-arms/arms-trade Amnesty International: Arms Trade]
* [http://www.bl.uk/collections/business/pdf/defence_industry_guide.pdf The British Library – Defence Industry Guide (sources of information)]
* [https://fas.org/asmp/index.html FAS's Arms Sales Monitoring Project]
* [https://www.theguardian.com/armstrade/0,10674,519643,00.html The Guardian's arms trade report]
* [http://rts.gn.apc.org/disarm/trad.html List of participators of the Defense System and Equipment international conference in London, 2003]
* [http://www.sipri.org/research/armaments/production SIPRI arms industry reports and database]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20110524090136/http://www.sipri.org/research/armaments/production/Top100 SIPRI list of Top 100 arms-producing companies]
* [http://www.spadeindex.com SPADE Defense Index (NYSE: DXS)] Defense sector market index
* [http://www.landmarkcash.com/articles/global-arms-trade.html The True Cost of Global Arms Trade &amp;#91;infographic included&amp;#93;]
* [http://un.org/disarmament UN Office for Disarmament Affairs]
* [http://repository.library.georgetown.edu/handle/10822/552545 U.S. Arms Sales to the Third World] from the Dean Peter Krogh Foreign Affairs Digital Archives
* [http://lebanese-economy-forum.com/wdi-gdf-advanced-data-display/?curve=MS-MIL-XPRT-KD World Map and Chart of Arms exports per country] by Lebanese-economy-forum, World Bank data
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20070504104156/http://www.worldsecurityinstitute.org/showarticle.cfm?id=195 World Security Institute's Center for Defense Information]
* [http://www.hartpub.co.uk/books/details.asp?isbn=9781841137469/ Z. Yihdego, Arms Trade and International Law, Hart: OXford, 2007]

{{Industries}}
{{Weapons}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Arms Industry}}
[[Category:Arms control]]
[[Category:Arms trafficking]]
[[Category:Industries]]
[[Category:Military comparisons lists of countries]]
[[Category:Military industry| ]]
[[Category:Military–industrial complex]]
[[Category:Weapons]]
[[Category:Weapons manufacturing companies]]
[[Category:Weapons trade]]</text>
      <sha1>qi505kpabseqdm2hgb74sdusanw8em3</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Audiovisual</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>11604823</id>
    <revision>
      <id>850368121</id>
      <parentid>849909974</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-07-15T12:58:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Kvng</username>
        <id>910180</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Reverted [[WP:AGF|good faith]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/152.81.8.161|152.81.8.161]] ([[User talk:152.81.8.161|talk]]): Inclusion in [[Audio-to-video synchronization]] is appropriate, this, not so much. ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="4352">[[File:Audiovisual.jpg|thumb|High quality audiovisual components reproduce the experience of a live concert]]
'''Audiovisual''' ('''AV''') means possessing  both a [[sound]] and a [[visual]] component, such as [[slide-tape]] presentations,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Barman|first=Charles R.|title=Slide-Tape Presentations on a Classroom Budget|jstor=4447864|publisher=University of California Press}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[film]]s, [[television program]]s, church services and live theater productions.

Audiovisual service providers frequently offer web streaming, video conferencing and live broadcast services.&lt;ref&gt;Clegg 2014, Audiovisual Services&lt;/ref&gt;

Computer-based audiovisual equipment is often used in education, with many schools and universities installing projection equipment and using interactive whiteboard technology.

Another audiovisual expression is the visual presentation of sound ([[visual music]]).

==Residential audiovisual==
Generally, residential audiovisual encompasses in-ceiling speakers, flat panel TVs, projectors and projector screens. This could include lighting, blinds, cinema rooms.&lt;ref&gt;Quin 2014, Universal Home Theatre&lt;/ref&gt;

==Commercial audiovisual==
The '''professional audiovisual industry''' is a multibillion-dollar industry, comprising the manufacturers, dealers, systems integrators, consultants, programmers, presentations professionals and technology managers of audiovisual products and services.

Commercial audiovisual can sometimes be a very lengthy process to get it right. Boardroom audio visual can be installed for a number of reasons, but usually it is because the executives of the organization/business wants to have meetings with colleagues/customers/suppliers around the world. When creating an array of boardrooms for customers it has been seen that you have to be able to balance the pattern from the audio and microphone so there is no interruption in the sound quality for the individual/s listening in.&lt;ref&gt;Quin 2014, Universal Home Theatre&lt;/ref&gt;

The proliferation of audiovisual [[communication technology|communications technologies]], including sound, video, lighting, display and projection systems, is evident in every sector of society: in business, education, government, the military, healthcare, retail environments, worship, sports and entertainment, hospitality, restaurants, and museums. The application of audiovisual systems is found in collaborative conferencing (which includes video-conferencing, audio-conferencing, web-conferencing and data-conferencing); presentation rooms, auditoriums, and lecture halls; command and control centers; [[digital signage]], and more. Concerts and corporate events are among the most obvious venues where audiovisual equipment is used in a staged environment. Providers of this type of service are known as rental and staging companies, although they may also be served by an in-house technology team (e.g., in a hotel or conference center).

According to a 2006 market forecast study by [[InfoComm International]], a leading trade association representing the audiovisual industry, 2006 was the fourth consecutive year that significant growth was projected for the industry.{{citation needed|date=September 2009}} Revenue for surveyed North American companies was expected to grow by 40% in 2006, and by 10.7% for European audiovisual companies. The single biggest factor for this increase is the increased demand for networked audiovisual products due to the integration of audiovisual and IT technology. The two leading markets for AV equipment in [[North America]] and [[Europe]] continue to be business/IT and education, especially as conference room technologies become more advanced.

==Audiovisual education==
{{main article|Audiovisual education}}
Audiovisual education is instruction where particular attention is paid to the audio and visual presentation of the material, with the goal of improving comprehension and retention.

==See also==
*[[Information and communications technology]]
*[[Multimedia]]
*[[Video]]
*[[World Day for Audiovisual Heritage]]

==References==
{{Library resources box
|by=no
|onlinebooks=no
|others=no
|about=yes
|label=Audiovisual}}

{{Reflist}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Audiovisual}}
[[Category:Multimedia]]
[[Category:Television terminology]]
[[Category:Industries]]
[[Category:Economics of the arts and literature]]</text>
      <sha1>i2owcllvw6djwdvb8aw8asaeh9oem58</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Business</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>39206</id>
    <revision>
      <id>870111276</id>
      <parentid>870111205</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-11-22T13:15:31Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Arjayay</username>
        <id>5718152</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 870111205 by [[Special:Contributions/45.64.9.122|45.64.9.122]] ([[User talk:45.64.9.122|talk]]) Spam</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="37418">{{Other uses|Business (disambiguation)}}
{{Redirect|Firm}}
{{pp-pc1|small=yes}}
{{more citations needed|date=August 2017}}{{Companies law}}{{Business administration}}
{{Capitalism}}

'''Business''' is the activity of making one's living or making [[money]] by producing or buying and selling [[Product (business)|products]] (such as [[goods and services]]).&lt;ref&gt;Compare: [https://www.ahdictionary.com/word/search.html?q=business American Heritage Dictionary] "business [:] 1. The activity of buying and selling [[commodity | commodities]], products, or services".&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Longman Business English Dictionary&lt;/ref&gt;{{qn|date=October 2018}}&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.ldoceonline.com/dictionary/business Longman Dictionary of Contemporary English] "business [:] 1 [...] the activity of making money by producing or buying and selling goods, or providing services".&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://en.oxforddictionaries.com/definition/us/business Oxford Living Dictionaries] "business [:] 2 The practice of making one's living by engaging in [[commerce]]."&lt;/ref&gt; Simply put, it is "any activity or enterprise entered into for profit. It does not mean it is a company, a corporation, partnership, or have any such formal organization, but it can range from a street peddler to General Motors."&lt;ref&gt;''Burton's Legal Thesaurus'', 4E. S.v. "business." Retrieved April 1, 2018 from https://legal-dictionary.thefreedictionary.com/business&lt;/ref&gt; 

Having a [[business name]] does not separate the business entity from the owner, which means that the owner of the business is responsible and liable for debts incurred by the business.  If the business acquires debts, the creditors can go after the owner's personal possessions.  A business structure does not allow for corporate tax rates. The proprietor is personally taxed on all income from the business.

The term is also often used colloquially (but not by lawyers or by public officials) to refer to a [[company]]. A company, on the other hand, is a separate legal entity and provides for [[limited liability]], as well as [[corporate tax]] rates.  A company structure is more complicated and expensive to set up, but offers more protection and benefits for the owner.

== Forms ==
{{Main|List of business entities}}

Forms of business ownership vary by [[jurisdiction]], but several common entities exist:

* '''Sole proprietorship:''' A [[sole proprietorship]], also known as a sole trader, is owned by one person and operates for their benefit. The owner operates the business alone and may hire [[employees]]. A sole proprietor has unlimited [[legal liability|liability]] for all obligations incurred by the business, whether from [[operating cost]]s or [[judgment]]s against the business. All [[asset]]s of the business belong to a sole proprietor, including, for example, computer infrastructure, any [[inventory]], [[manufacturing]] equipment, or [[retail]] [[Fixture (property law)|fixtures]], as well as any [[real property]] owned by the sole proprietor.
* '''Partnership:'''  A [[partnership]] is a business owned by two or more people. In most forms of partnerships, each partner has unlimited liability for the debts incurred by the business. The three most prevalent types of for-profit partnerships are: [[general partnership]]s, [[limited partnership]]s, and [[limited liability partnership]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite Journal|doi=10.5465/amj.2013.0581 |title=Friends and Profits Don't Mix: The Performance Implications of Repeated Partnerships |journal=Academy of Management Journal |volume=59 |issue=2 |page=460 |year=2014 |last1=Holloway |first1=S. S. |last2=Parmigiani |first2=A. }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''Corporation:'''  The owners of a [[corporation]] have [[limited liability]] and the business has a separate [[legal personality]] from its owners.  Corporations can be either [[State-owned enterprise|government-owned]] or privately owned. They can organize either for profit or as [[nonprofit organization]]s. A privately owned, for-profit corporation is owned by its [[shareholder]]s, who elect a [[board of directors]] to direct the corporation and hire its managerial staff.  A privately owned, for-profit corporation can be either [[privately held company|privately held]] by a small group of individuals, or [[public company|publicly held]], with publicly traded [[Share (finance)|shares]] listed on a [[stock exchange]].
* '''Cooperative:''' Often referred to as a "co-op", a [[cooperative]] is a limited-liability business that can organize as for-profit or not-for-profit. A cooperative differs from a corporation in that it has members, not shareholders, and they share decision-making authority. Cooperatives are typically classified as either [[Consumers' co-operative|consumer cooperatives]] or [[worker cooperative]]s. Cooperatives are fundamental to the ideology of [[economic democracy]].
* [[Limited liability company|Limited liability companies (LLC)]], limited liability partnerships, and other specific types of business organization protect their owners or shareholders from [[business failure]] by doing business under a separate legal entity with certain legal protections. In contrast, unincorporated businesses or persons working on their own are usually not as protected.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.sba.gov/starting-business/choose-your-business-structure US Small Business Administration]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://smallbusinesschamberofcommerce.blogspot.com/ Small Business Chamber of Commerce, Inc.]&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''Franchises:''' A [[franchising|franchise]] is a system in which entrepreneurs purchase the rights to open and run a business from a larger corporation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://smallbusiness.chron.com/definition-franchise-business-4467.html Definition of a Franchise Business]&lt;/ref&gt;  Franchising in the United States is widespread and is a major economic powerhouse.  One out of twelve retail businesses in the United States are franchised and 8 million people are employed in a franchised business.&lt;ref&gt;h{{Cite journal|doi=10.1080/1046669X.2011.533109|title=A Comparison of Retail Franchises, Independent Businesses, and Purchased Existing Independent Business Startups: Lessons from the Kauffman Firm Survey|journal=Journal of Marketing Channels|volume=18|page=3|year=2011|last1=Welsh|first1=Dianne H. B.|last2=Desplaces|first2=David E.|last3=Davis|first3=fAmy E.}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''A [[Private company limited by guarantee|company limited by guarantee]]:'''  Commonly used where companies are formed for noncommercial purposes, such as clubs or charities.  The members guarantee the payment of certain (usually nominal) amounts if the company goes into [[Liquidation|insolvent liquidation]], but otherwise, they have no economic rights in relation to the company. This type of company is common in [[England]]. A company limited by guarantee may be with or without having [[share capital]].
* '''A [[Private company limited by shares|company limited by shares]]:'''  The most common form of the company used for business ventures. Specifically, a limited company is a "company in which the liability of each shareholder is limited to the amount individually invested" with corporations being "the most common example of a limited company."&lt;ref name="Black's"&gt;Black's Law and lee Dictionary. Second Pocket Edition. Bryan A. Garner, editor. West. 2001.&lt;/ref&gt; This type of company is common in [[England]] and many English-speaking countries. A company limited by shares may be a
** [[Public company|publicly traded company]] or a
** [[privately held company]]
* '''A company limited by guarantee with a share capital:'''  A hybrid entity, usually used where the company is formed for noncommercial purposes, but the activities of the company are partly funded by investors who expect a return.  This type of company may no longer be formed in the UK, although provisions still exist in law for them to exist.&lt;ref&gt;Companies Act 2006&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''A [[limited liability company]]:''' "A company—statutorily authorized in certain states—that is characterized by limited liability, management by members or managers, and limitations on ownership transfer", i.e., L.L.C.&lt;ref name="Black's" /&gt; LLC structure has been called "hybrid" in that it "combines the characteristics of a corporation and of a partnership or sole proprietorship". Like a corporation, it has limited liability for members of the company, and like a partnership it has "flow-through taxation to the members" and must be "dissolved upon the death or bankruptcy of a member".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.investopedia.com/terms/l/llc.asp#ixzz2CEzgE239|title=Limited Liability Company (LLC) Definition - Investopedia|author=root|work=Investopedia}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''An [[unlimited company]] with or without a share capital:''' A hybrid entity, a company where the liability of members or shareholders for the debts (if any) of the company are not limited. In this case doctrine of a veil of incorporation does not apply.
''Less common types of companies are:''
* '''Companies formed by letters patent:'''  Most corporations by letters patent are ''[[Corporation sole|corporations sole]]'' and not companies as the term is commonly understood today.
* '''[[Royal charter|Charter corporations]]:'''  Before the passing of modern companies legislation, these were the only types of companies.  Now they are relatively rare, except for very old companies that still survive (of which there are still many, particularly many British banks), or modern societies that fulfill a quasi-regulatory function (for example, the [[Bank of England]] is a corporation formed by a modern charter).
* '''Statutory companies:'''  Relatively rare today, certain companies have been formed by a private statute passed in the relevant jurisdiction.
Note that "Ltd after the company's name signifies limited company, and PLC ([[public limited company]]) indicates that its shares are widely held."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.investopedia.com/terms/p/plc.asp|title=Investopedia - Public Limited Company|last=|first=|date=|website=|archive-url=|archive-date=|dead-url=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In legal parlance, the owners of a company are normally referred to as the "members". In a company limited or unlimited by shares (formed or incorporated with a share capital), this will be the [[shareholder]]s. In a company limited by guarantee, this will be the guarantors. Some [[Offshore financial center|offshore jurisdictions]] have created special forms of [[offshore company]] in a bid to attract business for their jurisdictions. Examples include "[[Segregated portfolio company|segregated portfolio companies]]" and restricted purpose companies.

There are, however, many, many sub-categories of types of company that can be formed in various jurisdictions in the world.

Companies are also sometimes distinguished for legal and regulatory purposes between '''[[Public limited company|public companies]]''' and '''[[Privately held company|private companies]]'''. Public companies are companies whose shares can be publicly traded, often (although not always) on a [[stock exchange]] which imposes [[Listing (finance)|listing requirements]]/[[Listing Rules]] as to the issued shares, the trading of shares and future issue of shares to help bolster the reputation of the exchange or particular market of an exchange. Private companies do not have publicly traded shares, and often contain restrictions on transfers of shares. In some jurisdictions, private companies have maximum numbers of shareholders.

A [[parent company]] is a company that owns enough voting stock in another firm to control management and operations by influencing or electing its board of directors; the second company being deemed as a subsidiary of the parent company. The definition of a parent company differs by jurisdiction, with the definition normally being defined by way of laws dealing with companies in that jurisdiction.

== Classifications ==
{{Main|Industry classification}}

* [[Agriculture]], such as the domestication of fish, animals and livestock, as well as [[lumber industry|lumber]], [[oil industry|oil]] and [[mining industry|mining]] businesses that extract natural resources and raw materials, such as [[wood]], [[petroleum]], [[natural gas]], [[ore]]s, plants or [[mineral]]s.
* [[Finance|Financial]] [[Financial services|services]] businesses include [[bank]]s, [[brokerage firm]]s, [[credit union]]s, [[credit card company|credit cards]], [[insurance company|insurance companies]], [[asset management company|asset]] and [[investment company|investment companies]] such as [[private equity firm]]s, [[private equity fund]]s, [[real estate investment trust]]s, [[sovereign wealth fund]]s, [[pension fund]]s, [[mutual fund]]s, [[index fund]]s, and [[hedge fund]]s, [[stock exchange]]s, and other companies that generate profits through investment and management of [[Capital (economics)|capital]].
* [[Entertainment industry|Entertainment]] companies and [[mass media]] agencies generate profits primarily from the sale of [[intellectual property]]. They include [[film studio]]s and [[production house]]s, mass media companies such as [[cable television network]]s, online [[digital media]] agencies, [[talent agency|talent agencies]], [[mobile media]] outlets, [[newspaper publisher|newspapers]], [[book publishing|book]] and [[magazine|magazine publishing]] houses.
* Industrial [[manufacturing|manufacturers]] produce [[product (business)|products]], either from [[raw material]]s or from component parts, then export the finished products at a [[profit (accounting)|profit]]. They include [[tangible]] [[good (economics)|goods]] such as [[Automotive industry|cars]], [[bus manufacturing|buses]], [[Medical device manufacturing|medical devices]], [[Glass manufacturing|glass]], or [[aircraft manufacturing|aircraft]].
* [[Real estate]] businesses sell, invest, construct and develop [[real property|properties]], including [[land]], residential [[home]]s, and other buildings.
* [[Retail]]ers, [[Wholesaling|wholesalers]], and [[distribution (business)|distributors]] act as middlemen and get goods produced by manufacturers to the intended consumers; they make their profits by marking up their prices. Most stores and catalog companies are distributors or retailers.
* [[Transport]]ation businesses such as [[Railway company|railways]], [[airline]]s, [[Shipping industry|shipping companies]] that deliver goods and individuals to their destinations for a fee.
* [[Utilities]] produce [[public service]]s such as [[water]], [[electricity]], [[waste management]] or [[sewage treatment]]. These industries are usually operated under the charge of a public [[State-owned enterprise|government]].
* [[Tertiary sector of the economy|Service businesses]] offer intangible goods or services and typically charge for labor or other services provided to [[government]], to [[consumer]]s, or to other businesses. Interior decorators, beauticians, hairstylists, make-up artists, tanning salons, laundromats, dry cleaners, and pest controllers are service businesses.

== Activities ==
=== Accounting ===
{{Main|Accounting}}
Accounting is the measurement, processing and communication of financial information about [[economic entity|economic entities]]&lt;ref name = "NP 2013"&gt;{{cite book |last1=Needles |first1=Belverd E. |last2=Powers |first2=Marian |year=2013 |title=Principles of Financial Accounting |publisher=Cengage Learning |edition=12 |series=Financial Accounting Series}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite report |date=November 1940 |title=Accounting Research Bulletins No. 7 Reports of Committee on Terminology |url=http://clio.lib.olemiss.edu/cdm/ref/collection/deloitte/id/9342 |publisher=Committee on Accounting Procedure, American Institute of Accountants |accessdate=31 December 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; such as businesses and [[corporation]]s. The modern field was established by the [[Italians|Italian]] mathematician [[Luca Pacioli]] in 1494.&lt;ref name=jkdiwan&gt;{{cite book|last=DIWAN|first=Jaswith|title=ACCOUNTING CONCEPTS &amp; THEORIES|publisher=MORRE|location=LONDON|id=id# 94452|pages=001–002}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Accounting, which has been called the "language of business",&lt;ref name="wharton-language"&gt;{{Citation | url =http://kwhs.wharton.upenn.edu/2013/09/peggy-bishop-lane-on-why-accounting-is-the-language-of-business/ | title =Peggy Bishop Lane on Why Accounting Is the Language of Business | publisher =Knowledge @ Wharton High School | date =September 23, 2013 | accessdate =25 December 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt; measures the results of an organization's economic activities and conveys this information to a variety of users, including [[investor]]s, [[creditor]]s, [[management]], and [[Regulatory agency|regulators]].&lt;ref name = "UW Dept"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.foster.washington.edu/academic/departments/accounting/Pages/accounting.aspx |title=Department of Accounting |year=2013 |website=Foster School of Business |publisher=Foster School of Business |accessdate=31 December 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Practitioners of accounting are known as [[accountant]]s. The terms "accounting" and "financial reporting" are often used as synonyms.

=== Finance ===
{{Main|Finance}}
Finance is a field that deals with the study of [[investments]]. It includes the dynamics of [[asset]]s and [[Liability (financial accounting)|liabilities]] over time under conditions of different degrees of uncertainty and risk. Finance can also be defined as the science of money management. Finance aims to price assets based on their risk level and their expected [[rate of return]]. Finance can be broken into three different sub-categories: [[public finance]], [[corporate finance]] and [[personal finance]].

=== Manufacturing ===
{{Main|Manufacturing}}
[[Manufacturing]] is the production of [[merchandise]] for use or sale using labour and [[machine]]s, [[tool]]s, chemical and biological processing, or formulation. The term may refer to a range of human activity, from [[handicraft]] to [[High tech manufacturing|high tech]], but is most commonly applied to [[Industry|industrial]] production, in which [[raw material]]s are transformed into [[finished good]]s on a large scale.

=== Marketing ===
{{Main|Marketing}}
Marketing is defined by the [[American Marketing Association]] as ''"the activity, set of institutions, and processes for creating, communicating, delivering, and exchanging offerings that have value for customers, clients, partners, and society at large."''&lt;ref&gt;Marketing definition approved in October 2007 by the [[American Marketing Association]]: [http://www.marketingpower.com/AboutAMA/Pages/DefinitionofMarketing.aspx].&lt;/ref&gt; The term developed from the original meaning which referred literally to going to a market to buy or sell goods or services.  Marketing tactics include [[advertising]] as well as determining product [[pricing]].

With the rise in technology, marketing is further divided into a class called [[digital marketing]]. It is marketing products and services using digital technologies.

=== Research and development ===
{{Main|Research and development}}
Research and development refer to activities in connection with corporate or government innovation. Research and development constitute the first stage of development of a potential new service or product. Research and development are very difficult to manage since the defining feature of the research is that the researchers do not know in advance exactly how to accomplish the desired result. {{citation needed|date=July 2017}}

=== Safety ===
{{Main|Safety}}
Safety is a key business concept that is defined by [[Merriam-Webster]] as “the condition of being safe from undergoing or causing hurt, injury, or loss”.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/safety Definition of "safety"], [[Merriam-Webster]], updated February 2018.&lt;/ref&gt; Injuries cost businesses billions of dollars annually.&lt;ref&gt;Leigh, J. (2011). Economic Burden of Occupational Injury and Illness in the United States. Milbank Quarterly, 89(4), 728-772. DOI: 10.1111/j.1468-0009.2011.00648.x&lt;/ref&gt;  Studies have shown how company acceptance and implementation of comprehensive safety and health management systems reduces incidents, insurance costs and workers’ compensation claims.&lt;ref&gt;Rowe, Kelly P. (2007). OSHA and small businesses: A winning combination: When small businesses tap into OSHA's many resources, everyone benefits. Occupational Hazards, 69(3), 33.&lt;/ref&gt;  New technologies, like wearable safety devices&lt;ref&gt;Goldberg, S. (2016). Business Technical: Wearable Devices at Work. Business Insurance, 50(2), 1.&lt;/ref&gt; and available online safety training, continue to be developed to encourage employers to invest in protection beyond the "[[:wikt:canary in a coal mine|canary in the coalmine]]" and reduce the cost to businesses of protecting their employees.

=== Sales ===
{{Main|Sales}}
Sales are activity related to selling or the amount of goods or services sold in a given time period. Sales are often integrated with all lines of business and are key to a companies' success.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=How To Organize Your Marketing Department In The Digital Age |url=https://www.cmo.com/features/articles/2015/2/12/organizing-for-digital-cwtk.html#gs.ZPr_RZ8 |accessdate=October 15, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Management ==
{{Main|Management}}
{{See also|Outline of business management}}
The efficient and effective [[Business operations|operation of a business]], and study of this subject, is called [[management]]. The major branches of management are [[finance|financial management]], [[marketing]] management, [[organizational studies|human resource management]], [[strategic management]], [[manufacturing|production management]], [[operations management]], [[service management]], and [[information technology management]]. {{Citation needed|date=September 2011}}

Owners may manage their businesses themselves, or employ managers to do so for them. Whether they are owners or employees, managers administer three primary components of the business' value: financial resources, capital (tangible resources), and human resources.  These resources are administered in at least six functional areas: legal contracting, manufacturing or service production, marketing, accounting, financing, and human resources.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

=== Restructuring state enterprises ===
In recent decades, states modeled some of their [[asset]]s and enterprises after business enterprises. In 2003, for example, the [[People's Republic of China]] modeled 80% of its [[state-owned enterprise]]s on a company-type management system.&lt;ref&gt;[http://english.people.com.cn/data/China_in_brief/Economy/Major%20Industries.html Major Industries]. People.com&lt;/ref&gt; Many state institutions and enterprises in China and Russia have transformed into joint-stock companies, with part of their shares being listed on public stock markets.

Business process management (BPM) is a holistic management approach focused on aligning all aspects of an organization with the wants and needs of clients. BPM attempts to improve processes continuously. It can, therefore, be described as a "process optimization process". It is argued that BPM enables organizations to be more efficient, effective and capable of change than a functionally focused, traditional hierarchical management approach.{{who|date=October 2013}} &lt;!-- also what does this have to do with state enterprises? --&gt;

== Organization and regulation ==
{{See also|Theory of the firm}}
Most legal [[jurisdiction]]s specify the forms of ownership that a business can take, creating a body of [[commercial law]] for each type.

The major factors affecting how a business is organized are usually:

* '''The size and scope of the business firm''' and its structure, management, and ownership, broadly analyzed in the [[theory of the firm]]. Generally, a smaller business is more flexible, while larger businesses, or those with wider ownership or more formal structures, will usually tend to be organized as corporations or (less often) partnerships. In addition, a business that wishes to raise money on a [[stock market]] or to be owned by a wide range of people will often be required to adopt a specific legal form to do so.
* '''The sector and country.''' Private profit-making businesses are different from government-owned bodies. In some countries, certain businesses are legally obliged to be organized in certain ways.
* '''[[Tax advantage]]s.''' Different structures are treated differently in tax law and may have advantages for this reason.
* '''Disclosure and compliance requirements'''. Different business structures may be required to make less or more information public (or report it to relevant authorities) and may be bound to comply with different rules and regulations.

Many businesses are operated through a separate entity such as a corporation or a partnership (either formed with or without limited liability). Most legal jurisdictions allow people to organize such an entity by filing certain charter documents with the relevant Secretary of State or equivalent and complying with certain other ongoing obligations. The relationships and legal rights of [[shareholder]]s, limited partners, or members are governed partly by the charter documents and partly by the law of the jurisdiction where the entity is organized. Generally speaking, shareholders in a corporation, limited partners in a limited partnership, and members in a limited liability company are shielded from [[Legal liability|personal liability]] for the debts and obligations of the entity, which is legally treated as a separate "person". This means that unless there is misconduct, the owner's own possessions are strongly protected in law if the business does not succeed.

Where two or more individuals own a business together but have failed to organize a more specialized form of vehicle, they will be treated as a general partnership. The terms of a partnership are partly governed by a partnership agreement if one is created, and partly by the law of the jurisdiction where the partnership is located. No paperwork or filing is necessary to create a partnership, and without an agreement, the relationships and legal rights of the partners will be entirely governed by the law of the jurisdiction where the partnership is located. A single person who owns and runs a business is commonly known as a ''sole proprietor'', whether that person owns it directly or through a formally organized entity. Depending on the business needs, an adviser can decide what kind is proprietorship will be most suitable.

A few relevant factors to consider in deciding how to operate a business include:

# General partners in a partnership (other than a limited liability partnership), plus anyone who personally owns and operates a business without creating a separate legal entity, are personally liable for the debts and obligations of the business.
# Generally, corporations are required to pay tax just like "real" people. In some tax systems, this can give rise to so-called [[double taxation]], because first the corporation pays tax on the profit, and then when the corporation distributes its profits to its owners, individuals have to include dividends in their income when they complete their personal tax returns, at which point a second layer of income tax is imposed.
# In most countries, there are laws which treat small corporations differently from large ones. They may be exempt from certain legal filing requirements or labor laws, have simplified procedures in specialized areas, and have simplified, advantageous, or slightly different tax treatment.
# "Going public" through a process known as an [[initial public offering]] (IPO) means that part of the business will be owned by members of the public. This requires the organization as a distinct entity, to disclose information to the public, and adhering to a tighter set of laws and procedures. Most public entities are corporations that have sold shares, but increasingly there are also public [[Limited liability company|LLC's]] that sell units (sometimes also called shares), and other more exotic entities as well, such as, for example, [[real estate investment trust]]s in the USA, and [[unit trust]]s in the UK. A general partnership cannot "go public".

=== Commercial law ===
{{Main|Corporate law}}
[[File:Downtownplazala.jpg|thumb|right|upright=0.9|[[Office]]s in the [[Los Angeles]] Downtown Financial District]]
A very detailed and well-established body of rules that evolved over a very long period of time applies to commercial transactions. The need to regulate trade and commerce and resolve business disputes helped shape the creation of law and courts. The [[Code of Hammurabi]] dates back to about 1772 BC for example, and contains provisions that relate, among other matters, to [[Freight transport|shipping]] costs and dealings between merchants and [[broker]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mcadams.posc.mu.edu/txt/ah/assyria/hammurabi.html|title=Law Code of Hammurabi}}&lt;/ref&gt; The word "corporation" derives from the Latin ''corpus'', meaning body, and the [[Maurya Empire]] in Iron-Age India accorded legal rights to business entities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.law.yale.edu/documents/pdf/cbl/Khanna_Ancient_India_informal.pdf |title=The Economic History of the Corporate Form in Ancient India |author=Vikramaditya S. Khanna |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131019095432/http://www.law.yale.edu/documents/pdf/cbl/Khanna_Ancient_India_informal.pdf |archivedate=2013-10-19 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In many countries, it is difficult to compile all the laws that can affect a business into a single reference source. Laws can govern treatment of labour and employee relations, [[Health and Safety Executive|worker protection and safety]], discrimination on the basis of age, gender, disability, race, and in some jurisdictions, sexual orientation, and the minimum wage,  as well as [[Trade union|unions]], worker compensation, and working hours and leave.

Some specialized businesses may also require licenses, either due to laws governing entry into certain trades, occupations or professions, that require special education or to raise revenue for local governments. Professions that require special licenses include law, medicine, piloting aircraft, selling liquor, radio broadcasting, selling investment securities, selling used cars, and roofing. Local jurisdictions may also require special licenses and taxes just to operate a business.

Some businesses are subject to ongoing special regulation, for example, [[Public utility|public utilities]], investment securities, banking, insurance, [[broadcasting]], [[aviation]], and health care providers. Environmental regulations are also very complex and can affect many businesses.

=== Capital ===
[[File:Bolsa Mexicana de Valores.png|thumb|left|[[Mexican Stock Exchange]] in [[Paseo de la Reforma]], Mexico City]] When businesses need to raise money (called [[Capital (economics)|capital]]), they sometimes offer [[Security (finance)|securities]] for sale.

Capital may be raised through private means, by an [[initial public offering]] or IPO on a [[stock exchange]], or in other ways.

Major stock exchanges include the [[Shanghai Stock Exchange]], [[Singapore Exchange]], [[Hong Kong Stock Exchange]], [[New York Stock Exchange]] and [[NASDAQ]] (the USA), the [[London Stock Exchange]] (UK), the [[Tokyo Stock Exchange]] (Japan), and [[Bombay Stock Exchange]] (India). Most countries with capital markets have at least one.

Businesses that have gone public are subject to regulations concerning their internal governance, such as how executive officers' compensation is determined, and when and how information is disclosed to shareholders and to the public. In the United States, these regulations are primarily implemented and enforced by the United States Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC). Other western nations have comparable regulatory bodies. The regulations are implemented and enforced by the China Securities Regulation Commission (CSRC) in China. In Singapore, the regulatory authority is the Monetary Authority of Singapore (MAS), and in Hong Kong, it is the Securities and Futures Commission (SFC).

The proliferation and increasing complexity of the laws governing business have forced increasing specialization in corporate law. It is not unheard of for certain kinds of corporate transactions to require a team of five to ten attorneys due to sprawling regulation. Commercial law spans general corporate law, employment and labor law, health-care law, securities law, mergers and acquisitions, tax law, employee benefit plans, food and drug regulation, intellectual property law on copyrights, patents, trademarks, telecommunications law, and financing.

Other types of capital sourcing include crowdsourcing on the Internet, venture capital, bank loans, and debentures.

=== Intellectual property ===
{{Main|Intellectual property}}
Businesses often have important "[[intellectual property]]" that needs protection from competitors for the company to stay profitable. This could require [[patent]]s, [[copyright]]s, [[trademark]]s, or preservation of [[trade secret]]s. Most businesses have names, logos, and similar branding techniques that could benefit from trademarking. Patents and copyrights in the United States are largely governed by federal law, while trade secrets and trademarking are mostly a matter of state law. Because of the nature of intellectual property, a business needs protection in every jurisdiction in which they are concerned about competitors. Many countries are signatories to international [[treaty|treaties]] concerning intellectual property, and thus companies registered in these countries are subject to national laws bound by these treaties. In order to protect trade secrets, companies may require employees to sign noncompete clauses which will impose limitations on an employee's interactions with stakeholders, and competitors.

=== Trade union ===
{{Main|Trade union}}
A trade union (or labor union) is an [[Political organisation#Labour unions|organization of workers]] who have come together to achieve common goals such as protecting the integrity of its trade, improving safety standards, achieving higher pay and benefits such as health care and retirement, increasing the number of employees an employer assigns to complete the work, and better [[working conditions]]. The trade union, through its leadership, bargains with the employer on behalf of union members ([[wikt: rank and file|rank and file]] members) and negotiates [[Labour and employment law|labor contracts]] ([[collective bargaining]]) with employers. The most common purpose of these associations or unions is "maintaining or improving the conditions of their [[employment]]".&lt;ref name="Webb"&gt;{{cite book |last=Webb |first=Sidney |last2=Webb|first2= Beatrice |title=History of Trade Unionism |publisher=Longmans and Co. London |year=1920}} ch. I&lt;/ref&gt; This may include the negotiation of [[wage]]s, work rules, complaint procedures, rules governing hiring, firing, and promotion of workers, benefits, [[Occupational safety and health|workplace safety]] and policies.

== See also ==
{{Wikipedia books}}
{{Portal|Business and economics}}
{{Main|Outline of business}}
{{columns-list|colwidth=18em|
* [[Accounting]]
** [[Index of accounting articles|List of accounting topics]]
* [[Advertising]]
* [[Bank]]
* [[Big business]]
* [[Business acumen]]
* [[Business broker]]
* [[Business ethics]]
** [[Social responsibility]]
* [[Business hours]]
* [[Outline of commercial law|Business law topics]]
* [[Business mathematics]]
* [[Business mediator]]
* [[Business school]]
* [[Business tourism]]
* [[Business valuation]]
* [[Businessperson]]
* [[Capitalism]]
* [[Change management analyst]]
* [[Commerce]]
* [[Company]]
* [[Corporate personhood]]
* [[Cost overrun]]
* [[E-commerce]]
** [[Electronic business]]
* [[Economics]]
** [[Economic democracy]]
** [[Financial economics]]
** [[Outline of economics|List of economics topics]]
* [[Entrepreneurship]]
* [[Finance]]
** [[Outline of finance|List of finance topics]]
* [[Franchising]]
* [[State ownership|Government ownership]]
* [[Human resources]]
* [[Industry]]
* [[Innovation]]
* [[Insurance]]
* [[Intellectual property]]
* [[Interim management]]
* [[International trade]]
** [[Index of international trade topics|List of international trade topics]]
* [[Investment]]
* [[Job creation program]]
* [[Labour economics]]
* [[Limited liability]]
* [[List of company registers]]
* [[List of largest employers]]
* [[List of oldest companies]]
* [[Lists of companies]]
* [[Management information system]]
* [[Manufacturing]]
** [[Outline of production|List of production topics]]
* [[Marketing]]
** [[Outline of marketing|List of marketing topics]]
* [[Money]]
* [[Organizational studies]]
* [[Profit (accounting)|Profit]]
* [[Real estate]]
** [[Index of real estate articles|List of real estate topics]]
* [[Benefit shortfall|Revenue shortfall]]
* [[Shareholder value]]
* [[Small business]]
* [[Strategic management]]
* [[Strategic planning]]
* [[Tax]]
* [[Trade]]
* [[Types of business entity]]
}}

== References ==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
{{Sister project links|Business}}
{{Library resources box
|by=no
|onlinebooks=no
|others=no
|about=yes
|label=Business}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Business| ]]
[[Category:Entrepreneurship]]</text>
      <sha1>jhbehed8fcq586mgyrhl150mogvgbc6</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Business acumen</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>18166327</id>
    <revision>
      <id>856832972</id>
      <parentid>856829108</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-08-27T20:17:57Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Kuru</username>
        <id>764407</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>rmv content marketing spam</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="11551">{{Multiple issues|
{{weasel|date=December 2016}}
{{notability|date=December 2016}}
}}
'''Business acumen''' ("Business savvy" and "business sense" are often used as synonyms) is keenness and quickness in understanding and dealing with a "business situation" ([[risk management|risks]] and [[Opportunity management|opportunities]]) in a manner that is likely to lead to a good outcome.&lt;ref name=reilly&gt;Reilly, Dr. Raymond R and Reilly, Dr. Gregory P. [http://www.acumenlearning.com/public/images/uploaded/reilly-building_business_acumen-hrwest1209.pdf "Building Business Acumen"], ''HR West'', December 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, business acumen has emerged as a vehicle for improving financial performance and [[leadership development]].&lt;ref name=summerfield&gt;Summerfield, Brian. [http://www.clomedia.com/executive-briefings/2008/April/2175/index.php "A Crisis in Leadership"] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090623215033/http://www.clomedia.com/executive-briefings/2008/April/2175/index.php |date=June 23, 2009 }}, ''Chief Learning Officer Magazine'', April 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Consequently, several different types of strategies have developed around improving business acumen.

== Characteristics ==

=== Executive level thinking ===

In his 2012 work, ''[[Seeing the Big Picture]], Business Acumen to Build Your Credibility, Career, and Company'', [[Kevin R. Cope]] put forward that an individual who possesses business acumen views the business with an "executive mentality" - they understand how the moving parts of a company work together to make it successful and how financial metrics like [[profit margin]], [[cash flow]], and [[stock price]] reflect how well each of those moving parts is doing its job.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Seeing the Big Picture|publisher=Greenleaf Book Group|year=2012|isbn=978-1-60832-246-6|location=USA|page=2|last1=Cope|first1=Kevin}}&lt;!--| accessdate=2012-06-25--&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; Cope proposes that an individual who has the following five abilities could be described as someone having a strong sense of business acumen: 
#See the “big picture” of the organization—how the key drivers of the business relate to each other, work together to produce profitable growth, and relate to the job
#Understand important company communications and data, including [[financial statement]]s
#Use knowledge to make good decisions
#Understand how actions and decisions impact key company measures and leadership objectives 
#Effectively communicate ideas to other employees, managers, executives, [[public relations|and the public]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Seeing the Big Picture|publisher=Greenleaf Book Group|year=2012|isbn=978-1-60832-246-6|location=USA|page=3|last1=Cope|first1=Kevin}}&lt;!--| accessdate=2012-06-25--&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Distinguishing traits ===

Raymond R. Reilly of the [[Ross School of Business]] at the [[University of Michigan]] and Gregory P. Reilly of the University of Connecticut document traits that individuals with business acumen possess: 
* An acute perception of the dimensions of business issues
* Ability to make sense out of complexity and an uncertain future
* Cognizance of the implications of a choice for all the affected parties
* Decisive
* Flexibility for further change if warranted in the future
Thus, developing stronger business acumen means a more thoughtful analysis, clearer logic underlying business decisions, closer attention to key dimensions of implementation and operation, and more disciplined performance management.&lt;ref name="reilly"/&gt;

=== Financial literacy ===

[[Financial literacy]] is a comprehensive understanding of the drivers of growth, profitability, and cash flow; an organization's financial statements; key performance measures; and the implications of decisions on value creation. In a [[SHRM]] article entitled, "Business Acumen Involves More Than Numbers"&lt;ref name=hastings&gt;Hastings, Rebecca R. [http://www.shrmindia.org/business-acumen-involves-more-numbers "Business Acumen Involves More Than Numbers"], ''SHRM'', April 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Chris Berger, member of human resources at CTPartners,&lt;ref&gt;https://nypost.com/2015/06/28/troubled-ctpartners-set-to-file-for-bankruptcy/&lt;/ref&gt; explains that business acumen starts with the ability to understand how a company makes decisions, and that leaders must be financially literate and be able to understand numbers on company financial statements. It entails the ability to take the knowledge of business fundamentals and use it to think strategically and then take appropriate action.

According to [[E. Ted Prince]], "Financial literacy is almost never the need for senior managers and high potentials. Most already possess degrees in business, including [[MBA]]s, and many have also had experience in the business sides of their professional roles. The need for these managers is to understand how their actions and their behavior impact their financial decision-making and how this in turn affects financial outcomes at the unit and the corporate level." It's evident that an individual with business acumen has some level of financial understanding and knowledge - but someone who is financially literate doesn't necessarily possess strong business acumen.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.perthleadership.org/documents/Business_Acumen_WP_Updated.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Business management and leadership ===

Bob Selden, faculty member of Mobilizing People, a [[leadership development]] program based in Switzerland, observes a complementary relationship between business acumen and leadership.&lt;ref&gt;Selden, Bob. [http://www.management-issues.com/2008/2/26/opinion/is-business-acumen-a-substitute-for-leadership.asp "Is Business Acumen a Substitute for Leadership?"] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080719105324/http://www.management-issues.com/2008/2/26/opinion/is-business-acumen-a-substitute-for-leadership.asp |date=July 19, 2008 }}, 26 February 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Selden states the importance of nurturing both the development of strategic skills and that of good leadership and management skills in order for business leaders to achieve effectiveness.

A study published in Human Resource Management International Digest titled, Business acumen: a critical concern of modern leadership development: Global trends accelerate the move away from traditional approaches,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Prince |first1=Ted |year=2008 |title=Business acumen: a critical concern of modern leadership development: Global trends accelerate the move away from traditional approaches |journal=Human Resource Management International Digest |volume=16 |issue=6 |pages=6–9 |publisher= |doi= |url= http://www.emeraldinsight.com/journals.htm?articleid=1741949&amp;show=abstract |accessdate=2011-02-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; reveals why traditional leadership development approaches, which rely on personality and competency assessments as the scientific core of their approach, are failing. The paper demonstrates the importance of business acumen in leadership-development approaches and contends that business acumen will have an increasing impact on leadership development and HR agendas. Research into this relationship resulted in the creation of the [[Perth Leadership Outcome Model]], which links [http://www.perthleadership.org/index.php/business-acumen-training/assessments/financial-outcome-assessment financial outcomes] to individual leadership traits.

In a study that interviewed 55 global business leaders, business acumen was cited as the most critical competency area for global leaders.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Leadership Without Borders|last=Cohen|first=Ed|publisher=John Wiley and Sons|year=2007|isbn=978-0-470-82227-2|location=USA|page=14}}&lt;!--| accessdate=2011-02-18--&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;

In their 2011 work, ''The Leadership Pipeline'', [[Ram Charan (consultant)|Ram Charan]], Stephen Drotter, and James Noel study the process and criteria for selecting a group manager, and suggest that the process and criteria are similar for selecting a CEO. According to them an obvious criterium for selecting a leader is well-developed business acumen.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Leadership Pipeline|last2=Noel|first2=James|last3=Drotter|first3=Stephen|publisher=John Wiley and Sons|year=2011|isbn=978-0-470-89456-9|location=USA|page=139|last1=Charan|first1=Ram}}&lt;!--| accessdate=2011-02-18--&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;

An organization full of high business acumen individuals can expect to see leaders with a heightened perspective that translates into an ability to inspire and excite the organization to achieve its potential.&lt;ref name="reilly"/&gt;

==Development==
Programs designed to improve an individual or group's business acumen have supported the recognition of the concept as a significant topic in the corporate world. Executive Development Associates' 2009/2010 survey of Chief Learning Officers, Senior Vice Presidents of Human Resources, and Heads of Executive and Leadership Development listed business acumen as the second most significant trend in executive development.&lt;ref name=hagemann&gt;Hagemann, Bonnie [http://www.hreonline.com/pdfs/02012010Extra_LeadershipStudy.pdf "2009/2010 Trends in Executive Development"], 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; A 2011 report explores the impact of business acumen training on an organization in terms of intangibles and more tangible expressions of value.&lt;ref name=anderson&gt;Anderson, Dr. Merrill C. [http://www.acumenlearning.com/public/images/uploaded/roi-business-acumen.pdf "MetrixGlobal Study of Business Acumen Training"], March 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; The findings support the notion that business acumen is a learned skill - developed on the job by learning the required skills from knowledge mentors while working in different employment positions. They also suggest that the learning process ranges widely, from structured internal company training programs, to an individual's self-chosen moves from one position to another.&lt;ref name="reilly"/&gt;

The combination of these reports and surveys indicate that business acumen is a learned skill of increasing importance within the corporate world. There are different types of business acumen development programs available:

=== Business simulations ===

A [[business simulation]] is another corporate development tool used to increase business acumen. Several companies offer business simulations as a way to educate mid-level managers and non-financial leaders within their organization on [[cash flow]] and financial-decision-making processes. Their forms can vary from computer simulations to boardgame-style simulations.

=== Psychological assessments ===

The advent of personal assessments for business acumen is based in the emerging theories of [[behavioral finance]] and attempts to correlate innate personality traits with positive financial outcomes.&lt;ref&gt;Perth Leadership Institute White Paper:[http://www.perthleadership.org/Documents/Business_Acumen_WP_Updated.pdf ''Business Acumen and Leadership Development for CEOs and Senior Executives'']&lt;/ref&gt; This method approaches business acumen not as entirely based in either knowledge or experience, but on the combination of these and other factors which comprise an individual's financial personality or "signature". The results from this research have been limited, but noteworthy.&lt;ref&gt;Prince, E. Ted. "Research note: how the financial styles of managers impact financial and valuation metrics." [http://www.emeraldinsight.com/Insight/viewContentItem.do?contentType=Article&amp;contentId=1728141 ''Review of Accounting and Finance''] 7.2 (2008):193-205&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
&lt;references/&gt;

{{DEFAULTSORT:Business Acumen}}
[[Category:Business]]</text>
      <sha1>plqurbl3x8f0zk2r0ktop5ny4bflvyg</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Business directory</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1725756</id>
    <revision>
      <id>858314357</id>
      <parentid>858311303</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-09-06T09:15:53Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Apparition11</username>
        <id>6046731</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/182.75.250.145|182.75.250.145]] ([[User talk:182.75.250.145|talk]]): Spam. using [[WP:TWINKLE|TW]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="1924">{{unreferenced|date=June 2009}}

[[File:PigotDirectory1839Kent.jpg|thumb|An example page from [[Pigot's Directory|Pigot's 1839 directory]] of businesses in the counties of Kent, Surrey and Sussex in England.]]
A '''business directory''' is a website or [[print media|printed]] listing of [[information]] which lists businesses within niche based categories. Businesses can be categorized by niche, location, activity, or size. Business may be compiled either manually or through an automated online search software. Online [[yellow pages]] are a type of business directory, as is the traditional [[phone book]].

The details provided in a business directory may vary. They may include the business name, addresses, telephone numbers, location, contact information, type of service or products the business provides, the number of employees, the served region and any [[professional association]]s. Some directories include a section for user reviews, comments, and feedback. Business directories in the past would take a printed format but have recently been upgraded to websites due to the advent of the internet.{{Citation needed|date=July 2017}}

Many business directories offer complimentary listings in addition to the premium options. There are many business directories and some of these have moved over to the [[internet]] and away from printed format. Whilst not being [[search engine]]s, business directories often have a search function, enabling users to search businesses by [[Zip Code]], country, state, area or city.

== Formats ==
Business directories can be in either [[hard copy]] or in [[Digital formats|digital format]]. Ease of use and distribution means that many trade directories have a digital version.

==See also==
*[[Web directory]]
*[[List of web directories]]
*[[Surplus Record Machinery &amp; Equipment Directory]]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Business Directory}}
[[Category:Business]]
[[Category:Directories]]</text>
      <sha1>0vbtw8trwfswhkilwjjxbs6ka43ho2o</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Business economics</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8613151</id>
    <revision>
      <id>868848928</id>
      <parentid>868065020</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-11-14T21:05:05Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rescuing 1 sources and tagging 0 as dead. #IABot (v2.0beta10)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="8814">{{Economics sidebar}}
'''Business economics''' is a field in [[applied economics]] which uses [[economic theory]] and quantitative methods to analyze [[Business|business enterprises]] and the factors contributing to the diversity of organizational structures and the relationships of firms with labour, [[Capital (economics)|capital]] and product markets.&lt;ref name="Moschandreas"&gt;Moschandreas, Maria (2000). ''Business Economics'', 2nd Edition, Thompson Learning,  [https://books.google.com/books?id=ncVfjhTULyAC&amp;printsec=find&amp;pg=PA410#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Description] and chapter-preview [https://books.google.com/books?id=ncVfjhTULyAC&amp;printsec=find&amp;pg=PR5#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false links].&lt;/ref&gt; A professional focus of the journal ''[[Business Economics (journal)|Business Economics]]'' has been expressed as providing "practical information for people who apply economics in their jobs."&lt;ref&gt;National Association for Business Economics, ''[http://www.nabe.com/busecon.htm ''Business Economics] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20111111082746/http://www.nabe.com/busecon.htm |date=November 11, 2011 }}''®&lt;/ref&gt;
Business economics is an integral part of traditional economics. It is an extension of economic concepts to the real business situations. It is an applied science in the sense of a tool of managerial decision-making and forward planning by management. In other words, Business economics is concerned with the application of economic theory to business management.

==Subject matter==
Business economics is concerned with economic issues and problems related to business organization, management, and strategy. Issues and problems include: an explanation of why ''corporate'' firms emerge and exist; why they expand: horizontally, vertically and spacially; the role of entrepreneurs and entrepreneurship; the significance of organizational structure; the relationship of firms with the employees, the providers of capital, the customers, the government; the interactions between firms and the business environment.&lt;ref name="Moschandreas"/&gt;

==Ambiguity in the use of term==
The term 'business economics' is used in a variety of ways.  Sometimes it is used as synonymously with industrial economics/[[industrial organisation]], [[managerial economics]], and economics for business. Still, there may be substantial differences in the usage of 'economics for business' and 'managerial economics' with the latter used more narrowly.
One view of the distinctions between these would be that business economics is wider in its scope than industrial economics in that it would be concerned not only with "industry" but also businesses in the service sector. Economics for business looks at the major principles of economics but focuses on applying these economic principles to the real world of business.&lt;ref&gt;Sloman, J and Sutcliffe (2004) Economics for Business, Financial Times/ Prentice Hall; 3 edition&lt;/ref&gt; Managerial economics is the application of economic methods in the managerial decision-making process.&lt;ref&gt;• Jones, Trefor, 2004 ''Business Economics and Managerial Decision Making'', Wiley. [http://www.wiley.com/WileyCDA/WileyTitle/productCd-EHEP000988.html Description] and chapter-preview  [https://books.google.com/books?id=qr7TORfhBwQC&amp;printsec=find&amp;pg=PR7#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false links].&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; • Wilkinson, Nick (2005). ''Managerial Economics: A Problem-Solving Approach'', Cambridge University Press. [http://www.cambridge.org/gb/knowledge/isbn/item1170271/?site_locale=en_GB Description] and [https://books.google.com/books?id=O-Fv7B4J-6EC&amp;printsec=find&amp;pg=PR5#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false preview.]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Interpretations from various universities ==
Many universities offer courses in business economics and offer a range of interpretations as to the meaning of the word.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.uel.ac.uk/programmes/business/undergraduate/summary/businesseco.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

The Bachelor of Business Economics (BBE) Program at [[University of Delhi]] is designed to meet the growing need for an analytical and quantitative approach to problem solving in the changing corporate world by the application of the latest techniques evolved in the fields of economics and business.&lt;ref&gt;http://du.ac.in/du/index.php?page=business-economics-2&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Autonomous University of Barcelona]] (UAB), the [[Universidad Pública de Navarra]] (UPNa) and the [[University of the Balearic Islands]] (UIB) developed an official Master of Science in Management, Organization and Business Economics focused on management and business topics to train professionals in the study of organizations, on a conceptual and quantitative basis. To achieve this, advanced analysis tools are used from the fields of [[Neoclassical economics]], [[New institutional economics]], [[Statistics]], [[Econometrics]] and [[Operations research]]. This focus is complemented with contributing ideas and theories to develop the necessary instruments to facilitate the management of sophisticated and complex organizations.&lt;ref&gt;UAB,UPNa, UIB - Master of Science (M.Sc.) in Management, Organization and Business Economics - MMOBE Program. [http://pagines.uab.cat/mmobe/ Link]&lt;/ref&gt;

The program at [[Harvard University]] uses economic methods to analyze practical aspects of business, including [[business administration]], management, and related fields of business economics.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.gsas.harvard.edu/programs_of_study/business_economics_4.php&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[University of Miami]] defines business economics as involving the study of how we use our resources for the production, distribution, and consumption of goods and services.  This requires business economists to analyze social institutions, banks, the stock market, the government and their relationships with labor negotiations, taxes, international trade, and urban and environmental issues.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.miami.muohio.edu/academics/majorsminors/majors/businesseconomics.cfm |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2009-01-06 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090725091346/http://www.miami.muohio.edu/academics/majorsminors/majors/businesseconomics.cfm |archivedate=2009-07-25 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Courses at the [[University of Manchester]] interpret business economics to be concerned with the economic analysis of how businesses contribute to welfare of society rather than on the welfare of an individual or a business. This is done via an examination of the relationship between ownership, control and firm objectives; theories of the growth of the firm; the behavioural [[theory of the firm]]; theories of entrepreneurship; the factors that influence the [[Structure-conduct-performance paradigm|structure, conduct and performance]] of business at the industry level.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.socialsciences.manchester.ac.uk/undergraduate/courses/modules/modulelist.html?department%3D3%26newcode%3DECON2 |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2009-01-13 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20081224053759/http://www.socialsciences.manchester.ac.uk/undergraduate/courses/modules/modulelist.html?department=3&amp;newcode=ECON2 |archivedate=2008-12-24 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Italian Universities borrow their concept of business economics from the tradition of [[Gino Zappa]], for example a standard course&lt;ref&gt;https://www11.ceda.polimi.it/schedaincarico/schedaincarico/controller/scheda_pubblica/SchedaPublic.do?&amp;evn_default=evento&amp;c_classe=618079&amp;__pj0=0&amp;__pj1=6f3356db456e221b165cf3ee421a14ec&lt;/ref&gt;  at the [[Politecnico di Milano]] involves studying [[corporate governance]], [[accounting]], [[investment analysis]], [[budgeting]] and [[business strategy]].

[[La Trobe University]] of Melbourne, Australia associates business economics with the process of demand, supply and equilibrium coordinating the behaviour of individuals and businesses in the market. Also, business economics extends to government policy, economic variables and international factors which influence business and competition.

== See also ==
* [[Industrial organisation]]
* [[Business studies]]

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==Journals==
* ''Business Economics'': [https://web.archive.org/web/20111111082746/http://www.nabe.com/busecon.htm Description] and archived article-abstract [https://web.archive.org/web/20081222000712/http://www.nabe.com/pubs.htm links]

== External links ==
* [[National Association for Business Economics]] (NABE, United States): [http://www.nabe.com/ Homepage]
* [http://www.cabe.ca Canadian Association for Business Economics (CABE)]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20120423013601/http://www.abe.org.au/ Australian Business Economists]
* [http://www.businesseconomics.com/ Directory of Business Economics and Finance links with relevant news]

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Business]]
[[Category:Business economics| ]]</text>
      <sha1>d9s0q97ktixj13aheulj251u8281fa3</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Business guru</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>47827092</id>
    <revision>
      <id>861447133</id>
      <parentid>827729476</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-09-27T14:08:48Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>GreenMeansGo</username>
        <id>24271879</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>remove promotional garbage/end round creating an article by making lots of little promotional articles here</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="4605">[[File:CK Prahalad WEForum 2009.jpg|thumb|right|250px|[[C. K. Prahalad]], who conceived the idea of [[core competency]], was ranked first in a list of influential modern business gurus by [[Stuart Crainer]] and [[Des Dearlove]].&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |url=https://www.forbes.com/2009/10/13/influential-business-thinkers-leadership-thought-leaders-guru_slide_11.html |title=The 10 Most Influential Business Gurus |date=14 October 2009 |publisher=Forbes |author=Klaus Kneale}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
A '''business guru''' or '''management guru''' is a leading authority on business practices and can be defined as 'a person with [[influencer|influential]] ideas or theories about business'. The earliest use of the term business guru can be tracked back to the 1960s being used in ''[[Business Week]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = business guru - definition of business guru in English from the Oxford dictionary|url = http://www.oxforddictionaries.com/definition/english/business-guru?q=business+guru|website = www.oxforddictionaries.com|accessdate = 2015-11-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; There are no existing qualifications that make someone a business guru. The lists of people who have been accepted as business gurus have constantly changed over time.&lt;ref name="Hindle"&gt;{{Cite book|title = Guide to Management Ideas and Gurus|url = https://books.google.com/books?id=-K_wp74bK3sC&amp;pg=PA1&amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|publisher = John Wiley &amp; Sons|date = 2008-09-01|isbn = 9781846681080|first = Tim|last = Hindle}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, there are some people who have been accepted by a great majority as a business guru and also some organizations which have created their own lists of gurus. One English&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.randomhouse.co.uk/authors/carol-kennedy |title=Carol Kennedy |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |website=Random House Group |access-date=2015-09-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; writer has described management gurus as "overwhelmingly a US phenomenon."&lt;ref name="Kennedy 2012"&gt;{{cite book|last=Kennedy|first=Carol|title=Guide to the Management Gurus: 5th Edition|year=2012|publisher=Random House|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=I-HqZ8wyeYMC}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Examples and lists==

There is no definitive list of business gurus, but some writers have proposed "personal" lists.&lt;ref name=":0"/&gt; These lists are mostly created by organizations such as business magazines or management writers.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; There have been many business guru lists created through history.

A list consisting of people who are included in almost all of the lists created, collectively known as the "Famous Five", are: [[Frederick Winslow Taylor]], [[Michael Porter]], [[Alfred Sloan]], [[Peter Drucker]], and [[Douglas McGregor]].&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{cite book|last=Hindle|first=Tim|title=Guide to Management Ideas and Gurus|year=2008|publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons|pages=1|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=-K_wp74bK3sC&amp;pg=PA1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2001, ''Harvard Business Review'' asked the gurus to name their favorite gurus. The people named were Peter Drucker, James March and Herbert Simon.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

Another list includes Peter Drucker, Michael Porter, and [[Tom Peters]] as the three leading gurus of our time.&lt;ref name="Kennedy 2012"/&gt;

There are also many gurus who have emerged and disappeared through history. For example, the Japanese were known for making improvements to the business world and bringing out gurus in the 1980s, which included Keniche Ohmae and Akio Morita. Then European gurus emerged, which included Yves Doz, Geert Hofstede, Manfred Kets De Vries and Charles Handy.&lt;ref name="Hindle"/&gt;

==Criticisms of "guru" status==
One management expert, [[Gary Hamel]], says there have been "few genuine breakthroughs" since the work of Taylor and [[Max Weber]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Asian Development Bank|title=Compendium of Knowledge Solutions|year=2010|publisher=Asian Development Bank|pages=304|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=vAo_CQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT304#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt; In his book, Hamel says that management is "stuck in a time warp."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Hamel|first=Gary|title=The Future of Management|year=2013|publisher=Harvard Business Press|pages=4|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=gLktvtlqHSYC&amp;pg=PA4}}&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, even one of the authors of a book about management gurus warns that [[management theory]] is "not served well by fads," citing [[Enron]] as a "[[management fad]] for its supposed culture of [[innovation]]."&lt;ref name="Kennedy 2012"/&gt;

==See also==
*[[Religion and business]]
*[[Technology evangelist]]
*[[Evangelism marketing]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

[[Category:Business]]</text>
      <sha1>8tirhv5ohf57qd2et8gfg0d6q2scwzv</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Business idea</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>16416558</id>
    <revision>
      <id>870111453</id>
      <parentid>870091443</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-11-22T13:17:51Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>GermanJoe</username>
        <id>12935443</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 870091443 by [[Special:Contributions/Abe Oluwasegun|Abe Oluwasegun]] ([[User talk:Abe Oluwasegun|talk]]) spam, not a reliable source</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="8905">{{Multiple issues|
{{notability|date=February 2015}}
{{refimprove|date=October 2015}}
{{Underlinked|date=October 2015}}
}}
A '''business idea''' is a concept that can be used for financial gain that is usually centered on a product or service that can be offered for money. An idea is the base of the pyramid when it comes to the business as a whole.

The characteristics of a promising business idea are:
* Innovative
* Unique
* Problem solving
* Profitable

A business idea is often linked to its creator who needs to identify the business' [[value proposition]] in order to launch to market and establish [[competitive advantage]].

== What is innovation? ==
For businesses this could mean; creating new ideas, new [[New product development|product development]] through research and development or improving existing services. Innovation can be the central focus of a business and this can help them to grow and become a [[market leader]] if they execute their ideas properly. Businesses that are focused on [[innovation]] are usually more efficient, cost effective and productive. Successful innovation should be built into the [[business strategy]], where you can create a culture of innovation and drive forward creative problem solving.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://www.business.gov.au/business-topics/business-planning/innovation/Pages/default.aspx|title = What is innovation?|date = |accessdate = 29 October 2015|website = Business.gov.au|publisher = |last = Unknown|first = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Examples of innovation===

* Apple was a $2 billion company in 1997, then it jumped to a $700 billion valuation in 2015 as a result of the innovation that came from the; Macbook, iPod, iPad, iPhone.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = https://www.forbes.com/sites/johnkotter/2013/11/22/innovation-its-not-the-idea-its-what-you-do-with-it/|title = It's not the idea, it's what you do with it.|date = 22 November 2013|accessdate = 29 October 2015|website = Forbes.com|publisher = |last = Kotter International|first = }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Tesla built an electric car with exceptional aesthetics and efficiency, which has helped build the electric sports car company earn a market capitalization of $33 billion, with revenues up 54% since 2014.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = https://www.forbes.com/sites/innovatorsdna/2015/08/19/teslas-secret-formula/|title = Decoding Tesla's secret formula|date = 19 August 2015|accessdate = 29 October 2015|website = Forbes.com|publisher = |last = Dyer|first = Jeff}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Uber was founded in 2009 and has become a $50 billion company in just 6 years, with its simple yet unusual idea of getting a taxi with the press of a button that has completely revolutionized the way we travel.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = https://www.telegraph.co.uk/finance/newsbysector/mediatechnologyandtelecoms/11816047/Uber-IPO-planned-for-first-half-of-2017-as-bookings-grow-fourfold-this-year.html|title = Uber IPO planned for first half of 2017 as bookings grow four-fold this year|date = 21 August 2015|accessdate = 29 October 2015|website = Telegraph.co.uk|publisher = |last = Davidson|first = Lauren}}&lt;/ref&gt;
These successful companies were built on sheer innovation and we can see how valuable they have become in the short time they have been around or have been focusing on innovation. When we compare Tesla's value to that of General Motors, we see that the [[market capitalization]] of [[General Motors]] is $53.98 billion today &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = https://uk.finance.yahoo.com/q?s=GM|title = General Motors Company - NYSE|date = 29 October 2015|accessdate = 29 October 2015|website = Yahoo.com|publisher = |last = Unknown|first = }}&lt;/ref&gt; in which the company has been around since 1908 &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://www.gm.com/company/historyAndHeritage/creation.html|title = General Motors company history|date = |accessdate = 29 October 2015|website = gm.com|publisher = General Motors|last = General Motors|first = }}&lt;/ref&gt; whereas [[Tesla Motors|Tesla]] was founded in 2003 &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://www.teslamotors.com/en_GB/about|title = About Tesla|date = |accessdate = 29 October 2015|website = Teslamotors.com|publisher = Tesla Motors|last = Tesla|first = }}&lt;/ref&gt; and has achieved 50% of General Motors value within 12 years.

== Unique selling point ==
A unique selling point (USP) is the factor that makes a company or a product stand out from its competitors, whether it is through; pricing, quality, customer service or innovation.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://whatis.techtarget.com/definition/unique-selling-point-USP|title = Definition of USP|date = |accessdate = 29 October 2015|website = whatis.com|publisher = |last = |first = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Each successful company has a [[Unique selling proposition|USP]] and this is what potentially makes their customers loyal to them, as this is the original reason as to why they chose to buy from them. A USP can be created through the element of being first to a market, for example with [[Uber (company)|Uber]]; who were the first company that gave you the ability to press a button and taxi would appear within 5 minutes to pick you up.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://www.telegraphindia.com/1140828/jsp/calcutta/story_18771304.jsp#.VjJxuPnhDWI|title = Uber tops where taxis fail to tread|date = 28 August 2014|accessdate = 29 October 2015|website = telegraphindia.com|publisher = |last = Basu|first = Anasuya}}&lt;/ref&gt; Because Uber had reached this market first, it gave them a USP and therefore they received loyal customers for this. However; with fierce competition copying Uber's [[business model]], Uber has had to develop their service through innovation and this is where innovation can be used as a USP, as Uber have had to develop their services to a wider market in which they are now working on a delivery service called "Uber Rush." &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = https://rush.uber.com/how-it-works|title = Uber Rush how it works|date = |accessdate = 29 October 2015|website = rush.uber.com|publisher = |last = |first = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Problem solving ==
Business ideas that solve problems are fundamental to developing our world and companies such as Curemark are one of many who do this. Curemark is a biotech company founded by Dr Joan Fallon, who noticed that a lot of the children she treated were low on an enzyme for processing protein and since then she has quit her job and has built Curemark to solve this problem. Curemark has now raised $50 million and is on its way to solving a problem that truly exists.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://www.fastcompany.com/3023216/leadership-now/great-companies-solve-problems-that-matter|title = great companies solve problems that matter|date = |accessdate = 29 October 2015|website = fastcompany.com|publisher = |last = Krippendorf|first = Kaihan}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Profitability ==
[[Profitability]] is a business's ability to generate earnings compared to its costs over a certain period of time.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://www.investopedia.com/terms/p/profitabilityratios.asp|title = Profitability ratios|date = |accessdate = 29 October 2015|website = investopedia.com|publisher = |last = |first = }}&lt;/ref&gt; This is possibly the most important aspect of any business idea in the long term, as this is what makes a business survive in order to keep having the impact that it has. Profitable ideas need a strong [[revenue stream]] against its costs and this tends to create the success of the business, however some companies defy this and make losses to begin with, yet are still exceptional business ideas that are worth billions.

=== High valued companies making a loss ===

* Snapchat is valued at $10 billion &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://money.cnn.com/2015/01/23/investing/shazam-tech-startups-lose-money/|title = Startup lose money despite being worth billions|date = 23 January 2015|accessdate = 29 October 2015|website = money.cnn.com|publisher = |last = Egan|first = Matt}}&lt;/ref&gt; despite making a loss, because of the monetization potential it has based on the 100 million everyday users of the app.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://expandedramblings.com/index.php/snapchat-statistics/|title = By the numbers: 60 amazing snaphat statistics|date = 8 October 2015|accessdate = 29 October 2015|website = expandedramblings.com|publisher = |last = Smith|first = Craig}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Uber is valued at $50 billion and is making a $417 million operating loss. Despite this; [[investor]]s are still willing to offer large amounts of money to fund the company because of the potential the company has in the longer term.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2015-06-30/uber-bonds-term-sheet-reveals-470-million-in-operating-losses|title = Uber bonds term sheet reveals $470 million in operating losses|date = 30 June 2015|accessdate = 29 October 2015|website = bloomberg.com|publisher = |last = Newcomer|first = Eric}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Viability study]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

[[Category:Business]]</text>
      <sha1>cgtmozu4kf8rp8unmd5z8ywj18sbkvf</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Business interaction networks</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>26085407</id>
    <revision>
      <id>764873658</id>
      <parentid>764848124</parentid>
      <timestamp>2017-02-11T12:22:49Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Kuru</username>
        <id>764407</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contribs/182.70.65.197|182.70.65.197]] ([[User talk:182.70.65.197|talk]]) to last version by Bender the Bot</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="1072">'''Business interaction networks''' are networks that allow businesses and their communities of interest to collaborate and do business online securely via the [[Internet]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=jRIEAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA34&amp;lpg=PA34&amp;dq=%22business+interaction+networks%22+network+world&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=J0ra0NYjmu&amp;sig=Ve9afBpbCgRXrv1oUHklIAlHOkw&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=gq1sS6bhEJTwsQPswoyyDQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=4&amp;ved=0CBAQ6AEwAw#v=onepage&amp;q=%22business%20interaction%20networks%22%20network%20world&amp;f=false | title=Deal underscores need for users to get serious about Internet services | author=Turner, Mary Johnston | publisher = [[Network World]] | accessdate = February 5, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Mary Johnston Turner first discussed the concept in a [[Network World]] opinion piece in August, 1995, and attributed the first advocacy for the concept to the now-defunct [[BBN_Planet#Computer_technologies_since_the_1990s|BBN Planet]], the ISP division of [[BBN Technologies]].

==References==
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Business]]
[[Category:Networks]]</text>
      <sha1>btzs3pogmtl3n79u3lqin3zumljnkoe</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Business sector</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>22697384</id>
    <revision>
      <id>868853258</id>
      <parentid>850385313</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-11-14T21:36:59Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rescuing 1 sources and tagging 0 as dead. #IABot (v2.0beta10)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="4347">{{Distinguish|private sector|division (business)}}
{{Expert-subject|Economics |date=May 2009}}
{{Economic sectors}}

In [[economics]], the '''business sector''' or '''corporate sector''' - sometimes popularly called simply "'''business'''" - is "the part of the [[economy]] made up by [[company|companies]]".&lt;ref&gt;Longman Business English Dictionary&lt;/ref&gt; It is a subset of the [[Sovereign state|domestic]] [[economy]],&lt;ref&gt;
But compare {{cite book
| last1                 = Keese
| first1                = Mark
| last2                 = Salou
| first2                = Gérard
| last3                 = Richardson
| first3                = Pete
| title                 = The measurement of output and factors of production for the business sector in OECD countries: the OECD business sector database
| url                   = https://books.google.com/books?id=Zzm5AAAAIAAJ
| series                = OECD Department of Economics and Statistics working papers
| volume                = 95-101
| issue                 = 99
| publisher             = Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development
| publication-date      = 1991
| page                  = i
| accessdate            = 2015-06-07
| quote                 = [...] recent work of the OECD Economics and Statistics Department to construct an international Business Sector Data Base (BSDB) for use in a wide variety of analyses of production and supply issues [...].
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
excluding the economic activities of general [[government]], of private households, and of [[non-profit organization]]s serving individuals.&lt;ref name="uslabor"&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.bls.gov/bls/glossary.htm |title = BLS Information |date= February 28, 2008|work= Glossary|publisher= U.S. Bureau of Labor Statistics Division of Information Services |accessdate= 2009-05-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; An alternative analysis of economies, the [[three-sector theory]], subdivides them  into:{{cn|date=June 2015}} 

* the [[primary sector of the economy | primary sector]] (producing raw materials)
* the [[secondary sector of the economy | secondary sector]] (carrying out manufacturing)
* the [[tertiary sector of the economy | tertiary sector]] (providing sales and services)

In the [[United States]] the business sector accounted for about 78 percent of the value of gross domestic product (GDP) {{as of | 2000 | lc = on}}.&lt;ref name="uslabor"/&gt; [[Kuwait]] and [[Tuvalu]] each had business sectors accounting for less than 40% of GDP {{as of | 2015 | lc = on}}.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book
| chapter = 1: Overview: Opportunities and challenges for Myanmar
| title = OECD Development Pathways Multi-dimensional Review of Myanmar
| url = https://books.google.com/books?id=kHKADAAAQBAJ
| volume = 3: From Analysis to Action
| location = Paris
| publisher = OECD Publishing
| publication-date = 2016
| page = 29
| isbn = 9789264256545
| access-date = 2017-12-27
| quote = The countries that have general government revenue more than 60% of GDP are Kiribati, Kuwait, Lesotho, Micronesia and Tuvalu. Source: IMF (2015), World Economic Outlook (database), International Monetary Fund.
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Bureau of Labor Statistics]] (BLS), a unit of the United States Department of Labor
* [[Business]]
* [[GDP]]
* [[Private sector]]
* [[State-owned enterprise]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==

===United States===
* [http://www.bls.gov/news.release/prod2.t01.htm Business sector: Productivity, hourly compensation, unit labor costs, and prices, seasonally adjusted], [[Bureau of Labor Statistics]]
* [http://www.epa.gov/lawsregs/bizsector/index.html Regulatory Information by Business Sector], [[United States Environmental Protection Agency|U.S. Environmental Protection Agency]]
* [https://www.cdc.gov/Partners/Business/ Business Sector], [[Centers for Disease Control and Prevention|CDC]]

===United Kingdom===
* [https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-business-innovation-skills], [[Department for Business, Innovation and Skills]]
* [http://www.businesslink.gov.uk/bdotg/action/layer?topicId=1081597476 Your business sector], [[Business Link]]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20110810130610/http://www.ukti.gov.uk/export/sectors.html Business Sectors], [[UK Trade &amp; Investment]]
* E

{{economics}}
{{employment}}

[[Category:Business]]
[[Category:Economic sectors]]


{{business-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>ikw8vy7ijzga6hr2712feut8iycpxg6</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Closure (business)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>18958074</id>
    <revision>
      <id>831027353</id>
      <parentid>794882720</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-03-18T09:04:29Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Marcocapelle</username>
        <id>14965160</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>added [[Category:Endings]] using [[WP:HC|HotCat]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="3565">{{Other uses|Closure (disambiguation){{!}}Closure}}
{{Unreferenced|date=August 2008}}
'''Closure''' is the term used to refer to the actions necessary when it is no longer necessary or possible for a [[business]] or other organization to continue to operate.  Closure may be the result of a [[bankruptcy]], where the organization lacks sufficient funds to continue operations, as a result of the [[proprietor]] of the business dying, as a result of a business being purchased by another organization (or a competitor) and shut down as superfluous, or because it is the non-surviving entity in a [[corporate merger]].  A closure may occur because the purpose for which the organization was created is no longer necessary.

While a closure is typically of a business or a [[non-profit organization]], any [[entity]] which is created by human beings can be subject to a closure, from a single church to a whole religion, up to and including an entire country if, for some reason, it ceases to exist.

Closures are of two types, voluntary or involuntary. Voluntary closures of organizations are much rarer than involuntary ones{{fact|date=December 2013}}, as, in the absence of some change making operations impossible or unnecessary, most operations will continue until something happens that causes a change requiring this situation.

The most common form of voluntary closure would be when those involved in an organization such as a social club, a band, or other non-profit organization decide to cease operating. Once the organization has paid any outstanding debts and completed any pending operations, closure may simply mean that the organization ceases to exist.

If an organization has debts that cannot be paid, it may be necessary to perform a liquidation of its assets. If there is anything left after the assets are converted to cash, in the case of a for-profit organization, the remainder is distributed to the stockholders; in the case of a non-profit, by law{{clarifyme|date=December 2013}} any remaining assets must be distributed to another non-profit.

If an organization has more debts than assets, it may have to declare bankruptcy. If the organization is viable, it may reorganizes itself as a result of the bankruptcy and continue operations. If it is not viable for the business to continue operating, then a closure occurs through a bankruptcy [[liquidation]]: its assets are liquidated, the creditors are paid from whatever assets could be liquidated, and the business ceases operations.

Possibly the largest "closure" in history (but more closely analogous to a demerger) was the split of the [[Soviet Union]] into its constituent countries. In comparison, the end of [[East Germany]] can be considered a [[merger]] rather than a closure as [[West Germany]] assumed all of the assets and liabilities of [[East Germany]]. The end of the Soviet Union was the equivalent of a closure through a bankruptcy liquidation, because while [[Russia]] assumed most of the assets and responsibilities of the former Soviet Union, it did not assume all of them. There have been issues over who is responsible for unpaid [[parking ticket]]s accumulated by [[motor vehicle]]s operated on behalf of [[diplomatic mission]]s operated by the former Soviet Union in other countries, as Russia claims it is not responsible for them.

Several major business closures include the bankruptcy of the [[Penn Central]] railroad, the [[Enron scandal]]s, and [[MCI Worldcom]]'s bankruptcy and eventual merger into [[Verizon]].

[[Category:Business]]
[[Category:Endings]]</text>
      <sha1>o54jgmgr6tzk7wnnjv3ncjfst1goc0z</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Core business</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2886264</id>
    <revision>
      <id>795298420</id>
      <parentid>795298407</parentid>
      <timestamp>2017-08-13T09:38:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>113.160.13.218</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="1907">The '''core business''' of an organization is an idealized construct intended to express that organization's "main" or "essential" activity.  

The [[corporation|corporate]] trend in the mid-20th Century, of acquiring new enterprises and forming [[Conglomerate (company)|conglomerate]]s, enabled [[corporation]]s to reduce costs funds and similar investment vehicles, and sometimes the following of a popular trend among corporate management seeking to appeal to current and impress investors.

Core business process means that a business's success depends not only on how well each department performs its work, but also on how well the company manages to coordinate departmental activities to conduct the core business process, which is;

1. '''The market-sensing process'''
Meaning all activities in gathering marketing intelligence and acting on the information.

2. '''The new-offering realization process'''
Covering all activities in research, development and launching new quality offerings quickly and within budget.

3. '''The customer acquisition process'''
all the activities defining the target market and prospecting for new customers

4. '''The customer relationship management process'''
all the activities covering building deeper understanding, relationships and offerings to individual customers.

5. '''The fulfillment management process'''
all the activities in receiving and approving orders, shipping out on time and collecting payment.

To be successful, a business needs to look for competitive advantages beyond its own operations. The business needs to look at the competitiveness value chain of suppliers, distributors and customers. Many companies today have partnered with specific suppliers and distributors to create a superior value delivery network.

== References ==
Kotler &amp; Keller, Marketing management, 2009, p76

==See also==
[[Core competency]]

[[Category:Business]]</text>
      <sha1>dqessxfdtzwiexrs5kknrhn5io7tjxy</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Initiative Q</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>58927325</id>
    <revision>
      <id>870108077</id>
      <parentid>870106528</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-11-22T12:40:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>David Gerard</username>
        <id>36389</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>rm claim cited to non-RS (Forbes contributor blog)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="6836">{{pp-semi|small=yes}}
{{short description|Speculative payment network and digital currency}}

'''Initiative Q''' is an attempt to create a new payment network and digital currency.&lt;ref name="not crypto"&gt;{{cite web |deadurl=no |accessdate=22 November 2018 |url=https://www.vox.com/the-goods/2018/11/8/18075816/initiative-q-email-cryptocurrency-bitcoin-paypal-saar-wilf |archivedate=9 November 2018 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20181109000341/https://www.vox.com/the-goods/2018/11/8/18075816/initiative-q-email-cryptocurrency-bitcoin-paypal-saar-wilf |title=This new would-be currency isn’t crypto — but is it for real? |first=Nadra |last=Nittle |date=8 November 2018 |website=[[Vox.com]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was created by [[State of Israel|Israel]]i [[entrepreneur]] Saar Wilf, who previously founded Fraud Sciences, a payment security company acquired by PayPal.&lt;ref name="news.com.au"/&gt;&lt;ref name="TiA"&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.techinasia.com/talk/founder-challenge-visa-global-currency |first2=Orr |last2=Hirschauge |first1=Lilach |last1=Baumer |date=23 August 2018 |title=This serial founder wants to challenge Visa through a ‘global currency’ for the future |accessdate=31 October 2018 |work=[[TechInAsia.com]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://techcrunch.com/2008/01/28/ebay-acquires-fraud-sciences-for-169-million/|title=eBay Acquires Fraud Sciences For $169 Million |work=[[TechCrunch]] |accessdate=8 November 2018|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="not crypto"/&gt; Q is backed by [[Cato Institute]] [[economist]] [[Lawrence H. White]].&lt;ref name="news.com.au"/&gt; Unlike Bitcoin the scheme would not take measures to evade state regulation.&lt;ref name="CUPMedia"&gt;{{cite web |language=Chinese |deadurl=no |website=cup.com.hk |publisher=CUP Media |url=http://www.cup.com.hk/2018/11/12/will-initiative-q-the-next-bitcoin/ |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20181122121712/http://www.cup.com.hk/2018/11/12/will-initiative-q-the-next-bitcoin/ |trans-title="Q coin" suddenly rises, is it the next Bitcoin? |title=Q 幣」突然冒起，是否下一個 Bitcoin？|date=12 November 2018 |accessdate=22 November 2018 |archivedate=22 November 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Marketing==
The currency is marketed through [[chain email]] [[multi-level marketing]],&lt;ref name="portfolio.hu"&gt;{{cite news |language=[[hungarian (language)|hungarian]] |title=Megőrül az internet az új fizetéses MLM-rendszerért - Kamu lenne? |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20181031110948/https://www.portfolio.hu/vallalatok/it/megorul-az-internet-az-uj-fizeteses-mlm-rendszerert-kamu-lenne.302726.html |archivedate=31 October 2018 |url=https://www.portfolio.hu/vallalatok/it/megorul-az-internet-az-uj-fizeteses-mlm-rendszerert-kamu-lenne.302726.html |deadurl=no |trans-title=Will the Internet be crazy about a new MLM pay-per-view system - would it be Kamu? |first=Daniel |last=Huszák |date=31 October 2018 |website=[[Portfolio.hu]] |accessdate=1 November 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; and will not be released until a critical mass of adopters identify themselves.&lt;ref name="TiA"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |date=26 October 2018 |first=Jemima |url=https://ftalphaville.ft.com/2018/10/26/1540526405000/Initiative-Q--an-elementary-pyramid-scheme-with-grandiose-ideas/ |last=Kelly |accessdate=31 October 2018 | website=[[FT Alphaville]] |title=Initiative Q: an elementary pyramid scheme with grandiose ideas [Update]}}&lt;/ref&gt; In November 2018, [[Vox.com]] reported that more than 2 Million people had signed-up in 180 countries.&lt;ref name="not crypto"/&gt;

==Criticism==
In October 2018, Frank Chung of [[news.com.au]] wrote that the marketing style could be "perceived as a [[scam]] or [[pyramid scheme]]".&lt;ref name="news.com.au"&gt;{{cite web |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20181030052631/https://www.news.com.au/finance/money/investing/what-is-initiative-q-payment-network-insists-its-not-a-pyramid-scheme/news-story/193102b9fbb5c35d6365f7f34226908f |archivedate=30 October 2018 |url=https://www.news.com.au/finance/money/investing/what-is-initiative-q-payment-network-insists-its-not-a-pyramid-scheme/news-story/193102b9fbb5c35d6365f7f34226908f |website=[[news.com.au]] |deadurl=no |title=What is Initiative Q? Payment network insists it’s not a 'pyramid scheme' |first=Frank |last=Chung |date=29 October 2018 |accessdate=1 November 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; and FINTECH Singapore and Daniel Huszák of [[portfolio.hu]] compared it to [[multi-level marketing]] without the fee.&lt;ref name="portfolio.hu"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Fintech"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://fintechnews.sg/25640/fintech/be-careful-new-currency-project-initiative-q-is-all-over-social-media-data-risk |website=[[FinTechNews.sg]] |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20181122115623/http://fintechnews.sg/25640/fintech/be-careful-new-currency-project-initiative-q-is-all-over-social-media-data-risk |title=Currency Project Initiative Q Is All Over Social Media– Be Careful, Your Data or Reputation are at Risk! |date=8 November 2018 |archivedate=22 November 2018 |accessdate=22 November 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; Owen Gough of [[Digital Spy]] wrote 
"Is Initiative Q real or fake? Short answer – we have absolutely no idea."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.digitalspy.com/tech/news/a869483/what-is-initiative-q-bitcoin-real-fake-scam/ |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20181101235354/http://www.digitalspy.com/tech/news/a869483/what-is-initiative-q-bitcoin-real-fake-scam/ |website=[[DigitalSpy.com]] |deadurl=no |archivedate=1 November 2018 |title=What is Initiative Q: Is it the new bitcoin, or just one big fake scam? |first=Owen |last=Gough |date=2 November 2018 |accessdate=7 November 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Brendan Markey-Tower of [[Stuff.co.nz]] explained in November 2018 that the scheme wouldn't "make you fabulously wealthy. It is, nonetheless, an interesting idea".&lt;ref name="stuff"&gt;{{cite web |title=Initiative Q is not the new Bitcoin, but here's why the idea has value |deadurl=no |archivedate=6 November 2018 |website=[[Stuff.co.nz]] |url=https://www.stuff.co.nz/business/opinion-analysis/108380918/Initiative-Q-is-not-the-new-Bitcoin-but-heres-why-the-idea-has-value |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20181106135456/https://www.stuff.co.nz/business/opinion-analysis/108380918/Initiative-Q-is-not-the-new-Bitcoin-but-heres-why-the-idea-has-value |first=Brendan |last=Markey-Towler |accessdate=22 November 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Huszák enumerated potential problems with the scheme such as no clear crypto-currency security measures, unclear transaction/[[Foreign exchange market|exchange]] costs, and potential for [[market manipulation]] by the largest holders of currency.&lt;ref name="portfolio.hu"/&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* {{official}}

{{Cryptocurrencies}}

[[Category:Business]]
[[Category:Cryptocurrencies]]
[[Category:Companies based in Middlesbrough]]

{{Authority control}}
{{cryptocurrency-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>cwsq3xs0ez78jyqopfap0q78lzkaqn5</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Marketing strategy</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>328240</id>
    <revision>
      <id>867922062</id>
      <parentid>867828545</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-11-08T21:05:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>196.62.96.28</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Fixed a grammar mistake</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="72143">{{Marketing}}
'''Marketing strategy''' is a long-term, forward-looking approach to planning with the fundamental goal of achieving a sustainable [[competitive advantage]].&lt;ref&gt;Baker, Michael ''The Strategic Marketing Plan Audit'' 2008. {{ISBN|1-902433-99-8}}. p. 3&lt;/ref&gt; Strategic planning involves an analysis of the company's strategic initial situation prior to the formulation, evaluation and selection of [[market-oriented]] competitive position that contributes to the company's goals and marketing objectives.&lt;ref&gt;Homburg, Christian; Sabine Kuester, Harley Krohmer, ''Marketing Management: A Contemporary Perspective'' (1st ed.), London, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

Strategic marketing, as a distinct field of study emerged in the 1970s, and built on strategic management that preceded it&lt;ref&gt;Simandan, D., 2018. Iterative lagged asymmetric responses in strategic management and long-range planning. Time &amp; Society, OnlineFirst, https://doi.org/10.1177/0961463X17752652 .&lt;/ref&gt;. Marketing strategy highlights the role of marketing as a link between the organisation and its customers. 

At its most basic level, strategic marketing addresses three deceptively simple questions: (1) Where are we now? (2) Where are we going? and (3) How are we going to get there? In attempting to answer these questions, strategic planners require sophisticated skills in both research and analysis&lt;ref&gt;Payne, A. and Frow, P., 2014. Developing superior value propositions: a strategic marketing imperative. Journal of Service Management, 25(2), pp.213-227.&lt;/ref&gt;.

==Definitions of marketing strategy==

Scholars continue to debate the precise meaning of marketing strategy. Consequently, the literature offers many different definitions. On close examination, however, these definitions appear to centre around the notion that strategy refers to a broad statement of what is to be achieved.

Marketing Strategy is:

: "The marketing strategy lays out target markets and the value proposition that will be offered based on an analysis of the best market opportunities." (Philip Kotler &amp; Kevin Keller, Marketing Management, Pearson, 14th Edition)

: “An over-riding directional concept that sets out the planned path.”  (David Aaker and Michael K. Mills, ''Strategic Market Management,'' 2001, p. 11)

: "Essentially a formula for how a business is going to compete, what its goals should be and what policies will be needed to carry out these goals." (Michael Porter, ''Competitive Strategy: Techniques for Analyzing Industries and Competitors ,'' NY, Free Press, 1980)

: "The pattern of major objectives, purposes and goals and essential policies and plans for achieving those goals, stated in such a way as to define what business the company is in or is to be in. (S. Jain, ''Marketing Planning and Strategy,'' 1993)

: "An explicit guide to future behaviour.” (Henry Mintzberg, “ Crafting Strategy,” ''Harvard Business Review,'' July–August, 1987 pp. 66–74)

:  Strategy is "reserved for actions aimed directly at altering the strengths of the enterprise relative to that of its competitors... Perfect strategies are not called for. What counts is... performance relative to competitors.” (Kenichi Ohmae, ''The Mind of the Strategist,'' 1982, p. 37)

: Strategy formulation is built on "the match between organisational resources and skills and environmental opportunities and risks it faces and the purposes it wishes to accomplish." (Dan Schendel and  Charles W. Hofer, ''Strategy Formulation: Analytical Concepts,'' South-Western, 1978, p. 11)

==Marketing management versus marketing strategy==

The distinction between “strategic” and “managerial” marketing is used to distinguish "two phases having different goals and based on different conceptual tools. Strategic marketing concerns the choice of policies  aiming at improving the competitive position of the firm, taking account of challenges and opportunities  proposed by the competitive environment. On the other hand, managerial marketing is focused on the implementation of specific targets."&lt;ref&gt;Volpato, G. and Stocchetti, A., "Old and new approaches to marketing: The quest of their epistemological roots," MPRA Paper No. 30841, 2009, &lt;Online: https://mpra.ub.uni-muenchen.de/30841&gt;, p. 34&lt;/ref&gt; Marketing strategy is about "lofty visions translated into less lofty and practical goals [while marketing management] is where we start to get our hands dirty and make plans for things to happen."&lt;ref&gt;Cited in Dann, S. and Dann, S., ''E-Marketing: Theory and Application'' London, Palgrave-McMillan, 2011, p. 109&lt;/ref&gt; Marketing strategy is sometimes called ''higher order'' planning because it sets out the broad direction and provides guidance and structure for the marketing program.

==Brief history of strategic marketing==

Marketing scholars have suggested that strategic marketing arose in the late 1970s and its origins can be understood in terms of a distinct evolutionary path:&lt;ref&gt;Brown, L., ''Competitive Marketing Strategy: Dynamic Manoeuvring for Competitive Position,'' Melbourne, Nelson, 1997; West, D., Ford, J. and Ibrahim, E., ''Strategic Marketing: Creating Competitive Advantage,'' Oxford, Oxford University Press, 2010, p. 50-56; Schaars, S.p., ''Marketing Strategy,'' The Free Press, 1998, [Chapter 4 - 'A Brief History of Marketing Strategy'], pp 18-29 &lt;/ref&gt;

: '''Budgeting Control'''  (also known as ''scientific management'')
{{See|Scientific management}}
: Date: From late 19th century
: Key Thinkers: [[Frederick Winslow Taylor]], [[Frank Bunker Gilbreth Sr.|Frank]] and [[Lillian Moller Gilbreth|Lillian Gilbreth]], [[Henry L. Gantt]], [[Harrington Emerson]] 
: Key Ideas: Emphasis on quantification and scientific modelling, reduce work to smallest possible units and assign work to specialists, exercise control through rigid managerial hierarchies, standardise inputs to reduce variation, defects and control costs, use quantitative forecasting methods to predict any changes.&lt;ref&gt;Lowson, R., "The Nature of Operations Strategy: Combining Strategic Decisions from an Operations and Market based Perspective," ''Management Decision,'' Vol. 41, No, 6, p. 541&lt;/ref&gt; 

:'''Long Range Planning''' 
{{See|Long-range planning}}
: Date: From 1950s
: Key Thinkers: [[Herbert A. Simon]] 
: Key Ideas: Managerial focus was to anticipate growth and manage operations in an increasingly complex business world.&lt;ref&gt;Pacios, A., "Strategic plans and long‐range plans: is there a difference?", ''Library Management,'' Vol. 25, No. 6/7, 2004, pp.259-269, https://doi.org/10.1108/01435120410547913&lt;/ref&gt;

:'''Strategic Planning''' (also known as ''corporate planning'')
{{See|Strategic management}}
: Date: From the 1960s 
: Key Thinkers: [[Michael Porter]] 
: Key Ideas: Organisations must find the right fit within an industry structure; advantage derives from industry concentration and market power; firms should strive to achieve a monopoly or quasi-monopoly; successful firms should be able to erect barriers to entry. 

: '''Strategic Marketing Management''' 
: Date: from late 1970s 
: Key thinkers: R. Buzzell and B. Gale
: Key Ideas:  Each business is unique and that there can be no formula for achieving competitive advantage; firms should adopt a flexible planning and review process that aims to cope with strategic surprises and rapidly developing threats; management's focus is on how to deliver superior customer value; highlights the key role of marketing as the link between customers and the organisation. 

: '''Resource Based View (RBV)''' (also known as ''resource-advantage theory'')
{{See|Resource-based view}}
: Date: From mid 1990s
: Key Thinkers: [[Jay Barney|Jay B. Barney]], [[George S. Day]], [[Gary Hamel]], [[Shelby D. Hunt]], G. Hooley and [[C.K. Prahalad]]
: Key Ideas: The firm's resources are financial, legal, human, organisational, informational and relational; resources are heterogeneous and imperfectly mobile, management's key task is to understand and organise resources for sustainable competitive advantage.&lt;ref&gt;Hunt, D. S. and Derozier, C., "The Normative Imperatives of Business and Marketing Strategy: Grounding Strategy in Resource-Advantage View," ''Journal of Business and Industrial Marketing,'' Vol. 19, No. 1, 2004, pp. 5–22&lt;/ref&gt;

==Strategic marketing planning: An overview==
[[File:The strategic gap.jpg|thumb|The strategic gap]]
Marketing strategy involves mapping out the company's direction for the forthcoming planning period, whether that be three, five or ten years. It involves undertaking a 360° review of the firm and its operating environment with a view to identifying new business opportunities that the firm could potentially leverage for competitive advantage. Strategic planning may also reveal market threats that the firm may need to consider for long-term sustainability.&lt;ref&gt;Frates, J. and Sharp, S., "Using Business Intelligence to Discover New Market Opportunities," ''Journal of Competitive Intelligence and Management,'' Vol. 3, No. 1, 2005, pp. 16–28&lt;/ref&gt; Strategic planning makes no assumptions about the firm continuing to offer the same products to the same customers into the future. Instead, it is concerned with identifying the business opportunities that are likely to be successful and evaluates the firm's capacity to leverage such opportunities. It seeks to identify the ''strategic gap''; that is the difference between where a firm is currently situated (the ''strategic reality'' or ''inadvertent strategy'') and where it should be situated for sustainable, long-term growth (the ''strategic intent'' or ''deliberate strategy'').&lt;ref&gt;Kerzner, H., ''Strategic Planning for Project Management Using a Project Management Using a Project Management Maturity Model,'' Wiley, 2002,  pp. 6–8&lt;/ref&gt;

Strategic planning seeks to address three deceptively simple questions, specifically:&lt;ref&gt;West, D., Ford, J. and Ibrahim, E., ''Strategic Marketing: Creating Competitive Advantage,'' Oxford, Oxford University Press, 2010, p. 22&lt;/ref&gt;
: * Where are we now? (Situation analysis)
: * What business ''should'' we be in? (Vision and mission)
: * How should we get there? (Strategies, plans, goals and objectives)

A fourth question may be added to the list, namely 'How do we know when we got there?' Due to increasing need for accountability, many marketing organisations use a variety of [[Marketing performance measurement|marketing metrics]] to track strategic performance, allowing for corrective action to be taken as required. On the surface, strategic planning seeks to address three simple questions, however, the research and analysis involved in strategic planning is very sophisticated and requires a great deal of skill and judgement.

==Strategic analysis: tools and techniques==

Strategic analysis is designed to address the first strategic question, "Where are we now?" &lt;ref&gt;West, D., Ford, J. and Ibrahim, E., ''Strategic Marketing: Creating Competitive Advantage,'' Oxford, Oxford University Press, 2010, p. 34&lt;/ref&gt; Traditional [[market research]] is less useful for strategic marketing because the analyst is not seeking insights about customer attitudes and preferences. Instead strategic analysts are seeking insights about the firm's operating environment with a view to identifying possible future scenarios, opportunities and threats. 

Strategic planning focuses on the three 3C’s, namely: Customer, Corporation and Competitors.&lt;ref name=":5"&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.toolshero.com/strategy/3c-model-ohmae/|title=3C model by Kenichi Ohmae|last=Vliet|first=Vincent van |date=February 17, 2015|publisher=toolshero.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; A detailed analysis of each factor is key to the success of strategy formulation. The 'competitors' element refers to an analysis of the strengths of the business relative to close rivals, and a consideration of competitive threats that might impinge on the business' ability to move in certain directions. &lt;ref name=":5" /&gt; The 'customer' element refers to an analysis of any possible changes in customer preferences that potentially give rise to new business opportunities. The 'corporation' element refers to a detailed analysis of the company's internal capabilities and its readiness to leverage market-based opportunities or its vulnerability to external threats. &lt;ref name=":5" /&gt;

[[File:Folio Plot BCG Matrix Example.png|thumb|The BCG Matrix is just one of the many analytical techniques used by strategic analysts as a means of evaluating the performance of the firm's current stable of brands]]
[[File:PerceptualMap2.png|thumb|Perceptual mapping assists analysts to evaluate the competitive performance of brands]]
[[File:Gartner Hype Cycle for Emerging Technologies.gif|thumb|A product evolutionary cycle helps to envision future directions for product development]]
[[File:Porters five forces.PNG|thumb|Porter's five forces]]
Mintzberg suggests that the top planners spend most of their time engaged in analysis and are concerned with industry or competitive analyses as well as internal studies, including the use of computer models to analyze trends in the organization.&lt;ref&gt;Mintzberg, H., "The Fall and Rise of Strategic Planning," ''Harvard Business Review,'' January–February, 1994 Online: https://hbr.org/1994/01/the-fall-and-rise-of-strategic-planning&lt;/ref&gt; Strategic planners use a variety of research tools and analytical techniques, depending on the environment complexity and the firm's goals. Fleitcher and Bensoussan, for instance, have identified some 200 qualitative and quantitative analytical techniques regularly used by strategic analysts&lt;ref&gt;Fleitcher, C. and Bensoussan, B., ''Strategic and Competitive Analysis: Methods and Techniques for Analyzing Business Competition,'' Prentice Hall, NJ  Prentice Hall, 2002&lt;/ref&gt; while a recent publication suggests that 72 techniques are essential.&lt;ref name="doi.org"&gt;Aghazadeh, H., "Business, Market, and Competitive Analysis (BMCA) Tools and Techniques," Chapter 5 in ''Principles of Marketology,'' Vol 1, Palgrave Macmillan, New York, 2016, https://doi.org/10.1057/9781137379320_6, pp. 187–247&lt;/ref&gt; No optimal technique can be identified as useful across all situations or problems. Determining which technique to use in any given situation rests with the skill of the analyst. The choice of tool depends on a variety of factors including: data availability; the nature of the marketing problem; the objective or purpose, the analyst’s skill level as well as other constraints such as time or  motivation. &lt;ref&gt;Farris, P., Bendle, N., Pfeifer, P. and Reibstein, D., ''Marketing Metrics: The Manager's Guide to Measuring Marketing Performance,'' [E-book edition], FT Press, 2015, Chapter 1&lt;/ref&gt;

The most commonly used tools and techniques include:&lt;ref name="doi.org"/&gt;

'''Research methods'''
* [[Environmental scanning]]&lt;ref&gt;Fahey, L., King, W. R. and Narayanan, V. K., "Environmental scanning and forecasting in strategic planning—The state of the art," ''Long Range Planning,'' Vol. 14, No. 1, 1981, pp. 32–39&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Marketing intelligence]] (also known as [[competitive intelligence]])&lt;ref&gt;Fleisher, C. and Bensoussan, B. ''Strategic and Competitive Intelligence Analysis: Methods &amp; Techniques for Analyzing Business Competition,'' 2003; Fleisher, C. &amp; Bensoussan, B., ''Business and Competitive Analysis: Effective Application of New and Classic Methods,'' 2007; Slater, S. F. and Narver, J. C., "Intelligence Generation and Superior Customer Value," ''Academy of Marketing Science,'' Vol. 28, No. 1, 2000, pp. 120–128&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Futures studies|Futures research]]&lt;ref&gt;Berkhout, F. and Hertin, J., "Foresight futures scenarios: developing and applying a participative strategic planning tool," ''Greener Management International,'' Spring 2002, pp. 37+; Skumanich, M. and Silbernagel, M., “Background on Foresighting Methods,” Ch. 2 in ''Foresighting Around the World,'' Battelle Seattle Research Centre, 1997, e-text, www.seattle.battelle.org&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Analytical techniques'''
* [[Brand development index (marketing)|Brand Development Index (BDI)]]/ [[Category development index (marketing)|Category development index (CDI)]]&lt;ref&gt;Farris, p., Bendle, N., Pfeifer, P and Reibstein, D., ''Marketing Metrics: The Manager's Guide to Measuring Marketing Performance,'' 3rd edition, [E-book edition], FT Press, 2015, pp 31-35&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Market penetration|Brand/ Category penetration]] &lt;ref&gt;Farris, P., Bendle, N.,  Pfeifer, P. and Reibstein, D., ''Marketing Metrics: The Manager's Guide to Measuring Marketing Performance,'' [E-book edition], FT Press, 2015, Chapter 2&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Benchmarking]]&lt;ref&gt;Vorhiesm D. W. and Morgan, N. A., "Benchmarking Marketing Capabilities for Sustainable Competitive Advantage," ''Journal of Marketing,'' Vol. 69. January, 2005,  pp. 80–94&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Blindspots analysis]]&lt;ref&gt;Fleisher, C. and Bensoussan, B. ''Strategic and Competitive Intelligence Analysis: Methods &amp; Techniques for Analyzing Business Competition,'' 2002&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Capability management in business|Functional capability]] and resource analysis&lt;ref&gt;Blanco, S. Caron-Fasan, M. L. and Lesca, H., “Developing Capabilities to Create Collective Intelligence within Organizations,” ''Journal of Competitive Intelligence and Management,'' Vol. 1, No. 1, pp. 80–92.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Change impact analysis|Impact analysis]]&lt;ref&gt;Aaker, D. A. and Mills, M. K. ''Strategic Market Management,'' Pacific Rim ed., Wiley, pp. 79–81&lt;/ref&gt; 
* Counterfactual analysis&lt;ref&gt;Booth, C., "Does history matter in strategy? The possibilities and problems of counterfactual analysis", ''Management Decision,' Vol. 41 Issue: 1, 2003, pp. 96–104, https://doi.org/10.1108/00251740310445545&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Demand forecasting|Demand analysis]] &lt;ref&gt;Kadiyali, V., Sudhir, K. and Vithala R. R., "Structural Analysis of Competitive behavior: New Empirical Industrial Organization Methods in Marketing," ''International Journal of Research in Marketing,'' Vol. 18, 2001, pp 161–186&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Emerging issues analysis|Emerging Issues Analysis]]&lt;ref&gt;Terranova, D., "Navigating by the Stars: Using Futures Methodologies to Create a Preferred Vision for the Workforce, a Case Study" ''Journal of Futures Studies,'' Vol. 12, No. 3, 2008, pp. 31–44&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Experience curve effects|Experience curve analysis]]&lt;ref&gt;Hall, G. and Howell, S., "The Experience Curve from the Economist's Perspective," ''Strategic Management Journal,'' Vol. 6, No. 3, 1985, pp 197–212, DOI: 10.1002/smj.4250060302 Online: http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/smj.4250060302/abstract;Schnaars, S.P., ''Marketing Strategy,'' The Free Press, 1998, pp 51-59&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Gap analysis]]
* [[Herfindahl index]] &lt;ref&gt;Farris, P., Bendle, N.,  Pfeifer, P. and Reibstein, D., ''Marketing Metrics: The Manager's Guide to Measuring Marketing Performance,'' [E-book edition], FT Press, 2015, Chapter 1 &lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Change impact analysis|impact analysis]]&lt;ref&gt;World Bank, ''A Users’ Guide to Poverty and Social Impact Analysis,'' 2003&lt;/ref&gt;
* Industry Analysis (also known as [[Porter's five forces analysis]])&lt;ref&gt;Aaker, D. A. and Mills, M. K. ''Strategic Market Management,'' Pacific Rim ed., Wiley, pp. 139–40; Aaker, D. A. and Mills, M. K. ''Strategic Market Management,'' Pacific Rim ed., Wiley, pp. 88–94; Porter, M., “How to Conduct an Industry Analysis,” Appendix A in ''Competitive Strategy,'' 1981&lt;/ref&gt;
* Management profiling
* [[Market segmentation]] analysis&lt;ref&gt;Dickson, P. R. and Ginter, J. L. "Market Segmentation, Product Differentiation, and Marketing Strategy," ''Journal of Marketing,'' Vol. 51, No. 2, 1987, pp. 1–10, DOI: 10.2307/1251125, Stable URL: https://www.jstor.org/stable/1251125&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Market share analysis]]
* [[Market Segmentation]] analysis  &lt;ref&gt;Hunt, S.D. and Arnett, D.B., "Market Segmentation Strategy, Competitive Advantage, and Public Policy: Grounding Segmentation Strategy in Resource-Advantage Theory," ''Australasian Marketing Journal,'' Vol. 12, No. 1, 2004, pp 7-25&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Perceptual mapping]]&lt;ref&gt;McDonald, M. and Leppard, J., ''Marketing By Matrix, 100 Practical Ways to Improve Your Strategic and Tactical Marketing,''  Lincolnwood, Ill., NTC, 1993&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[PEST analysis]] and its variants including PESTLE, STEEPLED and STEER (PEST is occasionally known as [[Six Segment Analysis]])
* Portfolio analysis, such as [[Growth–share matrix|BCG growth-share matrix]] or [[GE multifactoral analysis|GE business screen matrix]]&lt;ref&gt;Aaker, D. A. and Mills, M. K. ''Strategic Market Management,'' Pacific Rim ed., Wiley, pp. 38–39; Porter, M., Appendix A in ''Competitive Strategy,'' NY, Free Press, 1980, pp. 361–376&lt;/ref&gt;
* Precursor Analysis or Evolutionary analysis&lt;ref&gt;Foxall, G. R. and Fawn, J. R., "An evolutionary model of technological innovation as a strategic management process," ''Technovation.'' Vol. 12, No. 3, 1992, pp. 191–202, https://doi.org/10.1016/0166-4972(92)90035-G&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Product life-cycle management (marketing)|Product life cycle analysis]] and S-curve analysis (also known as [[technology life cycle]] or [[hype cycle]] analysis)
* Product evolutionary cycle analysis&lt;ref&gt;Holak, S. L. and Tang, E., “Advertising’s Effect on the Product Evolutionary Cycle,” ''Journal of Marketing,'' Vol. 54, July, 1990, p. 20; Lambkin, M. and Day, G. S., "Evolutionary Processes in Competitive Markets: Beyond the Product Life Cycle," ''Journal of Marketing,'' Vol. 53, No. 3. pp. 4–20, DOI: 10.2307/1251339, Stable URL: https://www.jstor.org/stable/1251339; Tellis, G. J. and Crawford, C. M. "An Evolutionary Approach to Product Growth Theory," ''Journal of Marketing,'' Vol. 45, No. 4, pp. 125–132, DOI: 10.2307/1251480, Stable URL: https://www.jstor.org/stable/1251480&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Scenario analysis]]&lt;ref&gt;Aaker, D. A. and Mills, M. K. ''Strategic Market Management,'' Pacific Rim ed., Wiley, pp. 81–83&lt;/ref&gt;
* Segment Share Analysis
* [[Situation analysis]]&lt;ref&gt;West, D., Ford, J. and Ibrahim, E., ''Strategic Marketing: Creating Competitive Advantage,'' Oxford, Oxford University Press, 2010, p. 80&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Strategic group|Strategic Group Analysis]] &lt;ref&gt;West, D., Ford, J. and Ibrahim, E., ''Strategic Marketing: Creating Competitive Advantage,'' Oxford, Oxford University Press, 2010, p. 82&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[SWOT analysis]]&lt;ref&gt;Helms, M. M. and Nixon, J., "Exploring SWOT analysis – where are we now?: A review of academic research from the last decade", ''Journal of Strategy and Management,'' Vol. 3, No. 3, 2010, pp. 215–251, https://doi.org/10.1108/17554251011064837&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Trend analysis|Trend Analysis]]&lt;ref&gt;Aaker, D. A. and Mills, M. K. ''Strategic Market Management,'' Pacific Rim ed., Wiley, 2005, pp. 143–45&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Value chain]] analysis&lt;ref&gt;Aaker, D. A. and Mills, M. K. ''Strategic Market Management,'' Pacific Rim ed., Wiley, pp. 142–43; Porter, M.,''Competitive advantage: Creating and Sustaining Superior Performance,'' cited in Kotler. P., ''Marketing Management,'' 2000, p. 44&lt;/ref&gt;

===Brief description of gap analysis===

Gap analysis is a type of higher order analysis that seeks to identify the difference between the organisation's current strategy and its desired strategy. This difference is sometimes known as the ''strategic gap.'' Mintzberg identifies two types of strategy namely ''deliberate strategy'' and ''inadvertent strategy.'' The deliberate strategy represents the firm's strategic intent or its desired path while the inadvertent strategy represents the path that the firm may have followed as it adjusted to environmental, competitive and market changes.&lt;ref&gt;Henry Mintzberg, ''The Rise and Fall of Strategic Planning,'' Prentice-Hall, 1994, pp. 24-27&lt;/ref&gt; Other scholars use the terms ''realized strategy'' versus ''intended'' strategy to refer to the same concepts.&lt;ref&gt;Ferrell, O. C., Lucas Jr, G. H. and Luck, D. J., ''Marketing Strategy,'' South Western, 1994&lt;/ref&gt; This type of analysis indicates whether an organisation has strayed from its desired path during the planning period. The presence of a large gap may indicate the organisation has become ''stuck in the middle''; a recipe for strategic mediocrity and potential failure.

===Brief description of Category/Brand Development Index===

The category/brand development index is a method used to assess the sales potential for a region or market and identify market segments that can be developed (i.e. high CDI and high BDI). In addition, it may be used to identify markets where the category or brand is under-performing and may signal underlying marketing problems such as poor distribution (i.e. high CDI and low BDI).

BDI and CDI are calculated as follows:&lt;ref&gt;Scissors, J. and Baron, R., ''Advertising Media Planning,'' 6th ed, Mc Graw-Hill 2002, pp. 182–187&lt;/ref&gt;

:: BDI =  (Brand Sales (%) in Market A/ Population (%) in Market A) X 100
:: CDI = (Category Sales (%) in Market/ Population (%) in Market A) X 100

===Brief description of PEST analysis===
[[File:Pest-analysis.jpg|thumb|PEST analysis: variables that may be considered in the environmental scan]]
Strategic planning typically begins with a scan of the business environment, both internal and external, this includes understanding strategic constraints.&lt;ref&gt;Aaker, David ''Strategic Market Management'' 2008. {{ISBN|978-0-470-05623-3}}.&lt;/ref&gt; An understanding of the external operating environment, including political, economic, social and technological which includes demographic and cultural aspects, is necessary for the identification of business opportunities and threats.&lt;ref name="Aaker David" /&gt; This analysis is called [[PEST analysis|PEST]]; an acronym for '''P'''olitical, '''E'''conomic, '''S'''ocial and '''T'''echnological. A number of variants of the PEST analysis can be identified in literature, including: PESTLE analysis (Political, Economic, Social, Technological, Legal and Environmental); STEEPLE (adds ethics); STEEPLED (adds demographics) and STEER (adds regulatory).&lt;ref&gt;Sammut-Bonnici, T. and Galea, F., "PEST Analysis" in ''Wiley Encyclopedia of Management,''John Wiley, 2015, p. 1 &lt;Online: https://www.researchgate.net/publication/257303449_PEST_Analysis&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;

The aim of the PEST analysis is to identify opportunities and threats in the wider operating environment. Firms try to leverage opportunities while trying to buffer themselves against potential threats. Basically, the PEST analysis guides strategic decision-making.&lt;ref&gt;Oxford Reference Online &lt;http://www.oxfordreference.com/view/10.1093/oi/authority.20110803100319664&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; The main elements of the PEST analysis are:&lt;ref&gt;Sammut-Bonnici, T. and Galea, F., "PEST Analysis" in ''Wiley Encyclopedia of Management,''John Wiley, 2015, pp. 2–6 &lt;Online: https://www.researchgate.net/publication/257303449_PEST_Analysis&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;

:* '''P'''olitical: political interventions with the potential to disrupt or enhance trading conditions e.g. government statutes, policies, funding or subsidies, support for specific industries, trade agreements, tax rates and fiscal policy.
:* '''E'''conomic: economic factors with the potential to affect profitability and the prices that can be charged, such as, economic trends, inflation, exchange rates, seasonality and economic cycles, consumer confidence, consumer purchasing power and discretionary incomes.
:* '''S'''ocial: social factors that affect demand for products and services, consumer attitudes, tastes and preferences like demographics, social influencers, role models, shopping habits.
:* '''T'''echnological: Innovation, technological developments or breakthroughs that create opportunities for new products, improved production processes or new ways of transacting business e.g. new materials, new ingredients, new machinery, new packaging solutions, new software and new intermediaries.

When carrying out a PEST analysis, planners and analysts may consider the operating environment at three levels, namely ''the supranational''; ''the national'' and ''subnational'' or local level. As businesses become more globalized, they may need to pay greater attention to the supranational level.&lt;ref&gt;Sammut-Bonnici, T. and Galea, F., "PEST Analysis" in ''Wiley Encyclopedia of Management,''John Wiley, 2015, p. 5&lt;/ref&gt;

===Brief description of SWOT analysis===

[[File:SWOT en.svg|thumb|A SWOT analysis, with its four elements in a 2×2 matrix.]]

In addition to the PEST analysis, firms carry out a Strengths, Weakness, Opportunities and Threats [[SWOT analysis|(SWOT) analysis]]. A SWOT analysis identifies:&lt;ref&gt;Fine, L. H., ''The SWOT Analysis: Using your Strength to Overcome Weaknesses, Using Opportunities to Overcome Threats,''Kickit LLC, 2010,&lt;/ref&gt; 
:* Strengths: distinctive capabilities, competencies, skills or assets that provide a business or project with an advantage over potential rivals; internal factors that are favourable to achieving company objectives 
:* Weaknesses: internal deficiencies that place the business or project at a disadvantage relative to rivals; or deficiencies that prevent an entity from moving in a new direction or acting on opportunities. internal factors that are unfavourable to achieving company objectives
:* Opportunities: elements in the environment that the business or project could exploit to its advantage
:* Threats: elements in the environment that could erode the firm's market position; external factors that prevent or hinder an entity from moving in a desired direction or achieving its goals.

Typically the firm will attempt to leverage those opportunities that can be matched with internal strengths; that is to say the firm has a capability in any area where strengths are matched with external opportunities. It may need to build capability if it wishes to leverage opportunities in areas of weakness. An area of weakness that is matched with an external threat represents a vulnerability, and the firm may need to develop contingency plans.&lt;ref&gt;Piercy, N., ''Market-Led Strategic Change,'' Butterworth-Heinemann, 2009, p. 321&lt;/ref&gt;

==Developing the vision and mission==

The vision and mission address the second central question, 'Where are we going?' At the conclusion of the research and analysis stage, the firm will typically review its [[vision statement]], [[mission statement]] and, if necessary, devise a new vision and mission for the outlook period. At this stage, the firm will also devise a generic competitive strategy as the basis for maintaining a sustainable competitive advantage for the forthcoming planning period. 

A vision statement is a realistic, long term future scenario for the organisation. (Vision statements should not be confused with slogans or mottos.)&lt;ref&gt;Lucas, J. R., "Anatomy of a Vision Statement," ''Management Review,'' Vol. 87,  No. 2, 1998, pp. 22–26&lt;/ref&gt; A vision statement is designed to present a realistic long-term future scenario for the organisation. It is a "clearly articulated statement of the business scope." A strong vision statement typically includes the following:&lt;ref&gt;Aaker, D. and Mills, M. K., ''Strategic Market Management,'' Pacific-rim edition, Wiley, 2001, pp. 28–29&lt;/ref&gt;
:* Competitive scope
:* Market scope
:* Geographic scope
:* Vertical scope
Some scholars point out the market visioning is a skill or competency that encapsulates the planners' capacity "to link advanced technologies to market opportunities of the future, and to do so through a shared understanding of a given product market.&lt;ref&gt;Susan E. Reid and Ulrike de Brentani, “The Impact of Market Vision on Early Success with Leader Users” ANZMAC, 2006 www.anzmac.org&lt;/ref&gt;

A mission statement is  a clear and concise statement of the organisation’s reason for being and its scope of operations,&lt;ref&gt;Pearce, J. A., and David, F., "Corporate Mission Statements: The Bottom Line," ''The Academy of Management Executive,'' Vol. 1, No. 2, pp. 109–116&lt;/ref&gt; while the generic strategy outlines how the company intends to achieve both its vision and mission.&lt;ref&gt;Campbell-Hunt, C., "What Have We Learned about Generic Competitive Strategy?" ''Strategic Management Journal,'' Vol. 21, 2000, pp. 127–154&lt;/ref&gt;

Mission statements should include detailed information and must be more than a simple ''motherhood statement''.&lt;ref&gt;Pierce, E. M., "Developing, Implementing and Monitoring an Information Product Quality Strategy," ''Proceedings of the Ninth International Conference on Information Quality,'' 2004&lt;/ref&gt; A mission statement typically includes the following:&lt;ref&gt;Pearce, J. A., and David, F., "Corporate Mission Statements: The Bottom Line," ''The Academy of Management Executive,'' Vol. 1, No. 2, p. 109&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Mission statement.png|thumb|This mission statement might be described as a "motherhood statement" because it lacks sufficient detail to be meaningful]]
:* Specification of target customers 
:* Identification of principal products or services offered
:* Specification of the geographic scope of operations
:* Identification of core technologies and/or core capabilities
:* An outline of the firm's commitment to long-term survival, growth and profitability
:* An outline of the key elements in the company's philosophy and core values
:* Identification of the company's desired public image

==Developing the generic competitive strategy==

The generic competitive strategy outlines the fundamental basis for obtaining a sustainable competitive advantage within a category. Firms can normally trace their competitive position to one of three factors:&lt;ref&gt;Rumelt, R. P., "The  Evaluation  of  Business  Strategy,"  in Quinn, James  Brian; Mintzberg, Henry; and Robert M. James (eds), ''The Strategy Process,'' Englewood Cliffs, New Jersey, 1988&lt;/ref&gt;

:* Superior skills  (e.g. coordination of individual specialists, created through the interplay of investment in training and professional development, work and learning)   
:* Superior resources (e.g. patents, trade-mark protection, specialized  physical assets and  relationships with suppliers and distribution infrastructure.)    
:* Superior position (the products or services offered, the market segments served, and the extent to which the product-market can be isolated from direct competition.)

It is essential that the internal analysis provide a frank and open evaluation of the firm's superiority in terms of skills, resources or market position since this will provide the basis for competing over the forthcoming planning period. For this reason, some companies engage external consultants to provide an independent assessment of the firms capabilities and resources.

===Porter and the positioning school: approach to strategy formulation===
{{Further|Porter's generic strategies}}
[[File:Michael Porter's Three Generic Strategies.svg|thumb|Porter's Three Generic Strategies]]

In 1980, Michael Porter developed an approach to strategy formulation that proved to be extremely popular with both scholars and practitioners. The approach became known as the ''positioning school'' because of its emphasis on locating a defensible ''competitive position'' within an industry or sector. In this approach, strategy formulation consists of three key strands of thinking: analysis of the five forces to determine the sources of competitive advantage; the selection of one of three possible positions which leverage the advantage and the value chain to implement the strategy.&lt;ref&gt;Stonehouse, G. and Snowdon, B., "Competitive Advantage Revisited: Michael Porter on Strategy and Competitiveness," ''Journal of Management Inquiry,'' Vol. 16 No. 3, 2007, pp.  256–273, DOI: 10.1177/1056492607306333&lt;/ref&gt; In this approach, the strategic choices involve decisions about whether to compete for a share of the total market or for a specific target group (competitive scope) and whether to compete on costs or product differences (competitive advantage). This type of thinking leads to three generic strategies: &lt;ref&gt; Porter, Michael E., ''Competitive Strategy,'' Free Press, 1980; Porter, Michael E., ''Competitive Advantage, '' Free Press, 1985, p.12&lt;/ref&gt;

:* Cost leadership - the firm targets the mass market and attempts to be the lowest cost producer in the market 
:* Differentiation - the firm targets the mass market and tries to maintain unique points of product difference perceived as desirable by customers and for which they are prepared to pay premium prices
:* Focus - the firm does not compete head to head, but instead selects a narrow target market and focuses its efforts on satisfying the needs of that segment

According to Porter, these strategies are mutually exclusive and the firm must select one approach to the exclusion of all others.&lt;ref&gt;Porter, Michael E., ''Competitive Advantage, '' Free Press, 1985, p.12&lt;/ref&gt; Firms that try to be all things to all people can present a confused market position which ultimately leads to below average returns. Any ambiguity about the firm's approach is a recipe for "strategic mediocrity" and any firm that tries to pursue two approaches simultaneously is said to be "stuck in the middle" and destined for failure.&lt;ref&gt;Godfrey, R., ''Strategic Management: A Critical Introduction,'' [E-book edition], Oxon, Routledge, 2016 &lt;/ref&gt;

Porter's approach was the dominant paradigm throughout the 1980s. However, the approach has attracted considerable criticism. One important criticism is that it is possible to identify successful companies that pursue a hybrid strategy - such as low cost position and a differentiated position simultaneously. Toyota is a classic example of this hybrid approach.&lt;ref&gt;Stonehouse, G. and Snowdon, B., "Competitive Advantage Revisited: Michael Porter on Strategy and Competitiveness," ''Journal of Management Inquiry,'' Vol. 16 No. 3, 2007, p. 257, DOI: 10.1177/1056492607306333&lt;/ref&gt; Other scholars point to the simplistic nature of the analysis and the overly prescriptive nature of the strategic choices which limits strategies to just three options. Yet others point to research showing that many practitioners find the approach to be overly theoretical and not applicable to their business.&lt;ref&gt;de Kare-Silver M.,  "The Inadequacies of Existing Strategy Models," Chapter 4 In: ''Strategy in Crisis,'' Palgrave Macmillan, London, 1997,DOI https://doi.org/10.1057/9780230378117_4, p. 37&lt;/ref&gt;

===Resource-based view (RBV) ===
{{Further|Resource-based view}}

During the 1990s, the ''resource-based view'' (also known as the ''resource-advantage theory'') of the firm became the dominant paradigm. It is an inter-disciplinary approach that represents a substantial shift in thinking.&lt;ref&gt;Fahy, J. and Smithee, "Strategic Marketing and the Resource Based View of the Firm," ''Academy of Marketing Science Review,'' Vol. 1999 No. 10, 1999, Online: http://www.amsreview.org/articles/fahy10-1999.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; It focuses attention on an organisation's internal resources as a means of organising processes and obtaining a competitive advantage. The resource-based view suggests that organisations must develop unique, firm-specific core competencies that will allow them to outperform competitors by doing things differently and in a superior manner.&lt;ref&gt;Prahalad,  C.  K. and Hamel,  G., "The Core Competence of the Corporation," ''Harvard Business Review,'' Vol. 68, No. 3, pp.  79–91&lt;/ref&gt;  

Barney stated that for resources to hold potential as sources of sustainable competitive advantage, they should be valuable, rare and imperfectly imitable.&lt;ref&gt;Barney, J. B., "Firm Resources and Sustained Competitive Advantage." ''Journal of Management,'' Vol. 17, No. 1, 1991, pp. 99–120&lt;/ref&gt; A key insight arising from the resource-based view is that not all resources are of equal importance nor possess the potential to become a source of sustainable competitive advantage.&lt;ref&gt;Fahy, J. and Smithee, "Strategic Marketing and the Resource Based View of the Firm," ''Academy of Marketing Science Review,'' Vol. 1999 No. 10, 1999, Online: http://www.amsreview.org/articles/fahy10-1999.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; The sustainability of any competitive advantage depends on the extent to which resources can be imitated or substituted.&lt;ref&gt;Lowson, R., "The Nature of Operations Strategy: Combining Strategic Decisions from an Operations and Market based Perspective," ''Management Decision,'' Vol. 41, No, 6, pp.  538–49&lt;/ref&gt; Barney and others point out that understanding the causal relationship between the sources of advantage and successful strategies can be very difficult in practice.&lt;ref&gt;Barney, J. B., "Firm Resources and Sustained Competitive Advantage." ''Journal of Management,'' Vol. 17, No. 1, 1991, pp. 108–09; Barney uses the term "causally ambiguous" which he describes as a situation when "the link between the resources controlled by the firm and the firm's sustained competitive advantage is not understood or understood only very imperfectly." &lt;/ref&gt; Thus, a great deal of managerial effort must be invested in identifying, understanding and classifying core competencies. In addition, management must invest in organisational learning to develop and maintain key resources and competencies. 

Market Based Resources include:&lt;ref&gt;Day, G.S. and Wensley, R., “Assessing Advantage: A Framework for Diagnosing Competitive Superiority,” ''Journal of Marketing,'' vol. 52, April, 1988, pp.  1–26; Day, G. S., “The Capabilities of Market-Driven Organizations,” ''Journal of Marketing,'' Vol. 58, October, 1994, pp. 37–52; Hooley, G. J., Greenley, G. E., Fahy, J. and Cadogan, J. W. “Market-focused Resources, Competitive Positioning and Firm Performance” ''Journal of Marketing Management,'' Vol. 17, No. 5–6, 2001, pp. 503–520&lt;/ref&gt;

:* Organisational culture e.g. market orientation, research orientation, culture of innovation, etc.
:* Assets e.g. brands, Mktg IS, databases, etc.
:* Capabilities (or competencies) e.g. market sensing, marketing research, relationships, know-how, tacit knowledge, etc

In the resource-based view, strategists select the strategy or competitive position that best exploits the internal resources and capabilities relative to external opportunities. Given that strategic resources represent a complex network of inter-related assets and capabilities, organisations can adopt many possible competitive positions. Although scholars debate the precise categories of competitive positions that are used, there is general agreement, within the literature, that the resource-based view is much more flexible than Porter's prescriptive approach to strategy formulation.

Hooley et al., suggest the following classification of competitive positions:&lt;ref&gt;Hooley, G., Broderick, A. and Moller, K., "Competitive Positioning and the Resource-Based View of the Firm," ''Journal of Strategic Marketing,'' Vol. 6, 1998, pp. 97–115&lt;/ref&gt;

:* Price positioning
:* Quality positioning
:* Innovation positioning
:* Service positioning
:* Benefit positioning
:* Tailored positioning ([[Personalized marketing|one-to-one marketing]])

===Other approaches===

The choice of competitive strategy often depends on a variety of factors including: the firm's market position relative to rival firms,&lt;ref&gt;Burns, A. C., "Generating Marketing Strategy Priorities Based on  Relative Competitive Position," ''Journal of Consumer Marketing,'' Vol. 3 Issue: 4, pp. 49–56, https://doi.org/10.1108/eb008179&lt;/ref&gt; the stage of the product life cycle.&lt;ref&gt;Swan, J. E. and Rink, D. E. "Fitting market strategy to varying product life cycles," ''Business Horizons,'' Vol. 25, No. 1, 1982, pp. 72–76, https://doi.org/10.1016/0007-6813(82)90048-9&lt;/ref&gt; A well-established firm in a mature market will likely have a different strategy than a [[startup company|start-up]].


====Growth strategies====
Growth of a business is critical for business success. A firm may grow by developing the market or by developing new products. The [[Ansoff Matrix|Ansoff product and  market growth matrix]] illustrates the two broad dimensions for achieving growth. The Ansoff matrix identifies four specific growth strategies: [[market penetration]], [[New product development|product development]], [[market development]] and [[Diversification (marketing strategy)|diversification]].&lt;ref name=":6"&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.ansoffmatrix.com|title=Ansoff Matrix|last=|first=|date=|website=|publisher=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
[[File:Ansoff Matrix.JPG|thumb|The Ansoff Product/market Growth Matrix]]

:''Market penetration'' involves selling existing products to existing consumers. This is a conservative, low risk approach since the product is already on the established market.&lt;ref name=":6" /&gt; 
: ''Product development'' is the introduction of a new product to existing customers. This can include modifications to an already existing market which can create a product that has more appeal.&lt;ref name=":6" /&gt; 
:''Market development'' involves the selling of existing products to new customers in order to identify and build a new clientele base. This can include new geographical markets, new distribution channels, and different pricing policies that bring the product price within the competence of new market segments. 
:''Diversification'' is the riskiest area for a business. This is where a new product is sold to a new market. &lt;ref&gt;Haq, F., Wong, H. and Jackson, J. (2008) [http://www.wbiconpro.com/Marketing/509-Haq,F%20%26%20Others.pdf Applying Ansoff’s growth strategy matrix to Consumer Segments and Typologies in Spiritual Tourism]. ''Eighth International Business Research Conference''&lt;/ref&gt; There are two type of Diversification; horizontal and vertical. 'Horizontal diversification'' focuses more on product(s) where the business is knowledgeable, whereas ''vertical diversification'' focuses more on the introduction of new product into new markets, where the business could have less knowledge of the new market.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt; 

; Horizontal integration
A horizontal integration strategy may be indicated in fast changing work environments as well as providing a broad knowledge base for the business and employees.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite journal|url=http://bibliotecadigital.fgv.br/ojs/index.php/joscm/article/viewFile/9130/8430|author=Teixeira, R., Koufteros, X. A., Peng, X. D.|title=Organizational Structure, Integration, and Manufacturing Performance: a Conceptual Model and Propositions|journal=Journal of Operations and Supply Chain Management |volume=5 |issue=1|year=2012|pages=69–81}}&lt;/ref&gt; A benefit of horizontal diversification is that it is an open platform for a business to expand and build away from the already existing market.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt; 

High levels of horizontal integration lead to high levels of communication within the business. Another benefit of using this strategy is that it leads to a larger market for merged businesses, and it is easier to build good reputations for a business when using this strategy.&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite journal|url=http://www.dklevine.com/archive/refs4122247000000002038.pdf|title=Firm Reputation and Horizontal Integration|last1=Obara|first1=Ichiro|last2=Cai|first2=H.|journal=The RAND Journal of Economics |volume=40|issue=2|pages=340–363|year=2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; A disadvantage of using a diversification strategy is that the benefits could take a while to start showing, which could lead the business to believe that the strategy in ineffective.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt; Another disadvantage or risk is, it has been shown that using the horizontal diversification method has become harmful for stock value, but using the vertical diversification had the best effects.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|doi=10.1057/9780230626317_11|chapter=The Impact of Vertical Integration and Horizontal Diversification on the Value of Energy Firms|title=The Econometrics of Energy Systems|pages=225|year=2007|last1=Pozzi|first1=Carlo|last2=Vassilopoulos|first2=Philippe|isbn=978-1-349-54149-2|url=http://www.wec-france.org/DocumentsPDF/RECHERCHE/40_RapportfinalPartie2(inenglish).pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A disadvantage of using the horizontal integration strategy is that this limits and restricts the field of interest that the business.&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{Cite journal|url=http://www.foswiki.org/pub/Sandbox/SimiWiki/Strategies_for_diversification.pdf |title=Strategies for Diversification |author=Ansoff, I. |journal=Harvard Business Review |volume=35 |issue=5 |year=1957 |pages=113–124 |deadurl=bot: unknown |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150413042229/http://www.foswiki.org/pub/Sandbox/SimiWiki/Strategies_for_diversification.pdf |archivedate=2015-04-13 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt; Horizontal integration can affect a business's reputation, especially after a merge has happened between two or more businesses. There are three main benefits to a business's reputation after a merge. A larger business helps the reputation and increases the severity of the punishment. As well as the merge of information after a merge has happened, this increases the knowledge of the business and marketing area they are focused on. The last benefit is more opportunities for deviation to occur in merged businesses rather than independent businesses.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;

; Vertical integration

Vertical integration is when business is expanded through the vertical production line on one business. An example of a vertically integrated business could be Apple. Apple owns all their own software, hardware, designs and operating systems instead of relying on other businesses to supply these.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://munin.uit.no/bitstream/handle/10037/2546/paper_3.pdf;jsessionid=EA9ACC5D1937248F507C45859394C53E?sequence=2|title=The Impact of Measurements and Industry|last=Isaksen|first=John R|date=|website=|publisher=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; By having a highly vertically integrated business this creates different economies therefore creating a positive performance for the business.&lt;ref name=":3"&gt;{{Cite journal|title=The Revival of Vertical Integration: Strategic Choice and Performance Influences |journal=Journal of Management and Strategy|last=Zhang|first=Dongli|date=2013|volume=4|issue=1|doi=10.5430/jms.v4n1p1}}&lt;/ref&gt; Vertical integration is seen as a business controlling the inputs of supplies and outputs of products as well as the distribution of the final product.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt; Some benefits of using a Vertical integration strategy is that costs may be reduced because of the reducing transaction costs which include finding, selling, monitoring, contracting and negotiating with other firms. Also by decreasing outside businesses input it will increase the efficient use of inputs into the business. Another benefit of vertical integration is that it improves the exchange of information through the different stages of the production line.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt; Some competitive advantages could include; avoiding foreclosures, improving the business marketing intelligence, and opens up opportunities to create different products for the market.&lt;ref&gt;Harrigan, K.R., "Formulating Vertical Integration Strategies," ''The Academy of Management Review,'' Vol. 9, No. 4, 1984 , pp. 638-652, DOI: 10.2307/258487, Stable URL: https://www.jstor.org/stable/258487&lt;/ref&gt; Some disadvantages of using a Vertical Integration Strategy include the internal costs for the business and the need for overhead costs. Also if the business is not well organised and fully equipped and prepared the business will struggle using this strategy. There are also competitive disadvantages as well, which include; creates barriers for the business, and loses access to information from suppliers and distributors.&lt;ref&gt;Harrigan, K.R., "Formulating Vertical Integration Strategies," ''The Academy of Management Review,'' Vol. 9, No. 4, 1984 , pp. 638-652, DOI: 10.2307/258487, Stable URL: https://www.jstor.org/stable/258487&lt;/ref&gt;

====Market position and strategy====
In terms of market position, firms may be classified as market leaders, market challengers, market followers or market nichers.&lt;ref&gt;While this classification is not the only way to think about competitors, it is very widely used. See for example: Aaker, D. and Mills, M. K., ''Strategic Market Management,'' Pacific Rim edition, Wiley, 2001; Dibb, D., Simkin, L., Pride, W. &amp; Ferrell, O. C., ''Marketing: Concepts and Strategies,'' Houghton, Boston, 1991&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Market position and strategic requirements.jpg|thumb|Market position and strategic implications]]

: ''Market leader'': The market leader dominates the market by objective measure of market share. Their overall posture is defensive because they have more to lose. Their objectives are to reinforce their prominent position through the use of PR to develop corporate image and to block competitors brand for brand, matching distribution through tactics such as the use of “fighting” brands, pre-emptive strikes, use of regulation to block competitors and even to spread rumours about competitors. Market leaders may adopt unconventional or unexpected approaches to building growth and their tactical responses are likely to include: product proliferation; diversification; multi-branding; erecting barriers to entry; vertical and horizontal integration and corporate acquisitions.

: ''Market challenger'': The market challenger holds the second highest market share in the category, following closely behind the dominant player. Their market posture is generally offensive because they have less to lose and more to gain by taking risks. They will compete head to head with the market leader in an effort to grow market share. Their overall strategy is to gain market share through product, packaging and service innovations; new market development and redefinition of the to broaden its scope and their position within it.

: ''Market follower'': Followers are generally content to play second fiddle. They rarely invest in R &amp; D and tend to wait for market leaders to develop innovative products and subsequently adopt a “me-too” approach. Their market posture is typically neutral. Their strategy is to maintain their market position by maintaining existing customers and capturing a fair share of any new segments. They tend to maintain profits by controlling costs.

: ''Market nicher'': The market nicher occupies a small niche in the market in order to avoid head to head competition. Their objective is to build strong ties with the customer base and develop strong loyalty with existing customers. Their market posture is generally neutral. Their strategy is to develop and build the segment and protect it from erosion. Tactically, nichers are likely to improve the product or service offering, leverage cross-selling opportunities, offer value for money and build relationships through superior after sales service, service quality and other related value adding activities.

As the speed of change in the marketing environment quickens, time horizons are becoming shorter. Nevertheless, most firms carry out strategic planning every 3- 5 years and treat the process as a means of checking whether the company is on track to achieve its vision and mission.&lt;ref name="Aaker David"&gt;Aaker, David ''Strategic Market Management'' 2008. {{ISBN|978-0-470-05623-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ideally, strategies are both dynamic and interactive, partially planned and partially unplanned. Strategies are broad in their scope in order to enable a firm to react to unforeseen developments while trying to keep focused on a specific pathway. A key aspect of marketing strategy is to keep marketing consistent with a company's overarching [[mission statement]].&lt;ref&gt;Baker, Michael (2008 ) ''The Strategic Marketing Plan Audit''. p. 27. {{ISBN|1-902433-99-8}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Strategies often specify how to adjust the [[marketing mix]]; firms can use tools such as [[Marketing Mix Modeling]] to help them decide how to allocate scarce resources, as well as how to allocate funds across a portfolio of brands. In addition, firms can conduct analyses of performance, customer analysis, [[competitor analysis]], and [[target market]] analysis.

==== Entry strategies ====

{{See|Market entry strategy}}

Marketing strategies may differ depending on the unique situation of the individual business. According to Lieberman and Montgomery, every entrant into a market – whether it is new or not – is classified under a Market Pioneer, Close Follower or a Late follower&lt;ref name="First-Mover Advantages"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Lieberman|first1=M.|last2=Montgomery|first2=D.|title=First-Mover Advantages|journal=Strategic Management Journal|volume=9|date=1998|issue=9|pages=41–58|doi=10.1002/smj.4250090706|url=http://www.anderson.ucla.edu/faculty/marvin.lieberman/publications/FMA1-SMJ1988.pdf|jstor=3094199}}&lt;/ref&gt; {{failed verification|date=December 2017}}

=====Pioneers =====

Market pioneers are known to often open a new market to consumers based off a major innovation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Farris, Paul W. |author2=Moore, Michael J. |title=The Profit Impact of Marketing Strategy Project: Retrospect and Prospects|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=fboPnwEACAAJ|date=4 November 2004|publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=978-0-521-84053-8|page=81}}&lt;/ref&gt; They emphasise these product developments, and in a significant amount of cases, studies have shown that early entrants – or pioneers – into a market have serious market-share advantages above all those who enter later.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Kalyanaram|first1=G.|last2=Gurumurthy|first2=R.|title=Market Entry Strategies: Pioneers versus Late Arrivals|journal=Strategy and Business|url=http://www.strategy-business.com/article/18881?gko=64116|date=1998|pages=74–84}}&lt;/ref&gt; Pioneers have the first-mover advantage, and in order to have this advantage, business’ must ensure they have at least one or more of three primary sources: Technological Leadership, Preemption of Assets or Buyer Switching Costs.&lt;ref name="First-Mover Advantages"/&gt; Technological Leadership means gaining an advantage through either Research and Development or the “learning curve”.&lt;ref name="First-Mover Advantages"/&gt; This lets a business use the research and development stage as a key point of selling due to primary research of a new or developed product. Preemption of Assets can help gain an advantage through acquiring scarce assets within a certain market, allowing the first-mover to be able to have control of existing assets rather than those that are created through new technology.&lt;ref name="First-Mover Advantages"/&gt; Thus allowing pre-existing information to be used and a lower risk when first entering a new market. By being a first entrant, it is easy to avoid higher switching costs compared to later entrants. For example, those who enter later would have to invest more expenditure in order to encourage customers away from early entrants.&lt;ref name="First-Mover Advantages"/&gt; However, while Market Pioneers may have the “highest probability of engaging in product development”&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Robinson|first1=W.|last2=Chiang|first2=J.|title=Product Development Strategies for Established Market Pioneers, Early Followers, and Late Entrants|doi=10.1002/smj.257|journal=Strategic Management Journal|date=2002|volume=23|issue=9|pages=855–866}}&lt;/ref&gt; and lower switching costs, to have the first-mover advantage, it can be more expensive due to product innovation being more costly than product imitation. It has been found that while Pioneers in both consumer goods and industrial markets have gained “significant sales advantages”,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Boulding|first1=W.|last2=Christen|first2=M.|title=First-Mover Disadvantage|url=https://hbr.org/2001/10/first-mover-disadvantage|website=Harvard Business Review|accessdate=31 March 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; they incur larger disadvantages cost-wise.

=====Close followers =====

Being a Market Pioneer can, more often than not, attract entrepreneurs and/or investors depending on the benefits of the market. If there is an upside potential and the ability to have a stable market share, many businesses would start to follow in the footsteps of these pioneers. These are more commonly known as Close Followers. These entrants into the market can also be seen as challengers to the Market Pioneers and the Late Followers. This is because early followers are more than likely to invest a significant amount in Product Research and Development than later entrants.&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"/&gt; By doing this, it allows businesses to find weaknesses in the products produced before, thus leading to improvements and expansion on the aforementioned product. Therefore, it could also lead to customer preference, which is essential in market success.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Fifield|first1=P.|title=Marketing Strategy|date=2008|publisher=Routledge}}&lt;/ref&gt; Due to the nature of early followers and the research time being later than Market Pioneers, different development strategies are used as opposed to those who entered the market in the beginning,&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"/&gt; and the same is applied to those who are Late Followers in the market. By having a different strategy, it allows the followers to create their own unique selling point and perhaps target a different audience in comparison to that of the Market Pioneers. Early following into a market can often be encouraged by an established business’ product that is “threatened or has industry-specific supporting assets”.&lt;ref name="ReferenceB"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Robinson|first1=W.|last2=Fornell|first2=C.|last3=Sullivan|first3=M.|title=Are Market Pioneers Intrinsically Stronger Than Later Entrants?|doi=10.1002/smj.4250130804|journal=Strategic Management Journal|date=1992|volume=13|issue=8|pages=609–624}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=====Late Entrants =====

Those who follow after the Close Followers are known as the Late Entrants. While being a Late Entrant can seem very daunting, there are some perks to being a latecomer. For example, Late Entrants have the ability to learn from those who are already in the market or have previously entered.&lt;ref name="ReferenceB"/&gt; Late Followers have the advantage of learning from their early competitors and improving the benefits or reducing the total costs. This allows them to create a strategy that could essentially mean gaining market share and most importantly, staying in the market. In addition to this, markets evolve, leading to consumers wanting improvements and advancements on products.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Haleblian|first1=J.|last2=Mcnamara|first2=G.|last3=Kolev|first3=K.|last4=Dykes|first4=B.|title=Exploring Firm Characteristics That Differentiate Leaders From Followers In Industry Merger Waves: A Competitive Dynamics Perspective|doi=10.1002/smj.1961|journal=Strategic Management Journal|date=2012|volume=33|issue=9|pages=1037–1052}}&lt;/ref&gt; Late Followers have the advantage of catching the shifts in customer needs and wants towards the products.&lt;ref name="First-Mover Advantages"/&gt; When bearing in mind customer preference, customer value has a significant influence. Customer value means taking into account the investment of customers as well as the brand or product.&lt;ref name="ReferenceC"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Christopher|first1=M.|title=From Brand Values to Customer Value|journal=Journal of Marketing Practice: Applied Marketing Science|volume=2|pages=55–66|doi=10.1108/EUM0000000000007|year=1996}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is created through the “perceptions of benefits” and the “total cost of ownership”.&lt;ref name="ReferenceC"/&gt; On the other hand, if the needs and wants of consumers have only slightly altered, Late Followers could have a cost advantage over early entrants due to the use of product imitation.&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"/&gt; However, if a business is switching markets, this could take the cost advantage away due to the expense of changing markets for the business. Late Entry into a market does not necessarily mean there is a disadvantage when it comes to market share, it depends on how the marketing mix is adopted and the performance of the business.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Wilkie|first1=D.|last2=Johnson|first2=L.|last3=White|first3=L.|title=Overcoming late entry: the importance of entry position, inferences and market leadership|doi=10.1080/0267257X.2014.981567|journal=Journal of Marketing Management|date=2015|volume=31|issue=3–4|page=424}}&lt;/ref&gt; If the marketing mix is not used correctly – despite the entrant time – the business will gain little to no advantages, potentially missing out on a significant opportunity.

'''The differentiated strategy'''
{{Further|Marketing Mix Modeling}}
'''The customised target strategy'''
{{Further|Strategy dynamics}}

The requirements of individual customer markets are unique, and their purchases sufficient to make viable the design of a new marketing mix for each customer.

If a company adopts this type of market strategy, a separate marketing mix is to be designed for each customer.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=foundations of marketing|last=|first=|publisher=|year=2016|isbn=|location=|pages=|quote=|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Specific marketing mixes can be developed to appeal to most of the segments when market segmentation reveals several potential targets.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=foundations of marketing|last=|first=|publisher=|year=2015|isbn=|location=|pages=128|quote=|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Developing marketing goals and objectives ==

Whereas the vision and mission provide the framework, the "goals define targets within the mission, which, when achieved, should move the organization toward the performance of that mission."&lt;ref&gt;Sawyer, G. C., ''Designing Strategy,'' 1986, p. 5 &lt;/ref&gt; ''Goals'' are broad primary outcomes whereas, ''objectives'' are measurable steps taken to achieve a goal or strategy.&lt;ref&gt;Belicove, M. R., "Understanding Goals, Strategy, Objectives And Tactics In The Age Of Social," ''Forbes,'' 27 September, 2013, Online: https://www.forbes.com/sites/mikalbelicove/2013/09/27/understanding-goals-strategies-objectives-and-tactics-in-the-age-of-social/#1e07d4a54c79&lt;/ref&gt; In strategic planning, it is important for managers to translate the overall strategy into goals and objectives. Goals are designed to inspire action and focus attention on specific desired outcomes. Objectives, on the other hand, are used to measure an organisation's performance on specific dimensions, thereby providing the organisation with feedback on how well it is achieving its goals and strategies. 

Managers typically establish objectives using the ''[[balanced scorecard]]'' approach. This means that objectives do not include desired financial outcomes exclusively, but also specify measures of performance  for customers (e.g. satisfaction, loyalty, repeat patronage), internal processes (e.g., employee satisfaction, productivity) and innovation and improvement activities.&lt;ref&gt;Kaplan, S. and Norton, D. P., "Putting the Balanced Scorecard to Work," in ''Focusing Your Organization on Strategy—with the Balanced Scorecard,'' [Harvard Business Review Collection], 2nd edition, 1993&lt;/ref&gt; 

After setting the goals marketing strategy or [[marketing plan]] should be developed. The marketing strategy plan provides an outline of the specific actions to be taken over time to achieve the objectives. Plans can be extended to cover many years, with sub-plans for each year.  Plans usually involve monitoring, to assess progress, and prepare for contingencies if problems arise. Simultaneous such as [[customer lifetime value]] models can be used to help marketers conduct "what-if" analyses to forecast what potential scenarios arising from possible actions, and to gauge how specific actions might affect such variables as the revenue-per-customer and the [[churn rate]].

==Strategy typologies==
Developing competitive strategy requires significant judgement and is based on a deep understanding of the firm's current situation, its past history and its operating environment. No heuristics have yet been developed to assist strategists choose the optimal strategic direction. Nevertheless some researchers and scholars have sought to classify broad groups of strategy approaches that might serve as broad frameworks for thinking about suitable choices.

===Raymond Miles' strategy categories===
In 2003, [[Raymond Miles]] proposed a detailed scheme using the categories:&lt;ref&gt;Miles, R. and Snow, C. C., ''Organizational Strategy, Structure, and Process,'' Stanford University Press, 2003, {{ISBN|0-8047-4840-3}}, p. 29&lt;/ref&gt;
* Prospectors: proactively seek to locate and exploit new market opportunities
* Analyzers: are very innovative in their product-market choices; tend to follow prospectors into new markets; often introduce new or improved product designs
* Defenders: are relatively cautious in their initiatives; seek to seal off a portion of the market which they can defend against competitive incursions; often market highest quality offerings and position as a quality leader
* Reactors: tend to vacillate in their responses to environmental changes and are generally the least profitable organisations

===Marketing warfare===

[[Marketing warfare strategies]] are competitor-centered strategies drawn from analogies with the field of military science. Warfare strategies were popular in the 1980s, but interest in this approach has waned in the new era of relationship marketing. An increased awareness of the distinctions between business and military cultures also raises questions about the extent to which this type of analogy is useful.&lt;ref&gt;Laufer, D., "Marketing Warfare Strategies," in ''Wiley International Encyclopedia of Marketing, Vol 1, 2010&lt;/ref&gt; In spite of its limitations, the typology of marketing warfare strategies is useful for predicting and understanding competitor responses.

In the 1980s, Kotler and Singh developed a typology of marketing warfare strategies:&lt;ref&gt;Kotler, P. and Singh, E., "Marketing Warfare in the 1980s," in ''Marketing: Critical Perspectives on Business and Management,'' Vol 3, Michael John Baker (ed),Taylor and Francis, 2001&lt;/ref&gt;

:* Frontal attack: where an aggressor goes head to head for the same market segments on an offer by offer, price by price basis; normally used by a market challenger against a more dominant player 
:* Flanking attack: attacking an organisation on its weakest front; used by market challengers
:* Bypass attack: bypassing the market leader by attacking smaller, more vulnerable target organisations in order to broaden the aggressor's resource base 
:* Encirclement attack: attacking a dominant player on all fronts
:* Guerilla warfare: sporadic, unexpected attacks using both conventional and unconventional means to attack a rival; normally practiced by smaller players against the market leader

==Relationship between the marketing strategy and the marketing mix==

The generic, competitive strategy provides overall structure and guidance for day-to-day operational planning and decision-making. The 4P’s (Price, Product, Place and Promotion), also known as the marketing mix or marketing program represent the tools that marketers can use in day-to-day operational planning. This marketing program enables marketers a means for turning the long-term vision into every day practice. By tweaking the elements of the marketing mix, marketers can  adjust the offer to meet different requirements for the current situation.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|doi=10.5539/ijms.v1n1p2|title=A Review of Marketing Mix: 4P's or More|last=Goi|first=Chai Lee|date=2009|volume=1|issue=1|journal=International Journal of Marketing Studies}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Asymmetric competition]]
* [[Business model]]
* [[Business triage]] 
* [[Corporate anniversary]]
* [[Customer engagement]]
* [[First-mover advantage]]
* [[Marketing]]
* [[Market segmentation]]
* [[Pricing strategies]]
* [[Right-time marketing]]
* [[Strategic planning]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
*[[Richard Laermer|Laermer, Richard]]; Simmons, Mark, ''Punk Marketing'', New York : Harper Collins, 2007 {{ISBN|978-0-06-115110-1}} (Review of the book by Marilyn Scrizzi, in ''Journal of Consumer Marketing'' 24(7), 2007)

==External links==
*{{Commonscat-inline}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Marketing Strategy}}
[[Category:Marketing strategy| ]]
[[Category:Business]]</text>
      <sha1>lvn2gslvd5497g6b1bz98mv0f50e7aq</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Registered office</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2633364</id>
    <revision>
      <id>846930632</id>
      <parentid>846929436</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-06-21T19:26:29Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ehrenkater</username>
        <id>7126990</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* In the United Kingdom */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="3777">{{Globalize|date=July 2010}}
A '''registered office''' is the official address of an [[Incorporation (business)|incorporated]] [[company (law)|company]], association or any other [[Juristic person|legal entity]]. Generally it will form part of the public record and is required in most countries where the registered [[organization]] or legal entity is incorporated.&lt;ref&gt;Andersen, Arthur. ''The European Film Production Guide: Finance, Tax, Legislation''. [[Routledge]], 1996. [https://books.google.com/books?id=_14gq_KsRwMC&amp;pg=PA21&amp;dq=%22Registered+office%22+definition&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=1tAuTPSHDcWqlAfJwIyTCQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CDIQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22Registered%20office%22%20definition&amp;f=false 21]. Retrieved from [[Google Books]] on 3 July 2010. {{ISBN|0-415-13665-2}}, {{ISBN|978-0-415-13665-5}}.&lt;/ref&gt; A registered physical office address is required for incorporated organizations to receive official correspondence and formal notices from government departments, investors, banks, shareholders and the general public.&lt;ref name="A&amp;T"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Adirondack|first1=Sandy|last2=Taylor|first2=James Sinclair|title=Voluntary sector legal handbook|date=2008|publisher=Directory of Social Change|location=London|isbn=9781903991879|edition=3rd}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|209}}

==In the United Kingdom==
In the [[United Kingdom]] and many other [[List of country legal systems#Common law|common law countries]], the registered office address does not have to be where the organization conducts its actual business or trade, and it is not unusual for [[law firms]], [[accountant]]s or incorporation agents to provide the official registered office address service. In the United Kingdom all statutory correspondence for an incorporated organization (e.g. formal notices, [[service of process]], tax and government communications) is posted or hand delivered to the registered office address as recorded on the [[Companies House]] register. A registered physical office address is required for incorporated organizations to receive official correspondence and formal notices from government departments, investors, banks, shareholders and the general public.&lt;ref name="A&amp;T"/&gt;{{rp|209}}

Under regulations implemented in the UK on 1 October 2009, company directors may now also use a registered office address instead of their private home address for contact on the Companies House register.

The company's full registered name must be visible to the public on the premises. The Company's records previously had to be kept at the registered office and available for public inspection. Since 1 October 2009 it has been possible for companies to designate a single alternative inspection location (SAIL) as a place to keep their records which must be available for public inspection.&lt;ref name="A&amp;T"/&gt;{{rp|210}}

==Other countries==
In many other countries the address with which a company is registered must be where its headquarters or [[Seat (legal entity)|seat]] is located, and this will often determine the subnational registry at which the company must be registered.

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Portal|Companies}}
*[http://www.companieshouse.gov.uk/ Companies House] holds the registration details of UK companies
*[http://www.companieshouse.gov.uk/about/gbhtml/gp1.shtml#ch1 Incorporating a company] UK Companies House guidance including explanation of registered office
*[http://www.business.govt.nz/companies/learn-about/companies/company-addresses Company addresses] NZ Companies Office guidance on registered office address
{{Use dmy dates|date=December 2010}}  
*[http://www.hmrc.gov.uk  HM Revenue and Customs] Link to UK Government Agency HMRC

{{DEFAULTSORT:Registered Office}}
[[Category:Business]]
[[Category:Address (geography)]]</text>
      <sha1>qelwvs644z7i3r3lrjr23lhygbwpr11</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Religion and business</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>30781093</id>
    <revision>
      <id>836360628</id>
      <parentid>831342475</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-04-14T09:08:59Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rescuing 1 sources and tagging 1 as dead. #IABot (v1.6.5)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="6978">[[Religion]] and [[business]] have throughout history interacted in ways that relate to and affected one another, as well as influenced [[sociocultural evolution]], [[political geography|political geographies]], and [[labour law]]s.

==Religious tourism==
{{Main|Religious tourism|Sacred travel}}
Some areas, countries or cities have an economy based on religious tourism. Examples include Islamic [[Hajj]] tourism and [[Holy See|Vatican]] tourism. The hotels and markets of important religious places are a source of income to the locals.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.upiasia.com/Society_Culture/2008/07/02/indias_booming_business_of_religion/2083/ India's booming business of religion - upiasia.com&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Pilgrimage sites===
{{See also|Pilgrimage|Hajj}}
The boards or shines sometimes receive so much in donations that governments to take it under control for proper utilization of resources and management.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.maavaishnodevi.org/shrine_board.asp Introduction&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; The annual revenues of most of the religious places are not regulated.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.banned-books.com/truth-seeker/1995archive/122_3/35business.html The Business of Religion&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Business ethics==
{{main|Religious views on business ethics}}

===Judaism===
{{main|Jewish business ethics}}
[[Judaism]] outlines requirements of accurate weights and measurements in commerce, as well as prohibitions on monetary deception, verbal deception and misrepresentation.&lt;ref name='Scheinman'&gt;{{citation | first = James | last = Scheinman | contribution = Jewish Business Ethics | title = The Evolution &amp; Impact of Jewish Law | publisher = Regents of the University of California U.C. Davis Journal of International Law &amp; Policy | year = 1995 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Food processing==

===Halal===
Globally, [[halal]] products comprise a US$2 trillion industry.&lt;ref name='Bladd 2010-09-09'&gt;{{cite news | first = Joanne | last = Bladd |author2=Claire Ferris-Lay  | title = Planet Islamic: the $2trn battle for the halal market | date = 2010-09-09 | url = http://www.arabianbusiness.com/planet-islamic---2trn-battle-for-halal-market-348084.html | work = Arabian Business | accessdate = 2011-05-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Kashrut===
As of 2003, the [[Kashrut|kosher]] industry had certified more than 100,000 products, which total approximately US$165 billion in sales annually.&lt;ref name='Shimoni'&gt;{{cite web | url = http://kosherfood.about.com/od/kosherbasics/p/kosherstats.htm | title = 10 Most Interesting Kosher Stats of 2006 | accessdate = 2011-05-18 | last = Shimoni | first = Giora }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Business law==

===United Kingdom===
[[United Kingdom labour law]] prohibits employer discrimination based on religion, belief, or any lack thereof.&lt;ref name='Acas'&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.acas.org.uk/media/pdf/f/l/religion_1.pdf | title = Religion or Belief and the Workplace | accessdate = 2011-05-18 | format = PDF | work = Acas | quote = From 2 December 2003, when the Employment Equality (Religion or Belief) Regulations came into force, it became unlawful to discriminate against workers because of religion or similar belief.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===United States===
In the [[United States]], [[United States labor law|labor law]]s including [[Civil Rights Act of 1964#Title VII|Title VII of the Civil Rights Act of 1964]] prohibit businesses from discriminating against employees based on the basis of religion.&lt;ref name='Foltin 2004'&gt;{{cite journal | title = Reconciling Faith and Livelihood | journal = Human Rights Magazine | year = 2004 | first = Richard T. | last = Foltin | author2 = James D. Standish | issue = Summer 2004 | url = http://www.americanbar.org/publications/human_rights_magazine_home/summer04_summer04_irr_hr_summer04_reconcile.html | accessdate = 2011-05-18 }}{{dead link|date=April 2018 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name='Steinberger'&gt;{{cite web | url = http://smallbusiness.yahoo.com/r-article-a-112582-m-5-sc-51-religion_and_the_workplace-i | title = Religion and the Workplace | accessdate = 2011-05-18 | last = Steinberger | first = Jeffrey | date = 2007-09-19 | publisher = [[Entrepreneur (magazine)|Entrepreneur]] | quote = Under Title VII, an employer can't refuse to reasonably accommodate an employee's religious observances, unless accommodation would constitute an "undue hardship" for the business. | deadurl = yes | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20110723235609/http://smallbusiness.yahoo.com/r-article-a-112582-m-5-sc-51-religion_and_the_workplace-i | archivedate = 2011-07-23 | df =  }}&lt;/ref&gt; Business law is also at times applied to religious organizations, due to their status as incorporated entities.&lt;ref name='Sternal 2009'&gt;{{cite journal | title = Current Legal Issues Facing Religious Organizations | journal = Business Law Today | date = July–August 2009 | first = Patrick | last = Sternal | volume = 18 | issue = 6 | url = http://apps.americanbar.org/buslaw/blt/2009-07-08/sternal.shtml | accessdate = 2011-05-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Economics of religion]]
* ''[[The Protestant Ethic and the Spirit of Capitalism]]''
* [[Wealth and religion]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
*{{cite book | last1 = Larkin | first1 = Geraldine A. | last2 = Larkin | first2 = Geri | title = Building a Business the Buddhist Way | publisher = Celestial Arts | date = 1991-03-01 | isbn = 978-0-89087-888-0}}
*{{cite book | last1 = Gambling | first1 = Trevor | last2 = Abdel Karim | first2 = Rifaat Ahmed | title = Business and accounting ethics in Islam | publisher = Mansell | date = 1991-05-01 | location = London and New York | isbn = 978-0-7201-2074-5}}
*{{cite book | last1 = Lundén | first1 = Rolf | title = Business and Religion in the American 1920s | publisher = Greenwood Press | year = 1988 | location = New York, New York | url = https://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;d=28008875 | accessdate = 2011-05-18}}
*{{cite book | last1 = Chewning | first1 = Richard C. | title = Business Through the Eyes of Faith | publisher = HarperOne | date = 1990-09-14 | isbn = 978-0-06-061350-1}}
*{{cite book | title = Christianity in Business: A Collection of Essays on Pedagogy and Practice | editors = Edward J. Trunfio | publisher = Christian Business Faculty Association | year = 1991 | isbn = 978-0-9627504-1-0}}
*{{cite book | last1 = Solomon | first1 = Lewis | title = Evangelical Christian Executives: A New Model for Business Corporations | publisher = Transaction Publishers | date = 2004-04-22 | isbn = 978-0-7658-0230-9}}
*{{cite book | last1 = Hill | first1 = Alexander | title = Just Business: Christian Ethics for the Marketplace | publisher = IVP Academic | date = 2008-01-10 | isbn = 978-0-8308-2676-6}}

==External links==
*[http://hbswk.hbs.edu/item/3511.html Can Religion and Business Learn From Each Other?] at ''[[Harvard Business School]]''

{{DEFAULTSORT:Religion And Business}}
[[Category:Business]]
[[Category:Economy and religion|Business]]</text>
      <sha1>pm1xv7lzvsefz7jlgehj65q9i8c6dwf</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Viability study</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>21041941</id>
    <revision>
      <id>783298074</id>
      <parentid>564130186</parentid>
      <timestamp>2017-06-01T11:10:12Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>197.93.201.113</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Feasibility report */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="2438">{{oneref|date=February 2012}}
A '''Viability study''' is an in depth investigation of the [[Profit (accounting)|profitability]] of the [[business idea]] to be converted into a business enterprise.&lt;ref&gt;Nieuwenhuizen, C., Le Roux, E.E. and Jacobs, H., (2004). Entrepreneurship and how to establish your own business. 2nd Edition, Juta, Pretoria, RSA.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Feasibility report==
This type of report studies a situation (for example, a problem or opportunity) and the plan for doing something about it, then determines whether that plan is "feasible". This would involve determining whether it is technologically possible to achieve and whether it is practical in the current technological, economical and social scenario. The feasibility report does not provide a simple "Yes" or "No" answer, but is used in the [[analysis]] of a decision. It is not just a tool to provide a recommendation, it is also used to gather data and give reasoning behind the recommendation given, to be later used in evaluation.

This study is the most important especially to people who plan to start their own business.

==Recommendation report==
{{Seealso|SWOT Analysis}}
This type of report examines either a stated need or a selection of choices, or in some cases both. The report is a collection of analysis and evaluation of the situation, and generally will examine the strengths and weaknesses, opportunities and threats in the situation, take them into account, and be combined with the feasibility report in order to give a recommendation. Sometimes a recommendation can be given to do nothing, if all options currently possible would prove unbeneficial. The recommendation report answers the question "Which option should we choose?" (or "Which are the best options?") by allowing a recommendation to be made. This can be linked into the analysis of the [[continuum of choice]] in the scenario.

==Evaluation report==
This type of report provides an opinion or judgment rather that is based on the above two report, along with additional data available. It provides a studied opinion on the value or worth of something. This type of report compares the object of the analysis to a set of requirements (or [[:wikt:criteria|criteria]]) and determines how well it meets those requirements. Generally, the evaluation report will feature an overall recommendation on the course of action to be taken.

== References ==
{{reflist}}


[[Category:Business]]</text>
      <sha1>st1k0f7st12jgm9ce4nj2ihvjxrtg39</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
