<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.33.0-wmf.4</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Alluvium</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>183243</id>
    <revision>
      <id>865070944</id>
      <parentid>865055828</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-10-21T14:50:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Keith D</username>
        <id>2278355</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Remove full stop</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="4077">{{redirect|Alluvial|the American racehorse|Alluvial (horse)|the type of flow diagram|Alluvial diagram}}

[[File:section.jpg|thumb|Section of alluvium at the [[Blue Ribbon Mine]] in [[Alaska]]]]
[[File:South Africa-Eastern Cape-Gamtoos Valley-Alluvial Gravel01.jpg|thumb|Alluvium deposits in the [[Gamtoos River|Gamtoos Valley]] in [[South Africa]]]]
[[File:AlluvialPlain.JPG|thumb|An [[alluvial plain]] in [[Red Rock Canyon State Park (California)]]]]
[[File:Amazon alluvium deposit - autazes.jpg|thumb|Alluvial river deposits in the [[Amazon Basin]], near Autazes, AM, [[Brazil]]. The seasonal deposits are extremely fertile, and crucial to [[subsistence farming]] in the Amazon Basin along the river banks.]]

'''Alluvium''' (from the [[Latin]] ''alluvius'', from ''alluere'', "to wash against") is loose, unconsolidated (not cemented together into a solid [[Rock (geology)|rock]]) [[soil]] or [[sediment]] that has been [[Erosion|eroded]], reshaped by water in some form, and redeposited in a non-[[marine (ocean)|marine]] setting.&lt;ref&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20110501155938/http://www.geotech.org/survey/geotech/dictiona.html Glossary of Geological Terms]. Geotech.org. Retrieved on 2012-02-12.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://geology.com/dictionary/glossary-a.shtml Geology Dictionary – Alluvial, Aquiclude, Arkose]. Geology.Com. Retrieved on 2012-02-12.&lt;/ref&gt; Alluvium is typically made up of a variety of materials, including fine particles of [[silt]] and [[clay]] and larger particles of [[sand]] and [[gravel]].  When this loose alluvial material is deposited or cemented into a [[Lithology|lithological]] unit, or [[Lithification|lithified]], it is called an '''alluvial deposit'''.&lt;ref name=EB&gt;Chisholm, 1911&lt;/ref&gt;

==Definitions==
The term "alluvium" is not typically used in situations where the formation of the sediment can clearly be attributed to another geologic process that is well described.  This includes (but is not limited to): lake sediments ([[Lake|lacustrine]]), river sediments ([[fluvial]]), or glacially-derived sediments ([[glacial till]]).  Sediments that are formed or deposited in a perennial stream or [[river]] are typically not referred to as alluvial.&lt;ref name=EB/&gt;

==Age==
Most alluvium is geologically [[Quaternary]] in age, and is often referred to as "cover" because these sediments obscure the underlying [[bedrock]].  Most sedimentary material that fills a [[Sedimentary basin|basin]] ("basin fill") that is not lithified is typically lumped together as "alluvial".&lt;ref name=EB/&gt; Alluvium of [[Pliocene]] age occurs, for example, in parts of Idaho.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | last = Ames | first = Dan | contribution = Formation of the Soils | year = 1998 | title = Soil Survey of Jerome County and Part of Twin Falls County, Idaho | pages = 238 | publisher = Natural Resources Conservation Service, [[United States Department of Agriculture|USDA]] | contribution-url = https://www.nrcs.usda.gov/Internet/FSE_MANUSCRIPTS/idaho/ID704/0/id704_text.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; Alluvium of late [[Miocene]] age occurs, for example, in the valley of the [[San Joaquin River]], California.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | url=http://pubs.usgs.gov/pp/1197/report.pdf | title=Amount and Timing of Late Cenozoic Uplift and Tilt of the Central Sierra Nevada, California—Evidence from the Upper San Joaquin River Basin (USGS Professional Paper 1197) | publisher=[[USGS]] | author=Huber, N. King | year=1981 | location=Washington D.C. | pages=13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Ores==
Alluvium can contain valuable [[ore]]s such as [[gold]] and [[platinum]] and a wide variety of [[gemstone]]s. Such a concentration of valuable ores is termed a [[placer deposit]].&lt;ref name=EB/&gt;

== See also ==
{{Div col|colwidth=12em}}
* [[Alluvial fan]]
* [[Alluvial plain]]
* [[Alluvion]]
* [[Bay mud]]
* [[Braided stream]]
* [[Colluvium]]
* [[Desert pavement]]
* [[Diluvium]]
* [[Eluvium]]
* [[Fluvial]]
* [[Hydraulic action]]
* [[Illuvium]]
{{Div col end}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Alluvium}}
*{{Cite EB1911|wstitle=Alluvium}}

[[Category:Sedimentology]]
[[Category:Geography]]</text>
      <sha1>4fl7mdimi4ggf71xf7e4spddk9yu0ke</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Boundary problem (spatial analysis)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>27288010</id>
    <revision>
      <id>860515338</id>
      <parentid>838682291</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-09-21T05:19:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mothman</username>
        <id>396142</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Recommend Merge from &lt; Boundary problem in geography</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="10989">{{mergefrom|Boundary problem in geography|discuss=Talk:Boundary problem (spatial analysis)#Merger proposal|date=September 2018}}{{no footnotes|date=July 2017}}
A '''boundary problem''' in analysis is a phenomenon in which geographical patterns are differentiated by the shape and arrangement of boundaries that are drawn for administrative or measurement purposes.  This is distinct from and must not be confused with the boundary problem in the philosophy of science that is also called the '''[[demarcation problem]]'''.

== Definition ==
In '''[[spatial analysis]]''', four major problems interfere with an accurate estimation of the statistical parameter: the boundary problem, scale problem, pattern problem (or [[spatial autocorrelation]]), and [[modifiable areal unit problem]] (Barber 1988). The boundary problem occurs because of the loss of neighbours in analyses that depend on the values of the neighbours. While geographic phenomena are measured and analyzed within a specific unit, identical spatial data can appear either dispersed or clustered depending on the boundary placed around the data. In analysis with point data, dispersion is evaluated as dependent of the boundary. In analysis with area data, statistics should be interpreted based upon the boundary.

In geographical research, two types of areas are taken into consideration in relation to the boundary: an area surrounded by fixed natural boundaries (e.g., coastlines or streams), outside of which neighbours do not exist (Henley 1981), or an area included in a larger region defined by arbitrary artificial boundaries (e.g., an air pollution boundary in modeling studies or an urban boundary in population migration) (Haining 1990). In an area isolated by the natural boundaries, the spatial process discontinues at the boundaries. In contrast, if a study area is delineated by the artificial boundaries, the process continues beyond the area.

If a spatial process in an area occurs beyond a study area or has an interaction with neighbours outside artificial boundaries, the most common approach is to neglect the influence of the boundaries and assume that the process occurs at the internal area. However, such an approach leads to a significant model misspecification problem (Upton and Fingleton 1985).

That is, for measurement or administrative purposes, geographic boundaries are drawn, but the boundaries per se can bring about different spatial patterns in geographic phenomena (BESR 2002). It has been reported that the difference in the way of drawing the boundary significantly affects identification of the spatial distribution and estimation of the statistical parameters of the spatial process (Cressie 1992; Fotheringham and Rogerson 1993; Griffith 1983; Martin 1987). The difference is largely based on the fact that spatial processes are generally unbounded or fuzzy-bounded (Leung 1987) but the processes are expressed in data imposed within boundaries for analysis purposes (Miller 1999). Although the boundary problem was discussed in relation to artificial and arbitrary boundaries, the effect of the boundaries also occurs according to natural boundaries as long as it is ignored that properties at sites on the natural boundary such as streams are likely to differ from those at sites within the boundary (Martin 1989).

The boundary problem occurs with regard not only to horizontal boundaries but also to vertically drawn boundaries according to delineations of heights or depths (Pineda 1993). For example, biodiversity such as the density of species of plants and animals is high near the surface, so if the identically divided height or depth is used as a spatial unit, it is more likely to find fewer number of the plant and animal species as the height or depth increases.

[https://web.archive.org/web/20111004212256/http://lh5.ggpht.com/_fHD7C68ZqPM/S-VBeClLMcI/AAAAAAAAARc/Fg3kytstuUg/s640/BP.jpg '''Boundary problem''': urban sprawl in central Florida (an evaluation by land cover analysis with raster datasets vs. an evaluation by population density bounded in the census tract)]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;sup&gt;Notes: Land cover datasets were obtained from USGS and population density from FGDL.&lt;/sup&gt;

== Types and examples ==

By drawing a boundary around a study area, two types of problems in measurement and analysis takes place (Fotheringham and Rogerson 1993). The first is an '''edge effect'''. This effect originates from the ignorance of interdependences that occur outside the bounded region. Griffith (1980; 1983) and Griffith and Amrhein (1983) highlighted problems according to the edge effect. A typical example is a cross-boundary influence such as cross-border jobs, services and other resources located in a neighbouring municipality (McGuire 1995).

The second is a '''shape effect''' that results from the artificial shape delineated by the boundary. As an illustration of the effect of the artificial shape, point pattern analysis tends to provide higher levels of clustering for the identical point pattern within a unit that is more elongated (Fotheringham and Rogerson 1993). Similarly, the shape can influence interaction and flow among spatial entities (Arlinghaus and Nystuen 1990; Ferguson and Kanaroglou 1998; Griffith 1982). For example, the shape can affect the measurement of origin-destination flows since these are often recorded when they cross an artificial boundary. Because of the effect set by the boundary, the shape and area information is used to estimate travel distances from surveys (Rogerson 1990) or to locate traffic counters, travel survey stations, or traffic monitoring systems (Kirby 1997). From the same perspective, Theobald (2001; retrieved from BESR 2002) argued that measures of urban sprawl should consider interdependences and interactions with nearby rural areas.

In spatial analysis, the boundary problem has been discussed along with the [[modifiable areal unit problem]] (MAUP) inasmuch as MAUP is associated with the arbitrary geographic unit and the unit is defined by the boundary (Rogerson 2006). For administrative purposes, data for policy indicators are usually aggregated within larger units (or enumeration units) such as census tracts, school districts, municipalities and counties. The artificial units serve the purposes of taxation and service provision. For example, municipalities can effectively respond to the need of the public in their jurisdictions. However, in such spatially aggregated units, spatial variations of detailed social variables cannot be identified. The problem is noted when the average degree of a variable and its unequal distribution over space are measured (BESR 2002).

== See also ==

* [[Central place theory]]
* [[Demarcation problem]] ('''boundary problem''' in the philosophy of science)
* [[Fuzzy architectural spatial analysis]]
* [[Generalized least squares]]
* [[Geographic information system]]
* [[Modifiable areal unit problem]]
* [[Sensitivity analysis]]
* [[Spatial analysis]]
* [[Spatial autocorrelation]]

== References ==

* Arlinghaus, S. L. and Nystuen, J. D. (1990) Geometry of boundary exchanges. Geographical Review 80, 21–31.
* Barber, G. M. (1988) Elementary Statistics for Geographers. Guilford Press: New York, NY.
* BESR (2002) Community and Quality of Life: Data Needs for Informed Decision Making. Board on Earth Sciences and Resources: Washington, DC.
* Cressie, N. (1992) Statistics for Spatial Data. John Wiley and Sons: New York, NY.
* Ferguson, M. R. and Kanaroglou, P. S. (1998) Representing the shape and orientation of destinations in spatial choice models. Geographical Analysis 30, 119–137.
* Fotheringham, A. S. and Rogerson, P. A. (1993) GIS and spatial analytical problems. International Journal of Geographical Information Systems 7, 3–19.
* Griffith, D. (1980) Towards a theory of spatial statistics. Geographical Analysis 12, 325–339.
* Griffith, D. (1983) The boundary value problem in spatial statistics. Journal of Regional Science 23, 377–387.
* Griffith, D. A. (1982) Geometry and spatial interaction. Annals of the Association of American Geographers 72, 332–346.
* Griffith, D. A. (1985) An evaluation of correction techniques for boundary effects in spatial statistical analysis: contemporary methods. Geographical Analysis 17, 81–88.
* Griffith, D. A. and Amrhein, C. G. (1983) An evaluation of correction techniques for boundary effects in spatial statistical analysis: traditional methods. Geographical Analysis 15, 352–360.
* Haining, R. (1990) Spatial Data Analysis in Social and Environmental Sciences. Cambridge University Press: New York, NY.
* Haslett, J., Wills, G., and Unwin, A. (1990) SPIDER: an interactive statistical tool for the analysis of spatially distributed data. International Journal of Geographical Information Systems 3, 285–296.
* Henley, S. (1981). Nonparametric Geostatistics. Applied Science Publishers: London, UK.
* Kirby, H. R. (1997) Buffon’s needle and the probability of intercepting short-distance trips by multiple screen-line surveys. Geographical Analysis, 29 64–71.
* Leung, Y. (1987) On the imprecision of boundaries. Geographical Analysis 19, 125–151.
* McGuire, J. (1995). What works: Reducing reoffending, guidelines from research and practice. Chichester: John Wiley &amp; Sons, Chichester, UK.
* Martin, R. J. (1989) The role of spatial statistical processes in geographic modeling. In D. A. Griffith (ed) Spatial Statistics: Past, Present, and Future. Institute of Mathematical Geography: Syracuse, NY, pp.&amp;nbsp;107–129.
* Martin, R. J. (1987) Some comments on correction techniques for boundary effects and missing value techniques. Geographical Analysis 19, 273–282.
* Miller, H. J. (1999) Potential contributions of spatial analysis to geographic information systems for transportation. Geographical Analysis 31, 373–399.
* Openshaw, S., Charlton, M., and Wymer, C. (1987) A mark I geographical analysis machine for the automated analysis of point pattern data. International Journal of Geographical Information Systems 1, 335–350.
* Ripley, B. D. (1979) Tests of "randomness" for spatial point patterns. Journal of the Royal Statistical Society, Series B 41, 368–374.
* Rogerson, P. A. (1990) Buffon’s needle and the estimation of migration distances. Mathematical Population Studies 2, 229–238.
* Rogerson, P. A. (2006) Statistical Methods for Geography: A Student Guide. Sage: London, UK.
* Upton, J. G. G. and Fingleton, B. (1985) Spatial Data Analysis by Example. Volume 1: Point Pattern and Quantitative Data. Wiley: Chichester, UK.
* Wong, D. W. S., and Fotheringham, A. S. (1990) Urban systems as examples of bounded chaos: exploring the relationship between fractal dimension, rank-size and rural-to-urban migration. Geografiska Annaler 72, 89–99.
* Yoo, E.-H. and Kyriakidis, P. C. (2008) Area-to-point prediction under boundary conditions. Geographical Analysis 40, 355–379.

[[Category:Geography]]
[[Category:Spatial data analysis]]</text>
      <sha1>q5fs2j52088ecpyve1p8lap7k32ckw5</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Caribmap</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>49525731</id>
    <revision>
      <id>724895494</id>
      <parentid>714145403</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-06-12T06:25:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>CommonsDelinker</username>
        <id>2304267</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Removing "Caribmap-interface.png", it has been deleted from Commons by [[commons:User:Ellin Beltz|Ellin Beltz]] because: Copyright violation, see [[:c:Commons:Licensing|]].</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="3558">'''Caribmap''' is a non-profit [[Digital library|online library]] of historical and modern maps, including [[topographic maps]], of the [[Caribbean islands]].&lt;ref name="cm"&gt;Hedges SB. 2013. {{Cite web|title = Caribmap: a mobile-friendly web resource for Caribbean maps that facilitates quantitative historical analysis. ''Journal of Map and Geography Libraries'' 9:350-360.|url = http://www.hedgeslab.org/pubs/247.pdf|website = |access-date = 2016-02-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since its establishment in 1999, the site has accumulated approximately 1800 maps of the islands that have been printed since the beginning of the [[16th century]] &lt;ref name="s"&gt;{{Cite web|title = Maps of the Caribbean now on caribmap.org.|url = http://library.stanford.edu/blogs/digital-library-blog/2013/10/maps-caribbean-now-caribmaporg|website = library.standford.edu|access-date = 2016-03-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; The purpose of the site is to allow users, such as historians and scientists, to gain detailed information, including place names, from the high resolution map scans.&lt;ref name="cm" /&gt; For this, it uses a [[zoomable user interface]] (ZUI), [[Deep Zoom]], so that the scale of the viewed area can be changed.

Caribmap is created and directed by a scientist, [[S. Blair Hedges]], who is responsible for managing all content.&lt;ref name="cm" /&gt; It has received large donations of map images from public and private institutions such as the [[Branner Earth Sciences Library|Branner Earth Sciences Library &amp; Map Collections]] of [[Stanford University]], the [[Norman B. Leventhal Map Center]] at the [[Boston Public Library]], the [[Perry–Castañeda Library|Perry-Castañeda Library]] of the [[University of Texas at Austin]], and the [[George A. Smathers Libraries]] of the [[University of Florida]].

== Contents ==

Caribmap encompasses the geographic range of the [[Caribbean Sea]] and its islands, including those bordering the Middle and South American mainland, such as the [[Bay Islands Department|Bay Islands]] of [[Honduras]], [[ABC islands (Lesser Antilles)|ABC Islands]] ([[Aruba]], [[Bonaire]], and [[Curaçao]]), [[Trinidad]], and [[Tobago]]. The [[Bahamas]] and [[Turks and Caicos Islands]] are also incorporated due to their cultural, economic, and historic links to the Caribbean islands.&lt;ref name="cm" /&gt;

The site features scans of high-resolution maps, organized by islands, which allow the capability to zoom in on details of historic or scientific importance. Map thumbnail images pertaining to that island are sorted in chronological order by the year the map was made, above the viewing area. Bibliographic information (title, year, maker, medium, size, and credit) is displayed under each map. The site also has a feature called “map tours,” focused on individual islands (currently only Jamaica), which are short videos featuring historical maps and 3D scenes from [[Google Earth]]. One demonstrated use of Caribmap, given its large number of high-resolution map images, has been quantitative historical analysis, which traces the use of [[toponymy|toponyms]] (place names) through time.&lt;ref name="cm" /&gt;

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.caribmap.org Official Website]

&lt;!-- STOP! Be warned that by using this process instead of Articles for Creation, this article is subject to scrutiny. As an article in "mainspace", it will be DELETED if there are problems, not just declined. If you wish to use AfC, please return to the Wizard and continue from there. --&gt;

[[Category:Digital libraries]]
[[Category:Maps]]
[[Category:Geography]]</text>
      <sha1>ds08saappsu2vqbovj5z07vwa2l3nxg</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>City marketing</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>24769645</id>
    <revision>
      <id>842678378</id>
      <parentid>794487078</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-05-23T23:38:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Trappist the monk</username>
        <id>10289486</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* See also */ cite repair;</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="6069">{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2013}}
[[File:Guggenheim-bilbao-jan05.jpg|thumb|200px|[[Guggenheim Museum Bilbao|Guggenheim Museum]] in [[Bilbao]] is an example of a structure used for city marketing&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Monclus|Guardia|2006|p=203}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
'''City marketing''' (related to '''city branding''') is the promotion of a [[city]], or a [[district]] within it, with the aim of encouraging certain activities to take place there.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Smyth|1994|p=2}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is used to alter the external perceptions of a city in order to encourage [[tourism]], attract inward migration of residents, or enable business relocation. A significant feature of city marketing is the development of new landmark, or 'flagship', buildings and structures.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Smyth|1994|p=3}}&lt;/ref&gt; The development of cities as a marketable product has led to competition between them for inward investment and government funding.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Gordon|1999|p=1001}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is often manifested in the attempts by cities to attract international sporting events, such as the [[Olympic Games]]. Competition between cities exists at the regional, national and international level; and is an effect of [[globalisation]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Gordon|1999|p=1001}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Some places are associated with certain brands and build on each other, but sometimes the commercial brand is so powerful that eclipses the place brand. An example of this is [[Maranello]], Italy, which uses the Ferrari headquarters as a primary attraction for tourists.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.maranello.it/en/what-to-do/|title=What To Do|last=|first=|date=April 6, 2017|website=Maranello|archive-url=http://www.maranello.it/en/what-to-do/|archive-date=April 6, 2017|dead-url=no|access-date=April 6, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

City marketing can occur ''strategically'' or ''organically''. An example of strategic city marketing is  [[Las Vegas Valley|Las Vegas]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Benjamin |last=Spillman |authorlink= |coauthors= |title=LVCVA: What works here, stays here |url=http://www.lvrj.com/business/43023617.html |work=[[Las Vegas Review-Journal]] |publisher= |date= 2009-04-15|accessdate=15 April 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The city is promoted through a variety of efforts with the strategic intent of acquiring cultural and economic bonuses. A case of organic city marketing is [[Jerusalem]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Michael Sebastian |last=Metti |authorlink= |coauthors= |title=Jerusalem - the most powerful brand in history |url=http://www.fek.su.se/en/Research/Subdisciplines/Marketing/Stockholm-Program-of-Place-Branding |work=[[Stockholm University School of Business]] |publisher= |date=2011-06-01 |accessdate=1 July 2011 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://archive.is/20110612234127/http://www.fek.su.se/en/Research/Subdisciplines/Marketing/Stockholm-Program-of-Place-Branding |archivedate=12 June 2011 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; The city is marketed without a grand strategy, as disorganized stakeholders over the course of centuries have glorified the city and encouraged pilgrimage, yielding cultural and economic bonuses. Both cases demonstrate city marketing, each with varying strategic and organic involvement. Generally, organic marketing occurs alongside strategic marketing, as the [[perception]] of the city is impossible to solely construct with strategic efforts. 

According to [[Scott Cutlip]], "one of the first, if not the first, municipal promotion programs" was led by [[Erastus Brainerd]] for the city of [[Seattle]] beginning in 1896. Seattle was in competition with Portland and Victoria as the preferred city in which to get supplied for the [[Klondike Gold Rush]]. A Bureau of Public Information was established within the city’s [[Chamber of Commerce]].&lt;ref&gt;Scott Cutlip (1995) ''Public Relations History'', "Seattle shows the way for cities", pp 166,7&lt;/ref&gt;

Like with any successful marketing effort, cities must be willing to commit to a long-term plan in order for their identity and message to be communicated effectively. A shared vision between stakeholders will help develop a cohesive overarching strategy for a city's image.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=City Branding|last=Dinnie|first=Keith|publisher=Palgrave Macmillan|year=2011|isbn=978-0-230-24185-5|location=New York|pages=150–158}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== City Brand Index ==
The City Brand Index is released biannually and ranks the image of 50 cities on 6 components: presence, place, potential, pulse, people, and prerequisites.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Competitive Identity|last=Anholt|first=Simon|publisher=Palgrave Macmillan|year=2007|isbn=978-0-230-50028-0|location=New York|pages=59-62}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the 2015 report, Paris took the top spot, with London, New York, Sydney, and Los Angeles taking the 2nd–5th spots respectively.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.gfk.com/insights/press-release/paris-wins-back-most-admired-city-from-london/|title=Paris wins back ‘most admired city’ from London|last=|first=|date=April 6, 2017|website=GFK|archive-url=http://www.gfk.com/insights/press-release/paris-wins-back-most-admired-city-from-london/|archive-date=April 6, 2017|dead-url=no|access-date=April 6, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

==References==
{{reflist}}

== See also ==
{{Refbegin}} 
*{{citation |title=Internationalisation and Urban Competition |first=Ian |last=Gordon |year=1999  |journal=Urban Studies |volume=36 |issue=5–6 |doi=10.1080/0042098993321 }}
* [[Philip Kotler]], Donald H. Haider, [[Irving J. Rein]] (1993) ''Marketing Places: attracting investment, industry, and tourism to cities, states, and nations'', [[Free Press (publisher)|Free Press]], {{ISBN|0-02-917596-8}} .
*{{citation | title=Marketing the city: the role of flagship developments in urban regeneration | first=Hedley  | last=Smyth | year=1994  | publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis | isbn=978-0-419-18610-6 }}
*{{citation | title=Culture, Urbanism and Planning | last=Monclus | first=Francisco | last2=Guardia | first2=Manuel| year=2006 | publisher =Ashgate  | isbn=978-0-7546-4623-5 }}
{{refend}}

{{Authority control}}
[[Category:Promotion and marketing communications]]
[[Category:Geography]]</text>
      <sha1>kvqma93cteojhkv4hvfdj8ut6ki0rvy</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Distance decay</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6786225</id>
    <revision>
      <id>863735007</id>
      <parentid>863734985</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-10-12T17:35:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ClueBot NG</username>
        <id>13286072</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverting possible vandalism by [[Special:Contribs/165.161.16.41|165.161.16.41]] to version by Oshwah. [[WP:CBFP|Report False Positive?]] Thanks, [[WP:CBNG|ClueBot NG]]. (3507195) (Bot)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="3412">'''Distance decay''' is a [[Human geography|geographical]] term which describes the effect of [[distance]] on cultural or spatial [[interaction]]s.  The distance decay effect states that the interaction between two locales declines as the distance between them increases. Once the distance is outside of the two locales' activity space, their interactions begin to decrease.

With the advent of faster travel, distance has less effect than it did in the past, except where places previously connected by now-[[abandoned railway]]&lt;nowiki/&gt;s, for example, have fallen off the beaten path. Advances in [[communications technology]], such as telegraphs, telephones, [[broadcasting]], and internet, have further decreased the effects of distance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url = http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0966692313000653 | doi=10.1016/j.jtrangeo.2013.04.001 | volume=31 | title=Boots are made for walking: interactions across physical and social space in infrastructure-poor regions | year=2013 | journal=Journal of Transport Geography | pages=226–235 | author=Matous Petr, Todo Yasuyuki, Mojo Dagne}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Distance decay is graphically represented by a curving line that swoops [[convex function|concavely]] downward as distance along the x-axis increases.  Distance decay can be mathematically represented as an [[Inverse-square law]] by the expression

&lt;math&gt;I = const. \times d^{-2}&lt;/math&gt; 
or
&lt;math&gt;I \propto 1/d^2&lt;/math&gt;,

where I is interaction and d is distance. It can take other forms such as [[Exponential decay|negative exponential]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Nekola J. C., White P. S. | year = 1999 | title = The distance decay of similarity in biogeography and ecology | url = http://labs.bio.unc.edu/Peet/ecoinfo/distance_decay/nekolapeter.pdf | format = PDF | journal = Journal of Biogeography | volume = 26 | issue = | pages = 867–878 | doi=10.1046/j.1365-2699.1999.00305.x}}&lt;/ref&gt; i.e.

&lt;math&gt;I \propto e^{-d}&lt;/math&gt;
.

Distance decay is evident in town/[[city centre]]s. It can refer to various things which decline with greater distance from the center of the [[Central Business District]] (CBD):
* density of [[pedestrian]] traffic
* street quality 
* quality of shops (depending on definitions of 'quality' and 'center')
* height of buildings 
* [[bid rent theory|price of land]]

Distance decay weighs into the decision to migrate, leading many [[Human migration|migrants]] to move less far.

== Related concepts ==

Related terms include "[[friction of distance]]", which describes the force that creates distance decay and [[Waldo R. Tobler]]'s "[[Tobler's first law of geography|First law of geography]]", an informal statement that "All things are related, but near things are more related than far things." 
"[[Loss of Strength Gradient]]" holds that the amount of a nation's military power that could be brought to bear in any part of the world depends on geographic distance.

== See also ==
* [[Inverse-square law]]
* ''[[The World Is Flat]]''
* [[Trip distribution]]

== References ==
* {{cite web|title=Working Group on Distance Decay|publisher=[[University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill]]|author=Kristin Taverna, Weimin Xi|url=http://www.bio.unc.edu/faculty/peet/lab/ecoinfo/distance_decay/distance_decay.htm}}
* Fellman, Getis, and Getis. ''Human Geography, eighth edition'', pp.&amp;nbsp;68–69.

{{Reflist}}

[[Category:Geography]]


{{geo-term-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>3rmh9g51z7mrek57lxhncvascpaen4g</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Earth section paths</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>57078824</id>
    <revision>
      <id>860318933</id>
      <parentid>851759476</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-09-19T21:02:42Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jerodlycett</username>
        <id>24269494</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>v1.43 - [[WP:WCW]] project (Math tag without correct match - Reference before punctuation - Spelling and typography)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="16674">'''Earth section paths''' are paths on the earth defined by the intersection of a [[reference ellipsoid]] and a plane. Common examples of earth sections include the great ellipse and normal sections. This page provides a unifying approach to all earth sections and their associated [[geodesy|geodetic problems]].

== The Indirect Problem ==
The indirect problem for earth sections is: given two points, &lt;math&gt;P_1&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;P_2&lt;/math&gt; on the surface of the reference ellipsoid, find the length, &lt;math&gt;s_{12}&lt;/math&gt;, of the short arc of a spheroid section from &lt;math&gt;P_1&lt;/math&gt; to &lt;math&gt;P_2&lt;/math&gt; and also find the departure and arrival (true north referenced) [[azimuth]]s of that curve, &lt;math&gt;\alpha_1&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;\alpha_2&lt;/math&gt;. Let &lt;math&gt;P_k&lt;/math&gt; have geodetic latitude  &lt;math&gt;\phi_k&lt;/math&gt; and longitude &lt;math&gt;\lambda_k&lt;/math&gt; (k=1,2). This problem is best solved using [[analytic geometry]] in [[ECEF]] coordinates.
Let &lt;math&gt;R_1=ECEF(P_1)&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;R_2=ECEF(P_2)&lt;/math&gt; be the ECEF coordinates of the two points, computed using the geodetic to ECEF transformations discussed [[Geographic coordinate conversion|here]].

=== Section plane ===
To define the section plane select any third point &lt;math&gt;R_0&lt;/math&gt; not on the line from &lt;math&gt;R_1&lt;/math&gt; to &lt;math&gt;R_2&lt;/math&gt;. Choosing &lt;math&gt;R_0&lt;/math&gt; to be on the surface normal at &lt;math&gt;P_1&lt;/math&gt; will define the normal section at &lt;math&gt;P_1&lt;/math&gt;. If &lt;math&gt;R_0&lt;/math&gt; is the origin then the earth section is the great ellipse. (The origin would be co-linear with 2 antipodal points so a different point must be used in that case). Since there are infinitely many choices for &lt;math&gt;R_0&lt;/math&gt;, the above problem is really a class of problems (one for each plane). Let &lt;math&gt;R_0&lt;/math&gt; be given. To put the equation of the plane into the standard form, &lt;math&gt;lx + my + nz = d&lt;/math&gt;, where &lt;math&gt;\ l^2 + m^2 + n^2 = 1&lt;/math&gt;, requires the components of a [[unit vector]], &lt;math&gt;{\hat{N}} = (l, m, n)&lt;/math&gt;, normal to the section plane. These components may be computed as follows: The vector from &lt;math&gt;R_0&lt;/math&gt; to &lt;math&gt;R_1&lt;/math&gt; has components &lt;math&gt;V_0=R_1 - R_0&lt;/math&gt;, and the vector from &lt;math&gt;R_1&lt;/math&gt; to &lt;math&gt;R_2&lt;/math&gt; has components &lt;math&gt;V_1=R_2 - R_1&lt;/math&gt;. Therefore, &lt;math&gt;{\hat{N}}&lt;/math&gt; = &lt;math&gt;unit(V_0&lt;/math&gt;×&lt;math&gt;V_1&lt;/math&gt;), where &lt;math&gt;unit(V)&lt;/math&gt; is the unit vector in the direction of &lt;math&gt;V&lt;/math&gt;. The orientation convention used here is that &lt;math&gt;{\hat{N}}&lt;/math&gt; points to the left of the path. If this is not the case then redefine &lt;math&gt;V_0&lt;/math&gt; = -&lt;math&gt;V_0&lt;/math&gt;. Finally, the parameter d for the plane may be computed using the [[dot product]] of &lt;math&gt;{\hat{N}}&lt;/math&gt; with a vector from the origin to any point on the plane, such as &lt;math&gt;R_1&lt;/math&gt;, i.e. d = &lt;math&gt;{\hat{N}}\cdot{R_1}&lt;/math&gt;. The equation of the plane (in vector form) is thus &lt;math&gt;{\hat{N}}&lt;/math&gt; ⋅ &lt;math&gt;R&lt;/math&gt; = d, where &lt;math&gt;R&lt;/math&gt; is the [[position vector]] of (x, y, z).

=== Azimuth ===
A unit vector pointing up at any point on the ellipsoid is: &lt;math&gt;\mathbf{\hat{u}}&lt;/math&gt;=&lt;math&gt;(\cos\phi\cos\lambda,\cos\phi\sin\lambda,\sin\phi)&lt;/math&gt;, a unit vector pointing north is &lt;math&gt;\mathbf{\hat{n}}&lt;/math&gt;=&lt;math&gt;(-\sin\phi\cos\lambda,-\sin\phi\sin\lambda,\cos\phi)&lt;/math&gt;, and east is &lt;math&gt;\mathbf{\hat{e}}&lt;/math&gt;=&lt;math&gt;(-\sin\lambda,\cos\lambda,0)&lt;/math&gt;. A vector tangent to the path is:
&lt;math&gt;\mathbf{t}= \hat{N} \times \mathbf{\hat{u}}&lt;/math&gt; so the east component of &lt;math&gt;\mathbf{t}&lt;/math&gt; is &lt;math&gt;\mathbf{t}\cdot\mathbf{\hat{e}}&lt;/math&gt;, and the north component is &lt;math&gt;\mathbf{t}\cdot\mathbf{\hat{n}}&lt;/math&gt;. Therefore, the azimuth may be obtained from a [[atan2|two-argument arctangent function]], &lt;math&gt;\alpha&lt;/math&gt;=&lt;math&gt;\operatorname{atan2}(\mathbf{t}\cdot\mathbf{\hat{e}},\mathbf{t}\cdot\mathbf{\hat{n}})&lt;/math&gt;. Use this method at both &lt;math&gt;P_1&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;P_2&lt;/math&gt; to get &lt;math&gt;\alpha_1&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;\alpha_2&lt;/math&gt;.

=== Section Ellipse ===
The (non-trivial) intersection of a plane and ellipsoid is an ellipse. Therefore, the arc length, &lt;math&gt;s_{12}&lt;/math&gt;, on the section path from &lt;math&gt;P_1&lt;/math&gt; to &lt;math&gt;P_2&lt;/math&gt; is an [[elliptic integral]] that may be computed to any desired accuracy using a truncated series. Before this can be done the ellipse must be defined and the limits of integration computed.
Let the ellipsoid given by &lt;math&gt;\frac{x^2}{a^2}+\frac{y^2}{a^2}+\frac{z^2}{b^2} = 1&lt;/math&gt;, and let &lt;math&gt; p=\sqrt{l^2+m^2}&lt;/math&gt;.
If p=0 then the section is a horizontal circle of radius &lt;math&gt;a\sqrt{1-\frac{d^2}{b^2}}&lt;/math&gt;, which has no solution if &lt;math&gt;|d|&gt;b&lt;/math&gt;.

If p&gt;0 then Gilbertson&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Gilbertson|first1=Charles|title=Earth Section Paths|journal=Navigation|date=Spring 2012|volume=59|issue=1|pages=1-7|url=https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1002/navi.2}}&lt;/ref&gt; showed that the ECEF coordinates of the center of the ellipse is &lt;math&gt;{R_c}=\frac{d}{C}(la^2, ma^2, nb^2)&lt;/math&gt;, where &lt;math&gt;C=a^2p^2+b^2n^2&lt;/math&gt;,

the semi-major axis is &lt;math&gt;a^*=a\sqrt{1-\frac{d^2}{C}}&lt;/math&gt;, in the direction &lt;math&gt;\mathbf{\hat{i^*}}=(\frac{m}{p}, \frac{-l}{p}, 0)&lt;/math&gt;, and
the semi-minor axis is &lt;math&gt;b^*=\frac{b}{\sqrt{C}}a^*&lt;/math&gt;,  in the direction &lt;math&gt;\mathbf{\hat{j^*}}=(\frac{ln}{p}, \frac{mn}{p}, -p)&lt;/math&gt;, which has no solution if &lt;math&gt;|d|&gt;\sqrt{C}&lt;/math&gt;.

=== Arc Length ===
The polar form relative to center for the equation of an ellipse is &lt;math&gt;R(\theta)= \frac{b^*}{\sqrt{1-e^2 \cos^2 \theta}}&lt;/math&gt;, where &lt;math&gt;e^2=1-\frac{(b^*)^2}{(a^*)^2}&lt;/math&gt;, relates to the ellipse eccentricity,  not the spheroid eccentricity (see [[ellipse]]). Let P be a point on the ellipse and &lt;math&gt;R=ECEF(P)&lt;/math&gt;, then the vector from &lt;math&gt;{R_c}&lt;/math&gt; to &lt;math&gt;R&lt;/math&gt; has components &lt;math&gt;R-R_c&lt;/math&gt;. Using an argument similar to the one for azimuth above, let &lt;math&gt;\mathbf{\hat{w}}=unit(R-R_c)&lt;/math&gt;, then &lt;math&gt;\cos\theta=\mathbf{\hat{w}}\cdot\mathbf{\hat{i^*}}&lt;/math&gt;, and &lt;math&gt;\sin\theta=\mathbf{\hat{w}}\cdot\mathbf{\hat{j^*}}&lt;/math&gt;, and &lt;math&gt;\theta =\operatorname{atan2}(\sin\theta,\cos\theta)&lt;/math&gt;. In this way we obtain the central angles &lt;math&gt;\theta_{1}&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;\theta_{2}&lt;/math&gt; corresponding to &lt;math&gt;P_1&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;P_2&lt;/math&gt; respectively. Care must be taken to ensure that 0 ≤ &lt;math&gt;\theta_1&lt;/math&gt; ≤ &lt;math&gt; \theta_2&lt;/math&gt; ≤ &lt;math&gt;\theta_1  + \pi &lt;/math&gt;. Then the [[arc length]] along the ellipse is given by &lt;math&gt;s_{12}&lt;/math&gt; =&lt;math&gt;\int_{\theta_1}^{\theta_2} \sqrt{R^2+(R^')^2}d\theta.&lt;/math&gt; Substituting &lt;math&gt;r(\theta)&lt;/math&gt; above into this formula, performing the indicated operations, using one more term than Gilbertson's expression and regrouping, results in 
&lt;math&gt;s_{12} = ArcLength(\theta_1,\theta_2) = b^*({c_0}\Delta\theta + {c_1}\Delta s2 + {c_2}\Delta s4 + {c_3}\Delta s6)&lt;/math&gt;, where
: &lt;math&gt;
\begin{align}
\Delta\theta&amp;=\theta_2-\theta_1,\\[6pt]
\Delta s2&amp;=\sin(2\theta_2)-\sin(2\theta_1),\\[6pt]
\Delta s4&amp;=\sin(4\theta_2)-\sin(4\theta_1),\\[6pt]
\Delta s6&amp;=\sin(6\theta_2)-\sin(6\theta_1),\\[6pt]
{c_0}&amp;=1+e^2(4096 + 3328e^2 + 2880e^4 + 2577e^6 + 16860e^8)/16384,\\[6pt]
{c_1}&amp;=e^2(512 + 384e^2 + 380e^4 + 385e^6 + 3408e^8)/4096,\\[6pt]
{c_2}&amp;=-e^4(64 + 80e^2 + 19e^4 - 3516e^6)/16384,\\[6pt]
{c_3}&amp;=-e^6(60 + 105e^2 - 528e^4)/12288.\\[6pt]
\end{align}
&lt;/math&gt;
Alternatively, expansions for the [[Meridian arc]] may be used here by replacing the spheroid eccentricity with the section ellipse eccentricity.

== The Direct Problem ==
The direct problem is given &lt;math&gt;{P_1}&lt;/math&gt;, the distance, &lt;math&gt;\delta&lt;/math&gt;, and departure azimuth, &lt;math&gt;\alpha_1&lt;/math&gt;, find &lt;math&gt;{P_2}&lt;/math&gt; and the arrival azimuth, &lt;math&gt;\alpha_2&lt;/math&gt;.
=== Section plane ===
Construct the tangent vector at &lt;math&gt;{P_1}&lt;/math&gt;, &lt;math&gt;\mathbf\hat{t_1}= \mathbf\hat{n_1}\cos{\alpha_1} + \mathbf{\hat{e_1}}\sin{\alpha_1}&lt;/math&gt;, where &lt;math&gt;\mathbf\hat{n_1}&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;\mathbf{\hat{e_1}}&lt;/math&gt; are unit vectors pointing north and east (respectively) at &lt;math&gt;{P_1}&lt;/math&gt;. Pick a vector,  &lt;math&gt;V_0&lt;/math&gt;, to define the section plane, paying attention to orientation. Observe that &lt;math&gt;V_0&lt;/math&gt; must not be in span{&lt;math&gt;\mathbf\hat{n_1} ,\mathbf{\hat{e_1}}&lt;/math&gt;} (otherwise the plane would be tangent to the earth at &lt;math&gt;{P_1}&lt;/math&gt;, so no path would result). The normal vector &lt;math&gt;{\hat{N}}&lt;/math&gt; = &lt;math&gt;unit(V_0&lt;/math&gt;×&lt;math&gt;\mathbf\hat{t_1}&lt;/math&gt;),  together with &lt;math&gt;{P_1}&lt;/math&gt; defines the plane.
=== Locate &lt;math&gt;{P_2}&lt;/math&gt;===
This is a 2-d problem in span{&lt;math&gt;\mathbf\hat{i^*} , \mathbf\hat{j^*}&lt;/math&gt;},  which will be solved with the help of the arc length formula above. The basic approach is to use Newton-Raphson iteration to arrive at &lt;math&gt;{P_2}&lt;/math&gt;. The basis of the estimate is that the position vector of any point on the section ellipse may be expressed in terms of the position vector of the center and the central angle as 
&lt;math&gt;V={V_c} + {r(\theta)}(\mathbf{\hat{i^*}}\cos\theta+\mathbf{\hat{j^*}}\sin\theta)&lt;/math&gt;.
To get an initial estimate of &lt;math&gt;{\theta_2}&lt;/math&gt;, let &lt;math&gt;{V_1}={R_1}-R{_c}&lt;/math&gt;, &lt;math&gt;{\theta_1}&lt;/math&gt;=Central_Angle&lt;math&gt;({V_1})&lt;/math&gt; (see the arc length section above),
&lt;math&gt;{r_1}=r({\theta_1})&lt;/math&gt;, &lt;math&gt;\Delta\theta=\frac{\delta}{r_1}&lt;/math&gt;.

Now initialize &lt;math&gt;\theta_2&lt;/math&gt; = &lt;math&gt;\theta_1 + \Delta\theta&lt;/math&gt;, and iterate the following steps:
: &lt;math&gt;
\begin{align}
s &amp;= ArcLength({\theta_1}, {\theta_2}),\\[6pt]
Err &amp;= \delta - s,\\[6pt]
s'({\theta}) &amp;= \frac{b^*}{(1-e^2 \cos^2 \theta)}\sqrt{\frac{(1-(2-e^2) e^2 \cos^2 \theta}{1-e^2 \cos^2 \theta}},\\[6pt]
\Delta\theta &amp;= \frac{Err}{s'({\theta_2})}, \\[6pt]
\theta_2 &amp;= \theta_2 + \Delta\theta, \\[6pt]
\end{align}
&lt;/math&gt;
exit when &lt;math&gt;abs(\Delta\theta) &lt; 10^{-12}&lt;/math&gt;

No more than three iterations are usually necessary, although nearly antipodal cases can be problematic.
Finally, let &lt;math&gt;{V_2}={V_c} + {r(\theta_2)}(\mathbf{\hat{i^*}}\cos\theta_2+\mathbf{\hat{j^*}}\sin\theta_2)&lt;/math&gt;, and &lt;math&gt;{P_2}&lt;/math&gt; = ECEF_to_Geo&lt;math&gt;({V_2})&lt;/math&gt; using Bowring’s 1985 algorithm,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Bowring|first1=B.R.|title=The accuracy of geodetic latitude and height equations|journal=Survey Review|date=1985|volume=28|issue=218|pages=202-206}}&lt;/ref&gt; or the algorithm [[Geographic coordinate conversion|here]].

Alternatively, inversion of the arc length series may be used to avoid iterations.

=== Azimuth ===
Azimuth may be obtained by the same method as the indirect problem: &lt;math&gt;{\alpha_2}&lt;/math&gt;=&lt;math&gt;\operatorname{atan2}(\mathbf{t_2}\cdot\mathbf{\hat{e_2}},\mathbf{t_2}\cdot\mathbf{\hat{n_2}})&lt;/math&gt;, where the subscript 2 indicates evaluation of the associated quantity at &lt;math&gt;P_2&lt;/math&gt;.

== Examples ==
=== The great ellipse ===
Let &lt;math&gt;R_0&lt;/math&gt; be the origin, so that &lt;math&gt;{V_0}&lt;/math&gt; = the position vector of &lt;math&gt;R_1&lt;/math&gt;. The above approach provides an alternative to that of others, such as Bowring.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Bowring|first1=B.R.|title=The Direct and Inverse Solutions for the Great Elliptic Line on the Reference Ellipsoid|journal=Bulletin Geodesique|date=1984|volume=58|issue=1|pages=101-108}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Normal sections ===
The normal section at &lt;math&gt;P_1&lt;/math&gt; is determined by letting &lt;math&gt;{V_0}&lt;/math&gt; =  &lt;math&gt;\mathbf\hat{u_1}&lt;/math&gt; (the surface normal at &lt;math&gt;P_1&lt;/math&gt;). The above approach provides an alternative to that of others, such as Bowring.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Bowring|first1=B.R.|title=The normal section -- forward and inverse formulae at any distance|journal=Survey Review|date=1971|volume=XXI|issue=161|pages=131-136}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== The mean normal section ===
The mean normal section from &lt;math&gt;P_1&lt;/math&gt; to &lt;math&gt;P_2&lt;/math&gt; is determined by letting &lt;math&gt;{V_0}&lt;/math&gt; =  &lt;math&gt;0.5(\mathbf\hat{u_1}+\mathbf\hat{u_2})&lt;/math&gt;. This is a good approximation to the geodesic from &lt;math&gt;P_1&lt;/math&gt; to &lt;math&gt;P_2&lt;/math&gt; for aviation or sailing.

=== A class of sections ===
A class of sections may be imagined by rotating &lt;math&gt;\mathbf\hat{u_1}&lt;/math&gt; about the chord connecting &lt;math&gt;P_1&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;P_2.&lt;/math&gt; All of these may be solved with the single approach above.

== Intersections ==
Let two section planes be given: &lt;math&gt;\hat{N_1}&lt;/math&gt;⋅&lt;math&gt;R&lt;/math&gt; = &lt;math&gt;d_1&lt;/math&gt;, and &lt;math&gt;\hat{N_2}&lt;/math&gt;⋅&lt;math&gt;R&lt;/math&gt; = &lt;math&gt;d_2&lt;/math&gt;. Assuming that the two planes are not parallel, the line of intersection is on both planes. Hence orthogonal to both normals, i.e. in the direction of &lt;math&gt;\hat{N_3} = \hat{N_1} \times \hat{N_2}&lt;/math&gt;.

Since &lt;math&gt;\hat{N_1}&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;\hat{N_2}&lt;/math&gt; are not colinear &lt;math&gt;\hat{N_1}&lt;/math&gt;, &lt;math&gt;\hat{N_2}&lt;/math&gt;, &lt;math&gt;\hat{N_3}&lt;/math&gt; is a basis for &lt;math&gt;R^3&lt;/math&gt;. Therefore, there exist constants &lt;math&gt;C_1&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;C_2&lt;/math&gt; such that the line of intersection of the 2 planes is given by &lt;math&gt;R&lt;/math&gt; = &lt;math&gt;C_1\hat{N_1}&lt;/math&gt; + &lt;math&gt;C_2\hat{N_2}&lt;/math&gt; + t&lt;math&gt;\hat{N_3}&lt;/math&gt;, where t is an independent parameter.

Since this line is on both section planes, it satisfies both: 
&lt;math&gt;C_1&lt;/math&gt; + &lt;math&gt;C_2&lt;/math&gt;(&lt;math&gt;\hat{N_1}&lt;/math&gt;·&lt;math&gt;\hat{N_2}&lt;/math&gt;) = &lt;math&gt;d_1&lt;/math&gt;, and 
&lt;math&gt;C_1&lt;/math&gt;(&lt;math&gt;\hat{N_1}&lt;/math&gt;·&lt;math&gt;\hat{N_2}&lt;/math&gt;) + &lt;math&gt;C_2&lt;/math&gt; = &lt;math&gt;d_2&lt;/math&gt;.

Solving these equations for &lt;math&gt;{C_1}&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;{C_2}&lt;/math&gt; gives 
&lt;math&gt;C_1&lt;/math&gt; [1 - (&lt;math&gt;\hat{N_1}\hat{N_2})^2&lt;/math&gt; ] = &lt;math&gt;d_1&lt;/math&gt; - &lt;math&gt;d_2&lt;/math&gt;(&lt;math&gt;\hat{N_1}&lt;/math&gt;·&lt;math&gt;\hat{N_2}&lt;/math&gt;), and 
&lt;math&gt;C_2&lt;/math&gt; [1 - (&lt;math&gt;\hat{N_1}\hat{N_2})^2&lt;/math&gt; ] = &lt;math&gt;d_2&lt;/math&gt; - &lt;math&gt;d_1&lt;/math&gt;(&lt;math&gt;\hat{N_1}&lt;/math&gt;·&lt;math&gt;\hat{N_2}&lt;/math&gt;).

Define the “dihedral angle”, &lt;math&gt;\alpha&lt;/math&gt;, by &lt;math&gt;\cos\alpha&lt;/math&gt; = &lt;math&gt;{\hat{N_1}}&lt;/math&gt;·&lt;math&gt;{\hat{N_2}}&lt;/math&gt;.
Then &lt;math&gt;C_1&lt;/math&gt; = &lt;math&gt;\frac{(d_1- d_2  \cos\alpha)}{\sin^2\alpha}&lt;/math&gt; ,  and &lt;math&gt;C_2&lt;/math&gt; = &lt;math&gt;\frac{(d_2- d_1 \cos\alpha)}{\sin^2 \alpha}&lt;/math&gt;.

On the intersection line we have &lt;math&gt;R&lt;/math&gt; = &lt;math&gt;R_0&lt;/math&gt; + t&lt;math&gt;\hat{N_3}&lt;/math&gt;,  where &lt;math&gt;R_0&lt;/math&gt; = &lt;math&gt;C_1\hat{N_1}&lt;/math&gt; + &lt;math&gt;C_2\hat{N_2}&lt;/math&gt;.
Hence: &lt;math&gt;x&lt;/math&gt; = &lt;math&gt;x_0&lt;/math&gt; + t&lt;math&gt;l_3&lt;/math&gt;, &lt;math&gt;y&lt;/math&gt; = &lt;math&gt;y_0&lt;/math&gt; + t&lt;math&gt;m_3&lt;/math&gt;,  and &lt;math&gt;z&lt;/math&gt; = &lt;math&gt;z_0&lt;/math&gt; + t&lt;math&gt;n_3&lt;/math&gt;, where
&lt;math&gt;x_0&lt;/math&gt;= &lt;math&gt;C_1l_1&lt;/math&gt; + &lt;math&gt;C_2l_2&lt;/math&gt;, &lt;math&gt;y_0&lt;/math&gt; = &lt;math&gt;C_1m_1&lt;/math&gt; + &lt;math&gt;C_2m_2&lt;/math&gt;, and &lt;math&gt;z_0&lt;/math&gt; = &lt;math&gt;C_1n_1&lt;/math&gt; +&lt;math&gt;C_2n_2&lt;/math&gt;.
and &lt;math&gt;\hat{N_i}&lt;/math&gt;=(&lt;math&gt;l_i&lt;/math&gt;,&lt;math&gt;m_i&lt;/math&gt;,&lt;math&gt;n_i&lt;/math&gt;), for i=1,2,3.

To find the intersection of this line with the earth, plug the line equations into &lt;math&gt;\frac{x^2}{a^2}+\frac{y^2}{a^2}+\frac{z^2}{b^2} = 1&lt;/math&gt;, to get
&lt;math&gt;At^2 + 2Bt + C = 0&lt;/math&gt;, where &lt;math&gt;A&lt;/math&gt; = &lt;math&gt;l_3^2 + m_3^2 + \frac{a^2}{b^2}n_3^2&lt;/math&gt;, 
&lt;math&gt;B&lt;/math&gt; = &lt;math&gt;x_0l_3 + y_0m_3 + \frac{a^2}{b^2}z_0n_3&lt;/math&gt;,
&lt;math&gt;C&lt;/math&gt; = &lt;math&gt;x_0^2 + y_0^2 + \frac{a^2}{b^2}z_0^2 - a^2&lt;/math&gt;.

Therefore, the line intersects the earth at &lt;math&gt;t = \frac{-B \pm \sqrt{{B}^2-AC}}{A}&lt;/math&gt;. If &lt;math&gt;B^2 &lt; AC&lt;/math&gt;, then there is no intersection. If &lt;math&gt;B^2 = AC&lt;/math&gt;, then the line is tangent to the earth at &lt;math&gt;t = -B/A&lt;/math&gt; (i.e. the sections intersect at that single point).

Observe that &lt;math&gt;A\ne0&lt;/math&gt; since &lt;math&gt;\hat{N_1}&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;\hat{N_2}&lt;/math&gt;are not colinear.  Plugging t into
&lt;math&gt;R&lt;/math&gt; = &lt;math&gt;R_0&lt;/math&gt; + t&lt;math&gt;\hat{N_3}&lt;/math&gt;, gives the points of intersection of the earth sections.

=== Examples ===
==== Maximum or Minimum Latitude ====
on a earth section path may be found by dropping the subscripts on the given section; &lt;math&gt;\hat{N_1} = (l, m, n)&lt;/math&gt;,  &lt;math&gt;d_1 = d&lt;/math&gt;, and setting &lt;math&gt;\hat{N_2} = (0, 0, 1)&lt;/math&gt;, so that &lt;math&gt;\hat{N_3} = (m, -l, 0)&lt;/math&gt;. Then solve for &lt;math&gt;d_2 = z_2&lt;/math&gt; such that &lt;math&gt;B^2 = AC&lt;/math&gt;.

Since &lt;math&gt;B = 0&lt;/math&gt;, and &lt;math&gt;A \ne 0&lt;/math&gt;, we must have &lt;math&gt;C = 0&lt;/math&gt;. Plugging t into &lt;math&gt;R&lt;/math&gt; = &lt;math&gt;R_0 + t\hat{N_3}&lt;/math&gt;, gives the points of intersection of the earth sections. Alternatively, just set &lt;math&gt;R = {R_c} \pm b^*\mathbf{\hat{j^*}}&lt;/math&gt;.

==== Maximum or Minimum Longitude ====
on a earth section path may be found by dropping the subscripts on the given section; &lt;math&gt;\hat{N_1} = (l, m, n)&lt;/math&gt;,  &lt;math&gt;d_1 = d&lt;/math&gt;, and setting &lt;math&gt;\hat{N_2} = (-\sin\theta, \cos\theta, 0)&lt;/math&gt;, where &lt;math&gt;\theta&lt;/math&gt; is the longitude to be solved for such that &lt;math&gt;B^2 = AC&lt;/math&gt;.

Alternatively, just set &lt;math&gt;R = {R_c} \pm a^*\mathbf{\hat{i^*}}&lt;/math&gt;.

==References==
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Geography]]
[[Category:Geodesy]]</text>
      <sha1>m2u474ax1rjh2bhmxmcqegjshqc4yp7</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Easting and northing</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9177450</id>
    <revision>
      <id>851601593</id>
      <parentid>821684761</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-07-23T11:41:49Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Smartse</username>
        <id>1640548</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Other usage */ this isn't related to the article subject. I've moved the ref to [[wikt:northing]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="2910">The terms '''easting''' and '''northing''' are [[Geography|geographic]] [[Cartesian coordinate system|Cartesian coordinates]] for a point. Easting refers to the [[east]]ward-measured distance (or the ''x''-[[coordinate]]), while northing refers to the [[north]]ward-measured distance (or the ''y''-coordinate). When using common projections such as the [[transverse Mercator projection]], these are distances [[Map projection|projected]] on an imaginary surface similar to a bent sheet of paper, and are not the same as distances measured on the [[Figure of the Earth|curved surface of the Earth]].
[[File:Utm-zones.jpg|thumb|UTM-zones]]

Easting and northing coordinates are commonly measured in metres from the axes of some [[datum (geodesy)#Horizontal datum|horizontal datum]]. However, other units (e.g., [[survey feet]]) are also used. The coordinates are most commonly associated with the [[Universal Transverse Mercator coordinate system#Locating a position using UTM coordinates|Universal Transverse Mercator coordinate system]] (UTM), which has unique zones that cover the Earth to provide detailed referencing.

==Notation and conventions==
Locations can be found using easting/northing (or '' x'', ''y'') pairs. The pair is usually represented conventionally with easting first, northing second.

For example, the peak of [[Mount Assiniboine]] (at {{coord|50|52|10|N|115|39|03|W}}) in UTM Zone 11 is represented by &lt;code&gt;11U 594934 5636174&lt;/code&gt;. Other conventions can also be used, such as a truncated grid reference,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bivouac.com/PgxPg.asp?PgxId=155 |title=Truncated Grid References |publisher=Bivouac.com - Canadian Mountain Encyclopedia|date=2006-11-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; which would shorten the example coordinates to &lt;code&gt;949-361&lt;/code&gt;.

Negative northing and easting values indicate a position due south and west of the origin, respectively.

{{anchor|False origin}}{{anchor|Natural origin}}Usually associated with a map projection is a ''natural origin'', e.g., at which the ellipsoid and flat map surfaces coincide.&lt;ref name=OGP7_2&gt;{{cite web|title=Geomatics  Guidance Note Number 7, part 2    Coordinate Conversions and Transformations including Formulas|url=http://info.ogp.org.uk/geodesy/guides/docs/G7-2.pdf|publisher=International Association of Oil and Gas Producers (OGP)|accessdate=5 March 2014|pages=9–10|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140306005736/http://info.ogp.org.uk/geodesy/guides/docs/G7-2.pdf|archivedate=6 March 2014|df=}}&lt;/ref&gt; To ensure that the northing and easting coordinates on a map are not negative, map projections may set up a ''false origin'', specified in terms of ''false northing'' and ''false easting'' values, that offset the true origin.

==See also==
* [[Horizontal plane]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Orientation (geometry)]]
[[Category:Geography]]
[[Category:Surveying]]
[[Category:Cartography]]</text>
      <sha1>j7mc3plo6lce8s1tbpd7dewaj6eai1t</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Economic restructuring</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>16971924</id>
    <revision>
      <id>798100753</id>
      <parentid>798087043</parentid>
      <timestamp>2017-08-31T00:27:04Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>AnomieBOT</username>
        <id>7611264</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Dating maintenance tags: {{Clarify}}</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="14352">'''Economic [[restructuring]]''' refers to the phenomenon of Western [[urban areas]] shifting from a [[manufacturing]] to a [[service sector]] economic base. This transformation has affected demographics including [[income]] distribution, [[employment]], and [[social hierarchy]]; institutional arrangements including the growth of the [[corporate]] complex, specialized producer services, capital mobility, [[informal economy]], nonstandard work, and public outlays; as well as geographic spacing including the rise of [[world cities]], [[spatial mismatch]], and metropolitan growth differentials.&lt;ref&gt;Sassen 1990, Noyelle &amp; Stanback 1984, Logan &amp; Swanstrom 1990, Musterd &amp; Ostendorf 1998, Kalleberg 2000 and Katz 1997&lt;/ref&gt;

==Demographic impact==
As cities experience a loss of manufacturing jobs and growth of services, sociologist [[Saskia Sassen]] affirms that a widening of the social hierarchy occurs where high-level, high-income, salaried professional jobs expands in the service industries alongside a greater incidence of low-wage, low-skilled jobs, usually filled by immigrants and minorities.&lt;ref name="Sassen 1990"&gt;Sassen 1990&lt;/ref&gt; A "missing middle" eventually develops in the wage structure.&lt;ref name="Musterd &amp; Ostendorf 1998"&gt;Musterd &amp; Ostendorf 1998&lt;/ref&gt; Several effects of this [[social polarization]] include the increasing concentration of poverty in large U.S. cities, the increasing concentration of black and Hispanic populations in large U.S. cities, and distinct social forms such as the [[underclass]], [[informal economy]], and entrepreneurial immigrant communities.&lt;ref name="Sassen 1990"/&gt; In addition, the declining manufacturing sector leaves behind strained blue-collared workers who endure chronic [[unemployment]], economic insecurity, and [[Economic stagnation|stagnation]] due to the global economy's [[capital flight]].&lt;ref name="Logan &amp; Swanstrom 1990"&gt;Logan &amp; Swanstrom 1990&lt;/ref&gt; Wages and unionization rates for manufacturing jobs also decline. One other qualitative dimension involves the [[Feminisation of the workplace|feminization]] of the job supply as more and more women enter the labor force usually in the service sector.&lt;ref name="Sassen economic restructuring"&gt;{{citation|author= Sassen, Saskia|title=Economic Restructuring and the American City|publisher=Annual Review of Sociology|year=1990}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Both costs and benefits are associated with economic restructuring. Greater efficiency, job creation, [[gentrification]], and enhanced national competitiveness are associated with [[social exclusion]] and inclusion.{{Clarify|date=August 2017}}&lt;ref name="Logan &amp; Swanstrom 1990"/&gt; The low-skilled, low-income population faces the loss of opportunities, full participation in society, lack of access in labor market and school, weak position in housing markets, limited political participation, and restricted social-cultural integration. Conversely, high-skilled, high-income professionals enjoy social inclusion with modern amenities, conveniences, social participation, and full access to public resources.&lt;ref name="Musterd &amp; Ostendorf 1998"/&gt;

Furthermore, sociologist [[William Julius Wilson]] argues that the [[deindustrialization]] of manufacturing employment have exacerbated joblessness in impoverished African American communities correlating with a rise in single-mother households, high premature mortality rates, and increasing [[incarceration]] rates among African American males. With some African Americans gaining professional [[upward mobility]] through [[affirmative action]] and [[equal opportunity]] sanctions in [[education]] and [[employment]], African Americans without such opportunities fall behind. This creates a growing economic class division among the African American demographic accentuated by global economic restructuring without government response to the disadvantaged. Furthermore, Wilson asserts that as the black [[middle class]] leave the predominantly black [[inner city]] neighborhoods, informal employment information networks are eroded. This isolates poor, inner city residents from the labor market compounding the concentration of poverty, [[welfare dependency]], rise of unemployment, and physical isolation in these areas.&lt;ref name="Wilson Declining Race"&gt;{{citation|author= Wilson, William J.|title=The Declining Significance of Race: Blacks and Changing American Institutions|publisher=University of Chicago Press|year=1980}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Wilson Truly Disadvantaged"&gt;{{citation|author= Wilson, William J.|title=The Truly Disadvantaged: the Inner City, the Underclass, and Public Policy|publisher=University of Chicago Press|year=1987}}&lt;/ref&gt;

City youth are also affected such as in New York City. The declines in education, health care, and social services and the dearth of jobs for those with limited education and training along with the decay of public environments for outdoor play and recreation have all contributed to fewer autonomous outdoor play or "hanging out" places for young people. This in turn affects their gross motor development, cultural build-up, and identity construction. Children become prisoners of home relying on television and other outlets for companionship. Contemporary urban environments restricts the opportunities for children to forge and negotiate peer culture or acquire necessary social skills. Overall, their ecologies have eroded in recent years brought about by global restructuring.&lt;ref name="Katz City Youth"&gt;{{citation|author= Katz, indi|title=Disintegrating Developments: Global Economic Restructuring and the Eroding of Ecologies of Youth|publisher=Routledge|year=1997}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Institutional arrangements==
When the [[1973 oil crisis]] affected the world capitalist economy, economic restructuring was used to remedy the situation by geographically redistributing production, consumption, and residences.
City economies across the globe moved from goods-producing to service-producing outlets.
Breakthroughs in transportation and communications made industrial capital much more mobile. Soon, producer services emerged as a fourth basic [[economic sector]] where routine low-wage service employment moved to low-cost sites and advanced corporate services centralized in cities.&lt;ref name="Logan &amp; Swanstrom 1990"/&gt; These technological upheavals brought about changes in institutional arrangements with the prominence of large corporations, allied business and financial services, nonprofit and public sector enterprises. [[Global cities]] such as New York and London become centers for international finance and headquarters for [[multinational corporations]] offering cross currency exchange services as well as buildup of foreign banking and trading. Other cities become regional headquarters centers of low-wage manufacturing. In all these urban areas the corporate complex grows offering banking, insurance, advertising, legal council, and other service functions. Economic restructuring allows markets to expand in size and capacity from regional to national to international scopes.&lt;ref name="Noyelle City Transformation"&gt;{{citation|author1=Noyelle, Thierry J.  |author2=Stanback, Thomas M., Jr.|title=The Economic Transformation of American Cities|publisher=Rowman &amp; Allanheld Publishers|year=1984}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Altogether, these institutional arrangements buttressed by improved technology reflect the interconnectedness and internationalization of firms and economic processes. Consequently, capital, goods, and people rapidly flow across borders.&lt;ref name="Musterd &amp; Ostendorf 1998"/&gt; Where the mode of regulation began with [[Fordism]] and [[Taylorization]] in the [[industrial age]] then to [[mass consumption]] of [[Keynesian economics]] policies, it evolves to differentiated and specialized consumption through international competition.&lt;ref name="Logan &amp; Swanstrom 1990"/&gt; Additionally, in the labor market, nonstandard work arrangements develop in the form of part-time work, temporary agency and contract company employment, short-term employment, [[contingent work]], and independent contracting. Global economic changes and technological improvements in communications and information systems encouraged competitive organizations to specialize in production easily and assemble temporary workers quickly for specific projects. Thus, the norm of standard, steady employment unravels beginning in the mid-1970s.&lt;ref name="Musterd Urban Segregation"&gt;{{citation|author1=Musterd, Sako  |author2=Ostendorf, Wim|title=Urban Segregation and the Welfare State: Inequality and Exclusion in Western Cities|publisher=Routledge|year=1998}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Kalleberg Nonstandard Work"&gt;{{citation|author= Kalleberg, Arne L.|title=Nonstandard Employment Relations: Part-time, Temporary, and Contract Work|publisher=Annual Review of Sociology|year=2000}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Another shift in institutional arrangement involves public resources. As economic restructuring encourages high-technology service and knowledge-based economies, massive public de-investment results. Across many parts of the U.S. and the industrialized Western nations, steep declines in public outlays occur in housing, schools, social welfare, education, job training, job creation, child care, recreation, and open space. To remedy these cutbacks, [[privatization]] is installed as a suitable measure. Though it leads to some improvements in service production, privatization leads to less public accountability and greater unevenness in the distribution of resources.&lt;ref&gt;Katz 1997&lt;/ref&gt; With this reform in privatizing public services, [[neoliberalism]] has become the ideological platform of economic restructuring. Free market economic theory has dismantled Keynesian and collectivists’ strategies and promoted the [[Reaganomics|Reagan]] and [[Thatcherism|Thatcher]] politics of the 1980s. Soon free trade, flexible labor, and capital flight are used from [[Washington D.C.]] to London to Moscow.&lt;ref&gt;Peck &amp; Tickell 2002&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, economic restructuring requires [[decentralization]] as states hand down power to local governments. Where the federal government focuses on mainly warfare-welfare concerns, local governments focus on productivity. Urban policy reflects this market-oriented shift from once supporting government functions to now endorsing businesses.&lt;ref name="Peck Neoliberalism"&gt;{{citation|author1=Peck, Jamie  |author2=Tickell, Adam|title=The Urbanization of Neoliberalism: Theoretical Debates Neoliberalizing Space|publisher=Antipode|year=2002}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Logan City Limits"&gt;{{citation|author1=Logan, John R.  |author2=Swanstrom, Todd|title=Beyond City Limits: Urban Policy and Economic Restructuring in Comparative Perspective|publisher=Temple University Press|year=1990}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Geographic impact==
Urban landscapes especially in the U.S. have significantly altered in response to economic restructuring. Cities such as Baltimore, Detroit, St. Louis and others face population losses which result in thousands of abandoned homes, unused buildings, and vacant lots, contributing to [[urban decay]]. Such transformations frustrate [[urban planning]] and revitalization, fostering deviance in the forms of drug-related activity and vagrancy.&lt;ref&gt;Cohen 2001&lt;/ref&gt; Older, compact, industrial U.S. cities have been rendered obsolete. Urban spaces become playgrounds for the urban gentry, wastelands for low-paid service workers, and denizens for the [[underground economy]]. In some areas, [[gentrification]] projects have caused displacement of poverty-stricken residents.&lt;ref name="Logan &amp; Swanstrom 1990"/&gt; [[Sunbelt]] cities such as [[Miami]] and [[Atlanta]] rise to become key business centers while Snowbelt cities such as [[Buffalo, New York|Buffalo]] and Youngstown decline.&lt;ref name="Noyelle &amp; Stanback 1984"&gt;Noyelle &amp; Stanback 1984&lt;/ref&gt; Even housing markets respond to economic restructuring with decaying housing stocks, escalating housing prices, depleting tax base, changes in financing, and reduction in federal support for housing. Soon, spatial divisions among wealthy and poor households exacerbate.&lt;ref name="Sassen 1990"/&gt; Moreover, with the movement of blue-collared employment from central cities, geographically entrenched housing discrimination, and suburban land use policy, African American youths in inner cities become victims of [[spatial mismatch]], where their residences provide only weak and negative employment growth and they usually lack access to intrametropolitan mobility.&lt;ref&gt;Raphael 1998&lt;/ref&gt; High-order services, an expanding sector in the industrialized world, become spatially concentrated in a relative small number of large metropolitan areas, particularly in suburban office agglomerations.&lt;ref name="Cohen Abandoned Houses"&gt;{{citation|author= Cohen, James R.|title=Abandoned Housing: Exploring Lessons from Baltimore|publisher=Housing Policy Debate|year=2001}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Raphael Spatial Mismatch"&gt;{{citation|author= Raphael, Steven|title=The Spatial Mismatch Hypothesis and Black Youth Joblessness|publisher=Journal of Urban Economics|year=1998}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Coffey Intrametropolitan"&gt;{{citation|author1=Coffey, William J. |author2=Drolet, Rejean |author3=Polese, Mario |title=The Intrametropolitan Location of High Order Services|publisher=Papers in Regional Science|year=1996}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Meaning==
In cultural terms, economic restructuring has been associated with [[postmodernity]] as its counterpart concerning flexible accumulation. Additionally, the term carries with it three core themes: historical, radical rupture into post-industrial economic order; priority of economic forces over social/political forces; and structure over agency where the process is independent of human will, as it takes place according to economic logic (Logan &amp; Swanstrom 1990). In addition, economic restructuring demonstrates the increasing complex and human-capital intensive modern society in Western nations.&lt;ref name="Noyelle &amp; Stanback 1984"/&gt;

==See also==
* [[Manufacturing]]
* [[Service sector]]
* [[Global city]]
* [[Spatial mismatch]]
* [[Informal economy]]
* [[Capital flight]]
* [[Gentrification]]
* [[Social exclusion]]
* [[Upward mobility]]
* [[Suburbanization]]
* [[Social hierarchy]]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Economic Restructuring}}
[[Category:Economic sectors]]
[[Category:Demography]]
[[Category:Geography]]</text>
      <sha1>orlz5bcogjca7l4932blpt6ex8s1r97</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Edgelands</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>47802272</id>
    <revision>
      <id>841192513</id>
      <parentid>801503980</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-05-14T15:04:54Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>DeprecatedFixerBot</username>
        <id>33330201</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Removed deprecated parameter(s) from [[Template:Columns-list]] using [[User:DeprecatedFixerBot| DeprecatedFixerBot]]. Questions? See [[Template:Div col#Usage of "cols" parameter]] or [[User talk:TheSandDoctor|msg TSD!]] (please mention that this is task #2!))</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="3141">{{redirect|Edgeland|the album by Karl Hyde|Edgeland (album)}}
'''Edgelands''' are the transitional, [[Liminality|liminal]] areas of space to be found on the boundaries of country and town - with the spread of [[urbanisation]], an increasingly important facet of the twenty-first century world.&lt;ref&gt;Andrew Walker - 2002 Aspects of Lincoln: Discovering Local History - Page 134 1473836131 "AN 'EDGE-LAND': THE DEVELOPMENT OF THE WITHAM VALLEY EAST OF CANWICK ROAD by Dennis Mills THE TERM 'EDGE-LAND' has been coined recently for the concept of a neglected area on the fringe of a city. Frequently such ..."&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
The concept of Edgelands was introduced by [[Marion Shoard]] in 2002, to cover the disorganised but often fertile hinterland between planned town and over-managed country.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.independent.co.uk/news/uk/this-britain/our-beautiful-edgelands-a-dark-light-on-the-edge-of-town-2217071.html Our beautiful edgelands]&lt;/ref&gt;  However a century and a half earlier, [[Victor Hugo]] had already highlighted the existence of what he called "bastard countryside...ugly but bizarre, made up of two different natures, which surrounds certain great cities";&lt;ref&gt;Quoted in [[Robert Macfarlane (writer)|Robert Macfarlane]], ''Landmarks'' (2015) p. 231&lt;/ref&gt; while [[Richard Jeffries]] similarly explored the London edgeland in ''Nature near London'' (1883).
[[Alice Coleman]] (Kings College London, dept geography) in 2nd Land Use Survey of Great Britain, refers to  "rurban fringe". Indicating a similar landscape but with negative overtones.

Nevertheless it was only in the last decades of the twentieth century - as a distinct realm of Nature increasingly disappeared beneath the commodifying impact of globalising [[late capitalism]]&lt;ref&gt;[[Frederic Jameson]], ''The Jameson Reader'' (2002) p. 251&lt;/ref&gt; - that the significance of the unstructured borderlands between organised town and organised country, part man-made, part natural,&lt;ref&gt;M. Pratt, ''My Wild Northumbria'' (2015) p. 176 and 208&lt;/ref&gt; both for wildlife and for human exploration, came into fuller focus. [[Psychogeography]] charted the London orbital, while bombsites, canal banks and brownfield sites were documented in poetry and prose, film and photography;&lt;ref&gt;Robert Macfarlane, ''Landmarks'' (2015) p. 232&lt;/ref&gt; and the borderlands as an untapped, transgressive resource became almost the object of a new cult.&lt;ref&gt;T. Fry, ''Design in the Borderlands'' (2014) p. 159&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Columns-list|colwidth=22em|
*[[Deep topography]]
*[[Geocriticism]]
*[[Human geography]]
*[[Edward Soja#Thirdspace|Thirdspace]]
*[[Topophilia]]
*[[W. G. Sebald]]
}}

== References ==
{{Reflist|2|}}

==Further reading==
*[[Richard Mabey]], ''The Unofficial Countryside'' (1973)
*[[Marion Shoard]], ''Edgelands'' (2002)
*[[Paul Farley]] and Michael Roberts, ''Edgelands'' (2012)

== External links ==
* [http://www.alluvium-journal.org/2015/06/26/towards-a-taxonomy-of-edgelands-literature/ Towards a Taxonomy of Edgelands Literature]

[[Category:Literary criticism]]
[[Category:Cultural geography]]
[[Category:Geography]]
[[Category:Environmental humanities]]</text>
      <sha1>704qhrw3nynzhhmaoozlgmkyy6qt8hy</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Extreme environment</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>16953152</id>
    <revision>
      <id>868990599</id>
      <parentid>866641480</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-11-15T18:30:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>192.107.120.90</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bolded title in article</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="5588">An '''extreme environment''' contains conditions that are hard to survive for most known [[life form]]s. These conditions may be extremely high or low [[temperature]] or [[pressure]]; high or low content of [[oxygen]] or [[carbon dioxide]] in the [[atmosphere]]; high levels of [[radiation]], [[acidity]], or [[alkalinity]]; absence of water; water containing a high concentration of salt or sugar; presence of [[sulphur]], [[petroleum]], and other [[toxic]] substances.

Examples of extreme environments include the [[geographical pole]]s, very arid [[deserts]], [[volcano]]es, deep [[ocean trench]]es, [[upper atmosphere]], [[Mt Everest]], [[outer space]], and the environments of every [[planet]] in the [[Solar System]] except the [[Earth]]. Any organisms living in these conditions are often very well adapted to their living circumstances, which is usually a result of long-term evolution. Physiologists have long known that organisms living in extreme environments are especially likely to exhibit clear examples of evolutionary adaptation because of the presumably intense past natural selection they have experienced.&lt;ref&gt;Garland, Jr., T., and P. A. Carter. 1994. Evolutionary physiology. Annual Review of Physiology 56:579–621.&lt;/ref&gt;

==On Earth==
The distribution of extreme environments on [[Earth]] has varied through [[geological time]]. Humans generally do not inhabit extreme environments. There are organisms referred to as [[extremophile]]s that do live in such conditions and are so well-adapted that they readily grow and multiply.

==Beyond Earth==
Most of the moons and planets in the [[Solar System]] are also extreme environments. [[Astrobiology|Astrobiologists]] have not yet found life in any environments beyond Earth, though experiments have shown that [[tardigrades]] can survive the harsh vacuum and intense radiation of outer space. The conceptual modification of  conditions in locations beyond Earth, to make them more habitable by humans and other terrestrial organisms, is known as [[terraforming]].

==Types==
Among extreme environments are [[alkaline]], [[acidic]], extremely cold, extremely hot, [[hyper-saline]], places without water or [[oxygen]], and places altered by humans, such as mine [[tailings]] or oil impacted habitats.
&lt;ref name="Types of Extreme Environments"&gt;{{cite web|title=Types of Extreme Environments|url=http://serc.carleton.edu/microbelife/extreme/environments.html|work=NSF|accessdate=16 May 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name="Extreme Environments"&gt;{{cite web|title=Extreme Environments|url=http://www.windows2universe.org/earth/extreme_environments.html|publisher=PeckHart Landscaping inc.|accessdate=17 May 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* Alkaline: broadly conceived as natural [[habitats]] above pH 9 whether persistently, or with regular frequency or for protracted periods of time.
* Acidic: broadly conceived as natural habitats below pH 5 whether persistently, or with regular frequency or for protracted periods of time.
* Extremely cold: broadly conceived habitats periodically or consistently below -17&amp;nbsp;°C either persistently, or with regular frequency or for protracted periods of time. Includes montane sites, polar sites, and deep ocean habitats.
* Extremely hot: broadly conceived habitats periodically or consistently in excess of 40&amp;nbsp;°C either persistently, or with regular frequency or for protracted periods of time. Includes sites with [[geological thermal]] influences such as Yellowstone and comparable locations worldwide or deep-sea vents.
* Hypersaline: (high salt) environments with salt concentrations greater than that of seawater, that is, &gt;3.5%. Includes salt lakes.
* Under pressure: broadly conceived as habitats under extreme hydrostatic pressure — i.e. aquatic habitats deeper than 2000 meters and enclosed habitats under pressure. Includes habitats in oceans and deep lakes.
* Radiation: broadly conceived as habitats exposed to abnormally high [[radiation]] or of radiation outside the normal range of light. Includes habitats exposed to high UV and IR radiation.
* Without water: broadly conceived as habitats without free water whether persistently, or with regular frequency or for protracted periods of time. Includes hot and cold desert environments, and some endolithic habitats.
* Without oxygen: broadly conceived as habitats without free oxygen - whether persistently, or with regular frequency, or for protracted periods of time. Includes habitats in deeper sediments.
* Altered by humans, i.e. anthropogenically impacted habitats. Includes mine tailings, oil impacted habitats, and pollution by [[Heavy metal (chemistry)|heavy metal]]s or [[organic compound]]s.

== Picture gallery ==
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Everest kalapatthar crop.jpg|[[Mount Everest]]
File:Libya 5230 Wan Caza Dunes Luca Galuzzi 2007.jpg|[[Desert]]
File:Top of Atmosphere.jpg|[[Atmosphere]] and [[Universe]]
File:MtCleveland ISS013-E-24184.jpg|[[Volcano]]
File:Blacksmoker in Atlantic Ocean.jpg|[[Hydrothermal vent]]
File:DeadSeaIsrael.jpg|High salinity of the [[Dead Sea]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Environment|Ecology}}
* [[Adaptation]]
* [[Ecology]]
* [[Ecophysiology]]
* [[Evolutionary physiology]]
* [[Extreme environment clothing]]
* [[Extremophile]]
* [[LExEN]] (Life in Extreme Environments)
* [[Natural environment]]

==References==
* [http://serc.carleton.edu/microbelife/extreme/environments.html  "Extreme Environment." Microbial Life. N.p., n.d. Web. 16 May 2013.]
* {{Reflist}}

* {{Original research|date=May 2012}}

* {{DEFAULTSORT:Extreme Environment}}
* [[Category:Extremophiles]]
* [[Category:Geography]]</text>
      <sha1>43z4xwabsbsqq6ab9pkvut9qn02fjyp</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Fictional geography</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3280844</id>
    <revision>
      <id>777863929</id>
      <parentid>713317145</parentid>
      <timestamp>2017-04-29T19:42:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Goustien</username>
        <id>4440889</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>added [[Category:Geography]] using [[WP:HC|HotCat]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="990">{{Unreferenced stub|auto=yes|date=December 2009}}
'''Fictional geography''' is the use of maps, text and imagery to create lands and territories to accompany works of fiction. Depending on the completeness and complexity of the work, varying media, levels of collaboration and a number of other factors, the depiction of geographical components to works of fiction can range from simple drawings of a small area as in ''[[The Twenty-One Balloons]]'' by [[William Pène du Bois]] to an entire fictional world as in ''[[The Lord of the Rings]]'' by [[Tolkien]] or even an entire galaxy as in ''[[Star Trek]]'' and its variants.

==Middle-earth==
One of the most notable examples of fictional geography is that created by [[J. R. R. Tolkien]] to produce the [[Shire (Middle-earth)|Shire]] and its expansion to include all of [[Middle-earth]].

==See also==
*[[List of fictional location types]]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Fictional Geography}}
[[Category:Fictional maps| geography]]
[[Category:Geography]]</text>
      <sha1>10mwdstozhz3993oszoxdu3s6ck9gv0</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Fluvio-glacial</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2855257</id>
    <revision>
      <id>865056593</id>
      <parentid>861571556</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-10-21T12:21:06Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>2405:204:4388:C3DE:0:0:235C:78AC</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="5244">Fluvio refers to things related to rivers and glacial refers to something that is of ice. '''Fluvio-glacial''' refers to the [[meltwater]] created when a [[glacier]] melts.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://en.oxforddictionaries.com/definition/us/fluvio-|title=fluvio- - definition of fluvio- in English {{!}} Oxford Dictionaries|website=Oxford Dictionaries {{!}} English|access-date=2017-05-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://en.oxforddictionaries.com/definition/glacial|title=glacial - definition... of glacial in English {{!}} Oxford Dictionaries|website=Oxford Dictionaries {{!}} English|access-date=2017-05-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fluvio-glacial processes can occur on the surface and within the glacier. The [[Deposition (geology)|deposits]] that happen within the glacier are revealed after the entire glacier melts or partially retreats. Fluvio-glacial [[landform]]s and [[erosion]]al surfaces include: [[outwash plain]]s, [[kame]]&lt;nowiki/&gt;s, kame terraces, [[Kettle (landform)|kettle holes]], [[esker]]s, [[varve]]s, and [[proglacial lake]]s.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.coolgeography.co.uk/A-level/AQA/Year%2012/Cold%20environs/Fluvioglacial/Fluvioglacial%20landforms.htm|title=Fluvioglacial Landforms|last=|first=|date=|website=Coolgeography.co.uk|archive-url=|archive-date=|dead-url=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Landforms ==

=== Outwash Plain ===
An outwash plain is both an erosional and depositional surface created by meltwater coming from the glacier. These plains are found in front of the glaciers and are typically characterized by small [[Braided river|braided streams]].&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; The streams are usually small and braided because the [[sediment]] size varies and the original stream gets broken up.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Since these streams [[meander]] around, the erosion happens laterally (left to right)  instead of vertically (up and down).&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; These plains are usually found beyond the [[Terminal moraine|end moraine]] deposited by the glacier.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

=== Kame and Kame Terrace ===
[[Kame]]&lt;nowiki/&gt;s are small hills that consist of sediments ranging from sands to gravels.&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite book|title=Geomorphology|last=Gutierrez|first=Mateo|publisher=CRC Press|year=2013|isbn=|location=Leiden|pages=538–545}}&lt;/ref&gt; Intraglacial movement of water carries sediments and deposits them inside cavaties, or holes, in the glacier; once the glacier melts or retreats, the kames is left behind as a deposit. These hills can range in size and be up to 50 m tall and 400 m wide.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; A kame terrace is a relatively flat surface of sediment that was deposited between the valley surface and the glacier. When kames, kame surfaces, and other fluvio-glacial landforms are combined into one landscape, it is called a kame complex or glacial [[Karst|karst topography]].

=== Kettle Holes ===
[[Kettle (landform)|Kettle holes]] are typically formed when a chunk of ice that came from the glacier is buried under fluvio-glacial sediments.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/bitesize/higher/geography/physical/lithosphere/revision/7/|title=BBC - Higher Bitesize Geography - Lithosphere : Revision, Page7|access-date=2017-05-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; Once the ice melts, the sediments fall and form a depression that can later be filled with rainwater and form [[Kettle (landform)|kettle lakes]]. Kettle holes can often be found in the outwash plain of a glacier.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Kettle holes can be anywhere from 5 m to 30&amp;nbsp;km wide.

=== Eskers ===
Eskers can be describes as long, curved ridges made up of sands and gravels.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://books.google.com/books/about/Soil_Geomorphology.html?id=H9FSveDbpbsC|title=Soil Geomorphology|last=Gerrard|first=A J|date=|website=Google Books|archive-url=|archive-date=|dead-url=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; These surfaces were created by intraglacial streams carrying and depositing sediments as they flow through the glacier. These landforms can range from 100 m to 500&amp;nbsp;km long and 3 m to 200 m tall.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

=== Varves ===
Varves are a depositional feature of a fluvio-glacial movement. They are layers of annual sediment deposits. The sizes of the sediments vary and depend on the volume of the streams, but are usually associated with mud deposits ([[silt]] and [[clay]]).&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.britannica.com/science/varved-deposit|title=varved deposit {{!}} geology|work=Encyclopædia Britannica|access-date=2017-05-12|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; The color and amount of the sediment deposited also varies depending upon the season; summer deposits typically have larger volumes of deposition and are characterized as being light, whereas winter deposits are usually the opposite.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt; Winter deposits are fairly uncommon because the water is frozen into ice again.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;

=== Proglacial Lakes ===
[[Proglacial lake]]s form as meltwater trapped behind a glacial feature such as an end moraine.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; These lakes have an intake of sediment deposited by streams within the glacier and their deposits are recorded within the varves.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

[[Category:Glaciology]]
[[Category:Geomorphology]]
[[Category:Geography]]
[[Category:Fluvial geomorphology]]</text>
      <sha1>dj7xi610nb8382ydzjfwtuhncmz3wnm</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Fundamental plane (spherical coordinates)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8081066</id>
    <revision>
      <id>858670566</id>
      <parentid>829604622</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-09-08T21:13:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Twinsday</username>
        <id>4897226</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* top */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="1765">{{For|the concept in extragalactic astronomy|Fundamental plane (elliptical galaxies)}}

The '''fundamental plane''' in a [[spherical coordinate system]] is a [[plane of reference]] that divides the [[sphere]] into two [[Sphere|hemisphere]]s. The [[latitude]] of a [[point (geometry)|point]] is then the [[angle]] between the fundamental plane and the line joining the point to the centre of the sphere.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=It's ONLY Rocket Science: An Introduction in Plain English|first=Lucy|last=Rogers|publisher=Springer|year=2008|isbn=9780387753782|page=136|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=JTFGAAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA136}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

For a [[geographic coordinate system]] of the Earth, the fundamental plane is the [[Equator]]. [[Celestial coordinate system]]s have varying fundamental planes:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=A Compendium of Spherical Astronomy with Its Applications to the Determination and Reduction of Positions of the Fixed Stars |first=Simon |last=Newcomb |publisher=Macmillan |year=1906 |page=92 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=CAxDAAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA92}}.&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[horizontal coordinate system]] uses the observer's [[horizon]].
* The Besselian coordinate system uses Earth's [[terminator (solar)|terminator]] (day/night boundary). This is a [[Cartesian coordinate system]] (''x'', ''y'', ''z'').
* The [[equatorial coordinate system]] uses the [[celestial equator]].
* The [[ecliptic coordinate system]] uses the [[ecliptic]].
* The [[galactic coordinate system]] uses the [[Milky Way]]'s galactic equator.

==See also==
*[[Plane of reference]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Fundamental Plane (Spherical Coordinates)}}
[[Category:Geography]]
[[Category:Spherical geometry]]
[[Category:Cartography]]


{{elementary-geometry-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>fmkate11pgmo7cn657tasrzfb1prgnc</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Geo-literacy</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>36248807</id>
    <revision>
      <id>805082132</id>
      <parentid>792775948</parentid>
      <timestamp>2017-10-12T23:09:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rescuing 1 sources and tagging 0 as dead. #IABot (v1.5.7)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="6535">As defined by [[National Geographic Society|National Geographic]], '''geo-literacy''' is "the ability to use [[geographic]] understanding and geographic reasoning to make decisions".&lt;ref name="nationalgeographic1"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://education.nationalgeographic.com/education/geoliteracy/?ar_a=1&amp;force_AR=True |title=Geo-Literacy |accessdate=June 26, 2012 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140416071705/http://education.nationalgeographic.com/education/geoliteracy/?ar_a=1&amp;force_AR=True |archivedate=April 16, 2014 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
The term "geo-literacy" arose from the National Geographic Society's "Fight against Geographic Illiteracy." The organization released various media to help explain the concept to the general public. In an editorial, Daniel C. Edelson, vice president for education at National Geographic, said, "The National Geographic Society's concern for geo-literacy comes from our mission. We see geo-literacy as providing the tools that will enable communities to protect [[natural resource|natural]] and cultural resources, reduce violent [[Armed conflict|conflict]], and improve the [[quality of life]] worldwide. However, having a geo-literate populace is also critical for maintaining [[Competition (economics)|economic competitiveness]], quality of life, and national security in our modern, interconnected world.",&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://geography.about.com/b/2012/05/13/geo-literacy.htm | title=Geo-Literacy | publisher=About.com | date=May 13, 2012 | accessdate=June 26, 2012 | author=Rosenberg, Matt}}&lt;/ref&gt; and have released various media to help explain it to the general public.&lt;ref name="nationalgeographic1"/&gt; In addition, the National Geographic Society set up the Fund for Geo-literacy, in which donations help fund the printing of materials for education, professional development for the educators, and programs to help build awareness of the importance of geo-literacy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://education.nationalgeographic.com/education/program/fund-for-geo-literacy/?ar_a=1&amp;force_AR=True |title=Fund for Geo-Literacy |accessdate=June 26, 2012 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120625130105/http://education.nationalgeographic.com/education/program/fund-for-geo-literacy/?ar_a=1 |archivedate=June 25, 2012 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Components==
According to Edelson, the 3 components of geo-literacy are:&lt;ref name="nationalgeographic1"/&gt;
* Interactions-Understanding of human and natural systems
* Interconnections-Geographic reasoning
* Implications-Systematic decision-making

==Educational activities==
"Kid World Citizen", a site which provides "multicultural, educational activities to teach...kids about the world", and who, listed the following "age-appropriate lessons to increase geo-literacy in primary school students":&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://kidworldcitizen.org/2012/05/13/what-is-geo-literacy/ | title=What is Geo-Literacy? | publisher=Kid World Citizen | date=May 13, 2012 | accessdate=June 26, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* Explore different homes around the world and guess why the types of home fit their environment
* Discover why certain cultures celebrate certain holidays, and what is important to them
* Investigate different [[habitats]] and [[biomes]], such as the [[rainforest]]; look at tangible ways kids can prevent their destruction
* Surround kids with geography: study maps, [[cartography|create maps]], follow maps, play with maps. The more you develop their spatial intelligence when they’re younger, the more kids will understand their place in this world.
* Learn about the [[water cycle]] and the conserving and managing our freshwater resources
* Research your child’s favorite animal, turning it into a global lesson about protecting their habitat and food sources; what decisions can we make that will affect the outcome of this animal?

==Research Studies and Education Projects==
In 2012, InTeGrate ("a community effort to improve geoscience literacy and build a workforce that can make use of geoscience to solve societal issues") held a Module Author Meeting from May 16–18 on the topic.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://serc.carleton.edu/integrate/info_team_members/meetings/geo_lit_agenda.html | title=Module Author Meeting Agenda | accessdate=June 26, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Earlier Uses of the Term "geo-literacy"==

In 2002, Robert E. Nolan of the [[Education Resources Information Center]] published a research report/journal article entitled "Geo-Literacy: How Well Adults Understand the World in Which They Live", which included  "a test of physical and geopolitical geography...completed by 321 adults". The years of formal education and age were correlated with geographic literacy, and informal learning, such as travel, reading, media, was used as the primary source of geographic knowledge for those with higher educational attainment. A notable finding was that women, regardless of education level, scored significantly lower than men."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.eric.ed.gov/ERICWebPortal/search/detailmini.jsp?_nfpb=true&amp;_&amp;ERICExtSearch_SearchValue_0=EJ658647&amp;ERICExtSearch_SearchType_0=no&amp;accno=EJ658647 | title=Geo-Literacy: How Well Adults Understand the World in Which They Live | accessdate=June 26, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2001, the [[Arizona Geographic Information Council|Arizona Geographic Alliance]] launched a project called "The GeoLiteracy Project" that integrated geography education into reading and writing instruction.  In this case, their term "GeoLiteracy" referred to the integration of geography and traditional language arts literacy. 

In 1997, Linda Ferguson and Eva LaMar established an educational project they called "The Geo-Literacy Project".  LaMar describes geo-literacy as "the use of visual learning and communication tools to build an in-depth understanding -- or literacy -- of geography, [[geology]], and local [[history]]." &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Ball|first=Ashley|title=Geo-Literacy: Using Technology to Forge New Ground|url=http://www.edutopia.org/geo-literacy-forging-new-ground|work=Edutopia|accessdate=6 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

==External links==
* [http://vimeo.com/album/1922395 National Geographic videos: "What is Geo-Literacy?" and "Why is Geo-Literacy Important?"]
* [http://www.directionsmag.com/articles/the-geo-literacy-coalition-tackles-americans-geographic-preparation/197867 Directions Magazine article "The Geo-Literacy Coalition Tackles Americans’ Geographic Preparation"]

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Geography topics}}

[[Category:Geography]]</text>
      <sha1>13ow9cjlaic8k31cm64e8vpflfyqv8d</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Geo-replication</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>15516115</id>
    <revision>
      <id>641231564</id>
      <parentid>554707506</parentid>
      <timestamp>2015-01-06T12:08:49Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Dai Pritchard</username>
        <id>21757787</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>cleanup and [[WP:NPOV]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="3644">{{unreferenced|date=May 2008}}
'''Geo-replication''' systems are designed to improve the distribution of data across geographically distributed [[Computer networking|data networks]]. This is intended to improve the response time for applications such as [[web portal]]s. Geo-replication can be achieved using software, hardware or a combination of the two. 

== Software ==
Geo-replication software is a [[network performance]]-enhancing technology that is designed to provide improved access to portal or [[intranet]] content for uses at the most remote parts of large organizations. It is based on the principle of storing complete replicas of portal content on local servers, and then keeping the content on those servers up-to-date using heavily compressed data updates.

=== Portal acceleration ===
Geo-replication technologies are used to provide replication of the content of portals, intranets, web applications, content and data between servers, across wide area networks [[Wide area network|WAN]] to allow users at remote sites to access central content at [[Local area network|LAN]] speeds. 

Geo-replication software can improve the performance of data networks that suffer limited [[Bandwidth (computing)|bandwidth]], [[Latency (engineering)|latency]] and periodic disconnection. [[Terabyte]]s of data can be replicated over a [[wide area network]], giving remote sites faster access to web applications.

Geo-replication software uses a combination of [[data compression]] and content [[web cache|caching]] technologies. [[Delta encoding|differencing]] technologies can also be employed to reduce the volume of data that has to be transmitted to keep portal content accurate across all servers. This update compression can reduce the load that portal traffic place on networks, and improve the response time of a portal.

=== Portal replication ===
Remote users of web portals and collaboration environments will frequently experience network bandwidth and latency problems which will slow down their experience of opening and closing files, and otherwise interacting with the portal. Geo-replication technology is deployed to accelerate the remote end user portal performance to be equivalent to that experienced by users locally accessing the portal in the central office.

=== Differencing engine technologies ===
To deliver this reduction in the size of the required data updates across a portal, geo-replication systems often use differencing engine technologies. These systems are able to difference the content of each portal server right down to the byte level. This knowledge of the content that is already on each server enables the system to rebuild any changes to the content on one server, across each of the other servers in the deployment from content already hosted on those other servers. This type of differencing system ensures that no content, at the byte level, is ever sent to a server twice.

=== Offline portal replication on laptops === 
Geo-replication systems are often extended to deliver local replication beyond the server and down to the laptop used by a single user. Server to laptop replication enables mobile users to have access to a local replica of their business portal on a standard laptop. This technology may be employed to provide in the field access to portal content by, for example, sales forces and combat forces.

== Geo-replication systems ==
{{col-begin}}
{{col-2}}
*[[iOra]]
*[[Syntergy]]
*[[Colligo Contributor]]

== See also ==
*[[Load balancing (computing)|Load balancing]]
*[[Round robin DNS]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Business software]]
[[Category:Geography]]</text>
      <sha1>en8x2tkztyv36d74ob08jj9xvk7xpgf</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Geoarchaeology</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1149904</id>
    <revision>
      <id>784920566</id>
      <parentid>722952564</parentid>
      <timestamp>2017-06-10T17:52:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Magic links bot</username>
        <id>30707369</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Replace [[Help:Magic links|magic links]] with templates per [[Special:Permalink/772743896#Future of magic links|local RfC]] and [[:mw:Requests for comment/Future of magic links|MediaWiki RfC]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="11543">[[Image:Geoarcheologue.JPG|thumb|right|A geoarchaeologist analyzes a stratigraphy on the route of the LGV Est high-speed railway line.]]
[[Image:Geoarchaeologistatwork.png|thumb|geoarchaeologist at work on column sample]]
'''Geoarchaeology''' is a multi-disciplinary approach which uses the techniques and subject matter of [[geography]], [[geology]] and other [[Earth science]]s to examine topics which inform [[archaeology|archaeological]] knowledge and thought. Geoarchaeologists study the natural physical processes that affect [[archaeological site]]s such as [[geomorphology]], the formation of sites through geological processes and the effects on buried sites and [[Artifact (archaeology)|artifacts]] post-deposition. Geoarchaeologists' work frequently involves studying [[soil]] and [[sediments]] as well as other geographical concepts to contribute an archaeological study. Geoarchaeologists may also use computer cartography, [[geographic information systems]] (GIS) and  [[digital elevation model]]s (DEM) in combination with disciplines from human and social sciences and earth sciences.&lt;ref&gt;[http://sapiens.revues.org/index422.html Ghilardi, M. and Desruelles, S. (2008) “Geoarchaeology: where human, social and earth sciences meet with technology”. ''S.A.P.I.EN.S.'' '''1''' (2) ]&lt;/ref&gt; Geoarchaeology is  important to society because it  informs archaeologists about the geomorphology of the soil, sediments and the rocks on  the buried sites and artifacts they're researching on. By doing this we are able locate ancient cities and artifacts and estimate by the quality of soil how  "prehistoric" they really are.

==Techniques used in geoarchaeology==

===Column sampling===
Column sampling is a technique of collecting samples from a [[archaeological section|section]] for analyzing and detecting the buried processes down the profile of the section. Narrow metal tins are hammered into the section in a series to collect the complete profile for study. If more than one tin is needed they are arranged offset  and overlapping to one side so the complete profile can be rebuilt offsite in laboratory conditions.

===Loss on ignition testing===
Loss on ignition testing for [[soil]] [[Soil organic matter|organic]] content.- a technique of measuring organic content in soil samples. Samples taken from a known place in the profile collected by column sampling are weighed then placed in a fierce oven which burns off the organic content. The resulting cooked sample is weighed again and the resulting loss in weight is an indicator of organic content in the profile at a certain depth. These readings are often used to detect buried soil horizons. A buried soil's [[archaeological horizon|horizons]] may not be visible in [[archaeological section|section]] and this horizon is an indicator of possible occupation levels. Ancient land surfaces especially from the prehistoric era can be difficult to discern so this technique is useful for evaluating an areas potential for [[prehistoric]] surfaces and archaeological evidence. Comparative measurements down the profile are made and a sudden rise in organic content at some point in the profile combined with other indicators is strong evidence for buried surfaces.

[[Image:Columns.002.png|thumb|right|offset column sampling of the soil profile]]

===Magnetic susceptibility analysis===
The magnetic susceptibility of a material is a measure of its ability to become magnetised by an external magnetic field (Dearing, 1999). The magnetic susceptibility of a soil reflects the presence of magnetic iron-oxide minerals such as maghaematite; just because a soil contains a lot of iron does not mean that it will have high magnetic susceptibility. Magnetic forms of iron can be formed by burning and microbial activity such as occurs in top soils and some anaerobic deposits. Magnetic iron compounds can also be found in igneous and metamorphic rocks.

The relationship between iron and burning means that magnetic susceptibility is often used for:
* Site prospection, to identify areas of archaeological potential prior to excavation.
* Identifying hearth areas and the presence of burning residues in deposits.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=Enhancement of magnetic susceptibility of soils on archaeological sites. |journal= Archaeometry |volume=13  |year=1971 |pages=209–219 |author1=Tite, M.S. |author2=Mullins, C. |doi=10.1111/j.1475-4754.1971.tb00043.x}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Explaining whether areas of reddening are due to burning or other natural processes such as gleying (waterlogging).

The relationship between soil formation and magnetic susceptibility means that it can also be used to:
* Identify buried soils in depositional sequences.
* Identify redeposited soil materials in peat, lake sediments etc.

===Phosphate and orthophosphate content with spectrophotometry===
Phosphate in man-made soils derives from people, their animals, rubbish and bones. 100 people excrete about 62&amp;nbsp;kg of phosphate annually, with about the same from their rubbish. Their animals excrete even more. A human body contains about 650g of PO4,(500g-80% in the skeleton), which results in elevated levels in burial sites. Most is quickly immobilised on the clay of the soil and ‘fixed’, where it can persist for thousands of years. For a 1 ha site this corresponds to about 150&amp;nbsp;kg PO4 ha-1yr-1 about 0.5% to 10% of that already present in most soils. Therefore, it doesn’t take long for human occupation to make orders of magnitude differences to the phosphate concentration in soil. Phosphorus exist in different ‘pools’ in the soil 1) organic (available), 2) occluded (adsorbed), 3) bound (chemically bound). Each of these pools can be extracted using progressively more aggressive chemicals. Some workers (Eidt especially), think that the ratios between these pools can give information about past land use, and perhaps even dating.
	
Whatever the method of getting the phosphorus from the soil into solution, the method of detecting it is usually the same. This uses the ‘molybdate blue’ reaction, where the depth of the colour is proportional to phosphorus concentration. In the lab, this is measured using a colorimeter, where light shining through a standard cell produces an electric current proportional to the light attenuation. In the field, the same reaction is used on detector sticks, which are compared to a colour chart.

Phosphate concentrations can be plotted on archaeological plans to show former activity areas, and is also used to prospect for sites in the wider landscape.

===Particle size analysis===
The particle size distribution of a soil sample may indicate the conditions under which the [[stratum|strata]] or [[sediment]] were deposited. Particle sizes are generally separated by means of dry or wet sieving (coarse samples such as [[till]], [[gravel]] and [[sand]]s, sometimes coarser [[silt]]s) or by measuring the changes of the density of a dispersed solution (in sodiumpyrophosphate, for example))of the sample (finer silts, [[clay]]s). A rotating clock-glass with a very fine-grained dispersed sample under a heat lamp is useful in separating particles.

The results are plotted on curves which can be analyzed with statistical methods for particle distribution and other parameters.

The fractions received can be further investigated for cultural indicators, macro- and microfossils and other interesting features, so particle size analysis is in fact the first thing to do when handling these samples.

===Trace element geochemistry===
Trace element geochemistry is the study of the abundances of elements in geological materials that do not occur in a large quantity in these materials. Because these trace elements' concentrations are determined by a large number of particular situations under which a certain geological material is formed, they are usually unique between two locations which contain the same type of rock or other geological material.

Geoarchaeologists use this uniqueness in trace element geochemistry to trace ancient patterns of resource-acquisition and trade. For example, researchers can look at the trace element composition of obsidian artifacts in order to "fingerprint" those artifacts. They can then study the trace element composition of obsidian outcrops in order to determine the original source of the raw material used to make the artifact.

===Clay mineralogy analysis===
Geoarchaeologists study the mineralogical characteristics of pots through macroscopic and microscopic analyses. They can use these characteristics to understand the various manufacturing techniques used to make the pots, and through this, to know which production centers likely made these pots. They can also use the mineralogy to trace the raw materials used to make the pots to specific clay deposits.&lt;ref&gt;Druca, I. C. and Q. H. J. Gwynb (1997), From Clay to Pots: A Petrographical Analysis of Ceramic Production in the Callejón de Huaylas, North-Central Andes, Peru, ''Journal of Archaeological Science'', ''25'', 707-718.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ostracod analysis===
Naturally occurring Ostracods in freshwater bodies are impacted by changes in salinity  and pH due to human activities.  Analysis of Ostracod shells in sediment columns show the changes brought about by farming and habitation activities.  This record can be correlated with age dating techniques to help identify changes in human habitation patterns and population migrations.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tnesr.com/images/Bayman_et_al._2004.pdf ^ Manuel R. Palacios-Fest, “Nonmarine ostracode shell chemistry from ancient hohokam irrigation canals in central Arizona: A paleohydrochemical tool for the interpretation of prehistoric human occupation in the North American Southwest” ''Geoarchaeology'', Volume 9 Issue 1, Pages 1 – 29, Published Online: 9 Jan 2007 ]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Archaeological geology==

'''Archaeological geology''' is a term coined by [[Werner Kasig]] in 1980. It is a sub-field of [[geology]] which emphasises the value of earth constituents for human life.

==See also==
*[[Deposit model]]

==In-text Citations==
{{reflist}}

==References==
* Slinger, A.,  Janse, H.. and Berends, G.  1980 . Natuursteen in  monumenten. Zeist / Baarn Rijksdienst voor de Monumentenzorg.
* Kasig, Werner 1980. Zur Geologie des Aachener Unterkarbons (Linksrheinisches Schiefergebirge, Deutschland) — Stratigraphie, Sedimentologie und Palaeogeographie des Aachener Kohlenkalks und seine Bedeutung fuer die Entwicklung der Kulturlandschaft im Aachener Raum Aachen RWTH Fak Bergbau… "zur Erlangung…" =. Aachen RWTH.
* Jonghe, Sabine de -, Tourneur, Francis, Ducarme, Pierre, Groessens, Eric  e.a. 1996 . Pierres à bâtir traditionnelles de la Wallonie - manuel de terrain. Jambes / Louvain la Neuve ucl,chab / dgrne / region wallonne
* Dreesen, Roland, Dusar, M. and Doperé, F., 2001 . Atlas Natuursteen in Limburgse monumentenx- 2nd print   320pp. .  LIKONA     {{ISBN|90-74605-18-4}}
* Dearing, J. (1999) Magnetic susceptibility. In, Environmental magnetism: a practical guide Walden, J., Oldfield, F., Smith, J., (Eds). Technical guide, No. 6. Quaternary Research Association, London, pp.&amp;nbsp;35–62.

== External links ==
* [http://www.lgakz.org The Laboratory of Geoarchaeology, Kazakhstan] Information about Geoarchaeological work in Central Asia
* [http://www.sassa.org.uk SASSA (Soil Analysis Support System for Archaeologists)]

[[Category:Geography]]
[[Category:Geological techniques]]
[[Category:Archaeological science]]
[[Category:Methods in archaeology]]</text>
      <sha1>gcezl8mc0fdpjon88m0x88ml2rc8lpl</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Geographer</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>74847</id>
    <revision>
      <id>870207312</id>
      <parentid>870185472</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-11-23T05:28:51Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Giraffedata</username>
        <id>105732</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>[[wikipedia:User:Giraffedata/comprised of|comprised of]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="23595">{{about||the musical group|Geographer (band)|the 17th-century painting|The Geographer}}
[[Image:The Geographer.jpg|thumb|''[[The Geographer]]'' (1668-69), by [[Johannes Vermeer]] ]]

A '''geographer''' is a person whose area of study is [[geography]], the study of [[Earth]]'s natural environment and human society. The Greek prefix, "geo," means "earth" and the Greek suffix, "graphy," meaning "description," so a geographer is someone who studies the earth. The word "[[geography]]" is a [[Middle French]] word that is believed to have been first used in 1540.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=geography (n.) |url=https://www.etymonline.com/word/geography |website=Online Etymology Dictionary |publisher=Douglas Harper |accessdate=10 October 2018 |format=Web article |date=n.d.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although geographers are historically known as people who make [[maps]], map making is actually the field of study of [[cartography]], a subset of geography. Geographers do not study only the details of the natural environment or human society, but they also study the reciprocal relationship between these two. For example, they study how the natural environment contributes to the human society and how the human society affects the natural environment.

In particular, physical geographers study the natural environment while human geographers study human society. Modern geographers are the primary practitioners of the GIS ([[geographic information system]]), who are often employed by local, state, and federal government agencies as well as in the private sector by environmental and engineering firms.

The paintings by [[Johannes Vermeer]] titled ''[[The Geographer]]'' and ''[[The Astronomer (Vermeer)|The Astronomer]]'' are both thought to represent the growing influence and rise in prominence of scientific enquiry in Europe at the time of their painting in 1668–69.

== Famous Geographers ==
=== Eratosthenes (Greek) ===
The [[ancient Greeks]] discovered much of the knowledge that formed the basis for later scientific and geographical discoveries. [[Eratosthenes of Cyrene]] (born circa 276 BCE in [[Cyrene, Libya]]; died circa 194 BCE in [[Alexandria, Egypt]]) was a Greek [[writer]], [[poet]], [[astronomer]], and geographer who created the first known measurements of the [[Earth#Infobox Physical characteristics|Earth's circumference]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Eratosthenes |url=https://www.britannica.com/biography/Eratosthenes |website=Encyclopædia Britannica |publisher=Encyclopædia Britannica, inc. |accessdate=5 September 2018 |format=Web article |date=January 25, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Eratosthenes used the angles at which the sun's rays fall on the ground to calculate the curvature of the Earth's surface, which he then used to determine the full horizontal length around the Earth. According to the works of [[Aristotle]], other scientists had estimated the circumference of the Earth prior to Eratosthenes's discovery, but the records of the specific methods and calculations that they used did not survive.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Eratosthenes |url=https://www.britannica.com/biography/Eratosthenes |website=Encyclopædia Britannica |publisher=Encyclopædia Britannica, inc. |accessdate=5 September 2018 |format=Web article |date=January 25, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Hipparchus (Greek) ===
[[Hipparchus]] (born in Nicaea, Bithynia [now Iznik, Turkey]; believed to have died after 127 BC in [[Rhodes]]) is best known for using [[astronomical]] studies to predict the movements and positions of [[celestial bodies]] such as the [[sun]], [[moon]], and [[stars]]. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Overview: Hipparchus |url=http://www.oxfordreference.com/view/10.1093/oi/authority.20110803095937997 |website=www.oxfordreference.com |publisher=Oxford University Press |accessdate=23 September 2018 |format=Web.}}&lt;/ref&gt; He discovered the [[equinoxes]] ([[autumnal equinox]] and [[spring equinox]]) and calculated the length of the [[solar year]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author1=Collins English Dictionary |title=Hipparchus |url=https://www.collinsdictionary.com/dictionary/english/hipparchus |website=www.collinsdictionary.com |publisher=HarperCollins Publishers |accessdate=23 September 2018 |format=Web.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hipparchus was also the first to correctly determine the distance between the earth and the moon (which he believed was equal to 63 times the earth's radius, although it is actually equal to 60 times the earth's radius). Building upon this knowledge, he developed the [[parallax]] theory to explain the apparent displacement of celestial bodies relative to the observer's vantage point.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Overview: Hipparchus |url=http://www.oxfordreference.com/view/10.1093/oi/authority.20110803095937997 |website=www.oxfordreference.com |publisher=Oxford University Press |accessdate=23 September 2018 |format=Web.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Jones |first1=Alexander Raymond |title=Hipparchus |url=https://www.britannica.com/biography/Hipparchus-Greek-astronomer |website=Encyclopædia Britannica |publisher=Encyclopædia Britannica, inc. |accessdate=23 September 2018 |format=Web. |date=August 17, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Alexander von Humboldt (German) ===
[[Alexander von Humboldt]] (born Sept. 14, 1769 in Berlin; died May 6, 1859) was a German geographer, [[naturalist]] and [[explorer]] who made major contributions to the field of [[biogeography]] by producing break-through research on the connection between the [[climate]] of a region and the [[plant life]] growing there.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Kellner |first1=Charlotte L. |title=Alexander von Humboldt |url=https://www.britannica.com/biography/Alexander-von-Humboldt |website=Encyclopædia Britannica |publisher=Encyclopædia Britannica, inc. |accessdate=5 September 2018 |format=Web article |date=May 4, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; The records he kept of his travels provided highly valuable data on the geography of [[Central Asia]], which was not very well understood by [[Europeans]] at the time. Furthermore, with the help of [[Sir Edward Sabine]], he was able to prove that the origin of [[storms]] is extraterrestrial by showing the relationship between magnetic storms on [[earth]] with the changing activity of [[sun spots]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Kellner |first1=Charlotte L. |title=Alexander von Humboldt |url=https://www.britannica.com/biography/Alexander-von-Humboldt |website=Encyclopædia Britannica |publisher=Encyclopædia Britannica, inc. |accessdate=16 September 2018 |format=Web article |date=September 11, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; In his latter years, Humboldt published a multi-volume series of books called ''[[Kosmos]]'', wherein he described the structure of the universe as it was then understood. Initially, he published four volumes, which were received with great success and were subsequently translated into almost every European language. Humboldt began work on the fifth volume, but died before it was completed (he was ninety years old).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Kellner |first1=Charlotte L. |title=Alexander von Humboldt |url=https://www.britannica.com/biography/Alexander-von-Humboldt |website=Encyclopædia Britannica |publisher=Encyclopædia Britannica, inc. |accessdate=16 September 2018 |format=Web article |date=September 11, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Humboldt Current]] (also known as the [[Peru Current]]), which was named after him, is an ocean current that holds warm air off a 600-mile coastal region between [[Peru]] and [[Chile]] in [[South America]], thereby keeping the [[climate]] cool. Humboldt had explored this region in 1802, and it is now known for containing the world's richest [[marine ecosystem]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Kiger |first1=Patrick J. |title=Who Was Alexander von Humboldt and What Is the Humboldt Current? |url=https://science.howstuffworks.com/environmental/earth/oceanography/alexander-von-humboldt-and-humboldt-current.htm |website=science.howstuffworks.com |publisher=HowStuffWorks.com |accessdate=16 September 2018 |format=Web. |date=April 12, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Alfred Russel (A.R.) Wallace (British) ===
[[Alfred Russel Wallace]], also known as A.R. Wallace, (born on Jan. 8, 1823, in [[Usk]], Monmouthshire, Wales; died on Nov. 7, 1913, in Broadstone, [[Dorset, England]]), was a British [[naturalist]], [[geographer]], and [[social critic]] who is most known for formulating the theory of [[evolution]] by [[natural selection]] before [[Charles Darwin]] published his famous work on the same subject, ''[[The Origin of Species]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Camerini |first1=Jane R. |title=Alfred Russel Wallace |url=https://www.britannica.com/biography/Alfred-Russel-Wallace |website=Encyclopædia Britannica |publisher=Encyclopædia Britannica, inc. |accessdate=30 September 2018 |format=Web article. |date=n.d.}}&lt;/ref&gt; An avid traveler and explorer, Wallace became both rich and famous from the work he did identifying new animal [[species]] in [[Indonesia]] and the [[Amazon_rainforest|Amazon region]]. Importantly, Wallace discovered and defined the concept of "[[speciation]]," which he discussed in a paper he published around 1865 describing his research on [[butterflies]]. Speciation refers to defining animal [[species]] based on their interbreeding capabilities; animals within the same species can breed with each other, but not with animals from other species. In this way, individual species can be identified for [[scientific classification]] purposes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Garrity |first1=Lyn |title=Out of Darwin’s Shadow |url=https://www.smithsonianmag.com/science-nature/out-of-darwins-shadow-48274065/ |website=www.smithsonianmag.com |publisher=Smithsonian.com |accessdate=30 September 2018 |format=Web article. |date=January 22, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Richard Francis Burton (British) ===
[[Sir Richard Francis Burton]] (born on March 19, 1821, in [[Torquay]], Devonshire, [[England]]; died on October 20, 1890, in [[Trieste]], [[Austria-Hungary]] [now in [[Italy]]]) is known for being the first European to discover [[Lake Tanganyika]] in east Africa and for gaining access to [[Muslim]] cities, which Europeans had previously been forbidden to access.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Brodie |first1=Fawn McKay |title=Sir Richard Burton |url=https://www.britannica.com/biography/Richard-Burton-British-scholar-and-explorer |website=Encyclopædia Britannica |publisher=Encyclopædia Britannica, inc. |accessdate=30 September 2018 |format=Web article. |date=March 12, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lake Tanganyika is estimated to be the second deepest and the second largest freshwater lake in the world and is believed to be one of the oldest lakes in the world (approximately twenty million years old by evolutionary timelines).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Lake Tanganyika |url=http://www.newworldencyclopedia.org/p/index.php?title=Lake_Tanganyika&amp;oldid=1012460 |website=www.newworldencyclopedia.org |publisher=New World Encyclopedia |accessdate=10 October 2018 |format=Web article |date=June 20, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Strabo (Greek) ===
[[Strabo]] (born circa 64 BC in [[Amaseia]], Pontus; died some time after 21 AD) was a Greek geographer and historian who left a remarkably comprehensive written record of all the people and countries known to the Greeks and Romans around 27 BC-14 AD. This record, a book called ''[[Geographica|Geography]]'', also provides information on the technology geographers used to study the world at that time as well as the history of the many of the countries mentioned in his records.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Strabo: Greek Geographer and Historian |url=https://www.britannica.com/biography/Strabo |website=www.britannica.com |publisher=Encyclopeadia Britannica |accessdate=10 October 2018 |format=Web article}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although Strabo's account is far from perfect (it assumes, for example, that the earth, then called [[oikoumene]], is one giant landmass consisting of [[Europe]], [[Asia]], [[Africa]], and their associated [[islands]] surrounded by a large [[ocean]]), his writing is highly valued for being a rich compilation of not only his own observations but also the research and ideas of other respected scientific figures and thinkers including [[Eratosthenes]], [[Hipparchus]], [[Polybius]], [[Artemidorus]], [[Apollodorus_of_Athens|Apollodorus]], [[Aristotle]], and [[Strato of Lampsacus|Strato]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Strabo |url=https://www.encyclopedia.com/people/science-and-technology/geography-biographies/strabo |website=www.encyclopedia.com |publisher=Encyclopedia of World Biography |accessdate=10 October 2018 |format=Web article}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Muhammad al-Idrisi (Moroccan) ===
[[Muhammad al-Idrisi]] (born in 1100 in Ceutah, [[Morocco]]; died around 1165-66 in Ceutah) is known for compiling an enormous  world geography for the Norman King of Sicily, [[Roger II]]. The book, subsequently named the ''[[Book of Roger]]'', was completed in January 1154 and was written as the commentary for a large map of the world created by al-Idrisi (also at the bequest of the King). An avid traveler himself, al-Idrisi relied on contemporary accounts of the world, the works of [[Ptolemy]], as well as geographical literature from Greek, Latin, and Arabic sources to create his work.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author1=(author unknown) |title=Muhammad ibn Muhammad al-Idrisi |url=https://www.encyclopedia.com/history/encyclopedias-almanacs-transcripts-and-maps/muhammad-ibn-muhammad-al-idrisi |website=Encyclopedia.com |publisher=Encyclopedia of World Biography |accessdate=14 October 2018 |format=Web article |date=2004}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Book of Roger'' contained fairly accurate information on the countries of Europe and was released in several editions although, as of the mid-1900s, the full text had never been edited.

=== Claudius Ptolemy (Ancient Roman) ===
Claudius Ptolemy, known simply as [[Ptolemy]], (born around 100 AD; died c. 170 AD) was an [[astronomer]], [[mathematician]], and [[geographer]] who lived in [[Alexandria]] and is known for (among other things) drawing detailed maps of what was known of the world at the time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Jones |first1=Alexander Raymond |title=Ptolemy |url=https://www.britannica.com/biography/Ptolemy |website=Encyclopædia Britannica |publisher=Encyclopædia Britannica, inc. |accessdate=14 October 2018 |format=Web article |date=May 11, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ptolemy's geographical works include tables of [[latitude]] and [[longitude]] and a discussion of how such lines could be mathematically calculated.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author1=World of Earth Science |title=Ptolemy (CA. 100-170) |url=https://www.encyclopedia.com/people/history/ancient-history-egypt-biographies/ptolemy-vii |website=https://www.encyclopedia.com |publisher=Encyclopedia.com |accessdate=27 October 2018 |format=Web article}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Ptolemy's most famous work, ''[[Almagest]]'', he comprehensively describes the layout of the stars and other astronomical objects as understood by ancient Greek and Babylonian scientists. He also put forth the idea of an earth-centered universe, an idea widely believed until the 1500s when [[Copernicus]] began to suggest that the earth and other planets in the solar system actually revolve around the [[sun]] (called the ''[[heliocentric]]'' (Sun-centered) theory).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Ptolemy |url=http://www.newworldencyclopedia.org/entry/Ptolemy |website=www.newworldencyclopedia.org |publisher=New World Encyclopedia |accessdate=27 October 2018 |format=Web article |date=June 15, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

=== Gerardus Mercator (Belgian) ===
[[Gerardus Mercator]], originally name Gerard De Cremer or simply Kremer(?) (born on March 5, 1512 in [[Rupelmonde]], [[Flanders]] [now in [[Belgium]]]; died on December 2, 1594 in [[Duisburg]], Duchy of Cleve [now in [[Germany]]]) was a [[cartographer]] famous for creating a heart-shaped representation of the earth (also called the "[[Mercator projection]]" of the earth) in response to a demand for flat [[maps]] that could accurately depict the earth as a [[spherical]] object.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Cavendish |first1=Richard |title=The Birth of Gerardus Mercator |url=https://www.historytoday.com/richard-cavendish/birth-gerardus-mercator |website=https://www.historytoday.com |publisher=History Today Ltd. |accessdate=27 October 2018 |format=Web article |date=March 3, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Mercator was also the first to begin using the term "atlas" to describe a collection of maps.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author1=The Editors of Encyclopaedia Britannica |title=Gerardus Mercator |url=https://www.britannica.com/biography/Gerardus-Mercator |website=Encyclopædia Britannica |publisher=Encyclopædia Britannica, inc. |accessdate=27 October 2018 |format=Web article |date=February 26, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; Because of his work, travelers and explorers could maintain a course over long distances using straight lines, thus eliminating the need to constantly adjust their [[compass]] readings in order to keep track of their movements.

=== Charles Lyell (British) ===
[[Charles Lyell]] (1797–1875) was a British [[geologist]] whose theory of [[Uniformitarianism]] significantly impacted the way modern scientists understand the earth's structure and how this structure can change over time. Uniformitarianism overturned the previously accepted theory of [[Catastrophism]], which held that earth's features were formed by sudden, violent forces rather than by gradual changes over time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author1=A Dictionary of Plant Sciences |title=catastrophism |url=https://www.encyclopedia.com/earth-and-environment/geology-and-oceanography/geology-and-oceanography/catastrophism |website=https://www.encyclopedia.com |publisher=Encyclopedia.com |accessdate=27 October 2018 |format=Web article}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lyell contended that major geological forces in effect today, including [[volcanic eruptions]], [[earthquakes]], and erosion due to [[wind]], [[water]], and [[gravity]], have happened throughout earth's history and are responsible changing its surface features.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author1=World of Earth Sciences |title=Lyell, Charles (1797-1875) |url=https://www.encyclopedia.com/people/history/historians-miscellaneous-biographies/charles-lyell |website=https://www.encyclopedia.com |publisher=Encyclopedia.com |accessdate=27 October 2018 |format=Web article}}&lt;/ref&gt; The theory of [[evolution]] is believed to have gained acceptance in part because of Lyell's efforts to promote gradual biological change rather than change due to sudden, extreme events. Building upon the work of James Hutton, Charles Lyell is also responsible for spreading the idea that older rocks are buried underneath newer ones, which led scientists to begin studying [[fossils]] and [[rock layers]] in order to better understand the history of the earth's [[geography]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author1=World of Earth Sciences |title=Lyell, Charles (1797-1875) |url=https://www.encyclopedia.com/people/history/historians-miscellaneous-biographies/charles-lyell |website=https://www.encyclopedia.com |publisher=Encyclopedia.com |accessdate=27 October 2018 |format=Web article}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Pytheas (Greek) ===
[[Pytheas]], a Greek geographer, astronomer, and explorer who lived around 300 bc near Massalia, [[Gaul]] (a region comprising mostly modern-day [[France]]) is known for producing the first known records of the history of Britain.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author1=Complete Dictionary of Scientific Biography |title=Pytheas of Massalia |url=https://www.encyclopedia.com/science/dictionaries-thesauruses-pictures-and-press-releases/pytheas-massalia |website=https://www.encyclopedia.com |publisher=Encyclopedia.com |accessdate=27 October 2018 |format=Web article}}&lt;/ref&gt; Pytheas's most important work, [[Pytheas|''On the Ocean'']], has since been lost, but most of what is known about him was recorded by the Greek historian, [[Polybius]] (approx. 200-118 BC). Through travel and detailed observation, Pytheas noticed that the length of the days increased as he traveled northward and that the [[moon]] affects the [[tides]] in the water. His travels took him to the northernmost parts of [[Europe]] including [[Thule]] (the northernmost inhabited island, roughly six days sail beyond [[Great_Britain|Britain]]) and at least to the [[Arctic Circle]] (possible [[Norway]] or [[Iceland]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author1=The Editors of Encyclopaedia Britannica |title=Pytheas |url=https://www.britannica.com/biography/Pytheas |website=Encyclopædia Britannica |publisher=Encyclopædia Britannica, inc. |accessdate=13 November 2018 |format=Web article |date=December 16, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Douglas Mawson (Australian) ===
Sir [[Douglas Mawson]] (born in [[Yorkshire]], England in 1882; died in [[Brighton]], England in 1958) is known for his exploration of [[Antarctica]], although he also studied [[uranium]] and other radioactive materials as a preeminent professor of [[geology]] at the [[University of Adelaide]] in [[Australia]]. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author1=Encyclopedia of World Biography |title=Sir Douglas Mawson |url=https://www.encyclopedia.com/people/science-and-technology/geography-biographies/sir-douglas-mawson |website=Encyclopedia.com |publisher=The Gale Group Inc. |accessdate=16 November 2018 |format=Web article |date=2004}}&lt;/ref&gt; Along with [[Edgeworth David]] and Dr. A.F. Mackay, Mawson was the first man to reach the summit of [[Mount Erebus]], an ice-covered volcanic mountain approximately 11,400 feet high. His expeditions led Britain to surrender its claims over the Antarctic territory to [[Australia]] in 1936, and the methods he developed to survive in, and travel through, freezing climates paved the way for subsequent explorations of sub-zero regions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author1=Encyclopedia of World Biography |title=Sir Douglas Mawson |url=https://www.encyclopedia.com/people/science-and-technology/geography-biographies/sir-douglas-mawson |website=Encyclopedia.com |publisher=The Gale Group Inc. |accessdate=16 November 2018 |format=Web article |date=2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Areas of study ==
{{History of geography sidebar}}
There are three major fields of study, which are further subdivided:
* [[Physical geography]]: including [[geomorphology]], [[hydrology]], [[glaciology]], [[biogeography]], [[climatology]], [[meteorology]], [[Pedology (soil study)|pedology]], [[oceanography]], [[geodesy]], and [[environmental geography]].
*[[Human geography]]: including [[Urban geography]], [[cultural geography]], [[economic geography]], [[political geography]], [[historical geography]], [[marketing geography]], [[health geography]], and [[social geography]].
* [[Regional geography]]: including [[atmosphere]], [[biosphere]], and [[lithosphere]]

The [[National Geographic Society]] identifies five broad key [[Five themes of geography|themes]] for geographers:

*location
*place
*human-environment interaction
*movement
*regions&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nationalgeographic.com/education/themes.html |title=Geography Education @ |publisher=Nationalgeographic.com |date=2008-10-24 |accessdate=2013-07-16 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100207230321/http://www.nationalgeographic.com/education/themes.html |archivedate=2010-02-07 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{div col}}
*[[Geography]]
*[[Human geography]]
*[[List of geographers]]
*[[Outline of geography]]
*[[Physical geography]]
*''[[Geographers on Film]]''
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{commonscat|Geographers}}
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
*[[Steven Seegel]].  ''Map Men: Transnational Lives and Deaths of Geographers in the Making of East Central Europe. [[University of Chicago Press]], 2018.  {{ISBN|978-0-226-43849-8}}.

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Science occupations]]
[[Category:Social science occupations]]
[[Category:Geographers| ]]</text>
      <sha1>s5ow0267xko9k60y94hp9wjfwvqq4bt</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Geography</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>18963910</id>
    <revision>
      <id>869741003</id>
      <parentid>868866727</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-11-20T02:15:07Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Emasterji</username>
        <id>15332335</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="38865">{{Other uses}}
{{pp|small=yes}}
{{short description|The science that studies the terrestrial surface, the societies that inhabit it and the territories, landscapes, places or regions that form it}}
{{More citations needed|date=February 2018}}
[[File:Map of the world by the US Gov as of 2016.svg|thumb|upright=1.2|Physical map of [[Earth]] with political borders as of 2016]]

'''Geography''' (from [[Ancient Greek|Greek]]: {{lang|el|γεωγραφία}}, ''geographia'', literally "earth description")&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?term=geography|title=Online Etymology Dictionary|last=Harper|first=Douglas|date=|website=Etymonline.com|publisher=Online Etymology Dictionary|accessdate=10 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; is a field of [[science]] devoted to the study of the lands, features, inhabitants, and phenomena of [[Earth]] and [[Universe|universe.]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/geography|title=Geography|last=|first=|date=|publisher=Houghton Mifflin Company|work=The American Heritage Dictionary/ of the English Language, Fourth Edition|accessdate=9 October 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first person to use the word γεωγραφία was [[Eratosthenes]] (276–194 BC).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books/about/Eratosthenes_Geography.html?id=8peKyWK_SWsC|title=Eratosthenes' Geography|last=Eratosthenes|publisher=[[Princeton University Press]]|isbn=978-0691142678|location=|year=2010|pages=|translator-last=Roller|translator-first=Duane W.|quote=|via=|date=2010-01-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; Geography is an all-encompassing discipline that seeks an understanding of Earth and [[world|its human and natural complexities]]—not merely where objects are, but also how they have changed and come to be.

Geography is often defined in terms of two branches: [[human geography]] and [[physical geography]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.physicalgeography.net/fundamentals/1b.html|title=Chapter 1: Introduction to Physical Geography|last=Pidwirny|first=Dr. Michael|last2=Jones|first2=Scott|date=|website=Physicalgeography.net|publisher=[[University of British Columbia Okanagan]]|accessdate=10 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books/about/What_is_Geography.html?id=G_491U8PQFEC|title=What is Geography?|last=Bonnett|first=Alastair|publisher=[[SAGE Publications]]|isbn=978-1849206495|location=|year=2008|pages=|quote=|access-date=10 November 2016|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Human geography deals with the study of people and their communities, cultures, economies, and interactions with the environment by studying their relations with and across space and place.&lt;ref name="HGDICT"&gt;{{Cite encyclopedia|last=Johnston|first=Ron|editor1-last=Johnston|editor1-first=Ron|editor2-last=Gregory|editor2-first=Derek|editor3-last=Pratt|editor3-first=Geraldine|display-editors = 3 |editor4-last=Watts|editor4-first=Michael|title=Human Geography|encyclopedia=The Dictionary of Human Geography| pages=353–360|publisher=Blackwell|location=Oxford|year=2000}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Physical geography deals with the study of processes and patterns in the natural environment like the [[atmosphere]], [[hydrosphere]], [[biosphere]], and [[geosphere]].

The four historical traditions in geographical research are: [[spatial analysis|spatial analyses]] of natural and the human phenomena, [[area studies]] of places and regions, studies of human-land relationships, and the [[Earth science]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Pattison|first=William D.|date=Summer 1990|title=The Four Traditions of Geography|url=http://www.geog.ucsb.edu/~kclarke/G200B/four_20traditions_20of_20geography.pdf|journal=[[Journal of Geography]]|publication-date=1964|volume=September/October 1990|issue=5|pages=202–206|doi=10.1080/00221349008979196|issn=0022-1341|access-date=10 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Geography has been called "the world discipline" and "the bridge between the human and the [[physical science]]s".

==Introduction==
Geography is a systematic study of the Universe and its features. Traditionally, geography has been associated with [[cartography]] and place names. Although many geographers are trained in [[toponymy]] and [[Cartography|cartology]], this is not their main preoccupation. Geographers study the [[space]] and the [[temporal database]] distribution of phenomena, processes, and features as well as the [[interaction]] of humans and their [[Natural environment|environment]].&lt;ref name="Hayes-Bohanan"&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://webhost.bridgew.edu/jhayesboh/environmentalgeography.htm|title=What is Environmental Geography, Anyway?|last=Hayes-Bohanan|first=James|date=29 September 2009|website=webhost.bridgew.edu|publisher=[[Bridgewater State University]]|access-date=10 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Because space and place affect a variety of topics, such as [[economics]], [[health]], [[climate]], [[plant]]s and [[animal]]s, geography is highly interdisciplinary. The interdisciplinary nature of the geographical approach depends on an attentiveness to the relationship between physical and human phenomena and its spatial patterns.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books/about/An_Introduction_to_Settlement_Geography.html?id=DLpzQgAACAAJ|title=An introduction to Settlement Geography|last=Hornby|first=William F.|last2=Jones|first2=Melvyn|publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]]|isbn=978-0521282635|publication-date=29 June 1991|pages=|quote=|access-date=10 November 2016|via=|date=1991-06-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|text= Names of places...are not geography...know by heart a whole [[gazetteer]] full of them would not, in itself, constitute anyone a [[geographer]]. Geography has higher aims than this: it seeks to classify phenomena (alike of the natural and of the political world, in so far as it treats of the latter), to compare, to generalize, to ascend from effects to causes, and, in doing so, to trace out the laws of nature and to mark their influences upon man. This is 'a description of the world'—that is Geography. In a word Geography is a Science—a thing not of mere names but of argument and reason, of cause and effect.&lt;ref&gt;Hughes, William. (1863). ''The Study of Geography''. Lecture delivered at King's College, London by Sir Marc Alexander. Quoted in {{Cite book|last=Baker |first=J.N.L |date=1963 |title=The History of Geography |publisher=Basil Blackwell |location=Oxford |pages=66 |isbn=978-0853280224}}&lt;/ref&gt;|sign=[[William Hughes (geographer)|William Hughes]], 1863}}

{{quote|text=Just as all phenomena exist in time and thus have a history, they also exist in space and have a geography.&lt;ref&gt;"Chapter 3: Geography's Perspectives". {{Cite book|author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |date=1997 |title=Rediscovering Geography: New Relevance for Science and Society |publisher=The National Academies Press |location=Washington, DC |pages=28 |accessdate=2014-05-06 |url=http://www.nap.edu/openbook.php?record_id=4913&amp;page=28 }}&lt;/ref&gt;|sign=[[United States National Research Council]], 1997}}

Geography as a discipline can be split broadly into two main subsidiary fields: [[human geography]] and [[physical geography]]. The former largely focuses on the [[built environment]] and how humans create, view, manage, and influence space. The latter examines the natural environment, and how [[organism]]s, climate, [[soil]], [[water]], and [[landform]]s produce and interact.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=What is geography? |work=AAG Career Guide: Jobs in Geography and related Geographical Sciences |publisher=American Association of Geographers |url=http://www.aag.org/Careers/What_is_geog.html |accessdate=October 9, 2006 |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20061006152742/http://www.aag.org/Careers/What_is_geog.html &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = October 6, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; The difference between these approaches led to a third field, [[environmental geography]], which combines physical and human geography and concerns the interactions between the environment and humans.&lt;ref name="Hayes-Bohanan"/&gt;

==Branches==

===Physical geography===
{{Main|Physical geography}}

Physical geography (or physiography) focuses on geography as an [[Earth science]]. It aims to understand the physical problems and the issues of [[lithosphere]], [[hydrosphere]], [[Earth's atmosphere|atmosphere]], [[pedosphere]], and global [[flora]] and [[fauna]] patterns ([[biosphere]]).

&lt;gallery mode="packed" caption="Physical geography can be divided into many broad categories, including:"&gt;
File:Línea de Wallace.jpg|[[Biogeography]]
File:Cyclone Catarina from the ISS on March 26 2004.JPG|[[Climatology]] &amp; [[meteorology]]
File:90 mile beach.jpg|[[Coastal geography]]
File:Gavin Plant.JPG|[[Environmental management]]
File:Meridian convergence and spehrical excess.png|[[Geodesy]]
File:Delicate Arch LaSalle.jpg|[[Geomorphology]]
File:Receding glacier-en.svg|[[Glaciology]]
File:Meander.svg|[[Hydrology]] &amp; [[hydrography]]
File:Khajuraho-landscape.jpg|[[Landscape ecology]]
File:World11.jpg|[[Oceanography]]
File:Soil profile.jpg|[[Pedology (soil study)|Pedology]]
File:Pangea animation 03.gif|[[Palaeogeography]]
File:Milankovitch Variations sv.png|[[Quaternary science]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;

===Human geography===
{{Main|Human geography}}

Human geography is a branch of geography that focuses on the study of patterns and processes that shape the human society. It encompasses the [[human]], [[politics|political]], [[culture|cultural]], [[social]], and [[economics|economic]] aspects.

&lt;gallery mode="packed" caption="Human geography can be divided into many broad categories, such as:"&gt;
File:Qichwa conchucos 01.jpg|[[Cultural geography]]
File:Pepsi in India.jpg|[[Development geography]]
File:Christaller model 1.jpg|[[Economic geography]]
File:Star of life.svg|[[Health geography]]
File:British Empire 1897.jpg|[[Historical geography|Historical]] &amp; [[Time geography|Time geog.]]
File:UN General Assembly.jpg|[[Political geography|Political geog.]] &amp; [[Geopolitics]]
File:Pyramide Comores.PNG|[[Population geography|Pop. geog.]] or [[Demography]]
File:ReligionSymbol.svg|[[Religion geography]]
File:US-hoosier-family.jpg|[[Social geography]]
File:Gare du Nord USFRT (Paris Metro).png|[[Transportation geography]]
File:Tourists-2-x.jpg|[[Tourism geography]]
File:New-York-Jan2005.jpg|[[Urban geography]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;

Various approaches to the study of human geography have also arisen through time and include:
* [[Behavioral geography]]
* [[Feminist geography]]
* [[Culture theory]]
* [[Geosophy]]

===Environmental geography===
{{Main|Integrated geography}}

Environmental [[Integrated geography|geography]] is concerned with the description of the spatial interactions between humans and the [[Natural environment|natural world]]. It requires an understanding of the traditional aspects of physical and human geography, as well as the ways that human societies conceptualize the environment. Environmental geography has emerged as a bridge between the human and the physical geography, as a result of the increasing specialisation of the two sub-fields. Furthermore, as human relationship with the environment has changed as a result of [[globalization]] and [[technological change]], a new approach was needed to understand the changing and dynamic relationship. Examples of areas of research in the environmental geography include: [[emergency management]], [[environmental management]], [[sustainability]], and [[political ecology]].

===Geomatics===
{{Main|Geomatics}}

[[File:Geabios3d.jpg|thumb|right|Digital Elevation Model (DEM)]]
[[Geomatics]] is concerned with the application of computers to the traditional spatial techniques used in [[cartography]] and [[topography]]. Geomatics emerged from the [[quantitative revolution]] in geography in the mid-1950s. Today, geomatics methods include [[spatial analysis]], [[geographic information system|geographic information systems (GIS)]], [[remote sensing]], and [[global positioning system|global positioning systems (GPS)]]. Geomatics has led to a revitalization of some geography departments, especially in Northern America where the subject had a declining status during the 1950s.

===Regional geography===
{{Main|Regional geography}}

Regional geography is concerned with the description of the unique characteristics of a particular region such as its natural or human elements. The main aim is to understand, or define the uniqueness, or character of a particular region that consists of natural as well as human elements. Attention is paid also to [[regionalisation|regionalization]], which covers the proper techniques of space [[delimitation]] into regions.

===Related fields===
* [[Urban planning]], [[regional planning]], and [[spatial planning]]: Use the science of geography to assist in determining how to develop (or not develop) the land to meet particular criteria, such as safety, beauty, economic opportunities, the preservation of the built or natural heritage, and so on. The planning of towns, cities, and rural areas may be seen as [[applied geography]].
* [[Regional science]]: In the 1950s, the regional science movement led by [[Walter Isard]] arose to provide a more quantitative and analytical base to geographical questions, in contrast to the descriptive tendencies of traditional geography programs. Regional science comprises the body of knowledge in which the spatial dimension plays a fundamental role, such as [[regional science|regional economics]], [[resource management]], [[location theory]], [[urban planning|urban]] and [[regional planning]], [[transport]] and [[communication]], [[human geography]], population distribution, [[landscape ecology]], and environmental quality.
* [[Planetary science|Interplanetary Sciences]]: While the discipline of geography is normally concerned with the [[Earth]], the term can also be informally used to describe the study of other worlds, such as the [[planet]]s of the [[Solar System]] and even beyond. The study of systems larger than the Earth itself usually forms part of [[Astronomy]] or [[Cosmology]]. The study of other planets is usually called [[planetary science]]. Alternative terms such as [[Geology of Mars|areology]] (the study of Mars) have been proposed but are not widely used.

==Techniques==
As spatial interrelationships are key to this synoptic science, [[map]]s are a key tool. Classical [[cartography]] has been joined by a more modern approach to geographical analysis, computer-based [[geographic information system]]s (GIS).

In their study, geographers use four interrelated approaches:
* Systematic&amp;nbsp;– Groups geographical knowledge into categories that can be explored globally.
* Regional&amp;nbsp;– Examines systematic relationships between categories for a specific region or location on the planet.
* Descriptive&amp;nbsp;– Simply specifies the locations of features and populations.
* Analytical&amp;nbsp;– Asks ''why'' we find features and populations in a specific geographic area.

===Cartography===
[[File:Cook chart of New Zealand.jpg|thumb|[[James Cook]]'s 1770 chart of [[New Zealand]]]]
{{Main|Cartography}}

Cartography studies the representation of the Earth's surface with abstract symbols (map making). Although other subdisciplines of geography rely on maps for presenting their analyses, the actual making of maps is abstract enough to be regarded separately. Cartography has grown from a collection of drafting techniques into an actual science.

Cartographers must learn [[cognitive psychology]] and [[ergonomics]] to understand which symbols convey information about the Earth most effectively, and [[behaviorism|behavioural psychology]] to induce the readers of their maps to act on the information. They must learn [[geodesy]] and fairly advanced [[mathematics]] to understand how the [[Figure of the Earth|shape of the Earth]] affects the distortion of map symbols projected onto a flat surface for viewing. It can be said, without much controversy, that cartography is the seed from which the larger field of geography grew. Most geographers will cite a childhood fascination with maps as an early sign they would end up in the field.

===Geographic information systems===
{{Main|Geographic information system}}
&lt;!-- the section's use of a singular verb for a seemingly plural noun is intentional. The name of the academic subject is "Geographic information systems". If you didn't care about parallel construction, you could precede the following with THE SUBJECT OF ---&gt;
Geographic information systems (GIS) deal with the storage of information about the Earth for automatic retrieval by a computer, in an accurate manner appropriate to the information's purpose. In addition to all of the other subdisciplines of geography, GIS specialists must understand [[computer science]] and [[database]] systems. GIS has revolutionized the field of cartography: nearly all mapmaking is now done with the assistance of some form of [[List of GIS software|GIS software]]. GIS also refers to the science of using GIS software and GIS techniques to represent, analyse, and predict the spatial relationships. In this context, GIS stands for ''geographic information science''.

===Remote sensing===
{{Main|Remote sensing}}
Remote sensing is the science of obtaining information about Earth features from measurements made at a distance. Remotely sensed data comes in many forms, such as [[satellite imagery]], [[aerial photography]], and data obtained from hand-held sensors. Geographers increasingly use remotely sensed data to obtain information about the Earth's [[land surface]], ocean, and atmosphere, because it: (a) supplies objective information at a variety of spatial scales (local to global), (b) provides a synoptic view of the area of interest, (c) allows access to distant and inaccessible sites, (d) provides spectral information outside the visible portion of the [[electromagnetic spectrum]], and (e) facilitates studies of how features/areas change over time. Remotely sensed data may be analysed either independently of, or in conjunction with other digital data layers (e.g., in a geographic information system).

===Quantitative methods===
{{Main|Geostatistics}}

[[Geostatistics]] deal with [[Numerical data|quantitative data]] analysis, specifically the application of statistical methodology to the exploration of geographic phenomena. Geostatistics is used extensively in a variety of fields, including [[hydrology]], [[geology]], [[petroleum]] exploration, weather analysis, [[urban planning]], [[logistics]], and [[epidemiology]]. The mathematical basis for geostatistics derives from [[cluster analysis]], [[linear discriminant analysis]] and [[non-parametric statistics|non-parametric statistical tests]], and a variety of other subjects. Applications of geostatistics rely heavily on [[geographic information system]]s, particularly for the [[interpolation]] (estimate) of unmeasured points. Geographers are making notable contributions to the method of quantitative techniques.

===Qualitative methods===
{{Main|Ethnography}}
Geographic qualitative methods, or ethnographical research techniques, are used by human geographers. In [[cultural geography]] there is a tradition of employing [[qualitative research]] techniques, also used in [[anthropology]] and [[sociology]]. [[Participant observation]] and in-depth interviews provide human geographers with qualitative data.

==History==
{{Main|History of geography}}

The oldest known [[world map]]s date back to [[ancient Babylon]] from the 9th century BC.&lt;ref name="Kurt A. Raaflaub &amp; Richard J.A. Talbert 2009 147"&gt;{{Cite book |title=Geography and Ethnography: Perceptions of the World in Pre-Modern Societies |author=Kurt A. Raaflaub &amp; Richard J.A. Talbert |publisher=[[John Wiley &amp; Sons]] |date=2009 |isbn=978-1405191463 |page=147 |postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; The best known [[Babylonia]]n world map, however, is the ''[[Babylonian Map of the World|Imago Mundi]]'' of 600 BC.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.henry-davis.com/MAPS/Ancient%20Web%20Pages/103.html|title=Slide 103|last=Siebold|first=Jim|date=|website=henry-davis.com|publisher=Henry Davis Consulting Inc.|access-date=10 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The map as reconstructed by [[Eckhard Unger]] shows [[Babylon]] on the [[Euphrates]], surrounded by a circular landmass showing [[Assyria]], [[Urartu]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|first=Catherine|year=1996|title=Imago Mundi's Logo the Babylonian Map of the World|journal=Imago Mundi|volume=48|pages=209–211|jstor=1151277|author=Delano Smith|doi=10.1080/03085699608592846}}&lt;/ref&gt; and several cities, in turn surrounded by a "bitter river" ([[Oceanus]]), with seven islands arranged around it so as to form a seven-pointed star. The accompanying text mentions seven outer regions beyond the encircling ocean. The descriptions of five of them have survived.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=A join to the map of the world: A notable discovery|last=Finkel|first=Irving|publisher=[[British Museum Magazine]]|isbn=978-0714120737|date=Winter 1995|pages=26–27|quote=|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt; In contrast to the ''Imago Mundi'', an earlier Babylonian [[world map]] dating back to the 9th century BC depicted Babylon as being further north from the center of the world, though it is not certain what that center was supposed to represent.&lt;ref name="Kurt A. Raaflaub &amp; Richard J.A. Talbert 2009 147"/&gt;

The ideas of [[Anaximander]] (c. 610–545 BC): considered by later Greek writers to be the true founder of geography, come to us through fragments quoted by his successors. Anaximander is credited with the invention of the [[gnomon]], the simple, yet efficient Greek instrument that allowed the early measurement of [[latitude]]. [[Thales of Miletus|Thales]] is also credited with the prediction of eclipses. The foundations of geography can be traced to the ancient cultures, such as the ancient, medieval, and early modern [[History of China|Chinese]]. The [[ancient Greece|Greeks]], who were the first to explore geography as both [[art]] and [[science]], achieved this through [[History of cartography|Cartography]], [[Greek philosophy|Philosophy]], and [[Ancient Greek literature|Literature]], or through [[History of mathematics|Mathematics]]. There is some debate about who was the first person to assert that the [[Spherical Earth|Earth is spherical]] in shape, with the credit going either to [[Parmenides]] or [[Pythagoras]]. [[Anaxagoras]] was able to demonstrate that the profile of the Earth was circular by explaining [[eclipse]]s. However, he still believed that the Earth was a flat disk, as did many of his contemporaries. One of the first estimates of the radius of the Earth was made by [[Eratosthenes]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books/about/A_Concise_History_of_Solar_and_Stellar_P.html?id=nRtUait0qTgC|title=A Concise History of Solar and Stellar Physics|first=Jean-Louis|last2=Tassoul|first2=Monique|publisher=[[Princeton University Press]]|year=2004|isbn=978-0691117119|location=London|pages=|quote=|access-date=10 November 2016|via=|author=Tassoul}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The first rigorous system of [[Geographic coordinate system|latitude and longitude]] lines is credited to [[Hipparchus]]. He employed a [[sexagesimal]] system that was derived from [[Babylonian mathematics]]. The meridians were sub-divided into 360°, with each degree further subdivided into 60 ([[minute of arc|minutes]]). To measure the longitude at different locations on Earth, he suggested using eclipses to determine the relative difference in time.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.tmth.edu.gr/en/aet/3/58.html|title=Hipparchus of Rhodes|last=|first=|date=2001|website=tmth.edu.gr|publisher=[[Thessaloniki Science Center and Technology Museum]]|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080720120522/http://www.tmth.edu.gr/en/aet/3/58.html|archive-date=20 July 2008|dead-url=yes|accessdate=10 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The extensive mapping by the [[Roman Empire|Romans]] as they explored new lands would later provide a high level of information for [[Ptolemy]] to construct detailed [[atlas]]es. He extended the work of [[Hipparchus]], using a grid system on his maps and adopting a length of 56.5 miles for a degree.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.math.rutgers.edu/~cherlin/History/Papers2000/sullivan.html|title=Mapmaking and its History|last=Sullivan|first=Dan|date=2000|website=|publisher=[[Rutgers University]]|accessdate=10 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

From the 3rd century onwards, [[History of China|Chinese]] methods of geographical study and writing of geographical literature became much more comprehensive than what was found in Europe at the time (until the 13th century).&lt;ref name="needham volume 3 512"/&gt; Chinese geographers such as [[Liu An]], [[Pei Xiu]], [[Jia Dan]], [[Shen Kuo]], [[Fan Chengda]], [[Zhou Daguan]], and [[Xu Xiake]] wrote important treatises, yet by the 17th century advanced ideas and methods of Western-style geography were adopted in China.

[[File:PtolemyWorldMap.jpg|thumb|The [[Ptolemy world map]], reconstituted from [[Ptolemy]]'s ''Geographia'', written {{circa|150}}]]
During the [[Middle Ages]], the [[Decline of the Roman Empire|fall of the Roman empire]] led to a shift in the evolution of geography from [[Europe]] to the [[Muslim world|Islamic world]].&lt;ref name="needham volume 3 512"&gt;{{Cite book|last=Needham|first=Joseph|year=1959|title=Mathematics and the Sciences of the Heavens and the Earth|url=https://books.google.com/books/about/Science_and_Civilisation_in_China_Volume.html?id=jfQ9E0u4pLAC|journal=Science and Civilization in China|location=Taipei|publisher=Caves Books, Ltd.|volume=3|page=512|isbn=978-0521058018|access-date=10 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Geography in medieval Islam|Muslim geographers]] such as [[Muhammad al-Idrisi]] produced detailed world maps (such as [[Tabula Rogeriana]]), while other geographers such as [[Yaqut al-Hamawi]], [[Abu Rayhan Biruni]], [[Ibn Battuta]], and [[Ibn Khaldun]] provided detailed accounts of their journeys and the geography of the regions they visited. Turkish geographer, [[Mahmud al-Kashgari]] drew a world map on a linguistic basis, and later so did [[Piri Reis]] ([[Piri Reis map]]). Further, Islamic scholars translated and [[interpreting|interpreted]] the earlier works of the [[Ancient Rome|Romans]] and the [[ancient Greece|Greeks]] and established the [[House of Wisdom]] in [[Baghdad]] for this purpose.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.islamicity.com/education/ihame/default.asp?Destination=/education/ihame/20.asp|title=Science and Scholarship in Al-Andalus|last=|first=|date=|website=IslamiCity.com|publisher=IslamiCity|accessdate=10 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Ahmed ibn Sahl al-Balkhi|Abū Zayd al-Balkhī]], originally from [[Balkh]], founded the "Balkhī school" of terrestrial mapping in [[Baghdad]].&lt;ref name="E61-3"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Edson|first=Evelyn|last2=Savage-Smith|first2=Emilie|title=Medieval Views of the Cosmos|journal=International Journal of the Classical Tradition|date=Winter 2007|volume=13:3|pages=61–63|jstor=30222166}}&lt;/ref&gt; Suhrāb, a late tenth century Muslim geographer accompanied a book of geographical coordinates, with instructions for making a rectangular world map with [[equirectangular projection]] or cylindrical equidistant projection.&lt;ref name = E61-3/&gt;{{Verify source|date=October 2011}}

[[Abu Rayhan Biruni]] (976–1048) first described a polar equi-[[azimuthal equidistant projection]] of the [[celestial sphere]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=King|first=David A.|year=1996|editor-last=Rashed|editor-first=Roshdi|title=Astronomy and Islamic society: Qibla, gnomics and timekeeping|url=http://qisar.fssr.uns.ac.id/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Qisar-Roshdi-Rashed-Encyclopedia-of-the-History-of-Arabic-Science.pdf|journal=Encyclopedia of the History of Arabic Science|volume=1|pages=128–184|isbn=978-0203711842|access-date=10 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; He was regarded as the most skilled when it came to mapping cities and measuring the distances between them, which he did for many cities in the [[Middle East]] and the [[Indian subcontinent]]. He often combined astronomical readings and mathematical equations, in order to develop methods of pin-pointing locations by recording degrees of [[latitude]] and [[longitude]]. He also developed similar techniques when it came to measuring the heights of [[mountain]]s, depths of the [[valley]]s, and expanse of the [[horizon]]. He also discussed [[human geography]] and the [[planetary habitability]] of the [[Earth]]. He also calculated the [[latitude]] of Kath, [[Khwarezm]], using the maximum altitude of the Sun, and solved a complex [[Geodesy|geodesic]] equation in order to accurately compute the [[Earth]]'s [[circumference]], which was close to modern values of the Earth's circumference.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://academic.emporia.edu/aberjame/histgeol/biruni/biruni.htm|title=Abu Rayhan al-Biruni|last=Aber|first=James Sandusky|date=2003|website=academic.emporia.edu|publisher=[[Emporia State University]]|access-date=10 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; His estimate of 6,339.9&amp;nbsp;km for the [[Earth radius]] was only 16.8&amp;nbsp;km less than the modern value of 6,356.7&amp;nbsp;km. In contrast to his predecessors, who measured the Earth's circumference by sighting the Sun simultaneously from two different locations, [[al-Biruni]] developed a new method of using [[trigonometry|trigonometric]] calculations, based on the angle between a [[plain]] and [[mountain]] top, which yielded more accurate measurements of the Earth's circumference, and made it possible for it to be measured by a single person from a single location.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/?id=VJ6x-pcqMicC&amp;pg=PA109&amp;q=biruni|title=Avicenna|last=Goodman|first=Lenn Evan|publisher=Routledge|year=1992|isbn=978-0415019293|location=Great Britain|pages=31|quote=It was Biruni, not Avicenna, who found a way for a single man, at a single moment, to measure the earth's circumference, by trigonometric calculations based on angles measured from a mountaintop and the plain beneath it – thus improving on Eratosthenes' method of sighting the sun simultaneously from two different sites, applied in  the ninth century by astronomers of the Khalif al-Ma'mun.|access-date=10 November 2016|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Alexander von Humboldt-selfportrait.jpg|thumb|Self portrait of [[Alexander von Humboldt]], one of the early pioneers of geography as an academic subject in modern sense]]
The European [[Age of Discovery]] during the 16th and the 17th centuries, where many new lands were discovered and accounts by European explorers such as [[Christopher Columbus]], [[Marco Polo]], and [[James Cook]] revived a desire for both accurate geographic detail, and more solid theoretical foundations in Europe. The problem facing both explorers and geographers was finding the latitude and longitude of a geographic location. The problem of latitude was solved long ago but that of longitude remained; agreeing on what zero meridian should be was only part of the problem. It was left to [[John Harrison]] to solve it by inventing the chronometer [[Harrison Number Four|H-4]] in 1760, and later in 1884 for the [[International Meridian Conference]] to adopt by convention the [[Greenwich meridian]] as zero meridian.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/?id=bz4GyOioMF4C&amp;pg=RA1-PA164#v=onepage|title=Voyages that changed the world|last=Aughton|first=Peter|publisher=[[Penguin Group]]|year=2009|isbn=978-1847240040|location=|page=164|quote=|access-date=10 November 2016|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The 18th and the 19th centuries were the times when geography became recognized as a discrete [[List of academic disciplines|academic discipline]], and became part of a typical [[university]] curriculum in [[Europe]] (especially [[Paris]] and [[Berlin]]). The development of many geographic societies also occurred during the 19th century, with the foundations of the [[Société de Géographie]] in 1821,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.socgeo.org/la-societe/qui-sommes-nous|title=Société de Géographie, Paris, France|last=|first=|date=|website=socgeo.org|publisher=Société de Géographie|language=French|accessdate=10 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; the [[Royal Geographical Society]] in 1830,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.rgs.org/AboutUs/about+us.htm |title=About Us |last= |first= |date= |website=rgs.org |publisher=[[Royal Geographical Society]] |accessdate=10 November 2016 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20161018192946/http://www.rgs.org/AboutUs/About%2Bus.htm |archivedate=18 October 2016 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Russian Geographical Society]] in 1845,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.rgo.org.ru/ |title=Русское Географическое Общество (основано в 1845 г.) |last= |first= |date= |website=rgo.org.ru |publisher=[[Russian Geological Society]] |language=Russian |archive-url=https://archive.is/20120524183911/http://www.rgo.org.ru/ |archive-date=2012-05-24 |dead-url=yes |accessdate=10 November 2016 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[American Geographical Society]] in 1851,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://americangeo.org/history/|title=History|last=|first=|date=|website=Amergeog.org|publisher=The American Geographical Society|accessdate=10 November 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161017130118/http://americangeo.org/history/|archive-date=2016-10-17|dead-url=yes|df=}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[National Geographic Society]] in 1888.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.state.gov/p/io/unesco/members/48805.htm|title=National Geographic Society|last=|first=|date=|website=state.gov|publisher=U.S. Department of State|accessdate=10 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The influence of [[Immanuel Kant]], [[Alexander von Humboldt]], [[Carl Ritter]], and [[Paul Vidal de la Blache]] can be seen as a major turning point in geography from a philosophy to an academic subject.

Over the past two centuries, the advancements in technology with computers have led to the development of [[geomatics]] and new practices such as participant observation and geostatistics being incorporated into geography's portfolio of tools. In the West during the 20th century, the discipline of geography went through four major phases: [[environmental determinism]], [[regional geography]], the [[quantitative revolution]], and [[critical geography]]. The strong interdisciplinary links between geography and the sciences of [[geology]] and [[botany]], as well as [[economics]], [[sociology]] and [[demographics]] have also grown greatly, especially as a result of [[earth system science]] that seeks to understand the world in a holistic view.

==Notable geographers==&lt;!-- Please respect chronoogial order --&gt;
{{Main|List of geographers|List of Graeco-Roman geographers}}
[[File:Gerardus Mercator3.jpg|thumb|[[Gerardus Mercator]]]]
* [[Eratosthenes]] (276–194 BC)&amp;nbsp;– calculated the size of the Earth.
* [[Strabo]] (64/63 BC&amp;nbsp;– c. AD 24)&amp;nbsp;–  wrote [[Geographica]], one of the first books outlining the study of geography.
* [[Ptolemy]] (c. 90–168)&amp;nbsp;– compiled Greek and Roman knowledge into the book [[Geographia]].
* [[Al Idrisi]] (Arabic: أبو عبد الله محمد الإدريسي; Latin: Dreses) (1100–1165/66)&amp;nbsp;– author of Nuzhatul Mushtaq.
* [[Gerardus Mercator]] (1512–1594)&amp;nbsp;– innovative [[cartography|cartographer]] produced the [[mercator projection]]
* [[Alexander von Humboldt]] (1769–1859)&amp;nbsp;– considered father of modern geography, published ''[[Cosmos (Humboldt)|Cosmos]]'' and founder of the sub-field biogeography.
* [[Carl Ritter]] (1779–1859)&amp;nbsp;– considered father of modern geography, occupied the first chair of geography at Berlin University.
* [[Arnold Henry Guyot]] (1807–1884)&amp;nbsp;– noted the structure of glaciers and advanced understanding in [[Glacial motion|glacier motion]], especially in fast ice flow.
* [[Radhanath Sikdar]] (1813–1870)&amp;nbsp;– calculated the height of [[Mount Everest]].
* [[William Morris Davis]] (1850–1934)&amp;nbsp;– father of American geography and developer of the [[cycle of erosion]].
* [[Paul Vidal de la Blache]] (1845–1918)&amp;nbsp;– founder of the French school of geopolitics, wrote the principles of human geography.
* [[John Francon Williams]] (1854–1911) - noted author of ''The Geography of the Oceans'' and other geography works.
* Sir [[Halford Mackinder]] (1861–1947)&amp;nbsp;– co-founder of the [[London School of Economics|LSE]], [[Geographical Association]].
* [[Ellen Churchill Semple]] (1863–1932)&amp;nbsp;– first influential female geographer in the United States.
* [[Carl O. Sauer]] (1889–1975)&amp;nbsp;– prominent cultural geographer.
* [[Walter Christaller]] (1893–1969)&amp;nbsp;– human geographer and inventor of [[Central place theory]].
* [[Yi-Fu Tuan]] (born 1930)&amp;nbsp;– Chinese-American scholar credited with starting Humanistic Geography as a discipline.
* [[Karl Butzer|Karl W. Butzer]] (1934–2016)&amp;nbsp;– influential German-American geographer, cultural ecologist and environmental archaeologist.
* [[David Harvey (geographer)|David Harvey]] (born 1935)&amp;nbsp;– Marxist geographer and author of theories on spatial and urban geography, winner of the [[Lauréat Prix International de Géographie Vautrin Lud|Vautrin Lud Prize]].
* [[Edward Soja]] (1941–2015)&amp;nbsp;– noted for his work on regional development, planning and governance along with coining the terms [[Synekism]] and Postmetropolis; winner of the [[Lauréat Prix International de Géographie Vautrin Lud|Vautrin Lud Prize]].
* [[Michael Frank Goodchild]] (born 1944)&amp;nbsp;– prominent GIS scholar and winner of the RGS founder's medal in 2003.
* [[Doreen Massey (geographer)|Doreen Massey]] (1944–2016)&amp;nbsp;– key scholar in the space and places of [[globalization]] and its pluralities; winner of the [[Lauréat Prix International de Géographie Vautrin Lud|Vautrin Lud Prize]].
* [[Nigel Thrift]] (born 1949)&amp;nbsp;– originator of [[non-representational theory]].

==Institutions and societies==
* [[American Geographical Society]] (US)
* [[Anton Melik Geographical Institute]] (Slovenia)
* [[American Association of Geographers|American Association of Geographers (AAG)]]
* [[National Geographic Society]] (US)
* [[Royal Canadian Geographical Society]] (Canada)
* [[Royal Geographical Society]] (UK)
* [[Russian Geographical Society]] (Russia)
* [[Royal Danish Geographical Society]] (Denmark)

==Publications==
* ''[[African Geographical Review]]''
* ''[[Geographical Review]]''

==Notes and references==
{{Reflist}}

{{Geography topics|state=uncollapsed}}
{{Social sciences}}
{{Glossaries of science and engineering}}
{{Subject bar |book=Geography |portal=Geography |commons=yes |wikt=yes |wikt-search=geography |n=yes |q=yes |s=yes |s-search=Portal:Geography |b=yes |b-search=Subject:Geography |v=yes |d=yes |d-search=Q1071}}

{{Authority control}}
{{Use British English Oxford spelling|date=August 2016}}

[[Category:Geography| ]]
[[Category:Earth sciences]]
[[Category:Social sciences]]</text>
      <sha1>ry2go71fdgi3ay160j3d3k920w669dp</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>List of geographers</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>223124</id>
    <revision>
      <id>845267185</id>
      <parentid>841235926</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-06-10T16:41:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Vouliagmeni</username>
        <id>10328124</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* P */ add geographer</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="10333">{{pp-semi|small=yes}}
This '''list of [[geographer]]s''' is presented in English alphabetical [[transliteration]] order (by [[surname]]s).

{{Dynamic list}}
{{Compact ToC|seealso=yes|q=}}
{{commons category|Geographers}}

==A==
* [[Hardo Aasmäe]] (Estonia, 1951–2014)
* [[Aziz Ab'Saber]] (Brazil, born 1924)
* [[Diogo Abreu (geographer)|Diogo Abreu]] (Portugal, born 1947)
* [[Peter Adams (politician)|Peter Adams]] (Canada, born 1936)
* [[Agatharchides]] (Ancient Greece, 2nd century BC)
* [[Agathedaemon of Alexandria]] (Ancient Greece, 2nd century AD)
* [[John A. Agnew]] (British-American, born 1949)
* [[A. W. Andrews]] (UK, 1868–1959)
* [[Ash Amin]] (UK, born 1955)
* [[Alypius of Antioch]] (Roman Empire, fl. c. 450)
* [[Jacques Ancel]] (France, 1879–1943)
* [[Karl Andree]] (Germany, 1808–1875)
* [[Richard Andree]] (Germany, 1835–1912)
* [[Aaron Arrowsmith]] (England, 1750–1823)
* [[Väinö Auer]] (Finland, 1895–1981)
* [[Félix de Azara]] (Spain, 1742–1821)

==B==
* [[Zonia Baber]] (1862–1955)
* [[Karl Ernst von Baer]] (1792–1876)
* [[Robert Bailey (geographer)|Robert Bailey]]
* [[Oliver Edwin Baker]] (US, 1883–1949)
* [[Abu Abdullah al-Bakri]] (1014–1094)
* [[Ahmed ibn Sahl al-Balkhi]] (Persia, 850–934)
* [[Robert Balling]]
* [[Mark Bassin]]
* [[Keith Barber (geographer)|Keith Barber]]
* [[John George Bartholomew]]
* [[Ibn Battuta]] (Morocco, 1304–1369)
* [[Anthony Bebbington]] (born 1962)
* [[Frederick William Beechey]]
* [[Walter Behrmann]]
* [[Charles Tilstone Beke]]
* [[Lev Semenovich Berg]]
* [[Luiza Bialasiewicz]]
* [[Abū Rayhān Bīrūnī]] (Persia, 973–1048)
* [[Joan Blaeu]] (Amsterdam 1596–1673)
* [[Harm de Blij]]
* [[Franz Boas]]
* Prince [[Roland Bonaparte]]
* [[Isaiah Bowman]]
* [[Edward William Brayley]]
* [[Harold Brookfield]] (born 1926)
* [[John Brown (geographer)|John Brown]] (1797–1861)
* [[Conrad Malte-Brun]]
* [[William Bunge]]
* [[Philip Burden]]
* Sir [[Richard Francis Burton]], Royal Geographical Society

==C==
* [[Manuel Castells]]
* [[Richard Cathcart]]
* [[Andreas Cellarius]]
* [[Samuel de Champlain]]
* [[Chen Cheng-Siang Chen]]
* [[George Chisholm (geographer)|George Chisholm]]
* [[Richard Chorley]]
* [[Walter Christaller]] (Germany 1893–1969)
* [[Václav Cílek]] (Czech Republic, born 1955)
* [[A. Rees Clark]]
* [[Claudius Clavus]] (Claudus Claussøn Swart)
* [[Philip Cluwer]]
* [[Denis Cosgrove]] (England 1948–2008)
* [[John Antony Cramer]]
* [[George Cressey]]
* [[James Croll]]
* [[Mike Crang]]
* [[Jovan Cvijić]] (Serbia 1865–1927)

==D==
* [[Alexander Dalrymple]]
* [[Jack Dangermond]]
* [[William Morris Davis]] (US, 1850–1934)
* [[Frank Debenham]]
* [[John Dee (mathematician)|John Dee]] (England, 1527–1608)
* [[Félix Delamarche]] (France)
* [[Jared Diamond]] (US, 1937)
* [[Dicaearchus]] (Greece, c. 350–285&amp;nbsp;BC)
* [[Peter Dicken]]
* [[Frans Dieleman]]
* [[Al-Dinawari]] (828–898)
* [[Vasily V. Dokuchaev]]
* [[William E. Doolittle]]

==E==
* [[William Gordon East]]
* [[Eratosthenes]] (Greece, 276–194&amp;nbsp;BC)
* [[Lewis Evans (surveyor)|Lewis Evans]]
* [[George Everest]]

==F==
* [[Ahmad ibn Fadlan]] (10th century)
* [[Ghazi Falah]]
* [[Ibn al-Faqih]] (10th century)
* [[Carlos Ferrás Sexto]]
* [[Abu al-Fida]] (Abulfeda) (Syria, 1273–1331)
* [[J. Keith Fraser]]
* [[Gemma Frisius]] (Netherlands, 1508–1555)
* [[Masahisa Fujita]]

==G==
* [[Alfons Gabriel]]
* [[Johann Georg August Galletti]]
* [[Paul Gallez]]
* [[Francis Galton]]
* [[Henry Gannett]]
* [[Luis García Sáinz]] (Spain, 1894–1965)
* [[Abu Said Gardezi]] (died 1061)
* [[William Garrison (geographer)|William Garrison]]
* [[Artur Gavazzi]] (Croatia, Slovenia, 1861–1944)
* [[Johann Gottlieb Georgi]]
* [[John Alan Glennon]]
* [[Johann Georg Gmelin]]
* [[Reginald G. Golledge]]
* [[Michael Frank Goodchild]] (born 1944)
* [[Jean Gottman]]
* [[Peter Gould (professor)|Peter Gould]]
* [[Derek Gregory]]
* [[Lev Gumilev]]
* [[Arnold Henry Guyot]]

==H==
* [[Mohammad Reza Hafeznia]] (Iran)
* [[Toni Hagen]]
* [[Torsten Hägerstrand]] (Sweden, 1916–2004)
* [[Peter Haggett]]
* [[Yaqut al-Hamawi]] (1179–1229)
* [[Abū Muhammad al-Hasan al-Hamdānī|Hamdani]] (893-945)
* [[Cole Harris]]
* [[Richard Hartshorne]] (United States, 1899–1992)
* [[David Harvey (geographer)|David Harvey]] (United States, Britain, born 1935)
* [[Henri Hauser]]
* [[Karl Haushofer]]
* [[Ibn Hawqal]] (died after 977)
* [[Ibn al-Haytham]] (Alhazen) (Iraq, 965-1039)
* [[Zheng He]]
* [[John Heap (geographer)|John Heap]]
* [[Sven Hedin]] (Sweden, 1865–1952)
* [[Gamal Hemdan]] (Egypt, 1928–1993)
* [[Alfred Hettner]]
* [[Hipparchus]] (Greece, 190-120&amp;nbsp;BC)
* [[Filip Hjulström]] (Sweden, 1092-1982)
* [[Thomas Holdich]]
* [[John Holmes (professor)|John Holmes]]
* [[Johann Homann]] (Germany, 1664–1724)
* [[J.F. Horrabin]]
* [[Robert E. Horton]]
* [[Carl Humann]]
* [[Alexander von Humboldt]] (Germany, 1769–1859)
* [[Ellsworth Huntington]]
* [[Thomas Hutchins]]

==I==
* [[Muhammad al-Idrisi]] (Dreses) (Islamic Spain, 1100–1166)
* [[Cosmas Indicopleustes]]
* [[Anastas Ishirkov]] (Bulgaria, 1868-1937)

==J==
* [[Jane Jacobs]]
* [[Kim Jeong-ho]]
* [[Alexander Keith Johnston (1804-1871)|Alexander Keith Johnston]] (1804-1871)
* [[Alexander Keith Johnston (1844-1879)|Alexander Keith Johnston]] (1844-1879)
* [[Ron J. Johnston]]
* [[Kelvyn Jones]]
* [[Reece Jones (geographer)|Reece Jones]]
* [[Ibn Jubayr]] (1145–1217)

==K==
* [[Felix Philipp Kanitz]]
* [[Mahmud al-Kashgari]] (1005–1102)
* [[Robert Kates]]
* [[Ibn Khordadbeh]] (820-912)
* [[Muhammad ibn Mūsā al-Khwārizmī]] (780-850)
* [[Heinrich Kiepert]]
* [[Richard Kiepert]]
* [[Al-Kindi]] (Alkindus) (801-873)
* [[Fred B. Kniffen]] (1900-1993)
* [[Peter Knight (scientist)|Peter Knight]]
* [[Grigorios Konstantas]] (1753-1844)
* [[Peter Kozler]]
* [[Stepan Krasheninnikov]]
* [[Peter Kropotkin]]

==L==
* [[Yves Lacoste]]
* [[Joannes de Laet]]
* [[William Lambton]]
* [[Marcia Langton]]
* [[Philippe Le Billon]]
* [[Peirce F. Lewis]]
* [[Liu An]] (China, 177-122&amp;nbsp;BC)
* [[David Livingstone]]

==M==
* [[Halford John Mackinder]] (UK, 1861–1947)
* [[Ahmad Bin Majid]] (born 1432)
* [[Conrad Malte-Brun]]
* [[Victor Adolphe Malte-Brun]]
* [[Kenneth Mason (geographer)|Kenneth Mason]]
* [[Doreen Massey (geographer)|Doreen Massey]]
* [[Abu al-Hasan 'Alī al-Mas'ūdī]] (896-956)
* [[Otto Maull]]
* [[Megasthenes]]
* [[Simion Mehedinți]] (Romania, 1868–1962)
* [[D. W. Meinig]]
* [[August Meitzen]] (Germany 1822-1910)
* [[Anton Melik]] (Slovenia, 1890–1966)
* [[Alfred Merz]]
* [[Nicolae Milescu]]
* [[Don Mitchell (geographer)|Don Mitchell]]
* [[Mark Monmonier]]
* [[Jedidiah Morse]]
* [[Michael Mortimore]]
* [[William G. Moseley]]
* [[Hamdollah Mostowfi]] (1281–1349)
* [[Al-Muqaddasi]] (945-1000)

==N==
* [[Christophe Neff]]
* [[Joseph Nicollet]]
* [[Pedro Nunes]]

==O==
* [[Erich Obst]]
* [[Vladimir Obruchev]]
* [[Patrick O'Flanagan]]
* [[Miles Ogborn]]
* [[Kenneth Olwig]]
* [[Gearóid Ó Tuathail]]

==P==
* [[Xoán Paredes]]
* [[Joseph Partsch]]
* [[Pasqualetti]]
*[[Patrick Geddes]]
* [[Pausanias  (geographer)|Pausanias]] (Greece, fl. c. 150)
* [[Ceri Peach]]
* [[Albrecht Penck]]
* [[Walther Penck]]
* [[Daniel Philippidis]] (c. 1750-1832) 
* [[Chris Philo]]
* [[Marco Polo]]
* [[Posidonius]] (Greece 135-51&amp;nbsp;BCE)
* [[Allan Pred]]
* [[John Robert Victor Prescott]]
* [[Nikolai Przhevalsky]]
* [[Pseudo-Scymnus]]
* [[Ptolemy]] (Roman Egypt, c. 85 - 165)
* [[Pytheas]] (Greece, fl. c. 360&amp;nbsp;BC)

==R==
* [[Sarah A. Radcliffe]]
* [[Friedrich Ratzel]]
* [[Amin Razi]] (Persia, 16th century)
* [[Elisee Reclus]]
* [[Piri Reis]] (Turkey, 1465–1554)
* [[James Rennell]]
* [[Orlando Ribeiro]] (Portugal, 1911–1997)
* [[Ferdinand Baron Von Richthofen]] (19th century)
* [[Carl Ritter]] (Germany, 1779–1859)
* [[Arthur H. Robinson]]
* [[Joseph Rock]]
* [[Friedrich Gerhard Rohlfs]]
* [[Bernard Romans]]
* [[Thomas E. Ross]]
* [[William Roy]]
* [[Averroes|Ibn Rushd]] (Averroes) (Islamic Spain, 1126–1198)
* [[Ibn Rustah]] (Persia, died 903)

==S==
* [[David Sadler (geographer)|David Sadler]]
* [[Milton Santos]] (Brazil, 1926—2001)
* [[Saskia Sassen]]
* [[Carl Sauer]] (US, 1889—1975)
* [[Fred K. Schaefer]] (Berlin, Germany 1904-US, 1953)
* {{Interlanguage link multi|Kurt Scharlau|de}}
* [[Henry Schoolcraft]]
* [[Leopold von Schrenck]]
* [[Allen J Scott]]
* [[Scymnus]]
* [[Pyotr Semenov-Tyan-Shansky]]
* [[Ellen Churchill Semple]]
* [[Edward Shackleton, Baron Shackleton]]
* [[Shen Kuo]] (China, 1031–1095)
* [[Yuly Shokalsky]]
* [[Avicenna|Ibn Sina]] (Avicenna) (Persia, 980-1037)
* [[Paul Allen Siple]]
* [[Andrew Sluyter]]
* [[Neil Smith (geographer)|Neil Smith]]
* [[Richard G. Smith (geographer)|Richard_G_Smith]]
* [[Edward Soja]] (Spain, 1942)
* [[Su Song]] (China, 1020–1101)
* [[Oskar Spate]]
* [[John Speke]], [[Royal Geographical Society]]
* [[Evelyn Stokes]] (New Zealand, 1936–2005)
* [[Strabo]] (Roman Empire, Greece, c. 63/64 - c. 24&amp;nbsp;BC)
* Ulf Strohmayer

==T==
* [[Andres Tarand]] (Estonia, born 1940)
* [[Ralph Stockman Tarr]]
* [[Peter J. Taylor]]
* [[Nigel Thrift]]
* [[Johann Heinrich von Thünen]] (Germany, 1783–1850)
* [[Waldo R. Tobler]]
* [[Wilhelm Tomaschek]]
* [[Roger Tomlinson]]
* [[George Trebeck]]
* [[Emil Trinkler]]
* [[Carl Troll]]
* [[Yi-Fu Tuan]] (United States, China, born 1930)
* [[Billie Lee Turner II]]
* [[Marinos of Tyre]]

==U==
* [[Edward Ullman]]

==V==
* [[Paul Vidal de la Blache]] (France, 1845–1918)
*[[Vasily Dokuchaev]]

==W==
* [[Alfred Russel Wallace]]
* [[Richard Waller]]
* [[Michael Watts]]
* [[Alfred Weber]] (Germany, 1868–1958)
* [[Alfred Lothar Wegener]]
* [[Gilbert F. White]]
* [[John Francon Williams]] FRGS (1854 – 4 September 1911)
* [[Alan Wilson (academic)|Alan Wilson]]
* [[Charles W. J. Withers]]
* [[Denis Wood]] (United States, born 1945)
* [[John Kirtland Wright]]

==X==
* [[Xu Xiake]]

==Y==
* [[Naomasa Yamasaki]]
* [[Ya'qubi]] (died 897)

==Z==
* [[Wilbur Zelinsky]] (United States, born 1921)
* [[Eberhard August Wilhelm von Zimmermann]]
* [[Karl Bernhard Zoeppritz]] (Germany, 1881-1908)

==See also==
*[[List of cartographers]]
*[[List of Graeco-Roman geographers]]
*[[List of Muslim geographers]]
*[[Russian geographers]]

{{Authority control}}
[[Category:Lists of social scientists|Geographers]]
[[Category:Geographers|*]]</text>
      <sha1>onboymqmo0b8ecs2wf2zrejqat7n93a</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Outline of geography</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>26044771</id>
    <revision>
      <id>867483800</id>
      <parentid>867483542</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-11-06T00:48:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>129.7.104.28</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Branches of geography */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="86990">{{short description|Hierarchical outline list of articles related to geography}}
&lt;!--... Attention:  THIS IS AN OUTLINE

        part of the set of 740+ outlines listed at
             [[Portal:Contents/Outlines]].

                 Wikipedia outlines are
              a special type of list article.
              They make up one of Wikipedia's
                content navigation systems

                See [[Wikipedia:Outlines]]
                      for more details.
                   Further improvements
              to this outline are on the way
...--&gt;
{{See also|Index of geography articles}}

The following [[Outline (list)|outline]] is provided as an overview of and topical guide to geography:

'''[[Geography]]''' &amp;ndash; study of earth and its people.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Geography |work=The American Heritage Dictionary/ of the English Language, Fourth Edition |publisher=Houghton Mifflin Company |url=http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/geography |accessdate=October 9, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Physical world.jpg|thumb|300px|right|The physical world.]]
[[File:Political world2.jpg|thumb|300px|right|The human world.]]

{{TOC limit|limit=3}}

== Nature of geography ==

=== Geography is  ===

* an [[academic discipline]] &amp;ndash; a body of knowledge given to − or received by − a disciple (student); a branch or sphere of knowledge, or field of study, that an individual has chosen to specialize in. Modern geography is an all-encompassing discipline that seeks to understand the Earth and all of its human and natural complexities − not merely where objects are, but how they have changed and come to be. Geography has been called 'the world discipline'.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last = Bonnett|first= Alastair |title =  What is Geography?|location= London|publisher = Sage|date = 2008|isbn =9781412918688}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* a [[fields of science|field of science]] &amp;ndash; widely recognized category of specialized expertise within science, and typically embodies its own terminology and nomenclature. Such a field will usually be represented by one or more scientific journals, where peer reviewed research is published. There are many geography-related scientific journals.
** a [[natural science]] &amp;ndash; field of academic scholarship that explores aspects of natural environment (physical geography).
** a [[social science]] &amp;ndash; field of academic scholarship that explores aspects of human society (human geography).
* an [[interdisciplinary field]] &amp;ndash; a field that crosses traditional boundaries between academic disciplines or schools of thought, as new needs and professions have emerged. Many of the branches of physical geography are also branches of Earth science.

== Branches of geography ==

As "the bridge between the human and physical sciences," geography is divided into two main branches:
*human geography
*physical geography&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://web.clas.ufl.edu/users/morgans/lecture_2.prn.pdf|title = Geography: The Mother of Sciences|deadurl = yes|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20030901102227/http://web.clas.ufl.edu/users/morgans/lecture_2.prn.pdf|archivedate = 1 September 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.physicalgeography.net/fundamentals/1b.html |title=Elements of Geography|last= Pidwirny|first= M.|date=2006|work = Fundamentals of Physical Geography|edition = 2nd |publisher=Physicalgeography.net}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other branches include:
*integrated geography
*geomatics
*regional geography

All the branches are further described below...

=== Physical geography ===

* [[Physical geography]] &amp;ndash; examines the natural environment and how the climate, vegetation &amp; life, soil, water, and landforms are produced and interact.&lt;ref name="AAG"/&gt;

==== Fields of physical geography ====

* [[Geomorphology]] &amp;ndash; study of landforms and the processes that them, and more broadly, of the processes controlling the topography of any planet. Seeks to understand why landscapes look the way they do, to understand landform history and dynamics, and to predict future changes through a combination of field observation, physical experiment, and numerical modeling.
* [[Hydrology]] &amp;ndash; study of the movement, distribution, and quality of water throughout the Earth, including the hydrologic cycle, water resources and environmental watershed sustainability.
** [[Glaciology]] &amp;ndash; study of glaciers, or more generally ice and natural phenomena that involve ice.
** [[Oceanography]] &amp;ndash; studies a wide range of topics pertaining to oceans, including marine organisms and ecosystem dynamics; ocean currents, waves, and geophysical fluid dynamics; plate tectonics and the geology of the sea floor; and fluxes of various chemical substances and physical properties within the ocean and across its boundaries.
* [[Biogeography]] &amp;ndash; study of the distribution of species spatially and temporally. Over areal [[ecology|ecological]] changes, it is also tied to the concepts of species and their past, or present living '[[refugium (population biology)|refugium]]', their survival locales, or their interim living sites. It aims to reveal where organisms live, and at what abundance.&lt;ref&gt;Martiny JBH et al. [http://alrlab.pdx.edu/media/HughesBiogeoNature.pdf Microbial biogeography: putting microorganisms on the map] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100621194350/http://alrlab.pdx.edu/media/HughesBiogeoNature.pdf |date=2010-06-21 }} ''Nature: FEBRUARY 2006 | VOLUME 4''&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Climatology]] &amp;ndash; study of [[climate]], scientifically defined as weather conditions averaged over a period of [[time]].&lt;ref&gt;Climate Prediction Center. [http://www.cpc.noaa.gov/products/outreach/glossary.shtml#C Climate Glossary.] Retrieved on 2006-11-23.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Meteorology]] is the interdisciplinary scientific study of the atmosphere that focuses on weather processes and short term forecasting (in contrast with climatology).
* [[Pedology (soil study)|Pedology]] &amp;ndash; study of soils in their natural environment&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://natres.psu.ac.th/Link/SoilCongress/bdd/symp45/75-t.pdf | title = Soil Preservation and the Future of Pedology | author = Ronald Amundsen |accessdate = 2006-06-08|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt; that deals with [[pedogenesis]], [[soil morphology]], and [[soil classification]].
* [[Palaeogeography]] &amp;ndash; study of what the geography was in times past, most often concerning the physical landscape, but also the human or cultural environment.
* [[Coastal geography]] &amp;ndash; study of the dynamic interface between the ocean and the land, incorporating both the physical geography (i.e. coastal geomorphology, geology and oceanography) and the human geography (sociology and history) of the coast. It involves an understanding of coastal weathering processes, particularly wave action, sediment movement and weather, and also the ways in which humans interact with the coast.
* [[Quaternary science]] &amp;ndash; focuses on the Quaternary period, which encompasses the last 2.6 million years, including the last ice age and the Holocene period.
* [[Landscape ecology]] &amp;ndash; the relationship between spatial patterns of urban development and ecological processes on a multitude of landscape scales and organizational levels.&lt;ref&gt;Wu, J. 2006. Cross-disciplinarity, landscape ecology, and sustainability science. Landscape Ecology 21:1-4.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="wu-2007"&gt;Wu, J. and R. Hobbs (Eds). 2007. Key Topics in Landscape Ecology. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Wu, J. 2008. Landscape ecology. In: S. E. Jorgensen (ed), Encyclopedia of Ecology. Elsevier, Oxford.&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Approaches of physical geography ====

* [[Quantitative geography]] &amp;ndash; [[Quantitative research]] tools and methods applied to geography. See also the [[quantitative revolution]].
* [[Systems approach]] &amp;ndash;

=== Human geography ===

* [[Human geography]] &amp;ndash; one of the two main subfields of geography, it is the study of human use and understanding of the world and the processes which have affected it. Human geography broadly differs from physical geography in that it focuses on the [[built environment]] and how space is created, viewed, and managed by humans as well as the influence humans have on the space they occupy.&lt;ref name="AAG"&gt;{{Cite web|title=What is geography? |work=AAG Career Guide: Jobs in Geography and related Geographical Sciences |publisher=Association of American Geographers |url=http://www.aag.org/Careers/What_is_geog.html |accessdate=October 9, 2006 |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20061006152742/http://www.aag.org/Careers/What_is_geog.html &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate=October 6, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Fields of human geography ====

* [[Cultural geography]] &amp;ndash; study of cultural products and norms and their variations across and relations to spaces and places. It focuses on describing and analyzing the ways language, religion, economy, government and other cultural phenomena vary or remain constant, from one place to another and on explaining how humans function spatially.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |author1=Jordan-Bychkov, Terry G. |author2=Domosh, Mona |author3=Rowntree, Lester | title=The human mosaic: a thematic introduction to cultural geography | year=1994 | publisher=HarperCollinsCollegePublishers | location=New York  | isbn=978-0-06-500731-2 | pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Children's geographies]] &amp;ndash; study of places and spaces of children's lives, characterized experientially, politically and ethically. Children's geographies rests on the idea that children as a social group share certain characteristics which are experientially, politically and ethically significant and which are worthy of study. The pluralisation in the title is intended to imply that children's lives will be markedly different in differing times and places and in differing circumstances such as gender, family, and class. The range of focii within children's geographies include:
*** Children and the city
*** Children and the countryside
*** Children and technology
*** Children and nature,
*** Children and globalization
*** Methodologies of researching children's worlds
*** Ethics of researching children's worlds
*** [[Otherness of childhood]]
** [[Animal geographies]] &amp;ndash; studies the spaces and places occupied by animals in human culture, because social life and space is heavily populated by animals of many differing kinds and in many differing ways (e.g. farm animals, pets, wild animals in the city). Another impetus that has influenced the development of the field are ecofeminist and other environmentalist viewpoints on nature-society relations (including questions of animal welfare and rights).
** [[Language geography]] &amp;ndash; studies the geographic distribution of language or its constituent elements. There are two principal fields of study within the geography of language:
**# Geography of languages &amp;ndash; deals with the distribution through history and space of languages,&lt;ref&gt;Delgado de Carvalho, C.M. (1962). ''The geography of languages.'' In Wagner, P.L.; Mikesell, M.W. ''Readings in cultural geography.'' Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 75-93.&lt;/ref&gt;
**# [[Linguistic geography]] &amp;ndash; deals with regional linguistic variations within languages.&lt;ref&gt;Pei, M. (1966). ''Glossary of linguistic terminology.'' New York: John Wiley.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Trudgill, P. (1974). ''Linguistic change and diffusion: description and explanation in sociolinguistic dialect geography.'' Language in Society 3:2, 215-46.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Trud3&gt;Trudgill, P. (1983). ''On dialect: social and geographical perspectives.'' Oxford: Basil Blackwell; New York: New York University Press.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Trud2&gt;Trudgill, P. (1975). ''Linguistic geography and geographical linguistics.'' Progress in Geography 7, 227-52&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Dict&gt;Withers, Charles W.J. [1981] (1993). Johnson, R.J. ''The Dictionary of Human Geography'', Gregory, Derek; Smith, David M., Second edition, Oxford: Blackwell, 252-3.&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Sexuality and space]] &amp;ndash; encompasses all relationships and interactions between human sexuality, space, and place, including the geographies of LGBT residence, public sex environments, sites of queer resistance, global sexualities, sex tourism,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.ingentaconnect.com/content/routledg/rtxg/2000/00000002/00000002/art00002|title=Constructing tourism landscapes - gender, sexuality and space|first1=Annette|last1=Pritchard|first2=Nigel J.|last2=Morgan|date=1 January 2000|journal=Tourism Geographies|volume=2|issue=2|pages=115–139|doi=10.1080/14616680050027851}}&lt;/ref&gt; the geographies of prostitution and adult entertainment, use of sexualised locations in the arts,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://wings.buffalo.edu/epc/authors/howe/syllabi/sexuality.html|title=Syllabus Poetics: Sexuality and Space in 17th - 19th Century American Literature, University at Buffalo|author=|date=|website=buffalo.edu}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.allacademic.com/meta/p_mla_apa_research_citation/0/1/4/9/2/p14928_index.html?phpsessid=43bac9979986e74e34d2496c52ebac62|title=Space and Modern (Homo)sexuality in Tsai Ming Liang's Films by Lyn Van Swol|author=|date=|website=allacademic.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; and sexual citizenship.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://pages.towson.edu/dherman/sexspace/sexhome.htm|title=Sexuality and Space, Course Syllabus Towson University|author=|date=|website=towson.edu}}&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Religion geography]] &amp;ndash; study of the influence of geography, i.e. place and space, on religious belief.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Park|first=Chris|title=Routledge Companion to the Study of Religion|editor=Hinnells, J|publisher=Routledge|year=2004|chapter=Religion and geography}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Development geography]] &amp;ndash; study of the Earth's geography with reference to the standard of living and quality of life of its human inhabitants. Measures development by looking at economic, political and social factors, and seeks to understand both the geographical causes and consequences of varying development, in part by comparing More Economically Developed Countries (MEDCs) with Less Economically Developed Countries (LEDCs).
* [[Economic geography]] &amp;ndash; study of the location, distribution and spatial organization of economic activities across the world. Subjects of interest include but are not limited to the location of industries, economies of agglomeration (also known as "linkages"), transportation, international trade and development, real estate, gentrification, ethnic economies, gendered economies, core-periphery theory, the economics of urban form, the relationship between the environment and the economy (tying into a long history of geographers studying culture-environment interaction), and globalization.
** [[Marketing geography]] &amp;ndash; a discipline within marketing analysis which uses geolocation (geographic information) in the process of planning and implementation of marketing activities.&lt;ref name= "qr10"&gt;[http://www.cl.cam.ac.uk/~dq209/publications/recommending10quercia.pdf "Recommending Social Events from Mobile Phone Location Data"], Daniele Quercia, et al., ICDM 2010&lt;/ref&gt; It can be used in any aspect of the marketing mix – the product, price, promotion, or place (geo targeting).
** [[Transportation geography]] &amp;ndash; branch of economic geography that investigates spatial interactions between people, freight and information. It studies humans and their use of vehicles or other modes of traveling as well as how markets are serviced by flows of finished goods and raw materials.
* [[Health geography]] &amp;ndash; application of geographical information, perspectives, and methods to the study of health, disease, and health care, to provide a spatial understanding of a population's health, the distribution of disease in an area, and the environment's effect on health and disease. It also deals with accessibility to health care and spatial distribution of health care providers.
** [[Time geography]] &amp;ndash; study of the temporal factor on spatial human activities within the following constraints:
# Authority - limits of accessibility to certain places or domains placed on individuals by owners or authorities
# Capability - limitations on the movement of individuals, based on their nature. For example, movement is restricted by biological factors, such as the need for food, drink, and sleep
# Coupling - restraint of an individual, anchoring him or her to a location while interacting with other individuals in order to complete a task
* [[Historical geography]] &amp;ndash; study of the human, physical, fictional, theoretical, and "real" geographies of the past, and seeks to determine how cultural features of various societies across the planet emerged and evolved, by understanding how a place or region changes through time, including how people have interacted with their environment and created the cultural landscape.
* [[Political geography]] &amp;ndash; study of the spatially uneven outcomes of political processes and the ways in which political processes are themselves affected by spatial structures. Basically, the inter-relationships between people, state, and territory.
** [[Electoral geography]] &amp;ndash; study of the relationship between election results and the regions they affect (such as the environmental impact of voting decisions), and of the effects of regional factors upon voting behavior.
** [[Geopolitics]] &amp;ndash; analysis of geography, history and social science with reference to spatial politics and patterns at various scales, ranging from the level of the state to international.
** [[Strategic geography]] &amp;ndash; concerned with the control of, or access to, spatial areas that affect the security and prosperity of nations.
** [[Military geography]] &amp;ndash; the application of geographic tools, information, and techniques to solve military problems in peacetime or war.
* [[Population geography]] &amp;ndash; study of the ways in which spatial variations in the distribution, composition, migration, and growth of populations are related to the nature of places.
* [[Tourism geography]] &amp;ndash; study of travel and tourism, as an industry and as a social and cultural activity, and their effect on places, including the [[environmental impact of tourism]], the geographies of tourism and leisure economies, answering tourism industry and management concerns and the sociology of tourism and locations of tourism.
* [[Urban geography]] &amp;ndash; the study of urban areas, in terms of concentration, infrastructure, economy, and environmental impacts.

==== Approaches of human geography ====

* {{Annotated link|Behavioral geography}}
* {{Annotated link|Cognitive geography}}
* {{Annotated link|Critical geography}}
* {{Annotated link|Feminist geography}}
* {{Annotated link|Marxist geography}}
* {{Annotated link|Non-representational theory}}
* {{Annotated link|Postcolonialism}}
* {{Annotated link|Post-structuralism}}&lt;ref&gt;Harrison, Paul; 2006; "Post-structuralist Theories"; pp122-135 in Aitken, S. and Valentine, G. (eds); 2006; ''Approaches to Human Geography''; Sage, London&lt;/ref&gt; &amp;ndash;
* [[Qualitative geography]] &amp;ndash; [[qualitative research]] tools and methods applied to geography.

=== Integrated geography ===

* [[Integrated geography]] &amp;ndash; branch of geography that describes the spatial aspects of interactions between humans and the natural world. It requires an understanding of the dynamics of geology, meteorology, hydrology, biogeography, ecology, and geomorphology, as well as the ways in which human societies conceptualize the environment.

=== Geomatics ===

* [[Geomatics]] &amp;ndash; branch of geography and the discipline of gathering, storing, processing, and delivering geographic information, or spatially referenced information. It is a widespread interdisciplinary field that includes the tools and techniques used in land surveying, remote sensing, cartography, Geographic Information Systems (GIS), Global Navigation Satellite Systems, photogrammetry, and related forms of earth mapping.

==== Fields contributing to geomatics ====

* {{Annotated link|Photogrammetry}} 
* {{Annotated link|Cartography}}
* {{Annotated link|Digital terrain modelling}}
* {{Annotated link|Geodesy}}
* {{Annotated link|Geographic information system}} 
* {{Annotated link|Geospatial}}
* [[Global navigation satellite system]]s represented by {{Annotated link|Satellite navigation}} &amp;ndash; Any system that uses satellite radio signals to provide autonomous geo-spatial positioning
** {{Annotated link|Global Positioning System}}
* {{Annotated link|Hydrography}}
* {{Annotated link|Mathematics}}
* {{Annotated link|Navigation}}
* {{Annotated link|Remote sensing}} 
* {{Annotated link|Surveying}}

=== Regional geography ===

[[Regional geography]] &amp;ndash; study of world regions. Attention is paid to unique characteristics of a particular region such as its natural elements, human elements, and regionalization which covers the techniques of delineating space into regions. Regional geography breaks down into the study of specific regions.

[[Region]] &amp;ndash; an area, defined by physical characteristics, human characteristics, or functional characteristics. The term is used in various ways among the different branches of geography. A region can be seen as a collection of smaller units, such as a country and its political divisions, or as one part of a larger whole, as in a country on a continent.

==== Supercontinents ====

[[File:Pangea animation 03.gif|thumb|300px|Earth may have had a single supercontinent called "[[Pangaea]]"]]

[[List of supercontinents]]
A ''supercontinent'' is a [[landmass]] comprising more than one [[continent]]al core, or [[craton]].

*[[Afro-Eurasia]] ''(formed 5 million years ago)
*[[Americas]] ''(formed 15 million years ago)
*[[Eurasia]] ''(formed 60 million years ago)

==== Continents ====

[[Continent]] &amp;ndash; one of several large [[landmass]]es on [[Earth]]. They are generally identified by [[Convention (norm)|convention]] rather than any specific criteria, but seven areas are commonly regarded as continents. They are:

::''1.'' [[Africa]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Africa|outline]]) &amp;ndash;
::''2.'' [[Antarctica]] &amp;ndash;
::''3.'' [[Australia]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Australia|outline]]) &amp;ndash;
: The Americas:
::''4.'' [[North America]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of North America|outline]]) &amp;ndash;
::''5.'' [[South America]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of South America|outline]]) &amp;ndash;
: Eurasia:
::''6.'' [[Europe]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Europe|outline]]) &amp;ndash;
::''7.'' [[Asia]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Asia|outline]]) &amp;ndash;

===== Subregions =====

[[Subregion]] [[Subregion#Subregions by continent|(list)]]

==== Biogeographic regions ====

[[File:Ecozones.png|thumb|300px|right|Map of six of the world's eight ecozones
{{legend|#8000ff|[[Nearctic]]}}
{{legend|#008000|[[Palearctic]]}}
{{legend|#ff8040|[[Afrotropic]]}}
{{legend|#ff0000|[[Indomalaya]]}}
{{legend|#808000|[[Australasia ecozone|Australasia]]}}
{{legend|#bb825b|[[Neotropic]]}}
{{legend|#f9f9f9|[[Oceania ecozone|Oceania]] and [[Antarctic ecozone|Antarctic]] ecozones not shown}}]]

===== Ecozone =====

[[Ecozone]]
The [[World Wildlife Fund]] (WWF) developed a system of eight biogeographic realms (ecozones):
* [[Nearctic]] 22.9 mil. km² (including most of [[North America]])
* [[Palearctic]] 54.1 mil. km² (including the bulk of [[Eurasia]] and [[North Africa]])
* [[Afrotropic]] 22.1 mil. km² (including [[Sub-Saharan Africa]])
* [[Indomalaya]] 7.5 mil. km² (including the [[Indian subcontinent|South Asian subcontinent]] and [[Southeast Asia]])
* [[Australasia ecozone|Australasia]] 7.7 mil. km² (including [[Australia]], [[New Guinea]], and neighboring islands). The northern boundary of this zone is known as the [[Wallace line]].
* [[Neotropic]] 19.0 mil. km² (including [[South America]] and the [[Caribbean]])
* [[Oceania ecozone|Oceania]] 1.0 mil. km² (including [[Polynesia]], [[Fiji]] and [[Micronesia]])
* [[Antarctic ecozone|Antarctic]] 0.3 mil. km² (including [[Antarctica]]).

===== Ecoregions =====

[[Ecoregion]]
Ecozones are further divided into ecoregions. The World has over 800 [[terrestrial ecoregion]]s. ''See [[Lists of ecoregions by country]].''

==== Geography of the political divisions of the World ====
{| style="margin-left:2em; padding:0px;"
{{col-begin}}
{{col-2}}
* [[Geography of Africa]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Africa|Outline]])
** [[West Africa#Geography and climate]] &lt;!--[[File:LocationWesternAfrica.png|40px|Outline]])--&gt;
*** [[Geography of Benin]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Benin|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Burkina Faso]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Burkina Faso|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Cape Verde]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Cape Verde|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Côte d'Ivoire]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Côte d'Ivoire|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Gambia]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of the Gambia|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Ghana]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Ghana|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Guinea]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Guinea|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Guinea-Bissau]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Guinea-Bissau|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Liberia]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Liberia|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Mali]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Mali|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Mauritania]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Mauritania|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Niger]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Niger|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Nigeria]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Nigeria|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Senegal]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Senegal|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Sierra Leone]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Sierra Leone|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Togo]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Togo|Outline]])
** [[North Africa#Geography]] &lt;!--[[File:LocationNorthernAfrica.png|40px|Outline]])--&gt;
*** [[Geography of Algeria]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Algeria|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Egypt]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Egypt|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Libya]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Libya|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Mauritania]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Mauritania|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Morocco]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Morocco|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Sudan]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Sudan|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Tunisia]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Tunisia|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Western Sahara]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Western Sahara|Outline]])
** [[Central Africa]] &lt;!--[[File:LocationCentralMiddleAfrica.png|40px|Outline]])--&gt;
*** [[Geography of Angola]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Angola|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Burundi]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Burundi|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Cameroon]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Cameroon|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Central African Republic]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of the Central African Republic|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Chad]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Chad|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Democratic Republic of the Congo]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of the Democratic Republic of the Congo|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Equatorial Guinea]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Equatorial Guinea|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Gabon]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Gabon|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Republic of the Congo]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of the Republic of the Congo|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Rwanda]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Rwanda|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of São Tomé and Príncipe]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of São Tomé and Príncipe|Outline]])
** [[East Africa#Geography and climate]] &lt;!--[[File:LocationEasternAfrica.png|40px|Outline]])--&gt;
*** [[Geography of Burundi]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Burundi|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Comoros]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Comoros|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Djibouti]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Djibouti|Outline]])
**** [[Geography of Eritrea]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Eritrea|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Ethiopia]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Ethiopia|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Kenya]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Kenya|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Madagascar]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Madagascar|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Malawi]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Malawi|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Mauritius]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Mauritius|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Mozambique]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Mozambique|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Rwanda]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Rwanda|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Seychelles]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Seychelles|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Somalia]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Somalia|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Tanzania]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Tanzania|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Uganda]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Uganda|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Zambia]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Zambia|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Zimbabwe]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Zimbabwe|Outline]])
** [[Southern Africa#Geography]] &lt;!--[[File:LocationSouthernAfrica.png|40px|Outline]])--&gt;
*** [[Geography of Botswana]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Botswana|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Lesotho]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Lesotho|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Namibia]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Namibia|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of South Africa]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of South Africa|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Swaziland]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Swaziland|Outline]])
** Dependencies in Africa
*** [[Geography of British Indian Ocean Territory]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of the British Indian Ocean Territory|Outline]])&amp;nbsp;&lt;small&gt;(UK)&lt;/small&gt;
*** [[Geography of Mayotte]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Mayotte|Outline]])&amp;nbsp;&lt;small&gt;(France)&lt;/small&gt;
*** [[Geography of Réunion]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Réunion|Outline]])&amp;nbsp;&lt;small&gt;(France)&lt;/small&gt;
*** [[Geography of Saint Helena]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of St.&amp;nbsp;Helena|Outline]])&amp;nbsp;&lt;small&gt;(UK)&lt;/small&gt;
*** [[Canary Islands#Geography]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of the Canary Islands|Outline]])&amp;nbsp;&lt;small&gt;(Spain)&lt;/small&gt;
*** [[Geography of Ceuta]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Ceuta|Outline]])&amp;nbsp;&lt;small&gt;(Spain)&lt;/small&gt;
*** [[Geography of Madeira]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Madeira|Outline]])&amp;nbsp;&lt;small&gt;(Portugal)&lt;/small&gt;
*** [[Geography of Melilla]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Melilla|Outline]])&amp;nbsp;&lt;small&gt;(Spain)&lt;/small&gt;
*** [[Geography of Socotra]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Socotra|Outline]])&amp;nbsp;&lt;small&gt;(Yemen)&lt;/small&gt;
*** [[Geography of Puntland]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Puntland|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Somaliland]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Somaliland|Outline]])
*** [[Sahrawi Arab Democratic Republic]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of the Sahrawi&amp;nbsp;Arab&amp;nbsp;Democratic&amp;nbsp;Republic|Outline]])
* [[Geography of Antarctica]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Antarctica|Outline]])
* [[Geography of Asia]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Asia|Outline]])
** [[Central Asia#Geography]]
*** [[Geography of Kazakhstan]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Kazakhstan|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Kyrgyzstan]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Kyrgyzstan|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Tajikistan]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Tajikistan|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Turkmenistan]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Turkmenistan|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Uzbekistan]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Uzbekistan|Outline]])
** [[East Asia]]
*** [[Geography of China]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of China|Outline]])
**** [[Geography of Tibet]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Tibet|Outline]])
**** [[Geography of Hong Kong]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Hong Kong|Outline]])
**** [[Geography of Macau]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Macau|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Japan]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Japan|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of North Korea]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of North Korea|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of South Korea]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of South Korea|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Mongolia]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Mongolia|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Taiwan]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Taiwan|Outline]])
** [[North Asia#Geography]]
*** [[Geography of Russia]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Russia|Outline]])
** [[Southeast Asia#Geography]]
*** [[Geography of Brunei]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Brunei|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Burma|Burma (Myanmar)]] - [[Outline of Burma|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Cambodia]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Cambodia|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of East Timor|East Timor (Timor-Leste)]] - [[Outline of East Timor|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Indonesia]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Indonesia|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Laos]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Laos|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Malaysia]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Malaysia|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of the Philippines]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of the Philippines|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Singapore]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Singapore|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Thailand]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Thailand|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Vietnam]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Vietnam|Outline]])
** [[South Asia#Geography]]
*** [[Geography of Afghanistan]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Afghanistan|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Bangladesh]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Bangladesh|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Bhutan]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Bhutan|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of India]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of India|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Maldives]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Maldives|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Nepal]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Nepal|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Pakistan]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Pakistan|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Sri Lanka]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Sri Lanka|Outline]])
** [[Western Asia#Geography]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/wfbExt/region_mde.html|title=West Asia/Middle East|accessdate=6 May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*** [[Armenia#Geography]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Armenia|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Azerbaijan]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Azerbaijan|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Bahrain]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Bahrain|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Cyprus]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Cyprus|Outline]]), including:
**** [[Geography of Northern Cyprus]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Northern Cyprus|Outline]]) (disputed territory)
*** [[Geography of Georgia (country)|Georgia]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Georgia (country)|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Iran]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Iran|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Iraq]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Iraq|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Israel]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Israel|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Jordan]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Jordan|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Kuwait]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Kuwait|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Lebanon]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Lebanon|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Oman]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Oman|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of the Palestinian territories]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of the Palestinian territories|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Qatar]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Qatar|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Saudi Arabia]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Saudi Arabia|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Syria]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Syria|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Turkey]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Turkey|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of United Arab Emirates]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of the United Arab Emirates|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Yemen]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Yemen|Outline]])
* [[Caucasus#Geography and ecology]] (a region considered to be in both Asia and Europe, or between them)
** [[North Caucasus]]
*** [[Geography of Russia]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Russia|Outline]]) (the following parts of Russia are in the North Caucasus: Chechnya, Ingushetia, Dagestan, Adyghea, Kabardino-Balkaria, Karachay–Cherkessia, North Ossetia, Krasnodar Krai, Stavropol Krai)
** [[South Caucasus]]
*** [[Geography of Georgia (country)|Georgia]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Georgia (country)|Outline]]), including:
**** [[Geography of Abkhazia]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Abhkazia|Outline]]) (disputed territory)
**** [[Geography of South Ossetia]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of South Ossetia|Outline]]) (disputed territory)
*** [[Armenia#Geography]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Armenia|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Azerbaijan]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Azerbaijan|Outline]]), including:
**** [[Geography of Nagorno-Karabakh]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Nagorno-Karabakh|Outline]]) (disputed territory)
* [[Geography of Europe]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Europe|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Akrotiri and Dhekelia]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Akrotiri and Dhekelia|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Åland]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Åland|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Albania]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Albania|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Andorra]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Andorra|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Armenia]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Armenia|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Austria]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Austria|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Azerbaijan]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Azerbaijan|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Belarus]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Belarus|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Belgium]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Belgium|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Bosnia and Herzegovina]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Bosnia and Herzegovina|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Bulgaria]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Bulgaria|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Croatia]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Croatia|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Cyprus]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Cyprus|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Czech Republic]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of the Czech Republic|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Denmark]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Denmark|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Estonia]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Estonia|Outline]])
** [[Faroe Islands#Geography]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of the Faroe Islands|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Finland]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Finland|Outline]])
** [[Geography of France]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of France|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Georgia (country)|Geography of Georgia]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Georgia (country)|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Germany]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Germany|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Gibraltar]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Gibraltar|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Greece]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Greece|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Guernsey]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Guernsey|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Hungary]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Hungary|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Iceland]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Iceland|Outline]])
** [[Republic of Ireland#Geography]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of the Republic of Ireland|Outline]])
** [[Geography of the Isle of Man]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of the Isle of Man|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Italy]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Italy|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Jersey]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Jersey|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Kazakhstan]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Kazakhstan|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Kosovo]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Kosovo|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Latvia]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Latvia|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Liechtenstein]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Liechtenstein|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Lithuania]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Lithuania|Outline]])
{{col-2}}
** [[Geography of Luxembourg]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Luxembourg|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Macedonia]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Macedonia|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Malta]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Malta|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Moldova]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Moldova|Outline]]), including:
*** [[Geography of Transnistria]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Transnistria|Outline]]) (disputed territory)
** [[Geography of Monaco]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Monaco|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Montenegro]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Montenegro|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Netherlands]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of the Netherlands|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Norway]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Norway|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Poland]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Poland|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Portugal]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Portugal|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Romania]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Romania|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Russia]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Russia|Outline]])
** [[Geography of San Marino]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of San Marino|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Serbia]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Serbia|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Slovakia]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Slovakia|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Slovenia]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Slovenia|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Spain]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Spain|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Svalbard]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Svalbard|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Sweden]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Sweden|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Switzerland]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Switzerland|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Turkey]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Turkey|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Ukraine]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Ukraine|Outline]])
** [[Geography of United Kingdom]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of the United Kingdom|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of England]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of England|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Northern Ireland]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Northern Ireland|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Scotland]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Scotland|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Wales]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Wales|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Vatican City]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Vatican City|Outline]])
* [[Geography of North America]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of North America|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Canada]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Canada|Outline]])
*** By province
**** [[Geography of Alberta]]
**** [[Geography of British Columbia]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of British Columbia|Outline]])
**** [[Geography of Manitoba]]
**** [[Geography of New Brunswick]]
**** [[Geography of Newfoundland and Labrador]]
**** [[Geography of Nova Scotia]]
**** [[Geography of Ontario]]
**** [[Geography of Prince Edward Island]]
**** [[Geography of Quebec]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Quebec|Outline]])
**** [[Geography of Saskatchewan]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Saskatchewan|Outline]])
*** By territory
**** [[Geography of the Northwest Territories]]
**** [[Geography of Nunavut]]
**** [[Geography of Yukon]]
** [[Geography of Greenland]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Greenland|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Mexico]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Mexico|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Saint Pierre and Miquelon]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Saint Pierre and Miquelon|Outline]])
** [[Geography of United States]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of the United States|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Alabama]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Alabama|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Alaska]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Alaska|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Arizona]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Arizona|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Arkansas]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Arkansas|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of California]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of California|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Colorado]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Colorado|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Connecticut]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Connecticut|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Delaware]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Delaware|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Florida]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Florida|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Georgia (U.S. state)|Geography of Georgia]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Georgia (U.S. state)|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Hawaii]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Hawaii|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Idaho]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Idaho|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Illinois]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Illinois|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Indiana]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Indiana|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Iowa]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Iowa|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Montana]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Montana|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Kansas]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Kansas|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Kentucky]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Kentucky|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Louisiana]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Louisiana|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Maine]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Maine|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Maryland]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Maryland|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Massachusetts]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Massachusetts|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Michigan]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Michigan|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Minnesota]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Minnesota|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Mississippi]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Mississippi|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Missouri]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Missouri|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Nebraska]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Nebraska|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Nevada]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Nevada|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of New Hampshire]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of New Hampshire|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of New Jersey]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of New Jersey|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of New Mexico]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of New Mexico|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of New York]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of New York|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of North Carolina]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of North Carolina|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of North Dakota]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of North Dakota|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Ohio]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Ohio|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Oklahoma]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Oklahoma|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Oregon]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Oregon|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Pennsylvania]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Pennsylvania|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Rhode Island]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Rhode Island|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of South Carolina]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of South Carolina|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of South Dakota]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of South Dakota|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Tennessee]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Tennessee|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Texas]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Texas|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Utah]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Utah|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Vermont]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Vermont|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Virginia]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Virginia|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Washington]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Washington|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of West Virginia]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of West Virginia|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Wisconsin]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Wisconsin|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Wyoming]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Wyoming|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Washington, D.C.]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of the District of Columbia|Outline]]) (Washington, D.C.)
** [[Central America#Geography]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Central America|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Belize]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Belize|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Costa Rica]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Costa Rica|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of El Salvador]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of El Salvador|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Guatemala]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Guatemala|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Honduras]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Honduras|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Nicaragua]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Nicaragua|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Panama]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Panama|Outline]])
** [[Geography of the Caribbean]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of the Caribbean|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Anguilla]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Anguilla|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Antigua and Barbuda]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Antigua and Barbuda|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Aruba]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Aruba|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Bahamas]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of the Bahamas|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Barbados]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Barbados|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Bermuda]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Bermuda|Outline]])
*** [[British Virgin Islands#Geography]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of the British Virgin Islands|Outline]])
*** [[Cayman Islands#Geography]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of the Cayman Islands|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Cuba]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Cuba|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Dominica]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Dominica|Outline]])
*** [[Dominican Republic#Geography]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of the Dominican Republic|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Grenada]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Grenada|Outline]]) &lt;!--
*** [[Geography of Guadeloupe]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Guadeloupe|Outline]]) --&gt;
*** [[Geography of Haiti]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Haiti|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Jamaica]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Jamaica|Outline]]) &lt;!--
*** [[Geography of Martinique]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Martinique|Outline]]) --&gt;
*** [[Geography of Montserrat]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Montserrat|Outline]]) &lt;!--
*** [[Geography of Navassa Island]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Navassa Island|Outline]]) --&gt;
*** [[Netherlands Antilles#Geography]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of the Netherlands Antilles|Outline]]) &lt;!--
*** [[Geography of Petrel Islands]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of the Petrel Islands|Outline]]) --&gt;
*** [[Geography of Puerto Rico]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Puerto Rico|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Saint Barthélemy]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Saint Barthélemy|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Saint Kitts and Nevis]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Saint Kitts and Nevis|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Saint Lucia]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Saint Lucia|Outline]]) &lt;!--
*** [[Geography of Serranilla Bank]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Serranilla Bank|Outline]]) --&gt;
*** [[Saint Martin#Geography]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Saint Martin|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Saint Vincent and the Grenadines]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Saint Vincent and the Grenadines|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Trinidad and Tobago]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Trinidad and Tobago|Outline]]) &lt;!--
*** [[Geography of Trinidad]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Trinidad|Outline]]) --&gt;
*** [[Turks and Caicos Islands#Geography]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of the Turks and Caicos Islands|Outline]])
*** [[United States Virgin Islands#Geography]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of the United States Virgin Islands|Outline]])
* [[Geography of Oceania]] (includes the continent of Australia)
** [[Australasia]]
*** [[Geography of Australia]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Australia|Outline]])
**** Dependencies and territories of Australia
***** [[Geography of Christmas Island]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Christmas Island|Outline]])
***** [[Cocos (Keeling) Islands#Geography]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of the Cocos (Keeling) Islands|Outline]])
***** [[Geography of Norfolk Island]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Norfolk Island|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of New Zealand]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of New Zealand|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Melanesia]]
*** [[Geography of Fiji]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Fiji|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Indonesia]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Indonesia|Outline]]) (Oceanian part only)
*** [[Geography of New Caledonia]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of New Caledonia|Outline]]) (France)
*** [[Geography of Papua New Guinea]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Papua New Guinea|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of the Solomon Islands]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of the Solomon Islands|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Vanuatu]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Vanuatu|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Micronesia]]
*** [[Geography of Federated States of Micronesia]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of the Federated States of Micronesia|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Guam]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Guam|Outline]]) (USA)
*** [[Geography of Kiribati]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Kiribati|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Marshall Islands]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of the Marshall Islands|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Nauru]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Nauru|Outline]])
*** [[Northern Mariana Islands#Geography and climate]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of the Northern Mariana Islands|Outline]]) (USA)
*** [[Geography of Palau]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Palau|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Wake Island]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Wake Island|Outline]]) (USA)
** [[Geography of Polynesia]]
*** [[Geography of American Samoa]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of American Samoa|Outline]]) (USA)
*** [[Chatham Islands#Geography]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of the Chatham Islands|Outline]]) (NZ)
*** [[Cook Islands#Geography]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of the Cook Islands|Outline]]) (NZ)
*** [[Easter Island#Location and physical geography]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Easter Island|Outline]]) (Chile)
*** [[Geography of French Polynesia]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of French Polynesia|Outline]]) (France)
*** [[Geography of Hawaii]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Hawaii|Outline]]) (USA)
*** [[Loyalty Islands#Geography]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of the Loyalty Islands|Outline]]) (France)
*** [[Geography of Niue]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Niue|Outline]]) (NZ)
*** [[Pitcairn Islands#Geography]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of the Pitcairn Islands|Outline]]) (UK)
*** [[Geography of Samoa]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Samoa|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Tokelau]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Tokelau|Outline]]) (NZ)
*** [[Geography of Tonga]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Tonga|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Tuvalu]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Tuvalu|Outline]])
*** [[Geography of Wallis and Futuna]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Wallis and Futuna|Outline]]) (France)
* [[Geography of South America]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of South America|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Argentina]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Argentina|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Bolivia]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Bolivia|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Brazil]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Brazil|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Chile]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Chile|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Colombia]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Colombia|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Ecuador]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Ecuador|Outline]])
** [[Geography of the Falkland Islands]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of the Falkland Islands|Outline]])
** [[Geography of French Guiana]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of French Guiana|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Guyana]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Guyana|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Paraguay]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Paraguay|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Peru]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Peru|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Suriname]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Suriname|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Uruguay]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Uruguay|Outline]])
** [[Geography of Venezuela]] &amp;nbsp; ([[Outline of Venezuela|Outline]])
{{col-end}}
|}

==== Other regions ====
* [[Atlantic World]]
* [[Bermuda Triangle]]
* [[Pacific Rim]]
* [[Pacific Ring of Fire]]

== History of geography ==
[[File:Hecataeus world map-en.svg|thumb|right|300px|Reconstruction of Hecataeus' map of the World, created during [[Ancient Greece|ancient Greek times]]]]
{{main article|History of geography|Historical geography}}

Topics pertaining to the geographical study of the World throughout history''':

=== By period ===
* [[Ancient roads]]
* [[Ancient Greek geography]]
* [[Age of discovery]]
* [[Major explorations after the Age of Discovery]]
* [[Critical geography]]
* [[Environmental determinism]]

=== By region ===
* {{annotated link|Chinese geography}}
** {{annotated link|History of human geography in China}}

=== By subject ===
* [[Historical demography#Historical population of the world|Historical population of the world]]

==== By field ====
* History of human geography
** {{annotated link|History of cartography}}
*** {{annotated link|History of longitude}}
**** {{annotated link|Longitude Prize}}
&lt;!--** [[Behavioral geography#History|History of behavioral geography]]--&gt;
** [[Cultural geography#History|History of cultural geography]]
** [[Economic geography#History of economic geography|History of economic geography]]
&lt;!--** [[Environmental geography#History|History of environmental geography]]
** [[Feminist geography#History|History of feminist geography]]
** [[Development geography#History|History of development geography]]--&gt;
** [[Health geography#History of health geography|History of health geography]]
&lt;!--** [[Military geography#History|History of military geography]]--&gt;
** [[Political geography#History|History of political geography]]
&lt;!--** [[Population geography#History|History of population geography]]--&gt;
*** [[Demography#History|History of demography]]
&lt;!--** [[Social geography#History|History of social geography]]
** [[Strategic geography#History|History of strategic geography]]
** [[Transportation geography#History|History of transportation geography]]
** [[Time geography#History|History of time geography]]
** [[Tourism geography#History|History of tourism geography]]
** [[Urban geography#History|History of urban geography]]--&gt;
* History of physical geography
** [[Biogeography#History|History of biogeography]]
** [[Climatology#History|History of climatology]]
** [[Meteorology#History|History of meteorology]]
&lt;!--** [[Coastal geography#History|History of coastal geography]]
** [[Environmental geography#History|History of environmental geography]]--&gt;
** {{annotated link|History of geodesy}}
** [[Geomorphology#History|History of geomorphology]]
** [[Hydrology#History|History of hydrology]]
&lt;!--*** [[Glaciology#History|History of glaciology]]--&gt;
*** [[Oceanography#History|History of oceanography]]
&lt;!--*** [[Limnology#History|History of limnology]]--&gt;
** [[Landscape ecology#History|History of landscape ecology]]
&lt;!--** [[Palaeogeography#History|History of palaeogeography]]
** [[Pedology (soil study)#History|History of pedology]]--&gt;
&lt;!--** [[Ethnography#History|History of ethnography]]
** [[Geoarchaeology#History|History of geoarchaeology]]
** [[Geographic information science#History|History of geographic information science]]
** [[Geostatistics#History|History of geostatistics]]--&gt;
&lt;!--** [[Philosophy of geography#History|History of the philosophy of geography]]--&gt;
* [[Regional geography#History|History of regional geography]]

== Elements of geography ==
Topics common to the various branches of geography include:

=== Tasks and tools of geography ===
[[File:Mollweide-projection.jpg|thumb|300px| The equal-area [[Mollweide projection]]]]
{{main article|Geosophy|Philosophy of geography}}

* {{annotated link|Exploration}}
* {{annotated link|Geocoding|Geocode|aka=Geospatial Entity Object Code}}
* {{annotated link|Geographic information system|abbreviation=GIS}}
* {{annotated link|Globe}}
* {{annotated link|Map}}
** {{annotated link|Atlas}}
** {{annotated link|Cartography}}
*** {{annotated link|Outline of cartography}}
** {{annotated link|Map projection}}
* {{annotated link|Demographics}}
* {{annotated link|Spatial analysis}}
* {{annotated link|Surveying}}

=== Types of geographic features ===

[[Geographic feature]] &amp;ndash; component of a planet that can be referred to as a location, place, site, area, or region, and therefore may show up on a map. A geographic feature may be natural or artificial.

====Location and place====
[[File:Countries by Population Density in 2015.svg|300px|thumb|Population density per square [[kilometre]] by country, 2006]]

* [[Location (geography)|Location]] &amp;ndash;
** {{Annotated link|Absolute location}}
*** {{Annotated link|Latitude}}
**** {{Annotated link|Prime meridian}}
*** {{Annotated link|Longitude}}
**** {{Annotated link|Equator}}
**** {{Annotated link|Tropic of Cancer}}
**** {{Annotated link|Tropic of Capricorn}}
**** {{Annotated link|Arctic Circle}}
**** {{Annotated link|Antarctic Circle}}
**** {{Annotated link|North Pole}}
**** {{Annotated link|South Pole}}
*** {{Annotated link|Altitude}}
**** {{Annotated link|Elevation}}
* Place
** Aspects of a place or region
*** {{Annotated link|Climate}}
*** {{Annotated link|Population}}
**** {{Annotated link|Demographics}}
***** {{Annotated link|Population density}}
**** {{Annotated link|Human overpopulation}}
**** {{Annotated link|World population}}
*** {{Annotated link|Sense of place}}
*** {{Annotated link|Terrain}}
*** {{Annotated link|Topography}}
*** {{Annotated link|Tourist attraction}}
** {{Annotated link|Lists of places}}

==== Natural geographic features ====

Natural geographic feature &amp;ndash; an ecosystem or natural landform.

===== Ecosystems =====

[[Ecosystem]] &amp;ndash; community of living organisms in conjunction with the nonliving components of their environment (things like air, water and mineral soil), interacting as a system. These biotic and abiotic components are regarded as linked together through nutrient cycles and energy flows. 
* {{Annotated link|Biodiversity hotspot}}
* [[Ecozone]] &amp;ndash; broadest biogeographic division of the Earth's land surface, based on distributional patterns of terrestrial organisms. 
** [[Ecoprovince]] &amp;ndash; biogeographic unit smaller than an ecozone that contains one or more ecoregions.
*** {{Annotated link|Ecoregion}}
**** {{Annotated link|Ecodistrict}}
**** {{Annotated link|Ecosection}}
***** {{Annotated link|Ecosite}}
****** {{Annotated link|Ecotope}}
******* {{Annotated link|Ecoelement}}
* {{Annotated link|Biome}}
** {{Annotated link|Bioregion}}
*** {{Annotated link|Biotope}}
**** {{Annotated link|Bioelement}}

===== Natural landforms =====
[[File:Ganges River Delta, Bangladesh, India.jpg|right|200px|thumb|The [[Ganges]] ''[[river delta]]'' in
[[India]] and [[Bangladesh]] is one of the most fertile regions in the world.]]
[[File:MSH82 st helens plume from harrys ridge 05-19-82.jpg|right|thumb|300px|The ''[[volcano]]'' [[Mount St. Helens]] in [[Washington (state)|Washington]], United States.]]
{{See also|List of landforms}}

[[Landform|Natural landform]] &amp;ndash; terrain or body of water. Landforms are topographical elements, and are defined by their surface form and location in the landscape. Landforms are categorized by traits such as elevation, slope, orientation, [[stratum|stratification]], rock exposure, and soil type. Some landforms are artificial, such as certain islands, but most landforms are natural.

==== Natural terrain feature types ====
* {{Annotated link|Continent}}
* {{Annotated link|Island}}
* {{Annotated link|Mainland}}
* {{Annotated link|Mountain}}
* {{Annotated link|Mountain range}}
* {{Annotated link|Subcontinent}}

==== Natural body of water types ====
* Natural {{Annotated link|body of water|bodies of water}}
** Bodies of {{Annotated link|seawater}}
*** {{Annotated link|Channel (geography)|Channel}}
*** {{Annotated link|Firth}}
*** {{Annotated link|Harbor}}
*** {{Annotated link|Inlet}}
**** {{Annotated link|Headlands and bays|Bay}}
***** {{Annotated link|Bight (geography)|Bight}}
***** {{Annotated link|Headlands and bays|Gulf}}
**** {{Annotated link|Cove}}
**** {{Annotated link|Creek (tidal)}}
**** {{Annotated link|Estuary}}
**** {{Annotated link|Fjord|alt=fiord}}  
*** {{Annotated link|Kettle (landform)|Kettle}}
*** {{Annotated link|Kill (body of water)|Kill}}
*** {{Annotated link|Lagoon}}
**** {{Annotated link|Barachois}}
*** {{Annotated link|Loch}}
**** Arm of the sea &amp;ndash;
**** {{Annotated link|Mere (lake)|Mere}}
*** {{Annotated link|Ocean}}
*** {{Annotated link|Phytotelma}}
*** {{Annotated link|Salt marsh}}
*** {{Annotated link|Sea}}
**** Types of sea:
***** {{Annotated link|Mediterranean sea (oceanography)|Mediterranean sea}}
***** {{Annotated link|Sound (geography)|Sound}}
**** Sea components or extensions:
***** {{Annotated link|Sea loch}}
***** {{Annotated link|Sea lough}}
*** {{Annotated link|Strait}}
** Bodies of fresh water
*** {{Annotated link|Bayou}}
*** {{Annotated link|Lake}}
**** {{Annotated link|Lists of lakes}}
**** {{Annotated link|Oxbow lake}}
**** {{Annotated link|Subglacial lake}}
**** {{Annotated link|Tarn (lake)|Tarn}}
*** {{Annotated link|Stream pool|Pool}}
**** {{Annotated link|Pond}}
***** {{Annotated link|Billabong}}
**** {{Annotated link|Tide pool}}
**** {{Annotated link|Vernal pool}}
**** {{Annotated link|Puddle}}
*** {{Annotated link|River}} 
**** {{Annotated link|Lists of rivers}}
***** Parts of a river:
***** {{Annotated link|Rapid}}
***** {{Annotated link|Source (river or stream)|Source}}
***** {{Annotated link|Waterfall}}
****** {{Annotated link|List of waterfalls}}
*** {{Annotated link|Roadstead}}
*** {{Annotated link|Spring (hydrosphere)|Spring}}
**** Boil -
*** {{Annotated link|Stream}}
**** {{Annotated link|stream|Beck}}
**** {{Annotated link|stream|Brook}}
**** {{Annotated link|Burn (stream)|Burn}}
**** {{Annotated link|stream|Creek}}
***** {{Annotated link|Arroyo (creek)}}
****** {{Annotated link|Arroyo (creek)|Wash}}
****** {{Annotated link|Arroyo (creek)|Draw}}
**** {{Annotated link|Stream|Run}}
*** {{Annotated link|Wetland}}
**** Freshwater {{Annotated link|marsh}}
**** {{Annotated link|Swamp|Slough (wetland)}}
***** {{Annotated link|Mangrove|Mangrove swamp}}

==== Artificial geographic features ====
Artificial geographic feature &amp;ndash; a thing that was made by humans that may be indicated on a map. It may be physical and exist in the real world (like a bridge or city), or it may be abstract and exist only on maps (such as the Equator, which has a defined location, but cannot be seen where it lies).

* {{annotated link|Human settlement|Settlement}}
** {{annotated link|Hamlet (place)}} &amp;ndash; rural settlement which is too small to be considered a village. Historically, when a hamlet became large enough to justify building a church, it was then classified as a village. One example of a hamlet is a small cluster of houses surrounding a mill.
** {{annotated link|Village}} &amp;ndash; clustered human settlement or community, larger than a hamlet with the population ranging from a few hundred to a few thousand (sometimes tens of thousands).
** {{annotated link|Town}} &amp;ndash; human settlement larger than a village but smaller than a city. The size a settlement must be in order to be called a "town" varies considerably in different parts of the world, so that, for example, many American "small towns" seem to British people to be no more than villages, while many British "small towns" would qualify as cities in the United States.
*** {{annotated link|Urban hierarchy}} &amp;ndash; ranks the structure of towns within an area.
**** {{annotated link|1st-order towns}} &amp;ndash; bare minimum of essential services, such as bread and milk.
**** {{annotated link|2nd-order towns}}
**** {{annotated link|3rd-order towns}}
**** {{annotated link|4th-order towns}}
** {{annotated link|City}} &amp;ndash; relatively large and permanent settlement. In many regions, a city is distinguished from a town by attainment of designation according to law, for instance being required to obtain articles of incorporation or a royal charter.
*** {{annotated link|Financial centre}}
*** {{annotated link|Primate city}} &amp;ndash; the leading city in its country or region, disproportionately larger than any others in the urban hierarchy.
*** {{annotated link|Metropolis}} &amp;ndash; very large city or urban area which is a significant economic, political and cultural center for a country or region, and an important hub for regional or international connections and communications.
*** {{annotated link|Metropolitan area}} &amp;ndash; region consisting of a densely populated urban core and its less-populated surrounding territories, sharing industry, infrastructure, and housing.&lt;ref&gt;Squires, G. Ed. Urban Sprawl: Causes, Consequences, &amp; Policy Responses. The Urban Institute Press (2002)&lt;/ref&gt;
*** {{annotated link|Global city}} &amp;ndash; city that is deemed to be an important node in the global economic system. Globalization is largely created, facilitated and enacted in strategic geographic locales (including global cities) according to a hierarchy of importance to the operation of the global system of finance and trade.
*** {{annotated link|Megalopolis (city type)|Megalopolis}} &amp;ndash; chain of roughly adjacent metropolitan areas. An example is the huge metropolitan area along the eastern seaboard of the U.S. extending from Boston, Massachusetts through New York City; Philadelphia, Pennsylvania; Baltimore, Maryland and ending in Washington, D.C..
*** {{annotated link|Eperopolis}} &amp;ndash; theoretical "continent city". The world does not have one yet. Will Europe become the first one?
*** {{annotated link|Ecumenopolis}} &amp;ndash; theoretical "world city". Will the world ever become so urbanized as to be called this?
* Engineered construct &amp;ndash; built feature of the landscape such as a [[highway]], [[bridge]], [[airport]], [[railroad]], [[building]], [[dam]], or [[reservoir (water)|reservoir]]. See also [[construction engineering]] and [[infrastructure]].
** Artificial landforms
*** {{annotated link|Artificial dwelling hill}}
*** {{annotated link|Artificial island}}
*** {{annotated link|Artificial reef}}
** {{annotated link|Airport}} &amp;ndash; place where airplanes can take off and land, including one or more runways and one or more passenger terminals.
** {{annotated link|Aqueduct (watercourse)|Aqueduct}} &amp;ndash; artificial channel that is constructed to convey water from one location to another.
** {{annotated link|Breakwater (structure)|Breakwater}} &amp;ndash; construction designed to break the force of the sea to provide calm water for boats or ships, or to prevent erosion of a coastal feature.
** {{annotated link|Bridge}} &amp;ndash; structure built to span a valley, road, body of water, or other physical obstacle such as a canyon, for the purpose of providing passage over the obstacle.
** {{annotated link|Building}} &amp;ndash; closed structure with walls and a roof.
** {{annotated link|Canal}} &amp;ndash; artificial waterway, often connecting one body of water with another.
** {{annotated link|Causeway}}
** {{annotated link|Dam}} &amp;ndash; structure placed across a flowing body of water to stop the flow, usually to use the water for irrigation or to generate electricity.
*** {{annotated link|Dike (construction)|Dike}} &amp;ndash; barrier of stone or earth used to hold back water and prevent flooding.
**** {{annotated link|Levee}} &amp;ndash; artificial slope or wall to regulate water levels, usually [[Soil|earthen]] and often [[Parallel (geometry)|parallel]] to the course of a [[river]] or the coast.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | title=Levees and Other Raised Ground | author=Henry Petroski | publisher=American Scientist | year=2006 | volume=94 | issue=1 | pages=7–11}}&lt;/ref&gt;
** {{annotated link|Farm}} &amp;ndash; place where agricultural activities take place, especially the growing of crops or the raising of livestock.
** {{annotated link|Harbor|Manmade harbor}} &amp;ndash; harbor that has deliberately constructed breakwaters, sea walls, or jettys, or which was constructed by dredging.
** {{annotated link|Industrial region}}
** {{annotated link|Marina}}
** {{annotated link|Orchard}}
** {{annotated link|Parking lot}}
** {{annotated link|Pier}}
** {{annotated link|Pipeline transport|Pipeline}}
** {{annotated link|Port}}
** {{annotated link|Railway}}
** {{annotated link|Ranch}}
** {{annotated link|Reservoir (water)|Reservoir}}
** {{annotated link|Road}}
*** {{annotated link|Highway}}
*** {{annotated link|Race track}}
*** {{annotated link|Street}}
** {{annotated link|Subsidence crater}}
** {{annotated link|Ski resort}}
** {{annotated link|Train station}}
** {{annotated link|Tree farm}}
** {{annotated link|Tunnel}}
** {{annotated link|Viaduct}}
** {{annotated link|Wharf}}
&lt;!-- Not sure where these should go, as they are human-designated but not particularly artificial
** {{annotated link|National park}}
** {{annotated link|Nature reserve}}
** {{annotated link|Park}}
** {{annotated link|Wildlife reserve}}
** {{annotated link|Marine protected area}} --&gt;

[[File:China administrative.gif|thumb|300px|[[Province (China)|Provinces]] and territorial disputes of the [[People's Republic of China]]]]
* Abstract geographic feature &amp;ndash; does not exist physically in the real world, yet has a location by definition and may be displayed on maps.
** {{annotated link|Geographical zone}}
*** {{annotated link|Hardiness zone}}
*** {{annotated link|Time zone}}
** {{annotated link|Political division}}
*** {{annotated link|Nation}}
*** {{annotated link|Administrative division}}
**** {{annotated link|Special Economic Zone}}
*** {{annotated link|Country subdivision}} &amp;ndash; a designated [[territory (country subdivision)|territory]] created within a country for administrative or identification purposes. Examples of the types of country subdivisions:
****{{annotated link|Bailiwick}}
****{{annotated link|canton (country subdivision)|Canton}}
****{{annotated link|Commune (country subdivision)|Commune}}
****{{annotated link|County}}
****{{annotated link|Department (country subdivision)|Department}}
****{{annotated link|District}}
****{{annotated link|Duchy}}
****{{annotated link|Emirate}}
****{{annotated link|Federal state}}
****{{annotated link|Parish}}
****{{annotated link|Prefecture}}
****{{annotated link|Province}}
****{{annotated link|Region#Administrative regions|Region}}
****{{annotated link|Rural district}}
****{{annotated link|Human settlement|Settlement}}
*****{{annotated link|Municipality}}
*****{{annotated link|City}}
******{{annotated link|Borough}}
******{{annotated link|Township}}
*****{{annotated link|Village}}
****{{annotated link|Shire}}
****{{annotated link|State (administrative division)|State}}
****{{annotated link|Subdistrict}}
****{{annotated link|Subprefecture}}
****{{annotated link|Voivodeship}}
****{{annotated link|Wilayat}}
** Cartographical feature &amp;ndash; theoretical construct used specifically on maps that doesn't have any physical form apart from its location.
*** {{annotated link|Latitude|Latitude line}}
**** {{annotated link|Equator}}
*** {{annotated link|Longitude|Longitude line}}
**** {{annotated link|Prime Meridian}}
*** {{annotated link|Geographical pole}}
**** {{annotated link|North pole}}
**** {{annotated link|South pole}}

==== Geographic features that include the natural and artificial ====

* {{annotated link|Waterway}} 
** {{annotated link|List of waterways}}

==Geography awards==
[[File:Hubbard Gold Medal, Anne Morrow Lindbergh.JPG|thumb|right|180px|Hubbard Medal awarded to [[Anne Morrow Lindbergh]], showing her flight route]]
{{See also|List of prizes, medals, and awards#Geography}}

Some awards and competitions in the field of geography:

* {{annotated link|Geography Cup}}
* {{annotated link|Gold Medal (RGS)|Gold Medal}}
* {{annotated link|Hubbard Medal}}
* {{annotated link|National Geographic World Championship}}
* {{annotated link|Victoria Medal (geography)|Victoria Medal}}

== Persons influential in geography ==
{{Main|Geographer|List of geographers|List of Graeco-Roman geographers}}

A [[geographer]] is a [[scientist]] who studies [[Earth]]'s physical [[environment (biophysical)|environment]] and [[human]] [[habitat (ecology)|habitat]]. Geographers are historically known for making [[map]]s, the subdiscipline of geography known as [[cartography]]. They study the physical details of the environment and also its effect on human and [[wildlife]] [[ecology|ecologies]], [[weather]] and [[climate]] patterns, [[economics]], and [[culture]]. Geographers focus on the spatial relationships between these elements.

=== Influential physical geographers ===
[[File:Alexander von Humboldt-selfportrait.jpg|thumb|right|120px|[[Alexander Von Humboldt]], considered to be the founding father of physical geography.]]
[[File:Richard Chorley.jpg|thumb|right|120px|[[Richard Chorley]], 20th-century geographer who progressed quantitative geography and who helped bring the systems approach to geography.]]

* [[Eratosthenes]] (276{{spaced ndash}}194&amp;nbsp;BC) &amp;ndash; who made the first known reliable estimation of the Earth's size.&lt;ref name="eratosthenes"/&gt; He is considered the father of [[geodesy]].&lt;ref name="eratosthenes"&gt;Avraham Ariel, Nora Ariel Berger (2006)."''[https://books.google.com/books?id=2xTJt3b3SHUC&amp;pg=PA12&amp;dq&amp;hl=en#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false Plotting the globe: stories of meridians, parallels, and the international]''". [[Greenwood Publishing Group]]. p.12.
{{ISBN|0-275-98895-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Jennifer Fandel (2006)."''[https://books.google.com/books?id=kRp7R_WnAiEC&amp;pg=PA4&amp;dq&amp;hl=en#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false The Metric System]''". The Creative Company. p.4. {{ISBN|1-58341-430-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Ptolemy]] ([[Circa|c.]]90{{spaced ndash}}c.168) &amp;ndash; who compiled Greek and Roman knowledge to produce the book ''[[Geographia]]''.
* [[Abū Rayhān Bīrūnī]] (973{{spaced ndash}}1048 AD) &amp;ndash; considered the father of [[geodesy]].&lt;ref name=Ahmed&gt;Akbar S. Ahmed (1984). "Al-Beruni: The First Anthropologist", ''RAIN'' '''60''', p. 9-10.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;H. Mowlana (2001). "Information in the Arab World", ''Cooperation South Journal'' '''1'''.&lt;/ref&gt;{{Verify source|date=September 2010}}
* [[Avicenna|Ibn Sina]] (Avicenna, 980&amp;ndash;1037) &amp;ndash; whose observations in ''[[Kitab al-Shifa|Kitab Al-Shifa]]'' contributed to later formulations of the [[law of superposition]] and concept of [[Uniformitarianism (science)|uniformitarianism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=vMk4t21fOvoC&amp;lpg=PA817&amp;ots=5b06q8o1lD&amp;dq=ibn%20sina%20uniformitarianism%20superposition&amp;pg=PA817#v=onepage&amp;q=ibn%20sina%20uniformitarianism%20superposition&amp;f=false|title=Encyclopedia of Earth and Space Science|last=Kusky|first=Timothy M.|last2=Cullen|first2=Katherine E.|date=2010-01-01|publisher=Infobase Publishing|year=|isbn=9781438128597|location=|pages=817|language=en|quote=|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Muhammad al-Idrisi]] (Dreses, 1100{{spaced ndash}}c.1165) &amp;ndash; who drew the ''[[Tabula Rogeriana]]'', the most accurate world map in pre-modern times.&lt;ref name=Scott&gt;{{cite book|first=S. P.|last = Scott|date= 1904|title = History of the Moorish Empire in Europe|page= 461 |quote =The compilation of Edrisi marks an era in the [[history of science]]. Not only is its historical information most interesting and valuable, but its descriptions of many parts of the earth are still authoritative. For three centuries geographers copied his maps without alteration. The relative position of the lakes which form the Nile, as delineated in his work, does not differ greatly from that established by [[Samuel Baker|Baker]] and [[Henry Morton Stanley|Stanley]] more than seven hundred years afterwards, and their number is the same.|url = https://books.google.com/books?id=pyM8UFGYaK0C&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Piri Reis]] (1465{{spaced ndash}}c.1554) &amp;ndash; whose [[Piri Reis map]] is the oldest surviving world map to include the [[Americas]] and possibly [[Antarctica]]
* [[Gerardus Mercator]] (1512&amp;ndash;1594) &amp;ndash; an innovative [[Cartography|cartographer]] and originator of the [[Mercator projection]].
* [[Bernhardus Varenius]] (1622–1650) &amp;ndash; Wrote his important work "General Geography" (1650) &amp;ndash; first overview of the geography, the foundation of modern geography.
* [[Mikhail Lomonosov]] (1711&amp;ndash;1765) &amp;ndash; father of Russian geography and founded the study of glaciology.
* [[Alexander Von Humboldt]] (1769&amp;ndash;1859) &amp;ndash; considered the father of modern geography. Published ''Kosmos'' and founded the study of biogeography.
* [[Arnold Henry Guyot]] (1807&amp;ndash;1884) &amp;ndash; who noted the structure of glaciers and advanced the understanding of glacial motion, especially in fast ice flow.
* [[Louis Agassiz]] (1807&amp;ndash;1873) &amp;ndash; the author of a glacial theory which disputed the notion of a steady-cooling Earth.
* [[Alfred Russel Wallace]] (1823&amp;ndash;1913) &amp;ndash; founder of modern biogeography and the [[Wallace line]].
* [[Vasily Dokuchaev]] (1846&amp;ndash;1903) &amp;ndash; patriarch of Russian geography and founder of pedology.
* [[Wladimir Peter Köppen]] (1846&amp;ndash;1940) &amp;ndash; developer of most important climate classification and founder of Paleoclimatology.
* [[William Morris Davis]] (1850&amp;ndash;1934) &amp;ndash; father of American geography, founder of Geomorphology and developer of the geographical cycle theory.
* [[Walther Penck]] (1888&amp;ndash;1923) &amp;ndash; proponent of the [[cycle of erosion]] and the simultaneous occurrence of [[Tectonic uplift|uplift]] and [[denudation]].
* Sir [[Ernest Shackleton]] (1874&amp;ndash;1922) &amp;ndash; Antarctic explorer during the [[Heroic Age of Antarctic Exploration]].
* [[Robert E. Horton]] (1875&amp;ndash;1945) &amp;ndash; founder of modern hydrology and concepts such as [[infiltration capacity]] and [[overland flow]].
* [[J Harlen Bretz]] (1882&amp;ndash;1981) &amp;ndash; pioneer of research into the shaping of landscapes by catastrophic floods, most notably the [[Missoula Floods|Bretz (Missoula) floods]].
* [[Willi Dansgaard]] (born 1922) &amp;ndash; [[palaeoclimatologist]] and quaternary scientist, instrumental in the use of oxygen-isotope dating and co-identifier of [[Dansgaard-Oeschger event]]s.
* [[Hans Oeschger]] (1927&amp;ndash;1998) &amp;ndash; palaeoclimatologist and pioneer in ice core research, co-identifier of Dansgaard-Orschger events.
* [[Richard Chorley]] (1927&amp;ndash;2002) &amp;ndash; a key contributor to the [[quantitative revolution]] and the use of [[systems theory]] in geography.
* Sir [[Nicholas Shackleton]] (1937&amp;ndash;2006) &amp;ndash; who demonstrated that oscillations in climate over the past few million years could be correlated with variations in the orbital and positional relationship between the Earth and the Sun.
* [[Stefan Rahmstorf]] (born 1960) &amp;ndash; professor of abrupt climate changes and author on theories of thermohaline dynamics.

=== Influential human geographers ===
[[File:Carl ritter.jpg|thumb|right|150px|Sketch of Carl Ritter]]
[[File:Paul Vidal Blache.jpg|thumb|right|150px|Paul Vidal de la Blache]]
[[File:David Harvey.jpg|thumb|right|120px|David Harvey]]
* [[Carl Ritter]] (1779–1859) &amp;ndash; considered to be one of the founding fathers of modern geography and first chair in geography at the [[Humboldt University of Berlin]], also noted for his use of organic analogy in his works.
* [[Friedrich Ratzel]] (1844–1904) &amp;ndash; [[Environmental determinism|environmental determinist]], invented the term ''[[Lebensraum]]''
* [[Paul Vidal de la Blache]] (1845–1918) &amp;ndash; founder of the French School of [[geopolitics]] and [[Possibilism (geography)|possibilism]].
* Sir [[Halford Mackinder|Halford John Mackinder]] (1861–1947) &amp;ndash; author of ''[[The Geographical Pivot of History]]'', co-founder of the [[London School of Economics]], along with the [[Geographical Association]].
* [[Carl O. Sauer]] (1889–1975) &amp;ndash; critic of [[environmental determinism]] and proponent of [[cultural ecology]].
* [[Walter Christaller]] (1893–1969) &amp;ndash; economic geographer and developer of the [[central place theory]].
* [[Richard Hartshorne]] (1899–1992) &amp;ndash; scholar of the history and philosophy of geography.
* [[Torsten Hägerstrand]] (1916–2004) &amp;ndash; critic of the [[quantitative revolution]] and [[regional science]], noted figure in [[critical geography]].
* [[Milton Santos]] (1926–2001) winner of the Vautrin Lud prize in 1994, one of the most important geographers in South America.
* [[Waldo R. Tobler]] (born 1930) &amp;ndash; developer of the [[First law of geography]].
* [[Yi-Fu Tuan]] (born 1930) A [[Chinese-American]] geographer.
* [[David Harvey (geographer)|David Harvey]] (born 1935) &amp;ndash; world's most cited academic geographer and winner of the [[Lauréat Prix International de Géographie Vautrin Lud]], also noted for his work in [[critical geography]] and critique of [[globalization|global capitalism]].
* [[Evelyn Stokes]] (1936–2005). Professor of geography at the [[University of Waikato]] in [[New Zealand]]. Known for recognizing inequality with marginalized groups including women and [[Māori people|Māori]] using geography.
* [[Allen J. Scott]] (born 1938) &amp;ndash; winner of [[Lauréat Prix International de Géographie Vautrin Lud|Vautrin Lud Prize]] in 2003 and the Anders Retzius Gold medal 2009; author of numerous books and papers on economic and urban geography, known for his work on regional development, new industrial spaces, agglomeration theory, global city-regions and the cultural economy.
* [[Edward Soja]] (born 1941) &amp;ndash; noted for his work on regional development, planning and governance, along with coining the terms [[synekism]] and postmetropolis.
* [[Doreen Massey (geographer)|Doreen Massey]] (born 1944) &amp;ndash; key scholar in the space and places of [[globalization]] and its pluralities, winner of the [[Lauréat Prix International de Géographie Vautrin Lud|Vautrin Lud Prize]].
* [[Michael Watts]], Class of 1963 Professor of Geography and Development Studies, University of California, Berkeley
* [[Nigel Thrift]] (born 1949) &amp;ndash; developer of [[non-representational theory]].
* [[Derek Gregory]] (born 1951) &amp;ndash; famous for writing on the Israeli, U.S. and UK actions in the Middle East after 9/11, influenced by [[Edward Said]] and has contributed work on [[imagined geographies]].
* [[Cindi Katz]] (born 1954) &amp;ndash; who writes on [[social reproduction]] and the production of space. Writing on [[children's geographies]], place and nature, everyday life and security.
* [[Gillian Rose (geographer)|Gillian Rose]] (born 1962) &amp;ndash; most famous for her critique: ''Feminism &amp; Geography: The Limits of Geographical Knowledge'' (1993) &amp;ndash; which was one of the first moves towards a development of [[feminist geography]].

== Geography educational frameworks ==
Educational frameworks upon which primary and secondary school [[curricula]] for geography are based upon include:

* {{Annotated link|Five themes of geography}}&lt;ref&gt;''Guidelines for Geographic Education—Elementary and Secondary Schools.''
Joint Committee on Geographic Education of the National Council for Geographic Education and the Association of American Geographers, 1984.&lt;/ref&gt; 
*# {{annotated link|Location (geography)|Location}} &amp;ndash; a position or point that something occupies on the Earth's surface.
*# {{annotated link|Place (geography)|Place}}
*# {{annotated link|Environmental sociology|Human-environment interaction}}
*# [[:wikt:movement|movement]] &amp;ndash;
*# {{annotated link|Region}}
* The six "essential elements" identified by the [[Geography Education Standards Project]],&lt;ref name="GESP"&gt;{{Cite web|title=The National Geography Standards |url=http://www.studentsfriend.com/onhist/ngs.html |accessdate=November 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; under which the [[National Geography Standards]] they developed are organized:&lt;ref name="National Geography Standards"&gt;{{Cite web|title=National Geography Standards |url=http://www.ncge.org/i4a/pages/index.cfm?pageid=3314 |accessdate=November 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Geography for Life"&gt;Richard G Boehm, Roger M Downs, Sarah W Bednarz. ''Geography for Life: National Geography Standards.'' National Council for Geographic Education, 1994&lt;/ref&gt;
*# The [[Earth|World]] in spatial terms
*# [[Place (geography)|Place]]s and [[region]]s
*# [[Physical system]]s
*# [[Social systems|Human systems]]
*# [[Natural environment|Environment]] and [[Society#In sociology|society]]
*# The uses of geography
* The three content areas of geography from the 2010 [[National Assessment of Educational Progress]]&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.nagb.org/publications/frameworks/gframework2010.pdf Geography Framework for the 2010 National Assessment of Educational Progress.]'' National Assessment Governing Board, U.S. Department of Education, p. vii: {{quote|It focuses on what geography students should know to be competent and productive 21st century citizens, and uses three content areas for assessing the outcomes of geography education. These content areas are Space and Place, Environment and Society, and Spatial Dynamics and Connections.}}&lt;/ref&gt; (U.S.):
*# [[Space#Geographical space|Space]] and [[Place (geography)|place]]
*# [[Natural environment|Environment]] and [[Society#In sociology|society]]
*# Spatial dynamics and [[Interconnectivity|connections]]

== See also ==
{{Portal|Geography}}
{{div col|colwidth=25em}}
* [[Association of American Geographers]]
* [[Canadian Association of Geographers]]
* [[Gazetteer]]
* [[Geographer]]
* [[Geographical renaming]]
* [[List of reference tables#Geography and places|Geography and places reference tables]]
* [[International Geographical Union]]
* [[Landform]]
* [[List of explorers]]
** [[List of Russian explorers]]
* [[Map]]
* [[Navigator]]
* [[Philosophy of geography]]
* [[World map]]
{{colend}}

== References ==
{{Reflist|2}}

== External links ==
{{Sister project links|Geography}}

* Pidwirny, Michael. (2014). ''Glossary of Terms for Physical Geography.'' Planet Earth Publishing, Kelowna, Canada. {{ISBN|9780987702906}}. Available on [https://play.google.com/store/books/details/Michael_Pidwirny_Glossary_of_Terms_for_Physical_Ge?id=jQoIBAAAQBAJ Google Play].
* Pidwirny, Michael. (2014). ''Understanding Physical Geography.'' Planet Earth Publishing, Kelowna, Canada. {{ISBN|9780987702944}}. Available on [https://play.google.com/store/search?q=Pidwirny Google Play].

{{Outline footer}}

[[Category:Wikipedia outlines|Geography]]
[[Category:Geography| 1]]
[[Category:Geography-related lists| ]]</text>
      <sha1>8y78gxgxfal6ba9ksqz27772hds55ir</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
