<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.33.0-wmf.4</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Abbreviation</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1171</id>
    <revision>
      <id>859220658</id>
      <parentid>855076118</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-09-12T15:35:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Nbarth</username>
        <id>570614</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Periods (full stops) and spaces */ Added Penna. sign</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="29006">{{redirect|Abbr|the &amp;lt;abbr&amp;gt; HTML tag|HTML element#abbr}}
{{More citations needed|date=May 2008}}
[[File:Schriftprobe Latein 15 Jh.jpg|thumb|Example of [[Latin]] text with abbreviations]]

An '''abbreviation''' (from [[Latin]] ''brevis'', meaning ''short'' &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=brevis/breve, brevis M – Latin is Simple Online Dictionary|url=https://www.latin-is-simple.com/en/vocabulary/adjective/91/|website=www.latin-is-simple.com|accessdate=29 March 2018|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;) is a shortened form of a word or phrase.  It consists of a group of letters taken from the word or phrase. For example, the word ''abbreviation'' can itself be represented by the abbreviation ''abbr.'', ''abbrv.'', or ''abbrev.''

In strict analysis, abbreviations should not be confused with [[Contraction (grammar)|contractions]], [[crasis]], [[acronym]]s, or [[initialism]]s, with which they share some [[semantic]] and [[phonetic]] functions, though all four are connected by the term "abbreviation" in loose parlance.&lt;ref name=harts&gt;{{cite book|title=New Hart's Rules: The handbook of style for writers and editors|publisher=Oxford University Press, 2005|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=3uwGtj8i_vkC&amp;dq=New+Hart%27s+Rules&amp;q=acronyms+contractions+10.1#v=snippet&amp;q=acronyms%20contractions%2010.1&amp;f=false|isbn=0-19-861041-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|p167}}An abbreviation is a shortening by any method; a contraction is a reduction of size by the drawing together of the parts. A contraction of a word is made by omitting certain letters or [[syllable]]s and bringing together the first and last letters or elements; an abbreviation may be made by omitting certain portions from the interior or by cutting off a part. A contraction is an abbreviation, but an abbreviation is not necessarily a contraction. Acronyms and initialisms are regarded as subsets of abbreviations (e.g. by the [[Council of Science Editors]]). They are abbreviations that consist of the initial letters or parts of words.

== History ==
{{See also|Scribal abbreviation}}

Abbreviations have a long history, created so that spelling out a whole word could be avoided. This might be done to save time and space, and also to provide secrecy. Shortened words were used and initial letters were commonly used to represent words in specific applications. In classical [[Ancient Greece|Greece]] and [[Ancient Rome|Rome]], the reduction of words to single letters was common.&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=HA9kAAAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA5&amp;dq=abbreviations+history&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=D2NaVIitA6vbsASp94DgAg&amp;ved=0CDoQ6AEwBA#v=onepage&amp;q=abbreviations%20history&amp;f=false ''The British Cyclopaedia of the Arts, Sciences, History, Geography, Literature, Natural History, and Biography'', Wm. S. Orr and Company, 1838, p.5.]&lt;/ref&gt; In Roman inscriptions, "Words were commonly abbreviated by using the initial letter or letters of words, and most inscriptions have at least one abbreviation." However, "some could have more than one meaning, depending on their context. (For example, ''A'' can be an abbreviation for many words, such as ''ager'', ''amicus'', ''annus'', ''as'', ''Aulus'', ''Aurelius'', ''aurum'' and ''avus''.)"&lt;ref&gt;Adkins, L., [https://books.google.com/books?id=zGY1Sqjwf8kC&amp;dq=abbreviations++fashionable&amp;q=abbreviated+%22the+initial%22#v=snippet&amp;q=abbreviated%20%22the%20initial%22&amp;f=false ''Handbook to Life in Ancient Rome''], Infobase Publishing, 2004, p. 261.&lt;/ref&gt;

Abbreviations in English were frequently used from its earliest days. Manuscripts of copies of the [[old English]] poem ''[[Beowulf]]'' used many abbreviations, for example ''7'' or ''&amp;'' for ''and'', and ''y'' for ''since'', so that "not much space is wasted".&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=68EjAwAAQBAJ&amp;dq=abbreviations+history&amp;q=abbreviations+beowulf#v=snippet&amp;q=abbreviations%20beowulf&amp;f=false Gelderen, E. v, ''A History of the English Language: Revised edition'', John Benjamins Publishing Company, 2014, Ch. 4 1.]&lt;/ref&gt; The standardisation of English in the 15th through 17th centuries included such a growth in the use of abbreviations.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.spellingsociety.org/journals/j7/shortcuts.php Spelling Society : Shortcuts 1483–1660&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071015214606/http://www.spellingsociety.org/journals/j7/shortcuts.php |date=October 15, 2007 }} Doesn't work.&lt;/ref&gt;{{citation needed|date=November 2014}} At first, abbreviations were sometimes represented with various suspension signs, not only periods. For example, sequences like ‹er› were replaced with ‹ɔ›, as in ‹mastɔ› for ''master'' and ‹exacɔbate› for ''exacerbate''. While this may seem trivial, it was symptomatic of an attempt by people manually reproducing academic texts to reduce the copy time. An example from the Oxford University Register, 1503:{{citation needed|date=November 2014}}

{{quote|Mastɔ subwardenɔ y ɔmēde me to you. And wherɔ y wrot to you the last wyke that y trouyde itt good to differrɔ thelectionɔ ovɔ to quīdenaɔ tinitatis y have be thougħt me synɔ that itt woll be thenɔ a bowte mydsomɔ.}}

The [[Early Modern English]] period, between the 15th and 17th centuries, had abbreviations like ''y&lt;sup&gt;e&lt;/sup&gt;'' for ''Þ&lt;sup&gt;e&lt;/sup&gt;'', used for the word ''the'': "hence, by later misunderstanding, Ye Olde Tea Shoppe."&lt;ref&gt;Lass, R., ''The Cambridge History of the English Language'', Cambridge University Press, 2006, Vol. 2, p. 36.&lt;/ref&gt;

During the growth of [[philology|philological]] linguistic theory in academic Britain, abbreviating became very fashionable. The use of abbreviation for the names of [[J. R. R. Tolkien]] and his friend [[C. S. Lewis]], and other members of the [[Oxford]] literary group known as the [[Inklings]], are sometimes cited as symptomatic of this.{{citation needed|date=October 2011}} Likewise, a century earlier in [[Boston]], a fad of abbreviation started that swept the United States, with the globally popular term [[Okay|OK]] generally credited as a remnant of its influence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.illinoisprairie.info/chocokeh.htm |title=The Choctaw Expression 'Okeh' and the Americanism 'Okay' |publisher=Jim Fay |date=2007-09-13 |accessdate=2008-05-12 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20101224185657/http://www.illinoisprairie.info/chocokeh.htm |archivedate=2010-12-24 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.straightdope.com/classics/a2_250.html |title=What does "OK" stand for? |work=[[The Straight Dope]] |accessdate=2008-05-12| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20080512085453/http://www.straightdope.com/classics/a2_250.html| archivedate= 12 May 2008 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After World War II, the British greatly reduced the use of the [[full stop]] and other punctuation points after abbreviations in at least semi-formal writing, while the Americans more readily kept such use until more recently, and still maintain it more than Britons{{Citation needed|date=April 2017}}. The classic example, considered by their American counterparts quite curious, was the maintenance of the internal comma in a British organisation of secret agents called the "[[Special Operations, Executive]]"—"S.O., E"—which is not found in histories written after about 1960.

But before that, many Britons were more scrupulous at maintaining the French form. In French, the period only follows an abbreviation if the last letter in the abbreviation is ''not'' the last letter of its antecedent:  "M." is the abbreviation for "monsieur" while "Mme" is that for "madame". Like many other cross-[[English Channel|channel]] linguistic acquisitions, many Britons readily took this up and followed this rule themselves, while the Americans took a simpler rule and applied it rigorously.{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}}

Over the years, however, the lack of convention in some style guides has made it difficult to determine which two-word abbreviations should be abbreviated with periods and which should not. The U.S. media tend to use periods in two-word abbreviations like United States (U.S.), but not [[personal computer]] (PC) or television (TV). Many British publications have gradually done away with the use of periods in abbreviations.

Minimization of punctuation in typewritten material became economically desirable in the 1960s and 1970s for the many users of carbon-film [[IBM Selectric typewriter#Ribbons|ribbons]] since a period or comma consumed the same length of non-reusable expensive ribbon as did a capital letter.

Widespread use of electronic communication through mobile phones and the Internet during the 1990s allowed for a marked rise in colloquial abbreviation. This was due largely to increasing popularity of textual communication services such as instant- and text messaging. [[Short Message Service|SMS]], for instance, supports message lengths of 160 characters at most (using the [[GSM 03.38]] character set). This brevity gave rise to an informal abbreviation scheme sometimes called [[SMS language|Textese]], with which 10% or more of the words in a typical SMS message are abbreviated.&lt;ref&gt;Crystal, David. [[Txtng: the Gr8 Db8]]. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2008. {{ISBN|978-0-19-954490-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; More recently Twitter, a popular [[social networking service]], began driving abbreviation use with 140 character message limits.

== Style conventions in English ==

In modern English, there are several conventions for abbreviations, and the choice may be confusing. The only rule universally accepted is that one should be ''consistent'', and to make this easier, publishers express their preferences in a [[style guide]]. Questions which arise include those in the following subsections.

=== Lowercase letters ===

If the original word was capitalized then the first letter of its abbreviation should retain the capital, for example Lev. for ''Leviticus''. When a word is abbreviated to more than a single letter and was originally spelled with lower case letters then there is no need for capitalization. However, when abbreviating a phrase where only the first letter of each word is taken, then all letters should be capitalized, as in YTD for ''year-to-date'', PCB for ''printed circuit board'' and FYI for ''for your information''. However, see the following section regarding abbreviations that have become common vocabulary: these are no longer written with capital letters.

=== Periods (full stops) and spaces ===
[[File:“To Penna. R.R. Station”.jpg|thumb|Sign in New York City subway, reading “Penna.” for Penn''sylvani''a, showing American style of including the period even for contractions.]]
A period (full stop) is often used to signify an abbreviation, but opinion is divided as to when and if this should happen.

According to [[Hart's Rules]], the traditional rule is that abbreviations (in the narrow sense that includes only words with the ending, and not the middle, dropped) terminate with a full stop, whereas contractions (in the sense of words missing a middle part) do not, but there are exceptions.&lt;ref name="harts"/&gt;{{rp|p167–170}} [[Fowler's Modern English Usage]] says full stops are used to mark both abbreviations and contractions, but recommends against this practice: advising them only for abbreviations and lower-case initialisms and not for upper-case initialisms and contractions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Pocket Fowler's Modern English Usage|edition=2nd|editor-first=Robert|editor-last=Allen|publisher=Oxford University Press|date=2008|isbn=9780191727078|contribution=Full stop}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class="wikitable" border="1"
|-
!Example
!Category
!Short form
!Source
|-
|[[Doctor (title)|Doctor]]
|Contraction
|Dr
|D——r
|-
|[[Professor]]
|Abbreviation
|Prof.
|Prof...
|-
|The [[Reverend]]
|Abbreviation
|Rev.
|Rev...
|-
|The [[Reverend]]
|Contraction
|Revd
|Rev——d
|-
|[[The Right Honourable]]
|Contraction and Abbreviation
|Rt Hon.
|R——t Hon...
|}

In [[American English]], the period is usually included regardless of whether or not it is a contraction, e.g. ''Dr.'' or ''Mrs.''. In some cases, periods are optional, as in either ''US'' or ''U.S.'' for  ''United States'', ''EU'' or ''E.U.'' for ''European Union'', and ''UN'' or ''U.N.'' for ''United Nations''. There are some house styles, however—American ones included—that remove the periods from almost all abbreviations. For example:
* The U.S. [[Manual on Uniform Traffic Control Devices]] advises that periods should not be used with abbreviations on road signs, except for cardinal directions as part of a destination name. (For example, ''"Northwest Blvd"'', ''"W. Jefferson"'', and ''"PED XING"'' all follow this recommendation.) 
* [[AMA Manual of Style|AMA style]], used in many [[medical journal]]s, uses no periods in abbreviations or acronyms, with almost no exceptions. Thus [[exempli gratia|eg]], [[id est|ie]], [[wikt:versus|vs]], [[et al.]], [[Doctor (title)|Dr]], [[Mr.|Mr]], [[magnetic resonance imaging|MRI]], [[intensive care unit|ICU]], and hundreds of others contain no periods. The only exceptions are "[[Numéro sign|No.]]" (to avoid the appearance of "[[yes and no|No]]"); initials within persons' names (such as "George R. Smith"); and "St." within persons' names when the person prefers it (such as "Emily R. St. Clair") (but not in city names such as ''St Louis''  or ''St Paul''). (AMA style also forgoes italic on terms long since naturalized into English from [[Latin]], [[New Latin]], other languages, or [[international scientific vocabulary|ISV]]; thus, no italic for [[exempli gratia|eg]], [[id est|ie]], [[wikt:versus|vs]], [[et al.]], [[in vivo]], [[in vitro]], or [[in situ]].)

Acronyms that were originally capitalized (with or without periods) but have since entered the vocabulary as generic words are no longer written with capital letters nor with any periods. Examples are [[sonar]], [[radar]], [[lidar]], [[laser]], [[SNAFU|snafu]], and [[Scuba set|scuba]].

Today, spaces are generally not used between single-letter abbreviations of words in the same phrase, so one almost never encounters "U.&amp;nbsp;S."

When an abbreviation appears at the end of a sentence, only one period is used: ''The capital of the United States is Washington, D.C''.

=== Plural forms ===

There is a question about how to pluralize abbreviations, particularly acronyms. Often a writer will add an 's' following an apostrophe, as in "PC's". However, this style is not preferred by many style guides. For instance, Kate Turabian, writing about style in academic writings,&lt;ref name="Chicago"&gt;Turabian, K., ''A Manual for Writers of Research Papers, Theses, and Dissertations'', 7th Edition, subsection 20.1.2&lt;/ref&gt; allows for an apostrophe to form plural acronyms "only when an abbreviation contains internal periods or both capital and lowercase letters". Turabian would therefore prefer "DVDs" and "URLs" and "Ph.D.'s", while the [[Modern Language Association]]&lt;ref name="MLA"&gt;Modern Language Association (MLA) Handbook for Writers of Research Papers, 7th Edition 2009, subsection 3.2.7.g&lt;/ref&gt; explicitly says, "do not use an apostrophe to form the plural of an abbreviation".  Also, the [[American Psychological Association]] specifically says,&lt;ref name="APA"&gt;Publication Manual of the American Psychological Association (APA), 5th Edition 2001, subsection 3.28&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;''Publication Manual of the American Psychological Association'', 6th Edition 2010, subsection 4.29&lt;/ref&gt; "without an apostrophe".

However, the 1999 style guide for ''[[The New York Times]]'' states that the addition of an apostrophe is necessary when pluralizing all abbreviations, preferring "PC's, TV's and VCR's".&lt;ref&gt;Siegal, AM., Connolly, WG., [https://books.google.com/books?ei=-y5aVHCTyLAEl5GB0AE&amp;id=RT5w0s7_op8C&amp;dq=new+york+times+style&amp;focus=searchwithinvolume&amp;q=plurals+abbreviations ''The New York Times Manual of Style and Usage''], Three Rivers Press, 1999, p. 24.&lt;/ref&gt;

Following those who would generally omit the apostrophe, to form the plural of [[run batted in]], simply add an s to the end of RBI.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Garner|first=Bryan|title=Garner's Modern American Usage|year=2009|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=Oxford; New York|isbn=978-0-19-538275-4|page=638}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*RBIs

For all other rules, see below:

To form the plural of an abbreviation, a number, or a capital letter used as a noun, simply add a lowercase ''s'' to the end. Apostrophes following decades and single letters are also common.
* A group of MPs
* The roaring 20s
* Mind your Ps and Qs

To indicate the plural of the abbreviation or symbol of a unit of measure, the same form is used as in the singular.
* 1&amp;nbsp;lb or 20&amp;nbsp;lb
* 1&amp;nbsp;ft or 16&amp;nbsp;ft
* 1 min or 45 min

When an abbreviation contains more than one full point, ''Hart's Rules'' recommends putting the ''s'' after the final one.
* Ph.D.s
* M.Phil.s
* the d.t.s
However, subject to any house style or consistency requirement, the same plurals may be rendered less formally as:
* PhDs
* MPhils
* the DTs. (This is the recommended form in the ''New Oxford Dictionary for Writers and Editors''.)

According to ''Hart's Rules'', an apostrophe may be used in rare cases where clarity calls for it, for example when letters or symbols are referred to as objects.
* The x's of the equation
* Dot the i's and cross the t's
However, the apostrophe can be dispensed with if the items are set in italics or quotes:
* The ''x''s of the equation
* Dot the 'i's and cross the 't's

In Latin, and continuing to the derivative forms in European languages as well as English, single-letter abbreviations had the plural being a doubling of the letter for note-taking. Most of these deal with writing and publishing. A few longer abbreviations use this as well.

{| class="wikitable" border="1"
|-
!Singular abbreviation
!Word/phrase
!Plural abbreviation
!Discipline
|-
|d.
| didot
|dd.
| typography
|-
|f.
| following line or page
|ff.
|notes
|-
|F.
| folio
|Ff.
|literature
|-
|h.
| hand
|hh.
| horse height
|-
|J.
| Justice
|JJ.
|law (job title)
|-
|l.
| line
|ll.
|notes
|-
|MS
| manuscript
|MSS
|notes
|-
|op.
| opus (plural: opera)
|opp.
|notes
|-
|p.
|page
|pp.
|notes
|-
|Q.
| quarto
|Qq.
|literature
|-
|s. (or §)
|section
|ss. (or §§)
|notes
|-
|v.
|volume
|vv.
|notes
|}

=== Conventions followed by publications and newspapers ===

==== United States ====

Publications based in the U.S. tend to follow the style guides of ''[[The Chicago Manual of Style]]'' and the [[Associated Press]].{{Verify source|date=May 2008}} The U.S. Government follows a style guide published by the [[U.S. Government Printing Office]].  The [[National Institute of Standards and Technology]] sets the style for abbreviations of units.

==== United Kingdom ====

Many British publications follow some of these guidelines in abbreviation:
* For the sake of convenience, many British publications, including the [[BBC]] and ''[[The Guardian]]'', have completely done away with the use of full stops or periods in all abbreviations. These include:
** Social titles, e.g. Ms or Mr (though these would usually have not had full stops—see above) Capt, Prof, ''etc.;''
** Two-letter abbreviations for countries (''"US"'', not ''"U.S."'');
** Abbreviations beyond three letters (full caps for all except initialisms{{clarify|date=November 2015}});
** Words seldom abbreviated with lower case letters (''"PR"'', instead of ''"p.r."'', or ''"pr"'')
** Names (''"FW de Klerk"'', ''"GB Whiteley"'', ''"Park JS"'').  A notable exception is ''[[The Economist]]'' which writes ''"Mr F. W. de Klerk"''.
** Scientific units (see Measurement below).
* Acronyms are often referred to with only the first letter of the abbreviation capitalized. For instance, the [[North Atlantic Treaty Organisation]] can be abbreviated as ''"Nato"'' or ''"NATO"'', and [[Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome]] as ''"Sars"'' or ''"SARS"'' (compare with ''"[[laser]]"'' which has made the full transition to an English word and is rarely capitalised at all).
* Initialisms are always written in capitals; for example the ''"British Broadcasting Corporation"'' is abbreviated to ''"BBC"'', never ''"Bbc"''. An initialism is similar to acronym but is not pronounced as a word.
* When abbreviating scientific units, no space is added between the number and unit (&lt;nowiki&gt;100mph, 100m, 10cm, 10°C&lt;/nowiki&gt;). (This is contrary to the SI standard; see below.)

==== Miscellaneous and general rules ====

* A doubled letter appears in abbreviations of some Welsh names, as in [[Welsh language|Welsh]] the double "l" is a separate sound: "Ll. George" for (British prime minister) [[David Lloyd George]].
* Some titles, such as "Reverend" and "Honourable", are spelt out when preceded by "the", rather than as "Rev." or "Hon." respectively.  This is true for most British publications, and some in the United States.
* A repeatedly used abbreviation should be spelt out for identification on its first occurrence in a written or spoken passage.&lt;ref&gt;[[Gary Blake]] and [[Robert W. Bly]], ''The Elements of Technical Writing'', pg. 53. New York City: Macmillan Publishers, 1993. {{ISBN|0020130856}}&lt;/ref&gt; Abbreviations likely to be unfamiliar to many readers should be avoided.

== Measurement shorthand—symbol or abbreviation ==
[[File:PRC Expressway RoadSign Distances.jpg|thumb|200px|Road sign in China—"km" is a symbol, not an abbreviation, as it is not a contraction of a Chinese word]]

Writers often use shorthand to denote units of measure.  Such shorthand can be an abbreviation, such as "in" for "[[inch]]" or can be a symbol such as "km" for "[[kilometre]]/kilometer".

The shorthand "in" applies to English only—in [[Afrikaans language|Afrikaans]] for example, the shorthand "dm" is used for the equivalent Afrikaans word "duim".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
| title = Woordeboek/Dictionary; Afrikaans-English / Engels-Afrikaans
| editor = Abel Coetzee
| publisher = Collins
| year = 1969
| oclc = 29232187
| location = Glasgow and Johannesburg}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since both "in" and "dm" are contractions of the same word, but in different languages, they are abbreviations. A symbol on the other hand, defined as "Mark or character taken as the conventional sign of some object or idea or process"&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|title = Oxford Concise Dictionary
|publisher = Oxford University Press
|year = 1964}}&lt;/ref&gt; applies the appropriate shorthand by ''substitution'' rather than by ''contraction''. Since the shorthand for kilometre/kilometer (''[[:pt:Quilômetro|quilômetro]]'' in Portuguese or ''[[:el:Χιλιόμετρο|χιλιόμετρο]]'' in Greek) is "km" in both languages and the letter "k" does not appear in the expansion of either translation, "km" is a symbol as it is a substitution rather than a contraction. It is a [[logogram]] rather than an abbreviation.

In the [[International System of Units]] (SI) manual&lt;ref&gt;{{SIbrochure8th}}&lt;/ref&gt; the word "symbol" is used consistently to define the shorthand used to represent the various SI units of measure. The manual also [[International System of Units|defines the way in which units should be written]], the principal rules being:
*The conventions for upper and lower case letters must be observed—for example 1&amp;nbsp;MW (megawatts) is equal to 1,000,000,000&amp;nbsp;mW (milliwatts).
*No periods should be inserted between letters—for example "m.s" (which is an approximation of "m·s", which correctly uses [[middle dot]]) is the symbol for "metres multiplied by seconds", but "ms" is the symbol for milliseconds.
*No periods should follow the symbol unless the syntax of the sentence demands otherwise (for example a full stop at the end of a sentence).
*The singular and plural versions of the symbol are identical—not all languages use the letter "s" to denote a plural.

== Syllabic abbreviation ==
&lt;!--irony is this is linked from the MOS on how not to do it like this! - see [[MOS:CAPSACRS]]--&gt;
A syllabic abbreviation is usually formed from the initial syllables of several words, such as ''[[Interpol]]'' = '''''Inter'''national'' + '''''pol'''ice''. It is a variant of the acronym. Syllabic abbreviations are usually written using [[lower case]], sometimes starting with a [[capital letter]], and are always pronounced as words rather than letter by letter. Syllabic abbreviations should be distinguished from [[portmanteau]]s, which combine two words without necessarily taking whole syllables from each.

=== Usage ===

Syllabic abbreviations are not widely used in English. Some UK government ministries such as [[Ofcom]] ('''''Of'''fice of '''Com'''munications'') and [[Oftel]] ('''''Of'''fice of '''Tel'''ecommunications'') use this style.

New York City has various neighborhoods named by syllabic abbreviation, such as [[Tribeca]] ('''''Tri'''angle '''be'''low '''Ca'''nal Street'') and [[SoHo]] ('''''So'''uth of '''Ho'''uston Street''). This usage has spread into other American cities, giving [[South of Market, San Francisco|SoMa]], San Francisco ('''''So'''uth of '''Ma'''rket'') and [[LoDo, Denver]] ('''''Lo'''wer '''Do'''wntown''), among others.

==== Languages other than English====

On the other hand, syllabic abbreviations prevailed both in Germany under the [[Nazi Germany|Nazis]] and in the Soviet Union for naming the plethora of new bureaucratic organisations. For example, ''[[Gestapo]]'' stands for '''''Ge'''heime '''Sta'''ats-'''Po'''lizei'', or "secret state police". Similarly, Leninist organisations such as the ''[[Comintern]]'' (''Communist International'') and ''[[Komsomol]]'' ('''''Kom'''munisticheskii '''So'''yuz '''Mol'''odyozhi'', or "Communist youth union") used Russian language syllabic abbreviations. This has given syllabic abbreviations negative connotations in some countries,{{citation needed|date=September 2012}} (as in Orwell's [[Newspeak]]), notwithstanding that such abbreviations were used in Germany even before the Nazis came to power, e.g., ''[[:de:Schupo|Schupo]]'' for ''Schutzpolizei'', and are still used, e.g. ''[[:de:Kripo|Kripo]]'' for ''[[:de:Kriminalpolizei|Kriminalpolizei]]''.

In the modern Russian language words like ''Minoborony'' (from '''Min'''isterstvo '''oborony''' — Ministry of Defence) and ''Minobrnauki'' (from '''Min'''isterstvo '''obr'''azovaniya i '''nauki''' — Ministry of Education and Science) are still commonly used.

Syllabic abbreviations were also typical for the [[German language]] used in the [[German Democratic Republic]], e.g. ''[[Stasi]]'' for '''''Sta'''ats'''si'''cherheit'' ("state security", the secret police) or ''Vopo'' for ''Volkspolizist'' ("people's policeman"). Other uses are in company or product names such as [[Aldi]], from the name of the founder, Theo '''Al'''brecht, and the German word '''''Di'''skont'' (discount) or [[Haribo]], from the name of the founder and the headquarters of the company, '''Ha'''ns '''Ri'''egl '''Bo'''nn.

Syllabic abbreviations are ''de rigueur'' in Spanish; examples abound in organization names such as [[Pemex]] for '''''Pe'''tróleos '''Mex'''icanos'' ("Mexican Petroleums") or Fonafifo for '''''Fo'''ndo '''Na'''cional de '''Fi'''nancimiento '''Fo'''restal'' (National Forestry Financing Fund).

East Asian languages whose writing systems use [[Chinese characters]] form abbreviations similarly by using key Chinese characters from a term or phrase.  For example, in Japanese the term for the [[United Nations]], ''kokusai rengō'' (国際連合) is often abbreviated to ''kokuren'' (国連). (Such abbreviations are called [[:ja:略語|ryakugo]] (略語) in Japanese; see also [[Japanese abbreviated and contracted words]]). The syllabic abbreviation is frequently used for universities: for instance, ''Běidà'' (北大) for ''Běijīng Dàxué'' (北京大学, [[Peking University]]) and ''Tōdai'' (東大) for ''Tōkyō daigaku'' (東京大学, [[University of Tokyo]]).  The English phrase "[[:wikt:gung ho|Gung ho]]" originated as a Chinese abbreviation.

==== Organizations ====
{{See also|Neologism}}

Partially syllabic abbreviations are preferred by the US Navy, as it increases readability amidst the large number of initialisms that would otherwise have to fit into the same acronyms. Hence ''[[DESRON]] 6'' is used (in the full capital form) to mean "Destroyer Squadron 6", while ''[[COMNAVAIRLANT]]'' would be "Commander, Naval Air Force (in the) Atlantic."

== See also ==

* [[Clipping (morphology)]]
* [[List of abbreviations used in medical prescriptions]]
* [[List of abbreviations in photography]]
* [[List of acronyms]]
* [[List of classical abbreviations]]
* [[List of medieval abbreviations]]
* [[Wiktionary:Wiktionary:Abbreviations in Webster|The abbreviations used in the 1913 edition of Webster's dictionary]]
* [[Abbreviation (music)]]
* [[Numeronym]]

== References ==

{{Reflist|30em}}

== External links ==
{{Wiktionary|abbreviation}}
{{Wikisource1911Enc|Abbreviation}}

*{{dmoz|Reference/Dictionaries/Acronyms/|Acronyms}}
{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Abbreviations| ]]</text>
      <sha1>s9k9rwpj22pw3dmstdsvfp7untaqawp</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Annotation</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>624684</id>
    <revision>
      <id>869763627</id>
      <parentid>869763595</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-11-20T05:55:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>HickoryOughtShirt?4</username>
        <id>32314202</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contribs/36.76.173.6|36.76.173.6]] ([[User talk:36.76.173.6|talk]]) to last version by ClueBot NG</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="7815">{{Multiple issues|
{{lead too short|date=February 2015}}
{{refimprove|date=February 2015}}
}}

An '''annotation''' is a [[metadata|metadatum]] (e.g. a post, explanation, [[markup language|markup]])  attached to location or other data.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/annotation|title=Definition of ANNOTATION|website=www.merriam-webster.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Literature and education==

===Textual scholarship===
{{Main|Textual scholarship}}
[[Textual scholarship]] is a discipline that often uses the technique of annotation to describe or add additional historical context to texts and physical documents.{{citation needed|date=June 2016}}

===Student uses===
Students often [[Highlighter|highlight]] passages in books in order to refer back to key phrases easily, or add [[marginalia]] to aid studying.  One educational technique when analyzing prose literature is to have students or teachers circle the names of [[Character (arts)|characters]] and put rectangular boxes around phrases identifying the [[Setting (narrative)|setting]] of a given scene.{{citation needed|date=May 2013}}

[[Annotated bibliography|Annotated bibliographies]] add commentary on the relevance or quality of each source, in addition to the usual bibliographic information that merely identifies the source.

===Learning and instruction ===
From a cognitive perspective annotation has an important role in learning and instruction.  As part of guided noticing it involves highlighting, naming or labelling and commenting aspects of visual representations to help focus learners' attention on specific visual aspects. In other words, it means the assignment of typological representations (culturally meaningful categories), to topological representations (e.g. images).&lt;ref&gt;Pea, R. D. (2006). Video-as-Data and Digital Video Manipulation Techniques for Transforming Learning Sciences Research, Education, and Other Cultural Practices. In J. Weiss, J. Nolan, J. Hunsinger, &amp; P. Trifonas (Eds.), The International Handbook of Virtual Learning Environments (pp. 1321-1393. Dordrecht: Springer&lt;/ref&gt; This is especially important when experts, such as medical doctors, interpret visualizations in detail and explain their interpretations to others, for example by means of digital technology.&lt;ref&gt;Coiera E. Communication spaces. J Am Med Inform Assoc 2013 Sep 4. [doi: 10.1136/amiajnl-2012-001520] [Medline: 24005797]&lt;/ref&gt; Here, annotation can be a way to establish [[Grounding in communication|common ground]] between interactants with different levels of knowledge.&lt;ref&gt;Clark HH. Using Language. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press; 1996.&lt;/ref&gt; The value of annotation has been empirically confirmed, for example, in a study which shows that in computer-based teleconsultations the integration of image annotation and speech leads to significantly improved knowledge exchange compared with the use of images and speech without annotation.&lt;ref&gt;Pimmer, C., Mateescu, M., Zahn, C., &amp; Genewein, U. (2013). Smartphones as multimodal communication devices to facilitate clinical knowledge processes - a randomized controlled trial. Journal of Medical Internet Research, 15(11), e263. {{doi|10.2196/jmir.2758}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Software engineering ==

=== Text documents===
[[Markup language]]s like [[XML]] and [[HTML]] annotate text in a way that is syntactically distinguishable from that text.  They can be used to add information about the desired visual presentation, or machine-readable semantic information, as in the [[semantic web]].&lt;ref name="Web Annotation Data Model"&gt;{{cite web | title = Web Annotation Data Model | url =http://www.w3.org/TR/annotation-model/ | publisher = [[World Wide Web Consortium]] | date = 11 December 2014 | accessdate = {{CURRENTDAY}} {{User:Ed Poor/this month}} {{CURRENTYEAR}} }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Source control ===
The "annotate" function (also known as "blame" or "praise") used in [[source control]] systems such as [[Git (software)|Git]], [[Team Foundation Server]] and [[Apache Subversion|Subversion]] determines who [[Revision control#Common vocabulary|committed]] changes to the source code into the repository.  This outputs a copy of the source code where each line is annotated with the name of the last contributor to edit that line (and possibly a revision number).  This can help establish blame in the event a change caused a malfunction, or identify the author of brilliant code.

=== Java annotations ===
{{Main|Java annotation}}
A special case is the [[Java (programming language)|Java programming language]], where annotations can be used as a special form of syntactic [[metadata]] in the source code.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.5.0/docs/guide/language/annotations.html|title = JDK 5.0 Developer's Guide: Annotations|date = 2007-12-18|accessdate = 2008-03-05|publisher = [[Sun Microsystems]]| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20080306060928/http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.5.0/docs/guide/language/annotations.html| archivedate= 6 March 2008 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Classes, methods, variables, parameters and packages may be annotated. The annotations can be embedded in [[class (file format)|class files]] generated by the compiler and may be retained by the [[Java virtual machine]] and thus influence the [[Run time (program lifecycle phase)|run-time]] behaviour of an application. It is possible to create meta-annotations out of the existing ones in Java.

==Computational biology==
{{main|DNA annotation}}
Since the 1980s, [[molecular biology]] and [[bioinformatics]] have created the need for [[DNA annotation]]. DNA annotation or genome annotation is the process of identifying the locations of genes and all of the coding regions in a genome and determining what those genes do. An annotation (irrespective of the context) is a note added by way of explanation or commentary. Once a genome is sequenced, it needs to be annotated to make sense of it.

==Imaging==
In the [[digital imaging]] community the term annotation is commonly used for visible [[metadata]] superimposed on an [[digital image|image]] without changing the underlying master image, such as [[sticky note]]s, virtual laser pointers, circles, arrows, and black-outs (cf. [[redaction]]).

In the [[medical imaging]] community, an annotation is often referred to as a [[region of interest]] and is encoded in [[DICOM]] format.

==Law==

In the United States, legal publishers such as [[Thomson West]] and [[Lexis Nexis]] publish annotated versions of [[statutes]], providing information about [[Legal opinions|court cases]] that have interpreted the statutes. Both the federal [[United States Code]] and state statutes are subject to interpretation by the [[courts]], and the annotated statutes are valuable tools in [[legal research]].

==Linguistics==

In [[linguistics]], annotations include comments and [[metadata]]; these non-transcriptional annotations are also [[linguistics|non-linguistic]]. A collection of texts with linguistic annotations is known as a [[corpus linguistics|corpus]] (plural ''corpora''). The Linguistic Annotation Wiki&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://annotation.exmaralda.org/|title=LinguisticAnnotation|website=annotation.exmaralda.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; describes tools and formats for creating and managing linguistic annotations.

== See also ==
{{Wiktionary|annotation}}
* [[Abstract (summary)]]
* [[Automatic image annotation]]
* [[Coding (social sciences)]]
* [[Drama annotation]]
* [[Comment (disambiguation)]]
* [[Footnote]]
* [[Hyperkino]]
* [[Index (publishing)]]
* [[Marginalia]]
* [[Nota Bene]]
* [[Portable Document Format#Annotation|PDF annotation]]
* [[Subject indexing]]
* [[Text annotation]]
* [[Web annotation]]
* [[XPS annotation]]

== References ==
{{reflist|2}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Writing]]
[[Category:Reference]]</text>
      <sha1>7178mu9vg2go1gk8g6bvlsh4eipmoa8</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Ask a Librarian</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9721437</id>
    <revision>
      <id>724481557</id>
      <parentid>711166160</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-06-09T14:49:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Tom.Reding</username>
        <id>9784415</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* History */Fix [[:Category:Pages using citations with accessdate and no URL]] when permanent identifier present using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="5808">'''Ask a Librarian''' is a live [[virtual reference]] service that offers online reference assistance to residents in the state of Florida. Ask a Librarian is an official service of the Florida Electronic Library and is administered by the [[Tampa Bay Library Consortium]] (TBLC).

Participating libraries provide users with virtual reference services via [[live chat]] software, text messaging, and e-mail forms which users can access through embedded links and widgets on their library’s official website. Live chat and text messaging are available from 10:00&amp;nbsp;a.m. to midnight EST from Sunday through Thursday, and from 10:00&amp;nbsp;a.m. to 5:00&amp;nbsp;p.m. EST on Friday and Saturday; the e-mail form is available to patrons 24 hours per day, seven days per week.&lt;ref name="about"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://info.askalibrarian.org/about|title=AskALibrarian.org: About|work=Ask A Librarian News and Information|accessdate=2016-03-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; As of March 2016, Ask a Librarian has 133 participating institutions including public libraries and library systems, K-12 libraries, and university and college libraries.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://info.askalibrarian.org/participating-libraries/|title=Participating Libraries|website=Ask a Librarian News and Information|language=en-US|access-date=2016-03-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
Ask a Librarian began as a partnership between the [[College Center for Library Automation]] (CCLA) and TBLC in the interest of creating a statewide virtual reference service that would increase the presence of librarians on the internet.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Sachs|first=Diana|date=2005|title=Ask a Librarian: Florida’s Virtual Reference Service|url=|journal=Community &amp; Junior College Libraries|volume=12|issue=4|pages=51–52|doi=10.1300/J107v12n04_06|pmid=}}&lt;!--|access-date=2016-03-18--&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; In 2002, the organizations successfully applied for a joint grant through the [[Library Services and Technology Act]] (LSTA) and were awarded $339,000 for the development and implementation of their pilot project as a service of the [[Florida Electronic Library]].&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

The Ask a Librarian virtual reference service was officially activated on July 28, 2003.&lt;ref name="about" /&gt; [[Tampa Bay Area|Tampa Bay-area]] libraries were the first to participate, with [[Pasco County, Florida|Pasco County]] libraries joining shortly afterward.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://docs.newsbank.com/openurl?ctx_ver=z39.88-2004&amp;rft_id=info:sid/iw.newsbank.com:AWNB:TTRB&amp;rft_val_format=info:ofi/fmt:kev:mtx:ctx&amp;rft_dat=0FCC97A666F1382A&amp;svc_dat=InfoWeb:aggregated5&amp;req_dat=0D0CB5811D21E575|title=Librarians' Help Offered On Web|last=Richardson|first=Rachel|date=4 August 2003|newspaper=[[The Tampa Tribune]]|page=4|accessdate=2013-04-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; Within the first year of operation, nearly 7,500 Floridians had used the service to get answers from a reference librarian.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://docs.newsbank.com/openurl?ctx_ver=z39.88-2004&amp;rft_id=info:sid/iw.newsbank.com:AWNB:PBPB&amp;rft_val_format=info:ofi/fmt:kev:mtx:ctx&amp;rft_dat=104BB78A4408DBED&amp;svc_dat=InfoWeb:aggregated5&amp;req_dat=0D0CB5811D21E575|title=Library offering live, on-line help with research|last=Haase|first=Linda|date=25 August 2004|newspaper=[[The Palm Beach Post]]|page=1 (Neighborhood Post)|accessdate=2013-04-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Ward, J. 2010"&gt;Ward, J., &amp; Barbier, P. (2010). Best Practices in Chat Reference Used by Florida's Ask a Librarian Virtual Reference Librarians. Reference Librarian, 51(1), 53-68. doi:10.1080/02763870903361854&lt;/ref&gt; By August 19, 2007, Ask a Librarian had answered its 100,000th reference question.{{citation needed|date=March 2016|reason=I cannot find a reference for this statistic.}} As of February 2011, Ask a Librarian had logged over 274,000 live virtual reference sessions and e-mail questions.{{citation needed|date=March 2016|reason=The original reference no longer states this statistic. I have not yet found a replacement reference.}}

Ask a Librarian has made several efforts meet user reference needs on smartphones and other mobile devices. In October 2010, Ask a Librarian introduced a text messaging service to accompany their traditional chat service.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://info.askalibrarian.org/2010/10/22/text-messaging-goes-live-on-monday-october-25th/|title=Text Messaging goes LIVE on Monday, October 25th|website=Ask a Librarian News and Information|access-date=2016-03-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2012, the service introduced a mobile-friendly website interface for tablets and phones.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.theledger.com/article/20120306/COLUMNISTS/203065001|title=Reference Questions Answered with Ask-A-Librarian|last=Nunez|first=Varrick|date=6 March 2012|newspaper=[[The Ledger]]|page=B9|accessdate=2013-04-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bishop, B., Sachs-Silveira, D., &amp; Avet, T. (2011). Populating a Knowledge Base with Local Knowledge for Florida's Ask a Librarian Reference Consortium. Reference Librarian, 52(3), 197-207. doi:10.1080/02763877.2011.555289&lt;/ref&gt; In April 2013, the service also launched the Ask A Librarian Mobile App, a mobile-friendly interface geared toward improving the user chat experience on smartphones and tablets.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://info.askalibrarian.org/2013/04/06/ask-a-librarian-mobile-app/|title=Ask a Librarian – Mobile App|website=Ask a Librarian News and Information|access-date=2016-03-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* {{official website|1=http://www.askalibrarian.org/|mobile=http://www.askalibrarian.org/m}}
* [http://info.askalibrarian.org/annual-reports/ Ask a Librarian Annual Reports ]
* [http://info.askalibrarian.org/news/ Ask a Librarian News and Information]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Ask A Librarian}}
[[Category:Library resources]]
[[Category:Libraries in Florida]]
[[Category:Reference]]</text>
      <sha1>d48h1xkeiela2vvyl6nrt53b4qmd7y8</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Citation</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>97585</id>
    <revision>
      <id>869411046</id>
      <parentid>869410989</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-11-18T12:28:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Orphan Wiki</username>
        <id>11316070</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contributions/2601:247:8200:2F90:D8D4:9A6C:F04:AF0D|2601:247:8200:2F90:D8D4:9A6C:F04:AF0D]] ([[User talk:2601:247:8200:2F90:D8D4:9A6C:F04:AF0D|talk]]) ([[WP:HG|HG]]) (3.4.4)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="32690">{{about||&lt;nowiki&gt;"&lt;cite&gt;"&lt;/nowiki&gt;|HTML element#cite|help making citations within Wikipedia|:Wikipedia:Citing sources|other uses|Citation (disambiguation)|and|Cité (disambiguation)|and|CITE (disambiguation)}}
[[File:Webcomic xkcd - Wikipedian protester.png|thumb|right|250px|[[xkcd]] webcomic titled "Wikipedian Protester"&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= https://xkcd.com/285/ |title= Wikipedian Protestor|author= Randall Munroe |accessdate= 20 May 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
A '''citation''' is a [[reference]] to a [[Publishing|published]] or unpublished source.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/citation|title=Definition of CITATION|website=www.merriam-webster.com|language=en|access-date=2018-08-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; More precisely, a citation is an abbreviated alphanumeric expression embedded in the body of an intellectual work that denotes an entry in the bibliographic references section of the work for the purpose of acknowledging the relevance of the works of others to the topic of discussion at the spot where the citation appears. Generally the combination of both the in-body citation and the bibliographic entry constitutes what is commonly thought of as a citation (whereas bibliographic entries by themselves are not). References to single, machine-readable assertions in electronic scientific articles are known as nanopublications, a form of [[microattribution]].

Citations have several important purposes: to uphold [[intellectual honesty]] (or avoiding [[plagiarism]]),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=What Does it Mean to Cite?| publisher=MIT Academic Integrity|url=https://integrity.mit.edu/handbook/citing-your-sources/avoiding-plagiarism-cite-your-source}}&lt;/ref&gt; to attribute prior or unoriginal work and ideas to the correct sources, to allow the reader to determine independently whether the referenced material supports the author's argument in the claimed way, and to help the reader gauge the strength and validity of the material the author has used.&lt;ref&gt;Association of Legal Writing Directors &amp; Darby Dickerson, ''ALWD Citation Manual: A Professional System of Citation,'' 4th ed.(New York: Aspen, 2010), 3.&lt;/ref&gt; As Roark and Emerson have argued, citations relate to the way authors perceive the substance of their work, their position in the academic system, and the moral equivalency of their place, substance, and words.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |title=Signals |ssrn=2688685 |date=2015-11-10 |location=Rochester, N.Y. |first=Marc Lane |last=Roark |first2=Warren |last2=Emerson}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite these attributes, many drawbacks and shortcoming of citation practices have been reported, including for example honorary citations, circumstantial citations, discriminatory citations, selective and arbitrary citations.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Moustafa|first=Khaled|date=2016|year=|title=Aberration of the Citation|journal=Accountability in Research|volume=23|issue=4|pages=230–244|doi=10.1080/08989621.2015.1127763|issn=1545-5815|pmid=26636372|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The forms of citations generally subscribe to one of the generally accepted citations systems, such as the Oxford,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.lc.unsw.edu.au/onlib/refbib.html |title=Oxford Referencing System |accessdate=18 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Harvard, MLA, [[American Sociological Association]] (ASA), American Psychological Association (APA), and other citations systems, because their syntactic conventions are widely known and easily interpreted by readers. Each of these citation systems has its advantages and disadvantages. Editors often specify the citation system to use.

Bibliographies, and other list-like compilations of references, are generally not considered citations because they do not fulfill the true spirit of the term: deliberate acknowledgement by other authors of the priority of one's ideas.

== Concept ==
A '''bibliographic citation''' is a reference to a [[book]], [[article (publishing)|article]], [[web page]], or other published item. Citations should supply detail to identify the item uniquely.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ben.edu/library/help/glossary.htm |title=Library glossary |accessdate=2009-02-27 |date=August 22, 2008 |work= |publisher=[[Benedictine University]] |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080430220849/http://www.ben.edu/library/help/glossary.htm |archivedate=April 30, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Different citation systems and styles are used in [[scientific citation]], [[legal citation]], [[prior art]], [[the arts]], and the [[humanities]].

== Content ==
Citation content can vary depending on the type of source and may include:
*''Book:'' author(s), book title, place of publication, publisher, date of publication, and page number(s) if appropriate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www2.liu.edu/cwis/cwp/library/workbook/evaluate.htm#citing |title=Anatomy of a Citation |work=LIU.edu |accessdate=2015-09-28 |ref=refLongIslandUni}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*''Journal:'' author(s), article title, journal title, date of publication, and page number(s).
*''Newspaper:'' author(s), article title, name of newspaper, section title and page number(s) if desired, date of publication.
*''Web site:'' author(s), article and publication title where appropriate, as well as a [[Uniform Resource Locator|URL]], and a date when the site was accessed.
*''Play:'' inline citations offer part, scene, and line numbers, the latter separated by periods: 4.452 refers to scene 4, line 452. For example, "In Eugene Onegin, Onegin rejects Tanya when she is free to be his, and only decides he wants her when she is already married" (Pushkin 4.452–53).&lt;ref name=Brigham&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.byui.edu/english/mlaguide/MLA_intext_citation.htm |title=How to cite sources in the body of your paper |work=BYUI.edu |year=2008 |accessdate=2008-02-08 |ref=refBrigham |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20111113174823/http://www.byui.edu/english/mlaguide/MLA_intext_citation.htm |archivedate=November 13, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*''Poem:'' spaced [[Slash (punctuation)#In English text|slashes]] are normally used to indicate separate lines of a poem, and [[Parenthetical referencing|parenthetical citations]] usually include the line number(s). For example: "For I must love because I live&amp;nbsp;/ And life in me is what you give." (Brennan, lines 15–16).&lt;ref name=Brigham/&gt;
*''Interview:'' name of interviewer, interview descriptor (ex. personal interview) and date of interview.

=== Unique identifiers ===
Along with information such as author(s), date of publication, title and page numbers, citations may also include [[unique identifier]]s depending on the type of work being referred to.
* Citations of books may include an [[International Standard Book Number]] (ISBN).
* Specific volumes, articles or other identifiable parts of a periodical, may have an associated [[Serial Item and Contribution Identifier]] (SICI) or an [[International Standard Serial Number]] (ISSN).
* Electronic documents may have a [[digital object identifier]] (DOI).
* Biomedical research articles may have a PubMed Identifier ([[PMID]]).

== Systems ==
Broadly speaking, there are two types of citation systems, the Vancouver system and parenthetical referencing.&lt;ref name="Neville2012"&gt;Neville, C. (2012). Referencing: Principles, practices and problems. In RGUHS Journal of Pharmaceutical Sciences. Vol 2:2. pp. 1-8&lt;/ref&gt; However, the [[Council of Science Editors]] (CSE) adds a third, the'' citation-name system''.&lt;ref name="council2006scientific"&gt;Council of Science Editors, Style Manual Committee (2007). Scientific style and format: the CSE manual for authors, editors, and publishers.
&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Vancouver system ===
{{main|Vancouver system}}
The Vancouver system uses sequential numbers in the text, either bracketed or superscript or both.&lt;ref name="Neville2012" /&gt; The numbers refer to either footnotes (notes at the end of the page) or endnotes (notes on a page at the end of the paper) that provide source detail. The notes system may or may not require a full bibliography, depending on whether the writer has used a full-note form or a shortened-note form.

For example, an excerpt from the text of a paper using a notes system ''without'' a full bibliography could look like:

:"The five stages of grief are denial, anger, bargaining, depression, and acceptance."&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;

The note, located either at the foot of the page (footnote) or at the end of the paper (endnote) would look like this:

:1. Elisabeth Kübler-Ross, ''On Death and Dying'' (New York: Macmillan, 1969) 45–60.

In a paper with a full bibliography, the shortened note might look like:

:1. Kübler-Ross, ''On Death and Dying'' 45–60.

The bibliography entry, which is required with a shortened note, would look like this:

:Kübler-Ross, Elisabeth. ''On Death and Dying''. New York: Macmillan, 1969.

In the humanities, many authors also use footnotes or endnotes to supply anecdotal information. In this way, what looks like a citation is actually supplementary material, or suggestions for further reading.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.studenthandouts.com/citations.htm |title=How to Write Research Papers with Citations: MLA, APA, Footnotes, Endnotes |accessdate=2010-01-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Parenthetical referencing ===
{{main|Parenthetical referencing}}
Parenthetical referencing, also known as Harvard referencing, has full or partial, in-text, citations enclosed in circular brackets and embedded in the paragraph.&lt;ref name="Neville2012" /&gt;

An example of a parenthetical reference:
:"The five stages of grief are denial, anger, bargaining, depression, and acceptance" (Kübler-Ross,1969, p 45–60).

Depending on the choice of style, fully cited parenthetical references may require no end section. Other styles include a list of the citations, with complete bibliographical references, in an end section, sorted alphabetically by author. This section is often called "References", "Bibliography", "Works cited" or "Works consulted".

In-text references for online publications may differ from conventional parenthetical referencing. A full reference can be hidden, only displayed when wanted by the reader, in the form of a [[tooltip]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://livereference.org Live Reference Initiative]. Retrieved 2012-04-28.&lt;/ref&gt; This style makes citing easier and improves the reader's experience.

=== Citation-name system ===
Superscripted numbers are inserted at the point of reference, just as in the citation‐sequence system, but the citations are numbered according to the order of cited works at the end of the paper or book; this list is often sorted alphabetically by author.

== Styles ==
{{styles}}
{{Main|APA style|MLA style|The Chicago Manual of Style|Bluebook|ALWD Citation Manual|ASA style|Harvard referencing|Vancouver system}}

Citation styles can be broadly divided into styles common to the Humanities and the Sciences, though there is considerable overlap. Some style guides, such as [[the Chicago Manual of Style]], are quite flexible and cover both parenthetical and note citation systems. Others, such as [[MLA style manual|MLA]] and [[APA style|APA]] styles, specify formats within the context of a single citation system. These may be referred to as citation formats as well as citation styles.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.csuchico.edu/lref/newciting.html |title=Citation Formats &amp; Style Manuals |work=CSUChico.edu |year=2007 |accessdate=2008-02-11 |ref=refCaliforniaStateUni}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.lesley.edu/library/guides/citation/apa.html |title=APA Citation Format |work=Lesley.edu |year=2005 |accessdate=2008-02-11 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071228053242/http://www.lesley.edu/library/guides/citation/apa.html |archivedate=December 28, 2007 |ref=refLesleyUni}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://wally.rit.edu/pubs/guides/apa.html |title=APA Citation Format |work=RIT.edu |year=2003 |accessdate=2008-02-11 |ref=refRIT |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080203115324/http://wally.rit.edu/pubs/guides/apa.html |archivedate=February 3, 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The various guides thus specify order of appearance, for example, of publication date, title, and page numbers following the author name, in addition to conventions of punctuation, use of italics, emphasis, parenthesis, quotation marks, etc., particular to their style.

A number of organizations have created styles to fit their needs; consequently, a number of different guides exist. Individual publishers often have their own in-house variations as well, and some works are so long-established as to have their own citation methods too: [[Stephanus pagination]] for [[Plato]]; [[Bekker numbers]] for [[Aristotle]]; citing the Bible by book, chapter and verse; or [[Shakespeare]] notation by play.

=== Humanities ===
* The [[The Chicago Manual of Style|Chicago Style]] (CMOS) was developed and its guide is ''The Chicago Manual of Style''. It is most widely used in history and economics as well as some social sciences. The closely related [[Turabian]] style—which derives from it—is for student references, and is distinguished from the CMOS by omission of quotation marks in reference lists, and mandatory access date citation.
* The Columbia Style was created by Janice R. Walker and Todd Taylor to give detailed guidelines for citing internet sources. Columbia Style offers models for both the humanities and the sciences.
* ''Evidence Explained: Citing History Sources from Artifacts to Cyberspace'' by Elizabeth Shown Mills covers primary sources not included in CMOS, such as censuses, court, land, government, business, and church records. Includes sources in electronic format. Used by genealogists and historians.&lt;ref name="evidence"&gt;Elizabeth Shown Mills. ''Evidence Explained : Citing History Sources from Artifacts to cyberspace.'' 2d ed. Baltimore:Genealogical Pub. Co., 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Harvard referencing]] (or author-date system) is a specific kind of [[parenthetical referencing]]. Parenthetical referencing is recommended by both the [[BSI Group|British Standards Institution]] and the [[Modern Language Association]]. Harvard referencing involves a short author-date reference, e.g., "(Smith, 2000)", being inserted after the cited text within parentheses and the full reference to the source being listed at the end of the article.
* [[The MLA Style Manual|MLA style]] was developed by the [[Modern Language Association]] and is most often used in [[the arts]] and the [[humanities]], particularly in [[English studies]], other [[Literary criticism|literary studies]], including [[comparative literature]] and [[literary criticism]] in languages other than English ("[[foreign languages]]"), and some [[Interdisciplinarity|interdisciplinary]] studies, such as [[cultural studies]], [[drama]] and [[theatre]], [[film]], and other [[Mass media|media]], including [[television]]. This style of citations and bibliographical format uses [[parenthetical referencing]] with author-page (Smith 395) or author-[short] title-page (Smith, ''Contingencies'' 42) in the case of more than one work by the same author within parentheses in the text, keyed to an alphabetical list of sources on a "Works Cited" page at the end of the paper, as well as notes (footnotes or endnotes). See ''[[The MLA Style Manual]]'' and ''[[The MLA Handbook for Writers of Research Papers]]'', particularly [[The MLA Style Manual#Citation and bibliography format|Citation and bibliography format]].{{efn|The field of [[Communication]] (or Communications) overlaps with some of the disciplines also covered by the [[Modern Language Association|MLA]] and has its own disciplinary style recommendations for documentation format; the style guide recommended for use in student papers in such departments in American colleges and universities is often ''[[APA style|The Publication Manual of the APA]]'' ([[American Psychological Association]]); designated for short as "[[APA style]]".}}
* The [[MHRA Style Guide]] is published by the [[Modern Humanities Research Association]] (MHRA) and most widely used in the arts and humanities in the [[United Kingdom]], where the MHRA is based.  It is available for sale both in the UK and in the [[United States]]. It is similar to [[The MLA Style Manual|MLA style]], but has some differences.  For example, MHRA style uses footnotes that reference a citation fully while also providing a bibliography.  Some readers find it advantageous that the footnotes provide full citations, instead of shortened references, so that they do not need to consult the bibliography while reading for the rest of the publication details.&lt;ref&gt;The 2nd edition (updated April 2008) of the ''[[MHRA Style Guide]]'' is downloadable for free from the [[Modern Humanities Research Association]] official Website.
&lt;/ref&gt;

In some areas of the Humanities, footnotes are used exclusively for references, and their use for conventional [[footnotes]] (explanations or examples) is avoided. In these areas, the term "footnote" is actually used as a synonym for "reference", and care must be taken by editors and typesetters to ensure that they understand how the term is being used by their authors.

=== Law ===
{{Main|Legal citation}}
*The [[Bluebook]] is a citation system traditionally used in American academic legal writing, and the Bluebook (or similar systems derived from it) are used by many courts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.law.cornell.edu/citation/ |title=Introduction to Basic Legal Citation (LII 2007 ed.) |work=Cornell.edu |first=Peter W |last=Martin |origyear=1993 |date=May 2007 |accessdate=2008-02-03 |ref=refMartin2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; At present, academic legal articles are always footnoted, but motions submitted to courts and court opinions traditionally use inline citations, which are either separate sentences or separate clauses. Inline citations allow readers to quickly determine the strength of a source based on, for example, the court a case was decided in and the year it was decided.
*The legal citation style used almost universally in Canada is based on the ''Canadian Guide to Uniform Legal Citation'' (AKA ''[[McGill Guide]]''), published by ''McGill Law Journal''.&lt;ref&gt;''[https://web.archive.org/web/20130210184155/http://lawjournal.mcgill.ca/citeguide.php Canadian Guide to Uniform Legal Citation (Cite Guide)]''. ''McGill Law Journal''. Updated October 2008. Retrieved 2009-02-05.&lt;/ref&gt;
*British legal citation almost universally follows the ''[[Oxford Standard for Citation of Legal Authorities]]'' (OSCOLA).

=== Sciences, mathematics, engineering, physiology, and medicine ===
*The [[American Chemical Society]] style, or [[ACS style]], is often used in [[Chemistry]] and some of the [[physical sciences]]. In ACS style references are numbered in the text and in the reference list, and numbers are repeated throughout the text as needed.
*In the style of the [[American Institute of Physics]] (AIP style), references are also numbered in the text and in the reference list, with numbers repeated throughout the text as needed.
*Styles developed for the [[American Mathematical Society]] (AMS), or AMS styles, such as [[AMS-LaTeX]], are typically implemented using the [[BibTeX]] tool in the [[LaTeX]] typesetting environment. Brackets with author's initials and year are inserted in the text and at the beginning of the reference. Typical citations are listed in-line with alphabetic-label format, e.g. [AB90]. This type of style is also called an "''Authorship trigraph.''"
*The [[Vancouver system]], recommended by the [[Council of Science Editors]] (CSE), is used in medical and scientific papers and research.
**In one major variant, that used by the American Society of Mechanical Engineers (ASME), citation numbers are included in the text in square brackets rather than as superscripts. All bibliographical information is exclusively included in the list of references at the end of the document, next to the respective citation number.
**The International Committee of Medical Journal Editors (ICMJE) is reportedly the original kernel of this biomedical style, which evolved from the Vancouver 1978 editors' meeting.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.icmje.org "Uniform Requirements for Manuscripts Submitted to Biomedical Journals"].&lt;/ref&gt;  The [[MEDLINE]]/[[PubMed]] database uses this citation style and the [[National Library of Medicine]] provides "ICMJE [[Uniform Requirements for Manuscripts Submitted to Biomedical Journals]] -- Sample References".&lt;ref&gt;International Committee of Medical Journal Editors.  [https://www.nlm.nih.gov/bsd/uniform_requirements.html "ICMJE Uniform Requirements for Manuscripts Submitted to Biomedical Journals -- Sample References"].&lt;/ref&gt;
*The AMA Style.
*The style of the [[Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers]] (IEEE), or [[IEEE style]], encloses citation numbers within square brackets and numbers them consecutively, with numbers repeated throughout the text as needed.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ieee.org/documents/style_manual.pdf IEEE Style Manual]. Retrieved 2015-02-16.&lt;/ref&gt;
*In areas of biology that falls within the [[ICNafp]] (which itself uses this citation style throughout), a variant form of author-title citation is the primary method used when making nomenclatural citations and sometimes general citations (for example in code-related proposals published in ''[[Taxon (journal)|Taxon]]''), with the works in question not cited in the bibliography unless also cited in the text. Titles use standardized abbreviations following ''Botanico-Periodicum-Huntianum'' for periodicals and ''Taxonomic Literature 2'' (later [[IPNI]]) for books.
*Pechenik Citation Style is a style described in ''A Short Guide to Writing about Biology'', 6th ed. (2007), by [[Jan Pechenik|Jan A. Pechenik]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gonzaga.edu/academics/colleges-and-schools/college-of-arts-and-sciences/majors-programs/Biology/Undergraduate_Research/Forms/citation_guide.pdf "Pechenik Citation Style QuickGuide"] ([[PDF]]). [[University of Alberta]], Augustana Campus, Canada. [[World Wide Web|Web]]. November 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;
*In 1955, Eugene Garfield proposed a [[citation index|bibliographic system for scientific literature]], to consolidate the integrity of [[scientific publishing|scientific publications]].&lt;ref name=cisn&gt;{{cite journal |last=Garfield |first=Eugene |authorlink= |title=Citation indexes for science. A new dimension in documentation through association of ideas |journal=International Journal of Epidemiology |volume=35 |issue=5 |pages=1123–1127 |publisher= |location= |year=2006 |url= |doi=10.1093/ije/dyl189 |id= |pmid=16987841}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Social sciences ===
* The style of the [[American Psychological Association]], or [[APA style]], published in the [[Publication Manual of the American Psychological Association]], is most often used in [[social sciences]]. APA citation style is similar to [[Harvard referencing]], listing the author's name and year of publication, although these can take two forms: ''name citations'' in which the surnames of the authors appear in the text and the year of publication then appears in parentheses, and ''author-date citations'', in which the surnames of the authors and the year of publication all appear in parentheses. In both cases, in-text citations point to an alphabetical list of sources at the end of the paper in a References section.
* The [[American Political Science Association]] publishes both a style manual and a style guide for publications in this field.&lt;ref name=APSA&gt;Stephen Yoder, ed. (2008). ''The APSA Guide to Writing and Publishing'' and ''Style Manual for Political Science''. Rev. ed. August 2006. [http://www.apsanet.org/PUBLICATIONS/Online-Store APSAnet.org Publications]. Retrieved 2015-09-28.&lt;/ref&gt; The style is close to the CMOS.
* The [[American Anthropological Association]] utilizes a modified form of the [[The Chicago Manual of Style|Chicago Style]] laid out in their Publishing Style Guide.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aaanet.org/publications/guidelines.cfm|title=Publishing Style Guide - Stay Informed|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[ASA style]] of [[American Sociological Association]] is one of the main styles used in [[sociological]] publications.

== Issues ==
{{see also|Impact factor#Editorial policies that affect the impact factor}}

In their research on footnotes in scholarly journals in the field of communication, Michael Bugeja and Daniela V. Dimitrova have found that citations to online sources have a rate of decay (as cited pages are taken down), which they call a "half-life", that renders footnotes in those journals less useful for scholarship over time.&lt;ref&gt;Bugeja, Michael and Daniela V. Dimitrova. ''Vanishing Act: The Erosion of Online Footnotes and Implications for Scholarship in the Digital Age''. Duluth, Minnesota: Litwin Books (2010)&lt;/ref&gt;

Other experts have found that published replications do not have as many citations as original publications.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=Replications and Extensions in Marketing: Rarely Published But Quite Contrary |author=Raymond Hubbard and J. Scott Armstrong |journal=International Journal of Research in Marketing |volume=11 |pages=233–248 |year=1994 |doi=10.1016/0167-8116(94)90003-5 |issue=3|url=http://cogprints.org/5199/1/Replications-and-Extensions-in-Marketing.pdf }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Another important issue is citation errors, which often occur due to carelessness on either the researcher or journal editor's part in the publication procedure. Experts have found that simple precautions, such as consulting the author of a cited source about proper citations, reduce the likelihood of citation errors and thus increase the quality of research.&lt;ref name="Wright2008"&gt;{{cite journal |title=The Ombudsman: Verification of Citations: Fawlty Towers of Knowledge? |first1=Malcolm |last1=Wright |first2=J.&amp;nbsp;Scott |last2=Armstrong |author2-link=J. Scott Armstrong |work=Interfaces |volume=38 |issue=2 |pages=125–139 |date=2008 |publisher=Institute for Operations Research and the Management Sciences |location=Catonsville, Maryland |url=http://pubsonline.informs.org/doi/pdf/10.1287/inte.1070.0317 |archive-url=https://www.researchgate.net/profile/J_Armstrong2/publication/45579289_Verification_of_Citations_Fawlty_Towers_of_Knowledge/links/00b7d52b08d80022a0000000.pdf |archive-date=2013-12-17 |dead-url=no |format=PDF |doi=10.1287/inte.1070.0317 |issn=0092-2102 |eissn=1526-551X |jstor=25062982 |oclc=5582131729 |ssrn=1941335}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Research suggests the impact of an article can be, partly, explained by superficial factors and not only by the scientific merits of an article.&lt;ref&gt;Bornmann, L., &amp; Daniel, H. D. (2008). What do citation counts measure? A review of studies on citing behavior. Journal of Documentation, 64(1), 45-80.&lt;/ref&gt; Field-dependent factors are usually listed as an issue to be tackled not only when comparison across disciplines are made, but also when different fields of research of one discipline are being compared.&lt;ref&gt;Anauati, Maria Victoria and Galiani, Sebastian and Gálvez, Ramiro H., Quantifying the Life Cycle of Scholarly Articles Across Fields of Economic Research (November 11, 2014). Available at SSRN: http://ssrn.com/abstract=2523078&lt;/ref&gt; For example, in medicine, among other factors, the number of authors, the number of references, the article length, and the presence of a colon in the title influence the impact; while in sociology the number of references, the article length, and title length are among the factors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1007/s11192-013-1154-x |first=M. |last=van Wesel |first2=S. |last2=Wyatt |first3=J. |last3=ten Haaf |title=What a difference a colon makes: how superficial factors influence subsequent citation |journal=Scientometrics |issue=3 |volume=98 |pages=1601–1615 |year=2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Citation patterns are also known to be affected by unethical behavior of both the authors and journal staff. Such behavior is called impact factor boosting, and was reported to involve even the top-tier journals. Specifically the high-ranking journals of medical science, including the Lancet, JAMA and New England Journal of Medicine, are thought to be associated with such behavior, with up to 30% of citations to these journals being generated by commissioned opinion articles.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1002/asi.22997 |first=P. |last=Heneberg |title=Parallel Worlds of Citable Documents and Others: Inflated Commissioned Opinion Articles Enhance Scientometric Indicators |journal=Journal of the Association for Information Science and Technology |year=2014 |volume=65 |issue=3 |page=635}}&lt;/ref&gt; On the other hand, the phenomenon of citation cartels is rising. Citation cartels are defined as groups of authors that cite each other disproportionately more than they do other groups of authors who work on the same subject.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | last1 = Fister Jr. | first1 = I. | last2 = Fister | first2 = I. | last3 = Perc | first3 = M.| doi = 10.3389/fphy.2016.00049 | title = Toward the Discovery of Citation Cartels in Citation Networks | journal = Frontiers in Physics | volume = 4 | pages = 49 | year = 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
&lt;!-- New links in alpphabetial order please --&gt;
{{columns-list|colwidth=30em|
*[[Acknowledgment (creative arts)]]
*[[Bible citation]]
*[[Case citation]]
*[[Citation analysis]]
*[[Citation creator]]
*[[Citation signal]]
*[[Citationality]]
*[[Coercive citation]]
*[[Credit (creative arts)]]
*[[Cross-reference]]
*[[San Francisco Declaration on Research Assessment]]
*[[Scholarly method]]
*[[Source evaluation]]
*[[Style guide]]
}}

== Notes ==
{{Notelist}}

== References ==
{{Reflist|30em}}

== Further reading ==
&lt;!-- This list needs to be ordered alphabetically. --&gt;
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite web |url=http://libguides.usc.edu/c.php?g=235076&amp;p=1561830 |title=Citation Guide: ACS (American Chemical Society) |work=USC.edu |year=2015 |accessdate=2015-09-28 |ref=refUSC}}
* {{cite journal |title=The Ombudsman: Management Folklore and Management Science—On Portfolio Planning, Escalation Bias, and Such |journal=Interfaces |publisher=Institute of Management Sciences |location=[[Providence, Rhode Island|Providence]] |first=J Scott |last=Armstrong |pages=28–42 |volume=26 |issue=4 |date=July 1996 |oclc=210941768 |doi=10.1287/inte.26.4.25 |ref=refArmstrong 2007}}
* {{cite web |url=http://journaltool.asme.org/Help/AuthorHelp/WebHelp/JournalsHelp.htm |title=ASME Journals Digital Submission Tool |publisher=American Society of Mechanical Engineers |accessdate=2008-02-08 |ref=refASME}}
*{{cite book |title=Vanishing Act: The Erosion of Online Footnotes and Implications for Scholarship in the Digital Age |publisher=Litwin Books |location=Duluth, Minnesota |first=Michael |last=Bugeja |year=2010 |isbn=978-1-936117-14-7 |ref=refBugeja2010}}
* {{cite web |url=http://www.fisher.edu/fisher-library/research-assistance/citing-sources/assembling-a-list-of-works-cited-in-your-paper/books |title=Cite Books |work=Fisher.edu |year=2007 |accessdate=2015-09-28 |ref=refFisherCollege}}
* {{cite web |url=http://writing.colostate.edu/guides/researchsources/documentation/cbe_citation/index.cfm |title=CBE - Council of Biology Editors (Citation/Sequence System) |work=ColoState.edu |year=2008 |accessdate=2008-02-11 |ref=refColoradoUni}}
* {{cite web |url=http://www.lib.umd.edu/ues/guides/citing-styles |title=Citation Systems and Style Manuals by Subject Discipline |work=lib.umd.edu |year=2012 |accessdate=2013-08-02 |ref=refUniMaryland}}
* {{cite web |url=http://www.ieee.org/documents/ieeecitationref.pdf |title=IEEE Citation Reference |publisher=Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers |year=2009 |accessdate=2011-05-12 |ref=refIEEEstyle}}
* {{cite web |url=http://www.mhra.org.uk/Publications/Books/StyleGuide/ |title=MHRA Style Guide: A Handbook for Authors, Editors, and Writers of Theses |publisher=Modern Humanities Research Association |year=2008 |accessdate=2009-02-05}} (2nd ed.)
*&lt;cite id=refPechenik2004&gt;{{cite book |title=A Short Guide to Writing About Biology |publisher=Pearson/Longman |location=[[New York City|New York]] |first=Jan A |last=Pechenik |year=2004 |edition=5th |isbn=0-321-15981-0 |oclc=52166026 |ref=refMHRA}}&lt;/cite&gt;
* {{cite web |url=http://ctl.yale.edu/writing/using-sources/why-are-there-different-citation-styles |title=Why Are There Different Citation Styles? |work=Yale.edu |year=2008 |accessdate=2015-09-28 |ref=refYaleUni}}
{{refend}}

== External links ==
{{Wiktionary|citation needed}}
{{Wikiquote}}
{{Commons category|Citation needed}}

*[http://www.library.unt.edu/help/tutorials/government-documents/citing-government-publications-general-guidelines Citing Government Documents/Government Agency Style Manuals], University of North Texas

[[Category:Bibliography]]
[[Category:Reference]]</text>
      <sha1>gd28n5gwjvpa73k22h8xju5u5u02f4m</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Citation Style Language</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>10018490</id>
    <revision>
      <id>836364438</id>
      <parentid>835817260</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-04-14T09:56:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Zuphilip</username>
        <id>4160879</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Styles */ update number of styles</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="2898">The '''Citation Style Language''' ('''CSL''') is an open [[XML]]-based language to describe the formatting of [[citation]]s and [[bibliographic|bibliographies]]. [[Reference management software|Reference management programs]] using CSL include [[Zotero]], [[Mendeley]] and [[Papers (software)|Papers]].

==History==

CSL was created by Bruce D'Arcus for use with [[OpenOffice.org]],&lt;ref&gt;CiteProc at OpenOffice Bibliographic Project. http://bibliographic.openoffice.org/citeproc/index.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;OpenOffice Bibliographic Project. http://bibliographic.openoffice.org/&lt;/ref&gt; and an [[XSLT]]-based "[[CiteProc]]" CSL processor. CSL was further developed in collaboration with [[Zotero]] developer Simon Kornblith. Since 2008, the core development team consists of D'Arcus, Frank Bennett and Rintze Zelle.

The releases of CSL are 0.8 (March 21, 2009), 0.8.1 (February 1, 2010), 1.0 (March 22, 2010), and 1.0.1 (September 3, 2012). CSL 1.0 was a backward-incompatible release, but styles in the 0.8.1 format can be automatically updated to the CSL 1.0 format.&lt;ref&gt;Update instructions to convert CSL 0.8.1 styles to the 1.0 format. http://citationstyles.org/downloads/upgrade-notes.html#updating-csl-0-8-styles&lt;/ref&gt;

On its release in 2006, [[Zotero]] became the first application to adopt CSL. In 2008 [[Mendeley]] was released with CSL support, and in 2011, [[Papers (software)|Papers]] and [[Qiqqa]] gained support for CSL-based citation formatting.

==Software support==

* [[Zotero]], [[Mendeley]], [[Papers (software)|Papers]], and [[Qiqqa]] all support CSL 1.0 ([[Zotero]] also supports CSL 0.8.1 styles, which are internally updated to CSL 1.0).
* [[Zotero]], [[Mendeley]], and [[Qiqqa]] rely on the ''citeproc-js'' JavaScript CSL processor.
* CSL 1.0 processors have also been written in Haskell (''citeproc-hs''), PHP, Python, and Ruby.&lt;ref name="jv"&gt;Jakob Voß (May 2010), "Quick introduction to the Citation Style Language (CSL)", Lightning Talk proposal European Library Automation Group Conference. http://www.slideshare.net/nichtich/voss-elag-csl2010&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Zotero]], [[Mendeley]], and [[Qiqqa]] provide a built-in CSL editor to help create and modify CSL styles.

==Styles==

The CSL project maintains a CSL 1.0 style repository, which contains over 9000 styles (more than 1700 unique styles).&lt;ref&gt;https://github.com/citation-style-language/styles&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.citationstyles.org Project home of the Citation Style Language]
** [http://citationstyles.org/downloads/specification.html CSL 1.0.1 Specification]
* [http://www.zotero.org/support/dev/citation_styles Zotero's CSL documentation]
* [http://editor.citationstyles.org/about/ WYSIWYG CSL 1.0 style editor] (in development, by [[Mendeley]])

[[Category:Metadata]]
[[Category:Bibliography file formats]]
[[Category:Library 2.0]]
[[Category:Reference]]


{{library-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>5ojrlakv4s0h77z4zytt9yt7n88z3v6</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Citation dynamics</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>54083241</id>
    <revision>
      <id>846402343</id>
      <parentid>845469627</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-06-18T15:03:09Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jmertel23</username>
        <id>32942831</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Copyedit (minor)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="3762">{{Orphan|date=June 2018}}

[[File:Yearly citation for research paper.png|thumb|Yearly citation c(t) for a research paper from the e Physical Review corpus.]]
'''Citation dynamics''' describes the number of [[references]] received by the [[article (publishing)|article]] or other scientific work over [[time]]. The [[citation]] dynamics is usually described by the bang, that take place 2–3 years after the work has been published, and the burst size spans several [[Order of magnitude|orders of magnitude]]. The presence of bursts is not consistent with other models based on [[preferential attachment]]. Those models are able to account for the skewed citation distribution but their reference accumulation is gradual.&lt;ref name="eom"&gt;{{cite web|last1=Eom|first1=Young-Ho|last2=Fortunato|first2=Santo|title=Characterizing and Modeling Citation Dynamics|url=http://journals.plos.org/plosone/article/file?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0024926&amp;type=printable|website=journals.plos.org|accessdate=26 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The dynamics of scientific production has changed significantly over the past years. Due to [[Technological change|technological progress]], the number of published papers has been increasing exponentially until now. This, along with a much shorter time needed for the article to be published, has affected the [[citation]] dynamics of the modern papers. Furthermore, if the [[reference list]] of the study includes papers published in different years, older papers tend to have more citations. This may not necessarily because they are better but just because they had more time to accumulate those references.

==Model==
It has been found that citation distributions are best described by a shifted [[Power law|power-law]].&lt;ref name='eom'/&gt; The [[probability]] that paper &lt;math&gt;i&lt;/math&gt; is cited at time &lt;math&gt;t&lt;/math&gt; after publication as:

: &lt;math&gt; \Pi_{i}(t) = \eta_{i}c_i^tP_{i}(t) &lt;/math&gt;

where &lt;math&gt;\Pi_{i}(t)&lt;/math&gt; serves as the outcome variable for each particular paper &lt;math&gt;i&lt;/math&gt; at time &lt;math&gt;t&lt;/math&gt;. Fitness,  &lt;math&gt;\eta_i&lt;/math&gt;, captures the inherent differences between papers, accounting for the perceived [[novelty]] and importance of a discovery. &lt;math&gt;c_i^t&lt;/math&gt; represents the cumulative number of citations acquired by a paper &lt;math&gt;i&lt;/math&gt; at time &lt;math&gt;t&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;P_{i}(t)&lt;/math&gt; is a log-normal survival probability.&lt;ref name="Barabasi"&gt;{{cite web|last1=Wang|first1=Dashun|last2=Song|first2=Chaoming|last3=Barabási|first3=Albert-László|title=Quantifying Long-Term Scientific Impact|url=http://science.sciencemag.org/content/sci/342/6154/127.full.pdf|website=science.sciencemag.org|accessdate=18 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; The probability is equal

: &lt;math&gt;P_{i}(t) = \frac{1}{\sqrt{2\pi}\sigma_it} exp \left \lbrack -\frac{(ln t - \mu_i)^2}{2\sigma_i^2} \right \rbrack &lt;/math&gt;

where &lt;math&gt;t&lt;/math&gt; is time; &lt;math&gt;\sigma&lt;/math&gt; is [[longevity]], capturing the decay rate; and &lt;math&gt;m&lt;/math&gt; indicates immediacy, governing the time for a paper to reach its citation peak.
The ultimate impact &lt;math&gt;c_i^{\infty}&lt;/math&gt; represents the total number or citations that the paper receives during its lifetime.

:  &lt;math&gt;c_i^{\infty} = m(e^{\lambda_i} - 1)&lt;/math&gt;

Where &lt;math&gt;m&lt;/math&gt; is a global parameter that has the same value for all publications. &lt;math&gt;\lambda_i&lt;/math&gt; represents the relative fitness of the paper. From the above formula, we can see that the total number of references that the paper can receive during its lifetime depends only on its relative fitness which is very hard to quantify.

==See also==
* [[Citation index]]
* [[Citation network]]

==References==
&lt;references /&gt;

{{DEFAULTSORT:Citation dynamics}}
[[Category:Academic publishing]]
[[Category:Citation indices| ]]
[[Category:Reference]]</text>
      <sha1>jpk8fheujjysbbv1fb6qdawht95go1x</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Citation network</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>46902218</id>
    <revision>
      <id>840738805</id>
      <parentid>830220239</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-05-11T21:01:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>MaxEnt</username>
        <id>1190064</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Wikipedia prefers straight quotes</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="3248">{{Multiple issues|{{advert|date=June 2015}}{{notability|date=June 2015}}
{{Underlinked|date=June 2015}}
}}

'''Citation Network''' is a [[social network]] which contains paper sources and linked by co-citation relationships. Egghe &amp; Rousseau once (1990, p.&amp;nbsp;228) explain "when a document ''d&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;'' cites a document ''d&lt;sub&gt;j&lt;/sub&gt;'', we can show this by an arrow going from the node representing ''d&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;'' to the document representing ''d&lt;sub&gt;j&lt;/sub&gt;''. In this way the documents from a collection D form a directed graph, which is called a 'citation graph' or 'citation network' ".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iva.dk/bh/Core%20Concepts%20in%20LIS/articles%20a-z/citation_network.htm Science Citation Index: Effectiveness in locating articles in the anaesthetics field: 'Perturbation of ion transport'. British Journal of Anaesthesia, 43: 814, Cawkell, A. E. (1971)]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Background and history ==
[[Citation]] is a reference to a published or unpublished source (not always the original source). More precisely, a citation is an abbreviated alphanumeric expression embedded in the body of an intellectual work that denotes an entry in the bibliographic references section of the work for the purpose of acknowledging the relevance of the works of others to the topic of discussion at the spot where the citation appears. Generally the combination of both the in-body citation and the bibliographic entry constitutes what is commonly thought of as a citation (whereas bibliographic entries by themselves are not). References to single, machine-readable assertions in electronic scientific articles are known as nanopublications, a form of microattribution.
Citation networks, the principal focus of this study, are one kind of social networks that have been studied quantitatively almost from the moment citation databases first became available. In 1965, Derek J. de Solla Price described the inherent linking characteristic of the SCI in his seminal paper titled "Networks of Scientific Papers". The links between citing and cited papers became dynamic when the SCI began to be published online. In 1973, Henry Small published his work on co-citation analysis which became a self-organizing classification system that led to document clustering experiments and eventually what is called "Research Reviews".&lt;ref name="background"&gt;[http://www.casos.cs.cmu.edu/publications/papers/CMU-ECE-2011-017.pdf Structures and Statistics of Citation Networks, Miray Kas]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Basis and figures&lt;ref name="background" /&gt; ==
* Citation networks are directed. The links go from one document to the other. 
* Citation networks are acyclic because a paper can cite only existing papers.
* All edges in the citation networks point backwards in time.
* Links in co-authorship networks are reciprocal (symmetric).
* The link weights between two authors in co-authorship networks can increase over time if they have further collaboration.
* Vertices and edges added to the citation/co-authorship networks are permanent and cannot be removed at a later time. 
* The already formed part of the network is mostly static and only the leading edge of the network changes.

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

[[Category:Reference]]
[[Category:Social networks]]</text>
      <sha1>q8neppnc98mftoo0nfkbyirc2dq6z30</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cross-reference</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1833848</id>
    <revision>
      <id>844835223</id>
      <parentid>831075013</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-06-07T13:55:27Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>168.159.213.210</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>A benefit of cross-references was mixed in with archetypes of cross-references.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="3762">{{refimprove|date=February 2010}}
{{wiktionary}}
The term '''cross-reference''' can refer to either:
* An instance within a [[document]] which refers to related information elsewhere in the same document. In both printed and online dictionaries cross-references are important because they form a network structure of relations existing between different parts of data, dictionary-internal as well as dictionary external.&lt;ref&gt;Sandro Nielsen (1999): "Mediostructures in Bilingual LSP Dictionaries." In: ''Lexicographica. International Annual for Lexicography'' 15, 90–113.&lt;/ref&gt;
* In an [[Index (publishing)|index]], a cross reference is often denoted by ''See also''.  For example, under the term ''Albert Einstein'' in the index of a book about Nobel Laureates, there may be the cross-reference ''See also: Einstein, Albert''.
* In [[hypertext]], cross-referencing is maintained to a document with either in-context (XRIC) or out-of-context (''XROC'') cross-referencing.  These are similar to [[Key Word in Context|KWIC and KWOC]].
* In programming, "cross-referencing" means the listing of every file name and line number where a given [[identifier#In computer science|named identifier]] occurs within the program's [[source tree]].
* In a [[relational database management system]], a table can have an xref as prefix or suffix to indicate it is a [[cross-reference table]] that joins two or more tables together via [[primary key]].

== Structure of a cross reference ==
In a document, especially those authored in a [[Content management system]],
a cross-reference has two major aspects:
* A visible form that appears when the document is presented to the reader
* A technical mechanism that resides within the system

The visible form contains text, graphics, and other indications that:
* Enable the reader to follow the cross reference to the referenced content
* May enable the reader to understand what is being referred to, or what to expect upon following the reference
* May present to the reader some information from the referenced content

The technical mechanism that resides within the system:
* Identifies what location is being referred to
* Permits the system to present appropriate referencing text when the location containing the reference is presented to a reader
* Permits the system to offer a control (such as a link) that a reader can use when the content is presented in electronic form to access the referenced content

== How cross references contribute to usability of a document or set of documents ==
If the cross reference mechanism is well designed, the reader will be able to follow each cross reference to the referenced content whether the content is presented in print or electronically.

An author working in a content management system is responsible for identifying subjects of interest that cross documents, and creating appropriate systems of cross references to support readers who seek to understand those subjects.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Rockley|first1=Ann|last2=Cooper|first2=Charles|title=Managing Enterprise Content: A Unified Content Strategy|date=2012|publisher=New Riders|isbn=978-0321815361|edition=2nd}}&lt;/ref&gt; For an individual cross reference, an author should ensure that location and content of the target of the cross reference are clearly identified, and the reader can easily determine how to follow the cross reference in each medium in which publication is supported.

[[Content strategy]] practitioners (known as content strategists) specialize in planning content to meet business needs, taking into account the processes for creating and maintaining the content, and the systems that support the content.

== See also ==
*[[Credo Reference]]

== References ==
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Reference]]</text>
      <sha1>eesegkprssbvgqom4porg9t53rrb4ws</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Digital reference</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1902180</id>
    <revision>
      <id>811639093</id>
      <parentid>808345595</parentid>
      <timestamp>2017-11-22T22:56:42Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Hamaxides</username>
        <id>10372892</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>deleted hyperlink to KnowItNow24x7, service ceased operations 12/31/2015</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="25757">{{Refimprove|date=March 2008}}
'''Digital reference''' (or '''virtual reference''') is a service by which a [[library]] reference service is conducted online, and the reference transaction is a [[computer-mediated communication]]. It is the remote, NextNextcomputer-mediated delivery of reference information provided by library professionals to users who cannot access or do not want face-to-face communication. Virtual reference service is most often an extension of a library's existing reference service program. The word "[[reference]]" in this context refers to the task of providing assistance to library users in finding information, answering questions, and otherwise fulfilling users’ information needs. Reference work often but not always involves using [[reference work]]s, such as dictionaries, encyclopedias, etc.  This form of reference work expands reference services from the physical reference desk to a "virtual" reference desk where the patron could be writing from home, work or a variety of other locations.

The terminology surrounding virtual reference services may involve multiple terms used for the same definition.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Pace |first=A. |title=Virtual Reference: What's in a Name? |journal=Computers in Libraries |date=April 2003 |volume=23 |issue=4 |pages=55–56}}&lt;/ref&gt; The preferred term for remotely delivered, computer-mediated reference services is "virtual reference", with the secondary non-preferred term "digital reference" having gone out of use in recent years. "Chat reference" is often used interchangeably with virtual reference, although it represents only one aspect of virtual reference. Virtual reference includes the use of both synchronous (i.e., IM, videoconferencing) and asynchronous communication (i.e., texting and email). Here, "synchronous virtual reference" refers to any real-time computer-mediated communication between patron and information professional. Asynchronous virtual reference is all computer-mediated communication that is sent and received at different times.&lt;ref name="Kern"&gt;{{cite book |last=Kern |first=M.K. |title=Virtual Reference Best Practices: Tailoring Services to Your Library |place=Chicago |publisher=ALA |year=2009}} {{ISBN|978-0-8389-0975-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==

The earliest digital reference services were launched in the mid-1980s, primarily by academic and medical libraries, and provided by [[e-mail]]. These early-adopter libraries launched digital reference services for two main reasons: to extend the hours that questions could be submitted to the reference desk, and to explore the potential of campus-wide networks, which at that time was a new technology.

With the advent of the graphical [[World Wide Web]], libraries quickly adopted webforms for question submission. Since then, the percentage of questions submitted to services via webforms has outstripped the percentage submitted via email.

In the early- to mid-1990s, digital reference services began to appear that were not affiliated with any library. These digital reference services are often referred to as "AskA" services. Examples of AskA services are the [[Internet Public Library]], [http://mathforum.org/dr.math/ Ask Dr. Math], and [http://americanart.si.edu/search/search_ajoa.cfm Ask Joan of Art].

Providing remote-based services for patrons has been a steady practice of libraries over the years.  For example, before the widespread use of chat software, reference questions were often answered via phone, fax, email and audio conferencing. Email is the oldest type of virtual reference service used by libraries.&lt;ref name="Kern" /&gt; Library services in America and the UK are just now gaining visibility in their use of virtual reference services using chat software. However, a survey in America revealed that by 2001 over 200 libraries were using chat reference services.&lt;ref name="Chow"&gt;{{cite book |last=Chowdhury |first=G.G. |title=Librarianship: an introduction |place=London |publisher=Facet |year=2008|display-authors=etal}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
The rapid global proliferation of information technology (IT) often leaves libraries at a disadvantage in terms of keeping their services current. However, libraries are always striving to understand their user demographics in order to provide the best possible services.&lt;ref name="Chow" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Bro"&gt;{{cite book |last=Brophy |first=P. |title=The library in the twenty-first century |edition=2nd |place=London |publisher=Facet |year=2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Therefore, libraries continue to take notes from current [[cyberculture]] and are continually incorporating a diversified range of interactive technologies in their service repertoires. Virtual reference represents only one small part of a larger library mission to meet the needs of a new generation, sometimes referred to as the "Google Generation", of users who have grown up with the internet.&lt;ref name="Row"&gt;{{cite journal |last=Rowlands |first=I. |title=The Google generation: the information behaviour of the researcher of the future |journal=Aslib Proceedings |volume=60 |issue=4 |pages=290–310 |year=2008 |url=http://www.emeraldinsight.com/journals.htm?articleid=1733495&amp;show=abstract |doi=10.1108/00012530810887953}}&lt;/ref&gt; For instance, virtual reference may be used in conjunction with embedded [[Web 2.0]] (online social media such as [[Facebook]], [[YouTube]], [[blogs]], [[del.icio.us]], [[Flickr]], etc.) applications in a library's suite of online services.&lt;ref name="Xiao"&gt;{{cite journal |last=Xiao |first=N. |title=Web 2.0 as catalyst: Virtually reaching out to users and connecting them to library resources and services |journal=Issues in Science and Technology Librarianship |volume=55 |issue=Fall |year=2008 |url=http://www.istl.org/08-fall/article2.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; As technological innovations continue, libraries will be watching to find new, more personalized ways of interacting with remote reference users.

The range of cost-per-transaction of reference interactions has been found to be large, due to the differences in librarian salaries and infrastructural costs required by reference interviews.&lt;ref&gt;Murfin, Marjorie E. "Cost Analysis of Library Reference Services," Advances in Library Administration and Organization, 11, 1993, pp. 1–36.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Eakin, Lorraine, &amp; Pomerantz, Jeffrey. "[https://dx.doi.org/10.1353/pla.0.0035 Virtual Reference, Real Money: Modeling Costs in Virtual Reference Services]," portal: Libraries and the Academy, 9, 2009, pp. 133-164.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Forms of digital reference==

===Webforms===
Webforms are created for digital reference services in order to help the patron be more productive in asking their question.  This document helps the librarian locate exactly what the patron is asking for.  Creation of webforms requires design consideration.  Because webforms substitute for the reference interview, receiving as much information as possible from the patron is a key function.

Aspects commonly found within webforms:

*A return email address to send the answer to the question
*The question being asked
*The type of question
*What sources have been consulted by the patron
*How the patron is planning to use the information
*Location of the patron (are they a library patron?)
*A name to personalize the interaction
*A date by which the information is needed
*The type of sources being requested (print or electronic)&lt;ref&gt;Janes, Joseph. "Introduction to Reference Work in the Digital Age", pages 64-65. Neal-Schuman Publishers Inc., 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Chat using commercial applications===
Several applications exist for providing chat-based reference. Some of these applications are: [http://www.questionpoint.org/ QuestionPoint], [https://www.omnireference.com/ OmniReference], [http://tutor.com/ Tutor.com], [https://libraryh3lp.com/ LibraryH3lp], [http://aspiringkidz.com/ AspiringKidz.com], and [http://Vienova.com/ Vienova.com]. These applications bear a resemblance to commercial help desk applications. These applications possess functionality such as: chat, co-browsing of webpages, webpage and document pushing, customization of pre-scripted messages, storage of chat transcripts, and statistical reporting.

===Chat using instant messaging===
{{See also|chatbot|virtual assistant (artificial intelligence)}}
[[Instant messaging]] (IM) services are used by some libraries as a low-cost means of offering chat-based reference, since most IM services are free.  Utilizing IM for reference services allows a patron to contact the library from any location via the internet.  This service is like the traditional reference interview because it is a live interaction between the patron and the librarian.  On the other side the reference interview is different because the conversation does not float away but instead is in print on the screen for the librarian to review if needed to better understand the patron.  IM reference services may be for the use of in-house patrons as well as patrons unable to go to the library. If library computers support IM chat programs, patrons may IM from within the library to avoid losing their use of a computer or avoid making embarrassing questions public.

Successful IM reference services will:
*Create a profile to convey information about the library and increase online presence.
*Accept imperfection in conversations without spending time to go back and make corrections.  Most words are recognizable through context.
*Become familiar with and use accepted IM abbreviations such as LOL (Laugh Out Loud).
*Don't panic.  While speed is important it is more important to not feel rushed.&lt;ref&gt;Anderson, Rick. "IM Me", Library Journal 130 (April 1, 2005): 34-35.&lt;/ref&gt;

At times, IM becomes challenging because of lack of non-verbal cues such as eye contact, and the perceived time pressure. Moreover, formulating the question online without the give and take of nonverbal cues and face to face conversation presents an added obstacle. In addition, to provide effective reference service through IM, it is important to meet higher level of information literacy standards. These standards include evaluating the information and its source, synthesizing the information to create new ideas or products, and understanding the societal, legal, and economic issues surrounding its use.&lt;ref&gt;Desai, Christina M. &amp; Graves, Stephanie J. "Instruction via Instant Messaging reference: what’s happening?", The Electronic Library 24 (2) ( 2006): 174-189.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Software for providing digital reference==
The article [http://slj.reviewsnews.com/index.asp?layout=article&amp;articleid=CA251679 Live, Digital Reference Marketplace] by Buff Hirko contains a comparison of the features of applications for chat-based reference.

See the entries in the [http://www.libsuccess.org/index.php?title=Online_Reference Library Success Wiki's Online Reference Section], including software recommended for web-based chat reference, IM reference, SMS (text messaging) reference, and other types like digital audio or video reference.

===Software features===
Virtual service software programs offered by libraries are often unique, and tailored to the individual library's needs.&lt;ref name="Bro" /&gt; However, each program may have several distinct features. A [[knowledge base]] is a chunk of information that users can access independently. An example of this is a serialized listing of [[frequently asked questions]] (FAQ) that a user can read and use at his or her leisure.

Online chat, or [[instant messaging]] (IM) has become a very popular Web-based feature.  Instant messaging is a real time conversation that utilizes typed text instead of language.  Users may feel a sense of satisfaction with the use of this tool because of their personalized interaction with staff.

The use of electronic mail (email) in responding to reference questions in libraries has been in use for years.  Also, in some cases with the IM feature, a question may be asked that cannot be resolved in online chat.  In this instance the staff member may document the inquiring patron’s email address and will the user a response.

With the increase in use of text messaging ([[Short Message Service]] or SMS), some libraries are also adopting text messaging in their virtual reference services. [[Librarian]]s can use mobile phones, text-to-instant messaging or web-based services to respond to reference questions via text messaging.

[[Co-browsing]], or cooperative browsing, is a virtual reference function that involves interactive control of a user’s web browser. This function enables the librarian to see what the patron has on his or her computer screen. Several types of co-browsing have been offered in mobile devices of late; libraries may have software that incorporates dual modes of co-browsing in a variety of formats. For instance, it is possible to browse on a mobile device within and between documents (such as Word), webpages, and images.&lt;ref name="Hua"&gt;{{cite book |last=Hua |first=Z. |title="Chapter 2.10: A Cooperative Framework for Information Browsing in Mobile Environment". In: Taniar, D. (2008) Mobile Computing: Concepts, Methodologies, Tools, and Applications |place=London |publisher=Information Science Reference |pages=497–505 |year=2008 |url=http://www.igi-global.com/reference|display-authors=etal}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==The UK==

Virtual reference services are growing in popularity in the UK with more institutions accepting queries via email, instant messaging and other chat based services.&lt;ref name="Barry, E 2010 pp.40-55"&gt;Barry, E et al (2010) Virtual Reference in UK academic libraries: The virtual enquiry project 2008–2009, Library Review, Vol. 59 (1) pp.40-55&lt;/ref&gt; A study of the use of virtual reference within UK academic institutions showed that 25% currently offer a form of virtual reference, with 54% of academic institutions surveyed considering adding this service.&lt;ref name="Barry, E 2010 pp.40-55"/&gt;

UK public libraries were instrumental in some of the first steps towards UK-wide internet collaboration amongst libraries with the EARL Consortium (Electronic Access to Resources in Libraries) in 1995,&lt;ref&gt;Woodhouse, S. (1998) Delivering the New Public Library: the role of the EARL Consortium, INFOCUS 3(1)&lt;/ref&gt; in a time where internet access was a rare commodity for both library staff and the public. Resources were collated and lines of communication opened between libraries across the UK, paving the way for services all over the world to follow suit. There are now a number of area-specific reference services across the UK including Ask A Librarian (UK-wide, established in 1997), Ask Cymru (Welsh and English language service), Enquire (Government funded through the People's Network, also UK-wide),&lt;ref&gt;Berube, L. (2005) People's Network Enquire: virtual reference in England, World Library and Information Congress: 71st IFLA General Conference and Council, August 14th - 18th 2005, Oslo, Norway.&lt;/ref&gt; and Ask Scotland. Ask Scotland was created by the Scottish Government's advisory body on libraries, SLIC (Scottish Library and Information Council),&lt;ref&gt;SLIC homepage: http://www.slainte.org.uk/slic/slicindex.htm&lt;/ref&gt; and funded by the Public Library Quality Improvement Fund (PLQIF) in June 2009. It uses the [[Online Computer Library Center]]'s QuestionPoint software.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.questionpoint.org/ QuestionPoint.org]&lt;/ref&gt;

==American Library Association's digital reference guidelines==
The definition formulated by the American Library Association's (ALA) 2004 MARS Digital Reference Guidelines Ad Hoc Committee contains three components:

# "Virtual reference is reference service initiated electronically, often in real-time, where patrons employ computers or other Internet technology to communicate with reference staff, without being physically present. Communication channels used frequently in virtual reference include chat, videoconferencing, Voice over IP, co-browsing, e-mail, and instant messaging.
# While online sources are often utilized in provision of virtual reference, use of electronic sources in seeking answers is not of itself virtual reference.
# Virtual reference queries are sometimes followed-up with telephone, fax, in-person and regular mail interactions, even though these modes of communication are not considered virtual."&lt;ref name="MARS"&gt;{{cite journal |author=MARS Digital Reference Guidelines Ad Hoc Committee |year=2004 |title=Guidelines for Implementing and Maintaining Virtual Reference Services |journal=Reference and User Services Quarterly |volume=44 |issue=1 |pages=9–14 |url=http://www.ala.org/ala/mgrps/divs/rusa/resources/guidelines/virtrefguidelines.cfm}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In January 2011 [[QuestionPoint]] and the [[American Library Association]] were in talks about offering a National Ask A Librarian service across the whole United States of America.&lt;ref&gt;http://questionpoint.blogs.com/questionpoint_247_referen/2011/01/a-national-virtual-reference-service-for-the-us.html&lt;/ref&gt; At present the Ask services in the US are run at a local level.

==Other countries==
In Europe some countries offer services in both their own national language and in English. European countries include: Finland,&lt;ref&gt;Finnish National Libraries online reference service: http://www.libraries.fi/en-GB/ask/&lt;/ref&gt; the Netherlands (in Dutch only),&lt;ref&gt;The Netherlands online reference service: http://www2.bibliotheek.nl/home&lt;/ref&gt; Denmark,&lt;ref&gt;Danish Libraries homepage, with links to a virtual reference form: http://bibliotek.dk/?lingo=eng&lt;/ref&gt; and France.&lt;ref&gt;Public library of Lyon, France: http://www.guichetdusavoir.org/&lt;/ref&gt;

Other countries which offer virtual reference services include: Australia,&lt;ref&gt;National Library of Australia's Ask a Librarian service: http://www.nla.gov.au/askalibrarian/&lt;/ref&gt; New Zealand,&lt;ref&gt;National Library of New Zealand's Ask a Librarian service: http://www.natlib.govt.nz/services/get-advice/ask-a-librarian&lt;/ref&gt; Canada,&lt;ref&gt;National Library of Canada's virtual reference services: http://vrl.tpl.toronto.on.ca/&lt;/ref&gt; and the state of Colorado in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;Ask Colorado, the service from the state of Colorado in the USA: {{cite web|url=http://www.askcolorado.org/ |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2010-07-25 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100725045834/http://www.askcolorado.org/ |archivedate=2010-07-25 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Chasing the Sun==

A collaboration between UK and Australian library services, entitled Chasing the Sun,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.changechampions.com.au/resource/Sue_Rockliff.pdf PDF presentation by Chasing the Sun Co-chair Sue Rockliff]&lt;/ref&gt; has been initiated using [[QuestionPoint]] software so that an all-hours digital reference chat service can be offered.  Targeted at health libraries where reference queries from health professionals could occur at any time of the day or night due to medical emergencies, the collaboration between the two countries means that someone will be on hand to field the query at any time. Although the UK libraries involved are currently based in England the programme may expand to other countries and health services if successful.

==See also==
* [[Ask a Librarian]]
* [[Reference library]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
*Godfrey, Krista, K. "A new world for virtual reference." Library Hi Tech 26(4) (2008): 525-539.
*Ronan, J. "Application of Reference Guidelines in Chat Reference Interactions: A Study of Online Reference Skills." College &amp; undergraduate libraries 13.4 (2006): 3-23.
* Cummings, J., et al. User Preferences in Reference Services: Virtual Reference and Academic Libraries. portal: Libraries and the Academy. Vol. 7, No. 1 (2007), pp.&amp;nbsp;81–96. [http://hdl.handle.net/2376/1416] or [http://muse.jhu.edu/journals/portal_libraries_and_the_academy/v007/7.1cummings.html]
* Boss, R.W. (2007) Tech Notes: virtual reference, Public Library Association, ALA, [http://www.ala.org/ala/mgrps/divs/pla/plapublications/platechnotes/Virtual_reference.pdf http://www.ala.org/ala/mgrps/divs/pla/plapublications/platechnotes/Virtual_reference.pdf]
* Breeding, M. (2001) Providing virtual reference service, ''Information Today'', '''18''' (4), 42-43.
* Francoeur, S. (2002) The Teaching Librarian: Index of Chat Reference Services, [http://www.teachinglibrarian.org/chatsoftware.htm http://www.teachinglibrarian.org/chatsoftware.htm].
* Hua, Z., et al. (2008) Chapter 2.10: A Cooperative Framework for Information Browsing in Mobile Environment, In Taniar, D., ed. (2008) ''Mobile Computing: Concepts, Methodologies, Tools, and Applications'', London, Information Science Reference, [http://www.igi-global.com/reference http://www.igi-global.com/reference].
* Lindbloom, M.-C., ''et al.'' (2006) Virtual reference: A reference question is a reference question … or is virtual reference a new reality? New career opportunities for librarians, ''The Reference Librarian'', '''45''' (93), 3-22, [http://www.informaworld.com/openurl?genre=issue&amp;issn=0276-3877&amp;volume=45&amp;issue=93 http://www.informaworld.com/]. 
* Lipow, A.G. (2002) ''The Virtual Reference Librarian’s Handbook'', Neal-Schuman.
* Pomerantz, J. (2006). [https://dx.doi.org/10.5860/rusq.46n1.45 Collaboration as the Norm in Reference Work]. ''Reference &amp; User Services Quarterly'', 46(1), 45-55.
* Sears, J. (2001) Chat reference service: An analysis of one semester's data, ''Issues in Science and Technology Librarianship'', '''32''' (Fall), [http://www.library.ucsb.edu/istl/01-fall/article2.html http://www.library.ucsb.edu/istl/01-fall/article2.html].

==External links==
* [http://www.ala.org/ala/rusa/rusaprotools/referenceguide/definitionsreference.htm Reference and User Services Association's Definitions of a Reference Transaction]
* [http://www.libsuccess.org/index.php?title=Online_Reference Online Reference Section of the Library Success Wiki]
* {{LISWiki_link|Virtual reference}}
* [http://liswiki.org/wiki/Chat_reference_libraries Chat reference libraries] at the Library and Information Science (LIS) Wiki - list of libraries providing chat reference services
* [http://www.libsuccess.org/index.php?title=Library_Success:_A_Best_Practices_Wiki Library Success Best Practice Wiki] - provides a list of recommended IM chat client software 
* [http://www.ala.org/ala/professionalresources/libfactsheets/alalibraryfactsheet19.cfm Virtual Reference: A Selected Annotated Bibliography], ALA Library Factsheet 19. Last updated: November 2013.

===Software Vendors===
The following provide software and technology infrastructure for digital/virtual reference.
* [https://us.libraryh3lp.com/ LibraryH3lp], pronounced "library-help",&lt;ref&gt;http://lj.libraryjournal.com/2009/03/people/movers-shakers-2009/pam-sessoms-movers-shakers-2009-advocates/#_&lt;/ref&gt; provides an [[XMPP]] chat client and SMS gateway.&lt;ref&gt;http://journal.code4lib.org/articles/107&lt;/ref&gt;
* [https://omnireference.com/ OmniReference] is a cloud solution with a single dashboard that integrates Chat, SMS, Email, and Twitter virtual reference services.
* [http://www.textalibrarian.com Text a Librarian] powered by Mosio.

===Providers===
;Egypt
;* [http://www.questionmart.org QuestionMART], published by: Cybrarians: the Arabic Portal for Librarianship and Information.
;United States
* [[Ask a Librarian]], Florida state's virtual reference service, provides live chat with co-browsing and email functions.
* KnowItNow24x7,&lt;ref&gt;https://www.nytimes.com/learning/teachers/featured_articles/20020829thursday.html&lt;/ref&gt; Ohio's statewide live chat reference service with email with additional text message access. Service ceased operation December 31, 2015.&lt;ref&gt;https://library.ohio.gov/news/knowitnow24-7-service-ends-december-31/&lt;/ref&gt;
* [http://www.answerland.org/ Answerland], Oregon's statewide online chat and email reference service.
* [http://www.researchhelpnow.org Research Help Now],  Michigan Virtual Reference Collaborative Service.

;Canada
* [http://www.askon.ca Ask Ontario] is a collaborative virtual reference service for Ontario's college and public libraries, coordinated by [http://www.ocls.ca Ontario Colleges Library Service]. 
* [http://spotdocs.scholarsportal.info/display/sp/Ask Ask a Librarian] is a collaborative virtual reference service for Ontario's university libraries, coordinated by the [http://spotdocs.scholarsportal.info/display/sp/Home Scholars Portal operations team].

;United Kingdom
* [http://www.questionpoint.org/crs/servlet/org.oclc.home.TFSRedirect?virtcategory=10836 Enquire] is the UK's national 24/7 online reference service, serving over 80 English and Scottish public libraries.
* [http://library.open.ac.uk Open University Library] LivePerson
* [http://www.tees.ac.uk/lis/chat/ University of Teesside Library &amp; Information Services] - IM Reference 
* [http://www.nls.uk/info/readingrooms/askalibrarian.html Ask A Librarian (NLS)] provided by the National Library of Scotland
* [http://askscotland.org.uk/ Ask Scotland], Scotland's online reference service manned by librarians in Scotland.
* [http://www.nls.uk/using-the-library/ask-a-librarian] National Library of Scotland's 'Ask a Librarian' service
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20100911213641/http://www.dundeecity.gov.uk/library/asklaunch] PR release for launch of Ask Scotland services, from Dundee City Council 
* [http://library.wales.org/askcymru/en/] Ask Cymru, Welsh/English language virtual reference service

;Spain
* [http://bib.us.es/servicios/pregunte/ayuda_chat-ides-idweb.html Pregunte al bibliotecario] is the University of Seville, Spain, online reference service with LibraryH3lp program

;International 
* [http://liswiki.org/wiki/Chat_reference_libraries Chat reference libraries]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Digital Reference Services}}
[[Category:Library resources]]
[[Category:Reference]]</text>
      <sha1>4dc2a7udihhr0dhjvrxuzdwq1g9fvd4</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Hashtag</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>20819040</id>
    <revision>
      <id>870237855</id>
      <parentid>870230101</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-11-23T12:05:59Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>141.100.10.220</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment># is NOT a hashtag ffs</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="45047">{{For|the punctuation mark itself|Number sign}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=May 2016}}
{{Use American English|date=May 2016}}
[[File:Chris Messina - South by Southwest 2010 (1).jpg|alt=Chris Messina proposed the use of hashtags in his famous 2007 tweet. |thumb|Chris Messina. The inventor of the hashtag. |440x440px]]A '''hashtag''' is a type of [[Tag (metadata)|metadata tag]] used on [[Social networking service|social networks]] such as [[Twitter]] and other [[microblogging]] services, allowing users to apply [[wikt:dynamic#Adjective|dynamic]], [[user-generated content|user-generated]] tagging which makes it possible for others to easily find messages with a specific theme or content. Users create and use hashtags by placing the number sign or pound sign &lt;code&gt;#&lt;/code&gt; usually in front of a word or unspaced phrase in a message. The hashtag may contain letters, digits, and underscores.&lt;ref name="charset"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.hashtags.org/featured/what-characters-can-a-hashtag-include/|title=What Characters Can A Hashtag Include?|author=|date=|website=hashtags.org|accessdate=21 September 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Searching for that hashtag will yield each message that has been tagged with it. A hashtag archive is consequently collected into a single stream under the same hashtag.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Chang|first=Hsia-Ching|last2=Iyer|first2=Hemalata|title=Trends in Twitter - Hashtag Applications: Design Features for Value-Added Dimensions to Future Library Catalogues|url=http://muse.jhu.edu/article/485537|journal=Library Trends|volume=61|issue=1|pages=248–258|doi=10.1353/lib.2012.0024|issn=1559-0682}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, on the [[photo sharing|photo-sharing]] service [[Instagram]], the hashtag ''#bluesky'' allows users to find all the posts that have been tagged using that hashtag.  

The use of hashtags was first proposed by [[Chris Messina (open-source advocate)|Chris Messina]] in a 2007 tweet&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://twitter.com/chrismessina/status/223115412|title=🅲🅷🆁🅸🆂 🅼🅴🆂🆂🅸🅽🅰︎ on Twitter|work=Twitter|access-date=2018-11-10|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; that, although initially decried by Twitter as a "thing for nerds"&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.smithsonianmag.com/smart-news/decade-ago-hashtag-reshaped-internet-180964605/|title=A Decade Ago, the Hashtag Reshaped the Internet|last=Panko|first=Ben|work=Smithsonian|access-date=2018-11-10|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;, eventually led to their use spreading like wild-fire through the platform. Messina, who made no attempt to copyright the use because he felt "they were born of the internet, and owned by no one"&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.quora.com/Twitter-Hashtags-1/Why-didnt-the-creator-of-the-hashtag-patent-the-concept/answer/Chris-Messina|title=Chris Messina's answer to Why didn't the creator of the hashtag patent the concept? - Quora|website=www.quora.com|language=en|access-date=2018-11-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;, has subsequently been credited as the godfather of the hashtag.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2011/06/12/fashion/hashtags-a-new-way-for-tweets-cultural-studies.html?_r=1&amp;pagewanted=all|title=Twitter's Secret Handshake|author=Parker, Ashley|date=June 10, 2011|work=The New York Times|accessdate=July 26, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/technology-30340622|title=BBC News – Hashtag inventor: It was an 'accidental trip over a simple idea':|date=December 5, 2014|work=BBC|accessdate=2014-12-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.businessinsider.com/chris-messina-talks-about-inventing-the-hashtag-on-twitter-2013-11|title=The Inventor of the Twitter Hashtag Explains Why He Didn't Patent It|website=Business Insider|access-date=2016-03-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; By the end of the decade hashtags could be seen in most emerging as well as established social media platforms including Instagram, Facebook, Reddit, and YouTube. So much so that Instagram had to officially place a "30 hashtags" limit on its posts to prevent people from abusing their use,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://help.instagram.com/351460621611097|title=How do I use hashtags? {{!}} Instagram Help Center|website=help.instagram.com|language=en|access-date=2018-11-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; a limit which [[Instagrammer|Instagrammers]] eventually circumvented by posting hashtags in the comments section of their posts.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.itchban.com/blog/2017/1/7/instagram-max-hashtags-how-to-post-up-to-60|title=Instagram Max Hashtags: How to post up to 60|work=itchban|access-date=2018-11-10|language=en-AU}}&lt;/ref&gt; As of 2018 more than 85% of the top 50 websites by traffic on the Internet use hashtags&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.similarweb.com/top-websites|title=Website Ranking: Top Websites Rank In The World - SimilarWeb|website=www.similarweb.com|language=en|access-date=2018-11-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; and their use is highly common with [[millennials]], [[Generation Z|Gen Z]], politicians, [[Influencer marketing|influencers]], and celebrities worldwide. Because of its widespread use, ''hashtag'' was added to the ''[[Oxford English Dictionary]]'' in June 2014.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.theregister.co.uk/2014/06/13/hashtag_added_to_the_oed/|title='Hashtag' added to the OED – but # isn't a hash, pound, nor number sign|date=June 13, 2014|work=The Register}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://public.oed.com/the-oed-today/recent-updates-to-the-oed/june-2014-update/new-words-notes-june-2014/|title=New words notes June 2014|date=June 2014|work=Oxford English Dictionary|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20141007085108/http://public.oed.com/the-oed-today/recent-updates-to-the-oed/june-2014-update/new-words-notes-june-2014/|archivedate=October 7, 2014|deadurl=yes|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The term ''hashtag'' is also sometimes erroneously used to refer to the hash symbol itself when used in the context of a hashtag.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oed.com/view/Entry/389023#eid301493073|title=Oxford English Dictionary – Hash|date=June 2014|work=Oxford English Dictionary}}&lt;/ref&gt; Formal taxonomies can be developed from the folk taxonomy rendered [[machine-readable data|machine-readable]] by the markup that hashtags provide; this process is called [[folksonomy]].
== Origin and use ==
The [[Number sign|US pound sign, number sign or hash symbol]] "#" is often used in [[information technology]] to highlight a special meaning. ("Pound sign" in the UK means "[[£]]"; "#" is called hash, gate, and occasionally [[octothorpe]].) In 1970, for example, the number sign was used to denote ''immediate'' [[address mode]] in the assembly language of the [[PDP-11]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://programmer209.wordpress.com/2011/08/03/the-pdp-11-assembly-language/ |title=PDP-11 assembly language |publisher=Programmer209.wordpress.com |date=August 3, 2011 |accessdate=August 25, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; when placed next to a symbol or a number. In 1978, [[Brian Kernighan]] and [[Dennis Ritchie]] used ''#'' in the [[C (programming language)|C programming language]] for special keywords that had to be processed first by the [[C preprocessor]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=[[The C Programming Language]]|authors=B.W. Kernighan &amp; d. Ritchie|publisher=Prentice Hall|year=1978|pages=86 and 207|isbn=0-13-110163-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the 1986 [[SGML]] standard, ISO 8879:1986 (q.v.), # is a reserved name indicator (rni) which precedes keyword syntactic literals, --e.g., the primitive content token #PCDATA, used for parsed character data.[[File:Global Summit to End Sexual Violence in Conflict (14203190979).jpg|thumb|A sign suggesting the use of a #TimeToAct hashtag at a 2014 conference|alt=|440x440px]]

The International Telecommunication Union approved in November 1988 recommendation E.161 that put the hash sign on the right side of the 0 in the 4 x 3 button arrangement for push buttons on telephones. This same arrangement is still used today in most software phones (see Android dialer for example). The ITU recommendation had 2 design options for the hash: a European version where the hash sign was built with a 90-degree angle and a North-American version with an 80-degree angle. The North-American version seems to have prevailed as most hash signs in Europe now follow the 80-degree inclination.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url=https://www.itu.int/rec/dologin_pub.asp?lang=e&amp;id=T-REC-E.161-198811-S!!PDF-E&amp;type=items |title=Recommendation E.161 - Arrangement of figures, letters and symbols on telephones and other devices that can be used for gaining access to a telephone network  |publisher=ITU |date=November 25, 1988}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The pound sign was adopted for use within [[Internet Relay Chat|IRC]] networks circa 1988 to label groups and topics.&lt;ref&gt;"Channel Scope". Section 2.2. {{IETF RFC|2811}}&lt;/ref&gt; Channels or topics that are available across an entire IRC network are prefixed with a hash symbol # (as opposed to those local to a server, which use an [[ampersand]] '&amp;').&lt;ref&gt;{{cite IETF |title=Internet Relay Chat Protocol |rfc=1459 |sectionname=Channels |section=1.3 |page= |last1=Oikarinen |first1=Jarkko |authorlink1=Jarkko Oikarinen |last2=Reed |first2=Darren |authorlink2= |year=1993 |month=May |publisher=[[Internet Engineering Task Force|IETF]] |accessdate=June 3, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The use of the pound sign in IRC inspired&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cmu.edu/homepage/computing/2014/summer/originstory.shtml |title=#OriginStory|publisher=Carnegie Mellon University|date=August 29, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Chris Messina (open source advocate)|Chris Messina]] to propose a similar system to be used on Twitter to tag topics of interest on the microblogging network.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=https://www.nytimes.com/2011/06/12/fashion/hashtags-a-new-way-for-tweets-cultural-studies.html?_r=1&amp;pagewanted=all | title=Twitter's Secret Handshake | work=The New York Times | date=June 10, 2011 | accessdate=July 26, 2011 | author=Parker, Ashley}}&lt;/ref&gt; He posted the first hashtag on Twitter:
{{quote |1=How do you feel about using # (pound) for groups. As in #barcamp [msg]? |author = Chris Messina |source = ("factoryjoe"), August 23, 2007&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = https://twitter.com/factoryjoe/statuses/223115412|title = Twitter post|author = Chris Messina ("factoryjoe")|date = August 23, 2007&lt;!-- 3:25 PM--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; |width  = 50% |align  = center }}
Messina’s suggestion to use the hashtag was not adopted by Twitter, but the practice took off after hashtags were widely used in tweets relating to the [[2007 California wildfires#San Diego County|2007 San Diego forest fires]] in Southern California.&lt;ref&gt;[http://mashable.com/2013/10/08/what-is-hashtag/ What is hashtag?"], Mashable, 8 October 2013&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="factoryjoe"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://factoryjoe.com/2007/10/22/twitter-hashtags-for-emergency-coordination-and-disaster-relief/|title=Twitter hashtags for emergency coordination and disaster relief|website=Factory Joe|accessdate=September 16, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Messina, he suggested use of the hashtag to make it easy for "lay" users to search for content and find specific relevant updates; they were for people who do not have the technological knowledge to navigate the site. Therefore, the hashtag "was created organically by Twitter users as a way to categorize messages." &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Scott|first=Kate|date=May 1, 2015|title=The pragmatics of hashtags: Inference and conversational style on Twitter|url=http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S037821661500096X|journal=Journal of Pragmatics|volume=81|pages=8–20|doi=10.1016/j.pragma.2015.03.015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Today they are for anyone, either with or without technical knowledge, to easily impose enough annotation to be useful without needing a more formal system or adhering to many technical details.

Internationally, the hashtag became a practice of writing style for Twitter posts during the [[2009–2010 Iranian election protests]]; Twitter users inside and outside Iran used both English- and [[Persian language|Persian]]-language hashtags in communications during the events.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=The story of the hashtag began with Iranians|url=http://www.dw.de/حکایت-هشتگی-که-ایرانیان-آغاز-کردند/g-18012627|accessdate=March 12, 2015|publisher=Deutsche Welle Persian|date=2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The first published use of the term "hash tag" was in a blog post by Stowe Boyd, "Hash Tags = Twitter Groupings,"&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://stoweboyd.com/post/39877198249/hash-tags-twitter-groupings |title=Stowe Boyd, Hash Tags = Twitter Groupings |publisher=Stoweboyd.com |date= |accessdate=September 19, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; on August 26, 2007, according to lexicographer [[Ben Zimmer]], chair of the [[American Dialect Society]]'s New Words Committee.

Beginning July 2, 2009,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Twitter Makes Hashtags More #Useful|url=https://techcrunch.com/2009/07/02/twitter-makes-hashtags-more-useful/|accessdate=December 27, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Twitter began to hyperlink all hashtags in tweets to Twitter search results for the hashtagged word (and for the standard spelling of commonly misspelled words). In 2010, Twitter introduced "[[Twitter#Trending topics|Trending Topics]]" on the Twitter front page, displaying hashtags that are rapidly becoming popular. Twitter has an algorithm to tackle attempts to [[spamming|spam]] the trending list and ensure that hashtags trend naturally.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.allisayis.com/the-secret-of-twitters-trending-hashtags-with-insight-and-tips/ |title=The Secret of Twitter's Trending Hashtags With Insight and Tips |publisher=AllISayIs.com |date= |accessdate=December 3, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although the hashtag started out most popularly on Twitter as the main social media platform for this use, the use has extended to other social media sites including Instagram, Facebook, Flickr, Tumblr, and Google+.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.cnn.com/2013/06/12/tech/social-media/facebook-hashtags/index.html|title=Facebook finally gets #hashtags - CNN.com|last=Mashable|first=By Christina Warren|website=CNN|access-date=May 16, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Style ==
A hashtag must begin with a hash character followed by other characters, and is terminated by a space, or end of message. It is always safe to precede the “#” with a space, and to include letters without diacritics, digits, and underscores.{{r|charset}} In many cases other characters are also allowed, in particular accented characters used in many languages, but handling may vary from one client to another, and from time to time as standards evolve. A discussion of hashtag standards suggests that if #Romeo&amp;Juliet is used, different Twitter clients might link to #Romeo, #Romeo&amp;, or #Romeo&amp;Juliet.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://shkspr.mobi/blog/2010/02/hashtag-standards/ |title=Hashtag Standards|website=Terence Eden's Blog|date=25 February 2010|author=Terence Eden|accessdate= 21 September 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hashtags are not case sensitive; a search for “#hashtag” will find “#HashTag”. The use of embedded capitals ([[CamelCase]]) increases readability and avoids confusion; a (real) pen shop would be advised to use #PenIsland rather than all lower-case.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.penisland.net/ |title=Pen Island Pens - Home |website=Penisland.net |date=  |author= |accessdate= 21 September 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; On microblogging and social networking sites hashtags can be inserted anywhere within a text, often at the beginning or the end, but also within the text, usually as a word (e.g. “It is #sunny today”).

Languages which do not use letters are handled slightly differently. In China, microblogs [[Sina Weibo]] and [[Tencent Weibo]] use a double-hashtag-delimited #HashName# format, since the lack of spacing between [[Chinese characters]] necessitates a closing tag. [[Twitter]] uses a different syntax for Chinese characters and [[orthographies]] with similar spacing conventions: the hashtag contains unspaced characters, separated from preceding and following text by spaces (e.g. '我 #爱 你' instead of '我#爱你')&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Martin|first1=Rick|title=Twitter Rolls Out Hashtag Support for Japanese, Korean, Chinese, and Russian|url=https://www.techinasia.com/twitter-hashtag-languages/|accessdate=March 5, 2015|publisher=Tech in Asia|date=July 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; or by  [[zero-width non-joiner]] characters before and after the hashtagged element, to retain a linguistically natural appearance (displaying as unspaced '我&amp;#8204;#爱&amp;#8204;你', but with invisible non-joiners delimiting the hashtag).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=International services team|title=Right-to-left languages on Twitter|url=https://blog.twitter.com/2012/right-to-left-languages-on-twitter|accessdate=March 5, 2015|publisher=Twitter|date=April 5, 2012|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150402172013/https://blog.twitter.com/2012/right-to-left-languages-on-twitter|archive-date=April 2, 2015|dead-url=yes|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It is considered acceptable to tag a post once when contributing to a specific conversation. Two hashtags are considered acceptable when adding a location to the conversation. Three hashtags are seen by some as the "absolute maximum", and any contribution exceeding this risks "raising the ire of the community."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=What is a (#) Hashtag?|url=http://www.hashtags.org/how-to/history/what-is-a-hashtag/|publisher=Hashtags.org|date=24 June 2012|accessdate=February 22, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As well as frustrating other users, the misuse of hashtags can lead to account suspensions. Twitter warns that adding hashtags to unrelated tweets, or repeated use of the same hashtag without adding to a conversation, could cause an account to be filtered from search, or suspended.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Twitter Rules|url=https://support.twitter.com/groups/56-policies-violations/topics/236-twitter-rules-policies/articles/18311-the-twitter-rules|publisher=Twitter, Inc.|accessdate=September 22, 2017|quote=if you post multiple unrelated updates to a topic using # ...}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Jimmy Fallon]] and [[Justin Timberlake]] performed a sketch parodying the often incorrect and misunderstood use of hashtags on ''[[Late Night with Jimmy Fallon]]'' in September 2013.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=The Tonight Show Starring Jimmy Fallon |url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=57dzaMaouXA |title="#Hashtag" with Jimmy Fallon &amp; Justin Timberlake (Late Night with Jimmy Fallon) |publisher=YouTube |date=September 24, 2013 |accessdate=August 25, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Function ==

[[File:Seguir hashtags.png|thumb|Search bar in the header of a social networking site, searching for most recent posts containing the hashtag #science|alt=|440x440px]]

Hashtags are mostly used in unmoderated, ad hoc discussion forums; any combination of characters led by a hash symbol is a hashtag, and any hashtag, if promoted by enough individuals, can "trend" and attract more individual users to discussion. On Twitter, when a hashtag becomes extremely popular, it will appear in the "Trending Topics" area of a user's homepage. The trending topics can be organized by geographic area or by all of Twitter. Hashtags are neither registered nor controlled by any one user or group of users. They cannot be "retired" from public usage, meaning that any given hashtag can theoretically be used in perpetuity. They do not contain any set definitions, meaning that a single hashtag can be used for any number of purposes, as chosen by the creators of them.

Hashtags intended for discussion of a particular event tend to use an obscure wording to avoid being caught up with generic conversations on similar subjects, such as a cake festival using #cakefestival rather than simply #cake. However, this can also make it difficult for topics to become "trending topics" because people often use different spelling or words to refer to the same topic. For topics to trend, there has to be a consensus, whether silent or stated, that the hashtag refers to that specific topic.

Hashtags also function as beacons in order for users to find and "follow" (subscribe) or "list" (organize into public contact lists) other users of similar interest.

Television broadcasters such as [[Channel 4]] have employed the hashtag during the transmission of programmes such as [[First Dates]] and [[The Undateables]]. Research has shown that audience numbers go up when individuals can be interactive by tweeting while viewing a programme.

Hashtags can be used on the social network [[Instagram]], by posting a picture and hashtagging it with its subject. As an example, a photo of oneself and a friend posted to the social network can be hashtagged #bffl or #friends. Instagram has banned certain hashtags, some because they are too generic, such as #photography #iPhone #iphoneography, and therefore do not fulfill a purpose. They have also blocked hashtags that can be linked to illegal activities, such as drug use.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/technology-24842750 |title=Instagram banned hashtags | date = November 7, 2013|publisher=[[BBC.co.uk]] |accessdate=November 25, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ban against certain hashtags has a consequential role in the way that particular [[subaltern]] communities are built and maintained on Instagram. Despite Instagram's content policies, users are finding creative ways of maintaining their practices and ultimately circumventing censorship.&lt;ref&gt;Olszanowski, M. (2014). "Feminist Self-Imaging and Instagram: Tactics of Circumventing Sensorship{{sic|hide=y}}". ''Visual Communication Quarterly,'' 21(1), 83–95. Retrieved February 8, 2015, from http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/15551393.2014.928154#.VNgGT7DF-7FF-7F&lt;/ref&gt;

Famous Youtube bloggers often use hashtags to promote their videos to a wide audience. Thus, by leaving various hashtags under the video, they are trying to increase their views and gain as many likes as possible. Usually, hashtags are left under the video itself in a special line. By clicking on the hashtag you go directly to the link to the video, which are similar in topic.

Hashtags are also used informally to express context around a given message, with no intent to categorize the message for later searching, sharing, or other reasons. One of the functions of the hashtag is to serve as a reflexive meta-commentary, which contributes to the idea of how written communication in new media can be paralleled to how pragmatic methodology is applied to speech.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.linguistics.fi/julkaisut/SKY2014/Wikstrom.pdf|title=#srynotfunny: Communicative Functions of Hashtags on Twitter|last=Wikström|first=Peter|date=2014|work=SKY Journal of Linguistics|publisher=|access-date=May 15, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

This can help express contextual cues or offer more depth to the information or message that appears with the hashtag. "My arms are getting darker by the minute. #toomuchfaketan". Another function of the hashtag can be used to express personal feelings and emotions. For example, with "It's Monday!! #excited #sarcasm" in which the adjectives are directly indicating the emotions of the speaker. It can also be used as a disclaimer of the information that the hashtag accompanies, as in, "BREAKING: US GDP growth is back! #kidding". In this case, the hashtag provides an essential piece of information in which the meaning of the utterance is changed entirely by the disclaimer hashtag. This may also be conveyed with #sarcasm, as in the previous example. Self-mockery is another informal function of the hashtag used by writers, as in this tweet: "Feeling great about myself till I met an old friend who now races at the Master's level. Yup, there's today's #lessoninhumility," where the informality of the hashtag provides commentary on the tweet itself.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.skase.sk/Volumes/JTL28/pdf_doc/05.pdf|title=The ‘hashtag’: A new word or a new rule?|last=Caleffi|first=Paola-Maria|date=|website=Skase Journal of Theoretical Linguistics|publisher=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Other uses ==
The feature has been added to other, non-short-message-oriented services, such as the user comment systems on [[YouTube]] and [[Gawker Media]]. In the case of the latter, hashtags for blog comments and directly submitted comments were used to maintain a more constant rate of user activity even when paid employees were not logged into the website.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://gawker.com/5382267/anarchy-in-the-machine-welcome-to-gawkers-open-forums|title = Anarchy in the Machine: Welcome to Gawker's Open Forums|author = Gabriel Snyder|publisher = Gawker|date = October 15, 2009&lt;!-- 3:25 PM--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.niemanlab.org/2009/10/got-a-tip-gawker-media-opens-tag-pages-to-masses-expecting-chaos/|title = Got a #tip? Gawker Media opens tag pages to masses, expecting "chaos"|author = Zachary M. Seward|publisher = Nieman Journalism Lab|date = October 15, 2009 &lt;!-- 8 a.m. --&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; Real-time search aggregators such as the former [[Google Real-Time Search]] also support hashtags in syndicated posts, meaning that hashtags inserted into Twitter posts can be hyperlinked to incoming posts falling under that same hashtag; this has further enabled a view of the "river" of Twitter posts that can result from search terms or hashtags.{{citation needed|date=September 2014}}

== Uses ==

=== Broadcast media ===

The use of hashtags has extended to [[television]]{{nsmdns}}a concept that began rising in prominence in the early 2010s. Broadcasters may display a hashtag as an on-screen [[digital on-screen graphic|bug]], encouraging viewers to participate in a [[backchannel]] of discussion via social media prior to, during, or after the program. [[Television commercial]]s have sometimes contained hashtags for similar purposes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.tvguide.com/News/New-TV-Screen-1032111.aspx|title = New to Your TV Screen: Twitter Hashtags|date = April 21, 2011&lt;!-- 3:25 PM--&gt;|author = Michael Schneider|publisher = TV Guide}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hashtag bugs appear on either corner of the screen, or they may appear at the end of an advertisement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://mashable.com/2012/12/03/mcdonalds-tv-ad-twitter-hashtag/|title = McDonald's Releases First TV Ad With Twitter Hashtag|date = December 3, 2012|author = Todd Wasserman|publisher = Mashable}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While personalities associated with broadcasts, such as hosts and correspondents, also promote their corporate or personal Twitter usernames to receive mentions and replies to posts, usage of related or "branded" hashtags alongside Twitter usernames (e.g., [[The Ed Show|#edshow]] as well as [[Ed Schultz|@edshow]]) is increasingly encouraged as a microblogging style to "trend" the hashtag (and, hence, the discussion topic) in Twitter and other search engines. Broadcasters also make use of such a style to index select posts for live broadcast. Chloe Sladden, Twitter's director of media partnerships, identified two types of television-formatted usage of hashtags: hashtags which identify a series being broadcast (i.e. [[It's Always Sunny in Philadelphia|#SunnyFX]]) and instantaneous, "temporary" hashtags issued by television personalities to gauge topical responses from viewers during broadcasts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.fastcompany.com/1747437/twitter-tv-hashtag-tips-twitters-own-expert|title = Twitter TV Hashtag Tips From Twitter's Own Expert|author = Gregory Ferenstein|date = April 15, 2011|publisher = Fast Company}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some have speculated that hashtags might take the place of (or co-exist with) the [[Nielsen ratings|Nielsen television ratings system]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ibtimes.com/twitter-chatter-correlates-tv-ratings-good-or-bad-news-nielsen-1144311 |title=Twitter Chatter Correlates With TV Ratings, But Is That Good Or Bad News For Nielsen? |work=International Business Times |date=March 22, 2013 |accessdate=September 19, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

An example of trending "temporary" hashtags garnering viewers during broadcasts is observed on ''[[The Tonight Show]]'' with [[Jimmy Fallon]], a variety [[talk show]] on [[NBC]]. Every Wednesday, Fallon hosts a segment on his show called "Tonight Show Hashtags," which engages viewers by inviting them via Twitter to post humorous stories based on a specific hashtag topic, such as #WhydidIsaythat, #Worstfirstdate, to #Onetimeinclass, reflecting on funny experiences in daily life. By using hashtags, Fallon creates a sense of community and solidarity among his viewers and draws a wider range of viewers through an online platform while they watch a classic, non-interactive television program. Because of its popularity, the "Tonight Show Hashtags" are usually the 'most tweeted hashtag' on Twitter, which promotes the show. By engaging viewers with a lighthearted subject and simple hashtags, Fallon can gauge topical responses from viewers during broadcasts and also use the hashtags to brand his show.{{citation needed|date=April 2016}}

The increased usage of hashtags as brand promotion devices has been compared to the promotion of branded "[[Index term|keywords]]" by [[AOL]] in the late 1990s and early 2000s, as such keywords were also promoted at the end of television commercials and series episodes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = https://techcrunch.com/2012/06/10/twitter-hashtag-pages-aol-keywords/|title = Twitter's Hashtag Pages Could Be The New AOL Keywords — But Better|author = Ryan Lawler|date = June 10, 2012|publisher = Techcrunch}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The late-night television comedy [[game show]] [[@midnight]] with [[Chris Hardwick]] on [[Comedy Central]] features a daily game entitled "Hashtag Wars," in which three comedians compete against one another to come up with phrases based on a given hashtag theme.

Some hashtags have become famous worldwide. For instance the slogan "''[[Je suis Charlie]],''" which was first used on Twitter as the hashtag #jesuischarlie and #iamcharlie to indicate solidarity with ''Charlie Hebdo'' offices attacked in Paris, spread to the internet at large.

=== Purchasing ===

Since February 2013 Twitter and [[American Express]] have collaborated to enable users to pay for discounted goods online by tweeting a special hashtag.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | first = Kelly | last = Heather | title = Twitter and Amex let you pay with a hashtag | date = February 12, 2013 | url = http://edition.cnn.com/2013/02/11/tech/social-media/twitter-hashtag-purchases/| work = CNN | accessdate = November 25, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; American Express members can sync their card with Twitter and pay for offers by tweeting; American Express tweets a response to the member that confirms the purchase.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://sync.americanexpress.com/Twitter/Index |title=Sync with Twitter |publisher=Amex Sync |accessdate=November 25, 2013 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131125121304/https://sync.americanexpress.com/Twitter/Index |archive-date=November 25, 2013 |dead-url=yes |df=mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Event promotion ===

[[File:Occupy for Rights.JPG|thumb|[[Stencil graffiti]] promoting the hashtag #OccupyForRights|alt=|440x440px]]

Organized real-world events have used hashtags and ad hoc lists for discussion and promotion among participants. Hashtags are used as beacons by event participants to find each other, both on Twitter and, in many cases, during actual physical events.

Companies and advocacy organizations have taken advantage of hashtag-based discussions for promotion of their products, services or campaigns.

Political protests and campaigns in the early 2010s, such as [[Occupy Wall Street|#OccupyWallStreet]] and [[2011 Libyan civil war|#LibyaFeb17]], have been organized around hashtags or have made extensive usage of hashtags for the promotion of discussion. Hashtags have also been used to promote official events; the [[Ministry for Foreign Affairs (Finland)|Finnish Ministry of Foreign Affairs]] officially titled the [[2018 Russia–United States summit]] as the "#HELSINKI2018 Meeting".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://um.fi/helsinki2018|title=#HELSINKI2018 - Ministry for Foreign Affairs|website=um.fi|access-date=2018-07-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Consumer complaints ===
Hashtags are often used by consumers on social media platforms  to complain about the customer service experience with large companies. The term "bashtag" has been created to describe situations in which a user refers to a corporate social media hashtag  to criticise the company or to tell others about poor customer service. For example, in January 2012, [[McDonald's]] created the #McDStories hashtag so that customers could share positive experiences about the restaurant chain. But, the marketing effort was cancelled after two hours when McDonald's received numerous complaint tweets rather than the positive stories they were anticipating.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | first = Alexis | last = Akwagyiram | title = Are Twitter and Facebook changing the way we complain? | date = May 17, 2012 | url = https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-18081651 | work = BBC News | accessdate = June 12, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Sentiment analysis ===
The use of hashtags also reveals what feelings or sentiment an author attaches to a statement. This can range from the obvious, where a hashtag directly describes the state of mind, to the less obvious. For example, words in hashtags are the strongest predictor of whether or not a statement is [[sarcasm|sarcastic]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Maynard|title=Who cares about sarcastic tweets? Investigating the impact of sarcasm on sentiment analysis|journal=Proceedings of the Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation|year=2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;—a difficult [[Artificial Intelligence|AI]] problem.&lt;ref name="huffingtonpost"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/entry/power-yourself-with-viral-marketing-become-a-hashtag_us_57bf13e6e4b06384eb3e7f1d?dxrywr9zcw30rizfr|title=Power yourself with viral marketing - become a HashTag Genius &amp;#124; HuffPost|website=huffingtonpost.com|accessdate=September 16, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Sports ===
The YouTuber Spencer FC used the hashtag for the name and crest of his YouTube-based association football team, [[Hashtag United F.C.]].

Since the 2012–13 season, the [[National Basketball Association]] (NBA) has allowed fans to vote players in as All-Star Game starters on Twitter and Facebook using #NBAVOTE. The tweets and Facebook posts must include #NBAVOTE along with the player's first and last name or Twitter handle.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.nba.com/2013/news/11/15/2014-nba-all-star-ballot-official-release/|title=NBA and Sprint tip off NBA All-Star Balloting 2014|last=|first=|date=November 15, 2013|website=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== In popular culture ==
During the [[2011 Canadian leaders debates|April 2011 Canadian party leader debate]], [[Jack Layton]], then-leader of the [[New Democratic Party of Canada|New Democratic Party]], referred to [[Conservative Party of Canada|Conservative]] Prime Minister [[Stephen Harper]]'s crime policies as "a hashtag fail" (presumably #fail).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url = https://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/politics/jack-laytons-debatable-hashtag-fail/article576224/|title = Jack Layton's debatable 'hashtag' #fail|author = Anna Mehler Paperny|publisher = The Globe and Mail|date = April 13, 2011 &lt;!-- , 6:00 AM EDT --&gt; }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url = http://www.cbc.ca/news/politics/canadavotes2011/story/2011/04/13/cv-debate-twitter.html|title = Canadians atwitter throughout debate|date = April 13, 2011&lt;!-- 3:25 PM--&gt;|publisher = CBC News}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The term "hashtag [[Hip hop music|rap]]", coined by [[Kanye West]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://blogs.villagevoice.com/music/2010/11/the_ten_best_qu.php|title = The Ten Best Quotes From Kanye West's Epic Hot 97 Interview With Funkmaster Flex|author = Zach Baron|publisher = The Village Voice|date = November 3, 2010|access-date = July 22, 2013|archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20130722084923/http://blogs.villagevoice.com/music/2010/11/the_ten_best_qu.php|archive-date = July 22, 2013|dead-url = yes|df = mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; was developed in the 2010s to describe a style of rapping which, according to Rizoh of the ''[[Houston Press]],'' uses "three main ingredients: a metaphor, a pause, and a one-word [[punch line]], often placed at the end of a rhyme".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://blogs.houstonpress.com/rocks/2011/07/a_brief_history_of_hashtag_rap.php|title = A Brief History Of Hashtag Rap|author = Rizoh|publisher = Houston Press|date = July 7, 2011 &lt;!-- at 9:00 AM --&gt; }}&lt;/ref&gt; Rappers [[Nicki Minaj]], [[Big Sean]], [[Drake (rapper)|Drake]], and [[Lil Wayne]] are credited with the popularization of hashtag rap, while the style has been criticized by [[Ludacris]], [[The Lonely Island]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.tucsonweekly.com/TheRange/archives/2013/05/22/the-lonely-island-puts-hashtag-rap-in-its-place-looking-at-you-drake|title = The Lonely Island Puts Hashtag Rap In Its Place (Looking at You, Drake)|author = David Mendez|date = May 22, 2013 &lt;!-- AT 11:43 AM --&gt; |publisher = Tucson Weekly}}&lt;/ref&gt; and various music writers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.joplinglobe.com/enjoy/x1666506743/Jeremiah-Tucker-Hashtag-rap-is-2010s-lamest-trend|title = Jeremiah Tucker: Hashtag rap is 2010's lamest trend|author = Jeremiah Tucker|date = December 17, 2010|publisher = Joplin Globe}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On September 13, 2013, a hashtag, #TwitterIPO, appeared in the headline of a ''[[The New York Times|New York Times]]'' front-page article regarding Twitter's [[initial public offering]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| title = Twitter / nickbilton: My first byline on A1 of the …
| url = https://twitter.com/nickbilton/status/378534272962793472/photo/1
| accessdate = September 14, 2013
 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Bird's Eye]] foods released in 2014 a shaped [[mashed potato]] food that included forms of @-symbols and hashtags, called "Mashtags".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Birds Eye launches Mashtags – social media potato shapes|url=http://www.thegrocer.co.uk/fmcg/birds-eye-launches-mashtags-potato-shapes/354514.article|work=The Grocer}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Hashtags have been used verbally to make a humorous point in informal conversations,&lt;ref name="macmillandictionary"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.macmillandictionary.com/dictionary/british/hashtag|title=hashtag (noun) definition and synonyms|website=Macmillan Dictionary|accessdate=September 16, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; such as "I’m hashtag confused!"&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; In August 2012, British journalist Tom Meltzer reported in ''[[The Guardian]]'' about a new [[hand gesture]] that mimicked the hashtag, sometimes called the "finger hashtag", in which both hands form a [[Peace sign#The V sign|peace sign]], and then the fingers are crossed to form the symbol of a hashtag.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.theguardian.com/technology/shortcuts/2012/aug/01/how-to-say-hashtag-fingers |title=How to say 'hashtag' with your fingers |work=[[The Guardian]] |author=Tom Meltzer |date=August 1, 2012 |accessdate=March 20, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; The emerging gesture was reported about in ''[[Wired (magazine)|Wired]]'' by [[Nimrod Kamer]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.wired.co.uk/news/archive/2013-03/06/hashtags |title=Finger-Hashtags |work=[[Wired (magazine)|Wired]] |author=[[Nimrod Kamer]] |date=March 2013 |accessdate=March 20, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; and during 2013, it was seen on TV as used by [[Jimmy Fallon]], and on ''[[The Colbert Report]],'' among other programs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.dailydot.com/lol/finger-hashtag-jimmy-fallon-twitter/ |title=I invented finger hashtags—and I regret nothing |work=[[The Daily Dot]] |author=[[Nimrod Kamer]] |date=February 26, 2014 |accessdate=March 20, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Writing in 2015, Paola Maria Caleff considered this usage a [[fad]], but noted that people talking the way that they write was a consequence of computer-mediated communication.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

=== Adaptations ===
*Hashflags: In 2010, Twitter introduced "hashflags" during the 2010 World Cup in South Africa.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=|url=http://www.ryanseacrest.com/2010/06/11/twitter-supports-world-cup-fever-with-hashflags/ |title=Twitter Supports World Cup Fever with Hashflags |publisher=Ryanseacrest.com |date=June 11, 2010 |accessdate=August 5, 2015 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20101129201517/http://ryanseacrest.com/2010/06/11/twitter-supports-world-cup-fever-with-hashflags/ |archivedate=November 29, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; They reintroduced the feature on June 10, 2014, in time for the 2014 World Cup in Brazil,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://howto.digidefen.se/twitter/What-are-hashflags.php |title=What are Hashflags? |publisher=Howto.digidefen.se |date=June 10, 2014 |accessdate=August 25, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Ben Woods |url=https://thenextweb.com/twitter/2014/06/10/twitter-brings-back-hashflags-just-time-world-cup-2014-kick/ |title=Twitter brings back hashflags just in time for World Cup 2014 kick-off |publisher=Thenextweb.com |date=June 10, 2014 |accessdate=August 25, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; and then again on April 10, 2015, with UK political party logos for the 2015 UK General Election.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Twitter just launched election hashflags|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/newsbeat/article/32249518/twitter-just-launched-election-hashflags|website=BBC News|accessdate=April 15, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; When a user tweets a hashtag consisting of the three letter country code of any of the 32 countries represented in the tournament, Twitter automatically embeds a flag emoticon for that country. A similar system was implemented for the 2015 [[Eurovision Song Contest]] in Vienna, Austria.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Eurovision Twitter hashflags go live!|url=http://www.eurovision.tv/page/news?id=eurovision_twitter_hashflags_go_live|website=eurovision.tv|accessdate=February 22, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Cashtags: In 2009, [[StockTwits]] used [[ticker symbol]]s preceded by the [[dollar sign]] to create "cashtags".&lt;ref name=Wong2012&gt;{{cite journal |author=Wong, Matthew |title=VCs and Start-Ups Pin Their Hopes on Pinterest |date=August 17, 2012 |work=[[The Wall Street Journal]] |url=https://blogs.wsj.com/venturecapital/2012/08/17/vcs-and-start-ups-pin-their-hopes-on-pinterest/ |accessdate=May 28, 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Taylor2012&gt;{{cite journal |author=Taylor, Colleen |title=Howard Lindzon on Why He Sold His Twitter Stock, And The 'Hijack' Of StockTwits’ Cashtags [TCTV] |date=July 1, 2012 |publisher=[[TechCrunch]] |url=https://techcrunch.com/2012/08/01/howard-lindzon-on-why-he-sold-his-twitter-stock-and-the-hijack-of-stocktwits-cashtags-tctv/ |accessdate=May 9, 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In July 2012, Twitter adapted the hashtag style to make company ticker symbols preceded by the dollar sign clickable (as in [[Apple, Inc.|$AAPL]]), a method that Twitter dubbed the "cashtag".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Kim |first=Erin |url=http://money.cnn.com/2012/07/31/technology/twitter-cashtag/ |title=Twitter unveils 'cashtags' to track stock symbols – Jul. 31, 2012 |publisher=Money.cnn.com |date=July 31, 2012 |accessdate=November 12, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url=https://www.theverge.com/2012/7/30/3205284/twitter-stock-ticker-cashtag-links-official |title=Twitter makes stock symbol $ 'cashtag' links official, following # and @ |publisher=The Verge |date=July 30, 2012 |accessdate=November 12, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; This is intended to allow users to search posts discussing companies and their stocks. This is also used for discussion of currency pairings on Twitter, e.g. using #USDGBP or $USDGBP,  when mentioning the US Dollar's level expressed in Pounds Sterling.

== See also ==
*[[Mention (blogging)|Mentioning]] a user's profile by using @ tagging in blogging.

== References ==

{{Reflist|30em}}

== External links ==

{{Commons category|Hashtags}}

* [//tools.wmflabs.org/hashtags/search/artandfeminism Wikipedia internal hashtag search engine] – for hashtags used in edit summaries
* Veszelszki, Ágnes 2016: [https://www.academia.edu/30714144/Veszelszki_%C3%81gnes_2016_time_truth_tradition._An_image-text_relationship_on_Instagram_photo_and_hashtag._In_Benedek_Andr%C3%A1s_Veszelszki_%C3%81gnes_eds._In_the_Beginning_was_the_Image_The_Omnipresence_of_Pictures_Time_Truth_Tradition._Frankfurt_am_Main_Peter_Lang_139-150 #time, #truth, #tradition. An Image-text Relationship on Instagram: photo and hashtag]. In: Benedek, András; Veszelszki, Ágnes (eds.): In the Beginning was the Image: The Omnipresence of Pictures: Time, Truth, Tradition. Frankfurt am Main: Peter Lang GmbH, Internationaler Verlag der Wissenschaften, pp.&amp;nbsp;139–150.
* [https://keywordtool.io/instagram Tool for generating Instagram hashtags] – for hashtags used on Instagram posts
* [https://kparser.com/youtube-keyword-tool/ Tool for generating youtube hashtags] - can be used in youtube videos` description, title, hashtags


{{Microblogging}}
{{Online social networking}}
{{Web syndication}}
{{authority control}}

[[Category:Hashtags| ]]
[[Category:2010s slang]]
[[Category:Collective intelligence]]
[[Category:Computer jargon]]
[[Category:Information retrieval techniques]]
[[Category:Knowledge representation]]
[[Category:Metadata]]
[[Category:Reference]]
[[Category:Social media]]
[[Category:Web 2.0]]
[[Category:Twitter]]</text>
      <sha1>n13h8z0su7pkl1zdyb8ptbyqw31m6c3</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Informationsdienst Wissenschaft</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>15293025</id>
    <revision>
      <id>849479971</id>
      <parentid>813833882</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-07-09T09:10:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Idw.p</username>
        <id>19395956</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Updated number of press releases, subscribers, journalists.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="4145">{{refimprove|date=February 2009}}
'''Informationsdienst Wissenschaft e.V.''' or idw (The Science Information Service) operates an Internet platform, which bundles the press reports and dates of important events from about 1,000 scientific institutions, including universities, technical colleges, governmental and non-governmental research institutes and institutes to support research or scientific administration. idw (a registered charitable society) also operates an expert broker, the idw expert finder, which is exclusively for journalists. This makes idw one of the most comprehensive sources of science news in the German-speaking area. Foreign journalists and institutions (mostly European) now use idw as well. 
[[Image: new idw-logo.png|thumb|Informationsdienst Wissenschaft e.v.]] 

The two main objectives of idw are:
* To provide the public with a comprehensive picture of science in the German-speaking area.
* To create a close network between the linked (research) institutions.

==Services==
The information in idw can be accessed free of charge - either directly on idw’s www pages, or by using an individually configurable RSS feed or as an e-mail subscriber. Any user can request the information covering the topics and regions which interest him. All idw services can be used free of cost - the current news ticker, the science calendar, research in the archive (which contains more than 350,000 press releases), and the list of institutions linked to idw. idw also provides journalists with instruments for contacting experts, and maintains a database with science photos.
The members' press offices have various possibilities of communicating with journalists. Membership is only offered to German or foreign institutions which perform research or teaching, or which support science or are active in science in some other way.

==Idea and Foundation==
The original idea of idw was to provide experts for journalists. Using the American ProfNet as example,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Heisser Draht zur Forschung |url=http://www.spiegel.de/unispiegel/studium/0,1518,140281,00.html |work=[[Der Spiegel]] |date=19 June 2001 |accessdate=17 November 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; the press officers of [http://www.uni-bayreuth.de Universitaet Bayreuth], the [[Ruhr University Bochum]] and the Clausthal University of Technology, in collaboration with Computing Centre of Clausthal University of Technology/[http://www.tu-clausthal.de TU Clausthal], developed a concept for a German language network, by means of the new media. The concept was technically implemented by the staff of the Computing Centre of the Clausthal University of Technology. A total of nine staff members in Bayreuth, Bochum and Clausthal are responsible for programming, maintaining and developing the idw operating system, for user services and further development of the content.

==Financial Support and Development==
The initial phase (1996–1999) was guaranteed by project support from the Federal Ministry for Education and Research ([[BMBF]]). The technical development of the idw was supported by the Ministry, together with the [http://www.stifterverband.de Stifterverband fuer die Deutsche Wissenschaft] (Donor Association for German Science). idw has been working closely for years with the initiative [[Wissenschaft im Dialog]] (Science in Dialogue). idw has been economically independent since 2000 and is financed by contributions from member institutions. It has been organised as a registered charitable society (gemeinnütziger e. V.) since 2002.

==Significance and Scope==
idw has developed as a recognised and accepted source for German language science and for science journalism. It has become an instrument for public relations work for scientific institutions. 
About 37,000 subscribers (figure for June 2018&lt;ref&gt;http://www.idw-online.de/en/aboutus&lt;/ref&gt;) receive regular reports from idw, including some 7,900 journalists. About 1,000 institutions publish their press reports and dates of important events via idw.

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*http://idw-online.de

[[Category:Publishing organizations]]
[[Category:Reference]]</text>
      <sha1>s3kcimml76ffe1bsqdwyiftdb2fx4r9</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Key Word in Context</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>41908</id>
    <revision>
      <id>801751346</id>
      <parentid>792820413</parentid>
      <timestamp>2017-09-21T16:35:07Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Henningta</username>
        <id>16440880</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Typo</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="5400">'''KWIC''' is an acronym for '''Key Word In Context''', the most common format for [[concordance (publishing)|concordance]] lines. The term KWIC was first coined by [[Hans Peter Luhn]].&lt;ref&gt;Manning, C. D., Schütze, H.: "Foundations of Statistical Natural Language Processing", p.35. The MIT Press, 1999&lt;/ref&gt; The system was based on a concept called ''keyword in titles'' which was first proposed for Manchester libraries in 1864 by [[Andrea Crestadoro]].&lt;ref name="index"&gt;{{cite book|title=Advanced Indexing and Abstracting Practices|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=nIUkl7bLzYUC&amp;pg=PA41&amp;dq=Andrea+Crestadoro#v=onepage&amp;q=Andrea%20Crestadoro&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A '''KWIC''' index is formed by sorting and aligning the words within an article title to allow each word (except the [[stop words]]) in titles to be searchable alphabetically in the index.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.janda.org/workshop/content%20analysis/kwic.htm&lt;/ref&gt; It was a useful indexing method for technical manuals before computerized [[full text search]] became common.

For example, a search query including all of the words in the title statement of this article ("KWIC is an acronym for Key Word In Context, the most common format for concordance lines") and the [[Wikipedia:Slogans|Wikipedia slogan]] in English ("the free encyclopedia"), searched against this very web page, might yield a KWIC index as follows. A KWIC index usually uses a wide layout to allow the display of maximum 'in context' information (not shown in the following example).

{| nowrap
|-
|align=right|KWIC is an
|'''acronym''' for Key Word In Context, ...
|page 1
|-
|align=right|... Key Word In Context, the most 
|'''common''' format for concordance lines.
|page 1
|-
|align=right|... the most common format for 
|'''concordance''' lines.
|page 1
|-
|align=right|... is an acronym for Key Word In 
|'''Context''', the most common format ...
|page 1
|-
|align=right|Wikipedia, The Free 
|'''Encyclopedia'''
|page 0
|-
|align=right|... In Context, the most common 
|'''format''' for concordance lines.
|page 1
|-
|align=right|Wikipedia, The 
|'''Free''' Encyclopedia
|page 0
|-
|align=right|KWIC is an acronym for 
|'''Key''' Word In Context, the most ...
|page 1
|-
|&amp;nbsp;
|'''KWIC''' is an acronym for Key Word ...
|page 1
|-
|align=right|... common format for concordance 
|'''lines'''.
|page 1
|-
|align=right|... for Key Word In Context, the 
|'''most''' common format for concordance ...
|page 1
|-
|&amp;nbsp;
|'''Wikipedia''', The Free Encyclopedia
|page 0
|-
|align=right|KWIC is an acronym for Key
|'''Word''' In Context, the most common ...
|page 1
|}

A KWIC index is a special case of a ''permuted index''.&lt;ref&gt;http://infohost.nmt.edu/tcc/help/lang/python/examples/kwic/web/theory.html&lt;/ref&gt; This term refers to the fact that it indexes all [[cyclic permutation]]s of the headings. Books composed of many short sections with their own descriptive headings, most notably collections of [[Manual page (Unix)|manual pages]], often ended with a '''permuted index''' section, allowing the reader to easily find a section by any word from its heading. This practice, also known as '''KWOC''' (“'''Key Word Out of Context'''”), is no longer common.

&lt;gallery&gt;
KWAC.png|Keyword alongside context (KWAC)
KWIC.png|Keyword in context (KWIC)
KWOC.png|Keyword out of context (KWOC)
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==References in literature==

''Note: The first reference does not show the KWIC index unless you pay to view the paper. The second reference does not even list the paper at all.''

* [[David Parnas|David L. Parnas]] uses a KWIC Index as an example on how to perform modular design in his paper [http://portal.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=361623&amp;coll=ACM&amp;dl=ACM&amp;CFID=9516243&amp;CFTOKEN=98251202 ''On the Criteria To Be Used in Decomposing Systems into Modules''], available as an [http://www.acm.org/classics/may96/ ACM Classic Paper]
* Christopher D. Manning and Hinrich Schütze describe a KWIC index and computer concordancing in section 1.4.5 of their book ''Foundations of Statistical Natural Language Processing''. Cambridge, Mass: MIT Press, 1999. {{ISBN|9780262133609}}. They cite an article from H.P. Luhn from 1960, "Key word-in-context index for technical literature (kwic index)".
* According to Rev. Gerard O'Connor's ''[http://www.clerus.org/clerus/dati/2004-09/13-13/CIMR1.htm Concordantia et Indices Missalium Romanorum]'', "Most of the concordances produced in recent times and with the aid of computer software use both the KWIC (keyword in context) and KWICn (keyword in center) formats, which lists the keyword, usually highlighted in bold text in a consistent position, within a limited amount of context text, i.e. three [or] four words of the text prior to the keyword and the same amount of text following. This format is extremely useful in that the keyword is easily identified together with its context. ... The Concordance of the Roman Missal is produced in both the KWIC and KWICn formats and is noteworthy in that each word form is listed as it appears in the text, that is, it is un-lemmatized."

==See also==
* &lt;tt&gt;[[Ptx (Unix)|ptx]]&lt;/tt&gt;, a Unix command-line utility producing a [[permuted index]]
*[[Concordancer]]
*[[Concordance (publishing)]]
*[[Burrows–Wheeler transform]]
*[[Hans Peter Luhn]]
*[[Suffix tree]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

[[Category:Index (publishing)]]
[[Category:Reference]]
[[Category:Concordances (publishing)]]</text>
      <sha1>91eq809ugyym98bxmhxhp09f7z16ipe</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Note (typography)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>330432</id>
    <revision>
      <id>869439617</id>
      <parentid>869438298</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-11-18T16:52:04Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Clean Copy</username>
        <id>700572</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Numbering and symbols */ combine alternate symbol lists</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="16617">{{Redirect|Endnote}}
{{Redirect|Footnote|the Israeli film|Footnote (film)}}
{{Selfref|For the usage of footnoting on [[Wikipedia]], see [[Wikipedia:Cite sources]] and [[Wikipedia:Footnotes]].}}
{{Punctuation marks|※|caption=reference mark}}

A '''note''' is a string of text placed at the bottom of a [[page (paper)|page]] in a book or document or at the end of a chapter, volume or the whole text.  The note can provide an author's comments on the main text or [[citation]]s of a reference work in support of the text, or both.

'''Footnotes''' are notes at the foot of the page while '''endnotes''' are collected under a separate heading at the end of a chapter, volume, or entire work.  Unlike footnotes, endnotes have the advantage of not affecting the layout of the main text, but may cause inconvenience to readers who have to move back and forth between the main text and the endnotes.

In some editions of the Bible, notes are placed in a narrow column in the middle of each page between two columns of biblical text.

== Numbering and symbols==

In English, a footnote is normally flagged by a [[superscript]]ed number immediately following that portion of the text the note references, each such footnote being numbered sequentially. Occasionally a number between brackets or parentheses is used instead, thus: [1], which can also be superscripted, as in Wikipedia's own citation style rendered within this very page.

Typographical devices such as the [[asterisk]] (*) or [[dagger (typography)|dagger]] (†) may also be used to point to footnotes; the traditional order of these symbols in English is [[Asterisk|*]], [[Dagger (typography)|†]], [[Double dagger (typography)|‡]], [[Section sign|§]], [[Vertical Bar|‖]], [[Pilcrow|¶]].&lt;ref&gt;Robert Bringhurst (2005).  ''The Elements of Typographic Style'' (version 3.1).  Point Roberts, WA: Hartley and Marks. pp 68–69.  Bringhurst goes on to say “But beyond the ... double dagger, this order is not familiar to most readers, and never was.”&lt;/ref&gt;  Other symbols, including the [[Number Sign|#]], [[Delta (letter)|Δ]], [[Lozenge|◊]], [[Arrow (symbol)|↓]], and [[Index (typography)|☞]], have also been used.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.livesandletters.ac.uk/papers/FOR_2005_04_001.pdf|author=William H. Sherman|title=Toward a History of the Manicule|accessdate=2013-06-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Many of these symbols are used, for example, in [[John Bach McMaster]], ''History of the People of the United States''&lt;/ref&gt; In documents like [[Public transport timetable|timetables]], many different symbols, letters and numbers may be used to refer the reader to particular notes.

== Academic usage==
Notes are most often used as an alternative to long explanatory notes that can be distracting to readers. Most literary style guidelines (including the [[Modern Language Association]] and the [[American Psychological Association]]) recommend limited use of foot and endnotes. However, publishers often encourage note references in lieu of parenthetical references. Aside from use as a bibliographic element, notes are used for additional information or explanatory notes that might be too digressive for the main text. Footnotes are heavily utilized in academic institutions to support claims made in academic essays covering myriads of topics.

In particular, footnotes are the normal form of citation in historical journals. This is due, firstly, to the fact that the most important references are often to archive sources or interviews which do not readily fit standard formats, and secondly, to the fact that historians expect to see the exact nature of the evidence which is being used at each stage.

The MLA (Modern Language Association) requires the superscript numbers in the main text to be placed following the punctuation in the phrase or clause the note is in reference to. The exception to this rule occurs when a sentence contains a dash, in which case the superscript would precede it.{{Citation needed|date=November 2014}}

Aside from their technical use, authors use notes for a variety of reasons:
* As signposts to direct the reader to information the author has provided or where further useful information is pertaining to the subject in the main text.
* To attribute a quote or viewpoint.
* As an alternative to parenthetical references; it is a simpler way to acknowledge information gained from another source.
* To escape the limitations imposed on the [[word count]] of various academic and legal texts which do not take into account notes. Aggressive use of this strategy can lead to a text affected by "foot and note disease" (a derogation coined by [[John Betjeman]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Rogers|first=Timothy|title=Rupert Brooke: Man and Monument|journal=English|year=1968|volume=17|issue=99|pages=79–84|url=http://english.oxfordjournals.org/content/17/99/79.full.pdf|accessdate=21 March 2011|doi=10.1093/english/17.99.79}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
Candida Lycett Green (Betjeman's daughter), quoted in [https://www.independent.co.uk/news/people/profiles/passedfailed-an-education-in-the-life-of-candida-lycett-green-writer-475699.html "Passed/Failed: An education in the life of Candida Lycett Green, writer"], interview by Jonathan Sale. ''The Independent'', Thursday 27 April 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Government documents==
The [[US Government Printing Office]] Style Manual devotes over 660 words to the topic of footnotes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Chapter 15: Footnotes, indexes, contents, and outlines | work=U.S. Government Printing Office Style Manual | url=http://www.gpo.gov/fdsys/pkg/GPO-STYLEMANUAL-2008/html/GPO-STYLEMANUAL-2008-17.htm | accessdate=October 26, 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[NASA]] has guidance for footnote usage in its historical documents.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=A Guide to Footnotes and Endnotes for NASA History Authors | work=NASA History Style Guide | url=https://history.nasa.gov/footnoteguide.html | accessdate=March 24, 2005 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!-- Editors: There are more examples/sources in https://web.archive.org/web/20030221040123/http://www.eia.doe.gov/neic/pubstyle/ch4_1.htm --&gt;

==Legal writing==
Associate Justice [[Stephen Breyer]] of the [[Supreme Court of the United States]] is famous in the American legal community for his writing style, in which he never uses notes. He prefers to keep all citations within the text (which is permitted in American legal citation).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | first= | last= | coauthors= | title=In Justice Breyer's Opinion, A Footnote Has No Place | date=1995-07-28 | publisher= | url =https://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE1DC163EF93BA15754C0A963958260 | work =[[The New York Times]] | pages = | accessdate = 2008-04-30 | language = }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Richard A. Posner]] has also written against the use of notes in judicial opinions.&lt;ref name=Posner2001&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Posner|first1=Richard A.|title=Against Footnotes|journal=Court Review|date=Summer 2001|url=http://aja.ncsc.dni.us/courtrv/cr38-2/CR38-2Posner.pdf|accessdate=2014-10-13|publisher=American Judges Association}}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Bryan A. Garner]], however, advocates using notes instead of inline citations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Oddi |first=Marcia |url=http://indianalawblog.com/archives/2005/01/indiana_courts_99.html |title=Indiana Courts - Footnotes in Judicial Opinions |publisher=The Indiana Law Blog |date=2005-01-07 |accessdate=2015-11-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==HTML==
[[HTML]], the predominant [[markup language]] for web pages, has no mechanism for marking up notes. Despite a number of different proposals over the years, and repeated pleas from the user base, the [[working group]] has been unable to reach a consensus on it. Because of this, [[MediaWiki]], for example, has had to introduce its own &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; tag for citing references in notes, an idea which has since also been implemented for generic use by the ''[[Nelson (HTML preprocessor)|Nelson]]'' HTML preprocessor.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Nelson HTML Preprocessor | url=http://nelsonhtml.com | accessdate=2009-06-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It might be argued that the [[hyperlink]] partially eliminates the need for notes, being the web's way to refer to another document. However, it does not allow citing to offline sources and if the destination of the link changes, the link can become dead or irrelevant.&lt;ref&gt;[[Jill Lepore]]. "[https://web.archive.org/web/20150125141230/http://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2015/01/26/cobweb The Cobweb]", ''[[The New Yorker]]'', 26 January 2015 issue. Retrieved 25 January 2015. Archived from [http://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2015/01/26/cobweb the original].&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
The sign is historically equal to the [[asterisks]] used by [[Aristarchus of Samothrace]] at the [[Musaeum|Mouseion at Alexandria]]. It was used for the critical editions of Homer's writings where it "marked a verse incorrectly repeated in another passage" and was used together with other signs such as the [[obelus]].&lt;ref&gt;L.D. Reynolds and N.G. Wilson. Scribes and Scholars: A guide to the Transmission of Greek and Latin Literature. Oxford University Press, 1991, 3rd edition, {{ISBN|0-19-872146-3}}, p. 10-11&lt;/ref&gt;

The London printer [[Richard Jugge]] is generally credited as the inventor of the footnote, first used in the [[Bishops' Bible]] of 1568.&lt;ref&gt;Chuck Zerby, ''The Devil's Details: A History of Footnotes'', 2007, {{ISBN|1931229058}}, p. 28 and ''passim''&lt;/ref&gt;

Early printings of the Douay Bible used two closely spaced colons (actually squared four dot punctuation mark U+2E2C) to indicate a marginal note.

==Literary device==
At times, notes have been used for their comical effect, or as a literary device.

* [[James Joyce]]'s ''[[Finnegans Wake]]'' uses footnotes along with left and right marginal notes in Book II Chapter 2. The three types of notes represent comments from the three siblings doing their homework: Shem, Shaun, and Issy.
* [[J.G. Ballard]]'s  "Notes Towards a Mental Breakdown," is one sentence ("A discharged Broadmoor patient compiles 'Notes Towards a Mental Breakdown,' recalling his wife's murder, his trial and exoneration.") and a series of elaborate footnotes to each one of the words.
*[[Mark Z. Danielewski]]'s ''[[House of Leaves]]'' uses what are arguably some of the most extensive and intricate footnotes in literature. Throughout the novel, footnotes are used to tell several different narratives outside of the main story. The physical orientation of the footnotes on the page also works to reflect the twisted feeling of the plot (often taking up several pages, appearing mirrored from page to page, vertical on either side of the page, or in boxes in the center of the page, in the middle of the central narrative).
* [[Flann O'Brien]]'s ''[[The Third Policeman]]'' utilizes extensive and lengthy footnotes for the discussion of a fictional philosopher, [[de Selby]]. These footnotes span several pages and often overtake the main plotline, and add to the absurdist tone of the book.
* [[David Foster Wallace]]'s ''[[Infinite Jest]]'' includes over 400 endnotes, some over a dozen pages long. Several literary critics suggested that the book be read with two bookmarks.  Wallace uses footnotes, endnotes, and in-text notes in much of his other writing as well.
*[[Manuel Puig]]'s ''Kiss of the Spider Woman'' (originally published in Spanish as ''El beso de la mujer araña'') also makes extensive use of footnotes.
*[[Garrison Keillor]]'s ''[[Lake Wobegon Days]]'' includes lengthy footnotes and a parallel narrative.
*[[Mark Dunn]]'s ''[[Ibid: A Life]]'' is written entirely in endnotes.
*[[Luis d'Antin van Rooten]]'s ''[[Mots d'Heures: Gousses, Rames]]'' (the title is in [[French language|French]], but when pronounced, sounds similar to the [[English language|English]] ''"Mother Goose Rhymes"''), in which he is allegedly the editor of a manuscript by the fictional François Charles Fernand d’Antin, contains copious footnotes purporting to help explain the nonsensical French text. The point of the book is that each written French poem ''sounds'' like an English [[nursery rhyme]].
*[[Terry Pratchett]] has made numerous uses within his novels. The footnotes will often set up running jokes for the rest of the novel.
*[[B.L.A.]] and [[G.B. Gabbler]]'s meta novel ''[[The Automation]]'' makes uses of footnotes to break the [[fourth wall]]. The narrator of the novel, known as "B.L.A.," tells the fantastical story as if true, while the editor, Gabbler, annotates the story through footnotes and thinks the manuscript is only a [[prose poem]] attempting to be a literary masterwork.
*[[Susanna Clarke]]'s ''[[Jonathan Strange &amp; Mr Norrell]]'' uses dozens of footnotes referencing a number of fictional books including magical scholarship and biographies.
*[[Jonathan Stroud]]'s ''[[The Bartimaeus Trilogy]]'' uses footnotes to insert comical remarks and explanations by one of the protagonists, Bartimaeus.
*[[Michael Gerber (parodist)|Michael Gerber]]'s ''[[Barry Trotter]]'' parody series used footnotes to expand [[one-line joke]]s in the text into paragraph-long comedic monologues that would otherwise break the flow of the narrative.
*[[John Green (author)|John Green]]'s ''[[An Abundance of Katherines]]'' uses footnotes in which he says: "[They] can allow you to create a kind of secret second narrative, which is important if, say, you're writing a book about what a story is and whether stories are significant."{{Citation needed|date=November 2014}}
* Dr Carol Bolton uses extensive footnotes to provide the modern reader with a cipher for a novel about the travels of the fictional Spanish traveller [https://www.researchgate.net/publication/275996974_Through_Spanish_Eyes_Robert_Southey's_Double_Vision_in_Letters_from_England_By_Don_Manuel_Alvarez_Espriella_%281807%29 Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella], an early 19th-century construct of Robert Southey's, designed to provide him with vehicle to critique the societal habits of the day.
*[[Jasper Fforde]]'s ''[[Thursday Next]]'' series exploits the use of footnotes as a communication device (the ''footnoterphone'') which allows communication between the main character’s universe and the fictional bookworld.
*[[Ernest Hemingway]]'s ''[[Natural History of the Dead]]'' uses a footnote to further satirize the style of a history while making a sardonic statement about the extinction of "humanists" in modern society.
*[[Pierre Bayle]]'s ''[[Dictionnaire Historique et Critique|Historical and Critical Dictionary]]'' follows each brief entry with a footnote (often five or six times the length of the main text) in which saints, historical figures, and other topics are used as examples for philosophical digression.  The separate footnotes are designed to contradict each other, and only when multiple footnotes are read together is Bayle's core argument for [[Fideism|Fideistic skepticism]] revealed.  This technique was used in part to evade the harsh censorship of 17th century France.
*[[Mordecai Richler]]'s novel ''[[Barney's Version (novel)|Barney's Version]]'' uses footnotes as a character device that highlights unreliable passages in the narration. As the editor of his father's autobiography, the narrator's son must correct any of his father's misstated facts. The frequency of these corrections increases as the father falls victim to both hubris and [[Alzheimer's disease]]. While most of these changes are minor, a few are essential to plot and character development.
*In [[Vladimir Nabokov]]'s ''[[Pale Fire]]'', the main plot is told through the annotative endnotes of a fictional editor.
*''[[Bartleby y Compañía]],'' a novel by [[Enrique Vila-Matas]], is stylized as footnotes to a nonexistent novel.
*The works of [[Jack Vance]] often have footnotes, detailing and informing the reader of the background of the world in the novel.
*[[Stephen Colbert]]'s ''[[I Am America (And So Can You!)]]'' uses both footnotes and margin notes to offer additional commentary and humor.
*[[Doug Dorst]]'s novel ''[[S. (Dorst novel)|S.]]'' uses footnotes to explore the story and relationship of characters V.M. Straka and F.X. Caldeira.

==See also==
* [[Annotation]]
* [[Citation]]
* [[Hyperkino]]
* [[Nota bene]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
*Denton, William (2014). ''Fictional Footnotes and Indexes''. Miskatonic University Press. 
*Grafton, Anthony (1997). ''The Footnote: A Curious History''. Cambridge, Massachusetts: [[Harvard University Press]]. {{ISBN|0-674-90215-7}}.
*Zerby, Chuck (2002). ''The Devil's Details: A History of Footnotes''. New York: Simon &amp; Schuster.

[[Category:Bibliography]]
[[Category:Reference]]
[[Category:Metadata]]</text>
      <sha1>ak7hjz2b5m8j59qrwzsbg7fftmjp49b</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Polymath (disambiguation)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>24673687</id>
    <revision>
      <id>782349815</id>
      <parentid>745167679</parentid>
      <timestamp>2017-05-26T10:13:07Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Dispenser</username>
        <id>2551723</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Fix invalid Wiktionary link and cleanup using [[tools:~dispenser/cgi-bin/dabfix.py|Dabfix]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="499">{{wiktionary|polymath|polymathic}}
A '''[[polymath]]''' is a person whose expertise spans a significant number of different subject areas and who has extraordinarily broad and comprehensive [[knowledge]].

'''Polymath''' may also refer to:

* [[Polymath (novel)|''Polymath'' (novel)]], 1974 novel by John Brunner
* [[Polymath Park]], resort in the Laurel Highlands of Pennsylvania, USA
* [[Polymath Project]], a particular collaborative mathematics project

{{disambiguation}}
[[Category:Reference]]</text>
      <sha1>5yukgd5jqiwq3fy9kv7p5odbqvtecj2</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Reference</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>20110874</id>
    <revision>
      <id>868584155</id>
      <parentid>868584152</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-11-13T03:37:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ClueBot NG</username>
        <id>13286072</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverting possible vandalism by [[Special:Contribs/Brinkisa|Brinkisa]] to version by TheRedBox. [[WP:CBFP|Report False Positive?]] Thanks, [[WP:CBNG|ClueBot NG]]. (3538275) (Bot)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="10206">{{other uses}}
{{pp-move-indef}}

'''Reference''' is a relation between objects in which one object designates, or acts as a means by which to connect to or link to, another object. The first object in this relation is said to ''refer to'' the second object. It is called a ''[[name]]'' for the second object. The second object, the one to which the first object refers, is called the ''[[referent]]'' of the first object. A name is usually a [[phrase]] or expression, or some other [[Symbol|symbolic representation]]. Its referent may be anything – a material object, a person, an event, an activity, or an abstract concept.

References can take on many forms, including: a thought, a sensory perception that is [[Hearing (sense)|audible]] ([[onomatopoeia]]), [[visual perception|visual]] (text), [[olfaction|olfactory]], or tactile, [[emotions|emotional state]], relationship with other,&lt;ref&gt;Treanor, Brian, ''Aspects of alterity: Levinas, Marcel, and the contemporary debate'', Fordham University Press, 2006, p.41&lt;/ref&gt; [[spacetime]] coordinate, [[symbolic system|symbolic]] or [[alpha-numeric grid|alpha-numeric]], a physical object or an energy projection. In some cases, methods are used that intentionally hide the reference from some observers, as in [[cryptography]].

References feature in many spheres of human activity and knowledge, and the term adopts shades of meaning particular to the contexts in which it is used. Some of them are described in the sections below.

==Etymology and meanings==
The word ''reference'' is derived from [[Middle English]] ''referren'', from [[Middle French]] ''référer'', from [[Latin]] ''referre'', "to carry back", formed from the [[prefix]] ''re''- and ''ferre'', "to bear".&lt;ref&gt;Klein, Ernest, ''A comprehensive etymological dictionary of the English language'', Vol II, Elsevier publishing company, Amsterdam, 1969, p.1317&lt;/ref&gt; A number of words derive from the same root, including ''refer'', ''[[referee]]'', ''referential'', ''[[referent]]'', ''[[referendum]]''.

The verb ''refer (to)'' and its derivatives may carry the sense of "link to" or "connect to", as in the meanings of ''reference'' described in this article. Another sense is "consult"; this is reflected in such expressions as [[reference work]], [[reference desk]], [[job reference]], etc.

== Semantics ==
{{further|Sense and reference|Theory of reference}}
[[File:Ogden semiotic triangle.png|thumb|right|220px|The [[triangle of reference]], from the influential book ''[[The Meaning of Meaning]]'' (1923) by [[C. K. Ogden]] and [[I. A. Richards]].]]
In [[semantics]], reference is generally construed as the relationships between [[noun]]s or [[pronoun]]s and objects that are named by them. Hence, the [[word]] "John" refers to the person John. The word "it" refers to some previously specified object. The object referred to is called the ''[[referent]]'' of the word.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title = Semantics|first = John | last = Saeed|page = 12|publisher = Blackwell |isbn = 0-631-22693-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sometimes the word-object relation is called "[[denotation]]"; the word denotes the object. The converse relation, the relation from object to word, is called "[[exemplification]]"; the object exemplifies what the word denotes. In syntactic analysis, if a word refers to a previous word, the previous word is called the "[[Antecedent (grammar)|antecedent]]".

===Meaning===
[[Gottlob Frege]] argued that reference cannot be treated as identical with [[meaning (linguistics)|meaning]]: "[[Hesperus]]" (an ancient Greek name for the evening star) and "[[Phosphorus]]" (an ancient Greek name for the morning star) both refer to [[Venus]], but the astronomical fact that '"Hesperus" is "Phosphorus"' can still be informative, even if the "meanings" of "Hesperus" and "Phosphorus" are already known. This problem led Frege to distinguish between the [[sense and reference]] of a word. Some cases seem to be too complicated to be classified within this framework; the acceptance of the notion of [[secondary reference]] may be necessary to fill the gap. See also [[Opaque context]].

===Linguistic sign===
The very concept of the [[linguistic sign]] is the combination of content and expression, the former of which may refer entities in the world or refer more abstract concepts, e.g. thought.
Certain parts of speech exist only to express reference, namely [[Anaphora (linguistics)|anaphora]] such as [[pronoun]]s. The subset of reflexives expresses co-reference of two participants in a sentence.  These could be the [[Agent (grammar)|agent]] (actor) and patient (acted on), as in "The man washed himself", the theme and recipient, as in "I showed Mary to herself", or various other possible combinations.

==Computer science==
{{Main|Reference (computer science)}}
In [[computer science]], [[Reference (computer science)|reference]]s are [[data type]]s that refer to an object elsewhere in memory and are used to construct a wide variety of [[data structure]]s, such as [[linked list]]s. Generally, a reference is a value that enables a program to directly access the particular data item. Most [[programming language]]s support some form of reference. For the specific type of reference used in the [[C++]] language, see [[reference (C++)]].

The notion of reference is also important in relational [[database theory]]; see [[referential integrity]].

==Library and information sciences==
{{see also|Reference work|Reference desk}}

References to many types of printed matter may come in an electronic or machine-readable form. For books, there exists the [[International Standard Book Number|ISBN]] and for journal articles, the [[Digital object identifier|Digital object identifier (DOI)]] is gaining relevance. Information on the [[Internet]] may be referred to by a [[Uniform Resource Identifier|Uniform Resource Identifier (URI)]].

==Psychology==
In terms of mental processing, a [[self-reference]] is used in psychology to establish identification with a mental state during self-analysis. This seeks to allow the individual to develop own frames of reference in a greater state of immediate awareness. However, it can also lead to circular reasoning, preventing evolution of thought.&lt;ref&gt;Engle, Eric, ''Lex Naturalis, Ius Naturalis: Law as Positive Reasoning &amp; Natural Rationality'', The Rlias Clark Group, Melbourne, 2010, p.75&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Perceptual Control Theory (PCT), a reference condition is the state toward which a control system's output tends to alter a controlled quantity. The main proposition is that "All behavior is oriented all of the time around the control of certain quantities with respect to specific reference conditions."&lt;ref&gt;Powers, William, ''Behavior: The Control of Perception'', 2nd ed., Benchmark Publications, New Canaan, Connecticut, 2005, pp.47 &amp; 299&lt;/ref&gt;

==Scholarship==
In academics and scholarship, an author-title-date information in [[Bibliography|bibliographies]] and [[footnote]]s, specifying complete works of other people. Copying of material by another author without proper citation or without required permissions is [[plagiarism]].

Keeping a [[diary]] allows an individual to use references for personal organization, whether or not anyone else understands the systems of reference used. However, scholars have studied methods of reference because of their key role in communication and co-operation between ''different'' people, and also because of misunderstandings that can arise. Modern academic study of reference has been developing since the 19th century.&lt;ref&gt;
Reimer, Marga (2009). "[http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/reference Reference]". ''[[Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy]]''&lt;/ref&gt;

In scholarship, a reference may be a [[citation]] of a text that has been used in the creation of a piece of work such as an essay, report, or oration. Its primary purpose is to allow people who read such work to examine the author's sources, either for [[Validity (logic)|validity]] or to learn more about the subject. Such items are often listed at the end of an article or book in a section marked "[[Bibliography]]" or "References". A bibliographical section often contains works not cited by the author, but used as background reading or listed as potentially useful to the reader. A reference section contains only those works cited by the author(s) in the main text.

==Law==
In [[patent]] law, a reference is a document that can be used to show the state of knowledge at a given time and that therefore may make a [[claim (patent)|claim]]ed [[invention]] [[Inventive step and non-obviousness|obvious]] or [[Novelty (patent)#United States|anticipated]]. Examples of references are patents of any country, magazine articles, [[Doctor of Philosophy|Ph.D.]] theses that are indexed and thus accessible to those interested in finding information about the subject matter, and to some extent Internet material that is similarly accessible.

==Arts==
In [[art]], a reference is an item from which a work is based. This may include:
* an existing artwork,
* a reproduction (i.e., photo),
* directly observed object (i.e., person), or
* the artist's memory.
Another example of reference is [[Sampling (music)|samples]] of various musical works being incorporated into a new one.

==See also==
*[[Antecedent (grammar)]]
*[[Exemplification]]
*[[Generic antecedent]]
*[[Hyperlink]]
*[[Indexicality]]
*[[ISO 690]]
*[[Recommendation letter]]
*[[Signified and signifier]]

==References==
&lt;references /&gt;

==External links==
{{Wiktionary}}
* {{SEP|reference|Reference|Marga Reimer|2014-09-26}}
*[http://www.reference.com/ Reference.com] – a multi-source encyclopedia search service, and language reference products provider
*[http://www.references.net/ References.net] – a directory of multidisciplinary reference resources on the web
*[http://dir.yahoo.com/Reference/ Reference Resources] – reference related websites in the Yahoo! Directory
*[http://www.refmuseum.com/ Refmuseum.com] - The online museum of references

{{logic}}

[[Category:Reference| ]]
[[Category:Semantics]]
[[Category:Philosophical logic]]
[[Category:Concepts in logic]]
[[Category:Syntactic relationships]]
[[Category:Meaning (philosophy of language)]]</text>
      <sha1>huu7wyq1tn3i4c22y25a52j7l11zm7i</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Reference desk</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>17892</id>
    <revision>
      <id>863109834</id>
      <parentid>863109729</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-10-08T19:37:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Shellwood</username>
        <id>2366721</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contributions/Sounsarath|Sounsarath]] ([[User talk:Sounsarath|talk]]) ([[WP:HG|HG]]) (3.4.4)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="11676">{{selfref|This is not the Wikipedia reference desk; this is the article about reference desks. The Wikipedia reference desk is at [[Wikipedia:Reference desk]].&lt;!-- If this is not Wikipedia, please remove this notice, or adapt it to this website as it was copied from Wikipedia.--&gt;}}
{{more footnotes|date=August 2014}}
[[Image:Historylink Ballardlib03.JPG|thumb|right|Librarian, [[Ballard Carnegie Library]], [[Seattle, Washington]] ca. 1907]]

The '''reference desk''' or '''information desk''' of a library is a public service counter where professional [[librarian]]s provide library users with direction to library materials, advice on library collections and services, and expertise on multiple kinds of information from multiple sources.

==Purpose and usage==
Library users can consult the staff at the reference desk for help in finding information.  Using a structured [[reference interview]], the librarian works with the library user to clarify their needs and determine what information sources will fill them.&lt;ref name="reference desk"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Miles|first1=Dennis B.|title=Shall We Get Rid Of The Reference Desk?|journal=Reference &amp; User Services Quarterly|date=2013|volume=52|issue=4}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="BLS Librarians"&gt;{{cite web|last1=Crosby|first1=Olivia|title=Librarians: Information Experts in the Information Age|url=http://www.bls.gov/careeroutlook/2000/Winter/art01.pdf|website=Bureau of Labor Statistics|accessdate=1 April 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;  To borrow a medical analogy, reference librarians diagnose and treat information deficiencies.

The ultimate help provided may consist of reading material in the form of a [[book]] or [[Academic journal|journal]] article, instruction in the use of specific searchable information resources such as the library's online [[library catalog|catalog]] or subscription [[bibliographic database|bibliographic/fulltext database]]s, or simply factual information drawn from the library's print or online [[reference work|reference collection]].  Information is also provided to patrons through electronic resources.&lt;ref name="BLS Librarians" /&gt; Typically, a reference desk can be consulted either in person, by telephone, through email or online chat, although a library user may be asked to come to the library in person for help with more involved research questions.  A staffed and knowledgeable reference desk is an essential part of a library.

The services that are provided at a reference desk may vary depending on the type of library, its purpose, its resources, and its staff.

==History==
Reference services did not become commonplace in libraries until the late 1800s. These services initially began in public libraries.&lt;ref name="Evolution of Library Reference"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Deng|first1=Liya|title=The Evolution of Library Reference Services: From General to Special, 1876-1920's|journal=Libri: International Journal of Libraries &amp; Information Services|date=September 2014|volume=64|issue=3|pages=254–262}}&lt;/ref&gt; At first librarians were hesitant to offer reference services because many libraries did not have a large enough staff to provide the services without other duties being neglected.&lt;ref name="Evolution of Library Reference" /&gt; Beginning in 1883 with the [[Boston Public Library]], libraries began to hire librarians whose primary duty was to provide reference services.&lt;ref name="Evolution of Library Reference" /&gt;

One of the earliest proponents of references services was [[Samuel Swett Green]]. He wrote an article titled "Personal Relations Between Librarians and Readers" which had a large impact on the future of reference services.&lt;ref name="Evolution of Library Reference" /&gt;
then, it operated to incorporate ... making the following variables relevant in offering reference services: the user's query; the reference librarian; and, the reference sources. Until hitherto the communication between the reference librarian and the user are through direct contact. Hence, Utor (2008), defined reference services as a direct personal assistance to readers seeking information. That is during the traditional era. towards the later decades of 19th century, however, reference and information services witnessed an insidious yet drastic paradigm-shift following the incorporation of information communication technology in reference services (and in library operations, by extension). Thus leading to an entirely new era, otherwise known as digital era with different information technologies coming in to aid the work of a reference librarian; changing information sources, reference processes and communication medium.

==Resources==
Resources that are often kept at a library reference desk may include:
* A computer with internet access. Librarians use both the public web and subscription databases to find and evaluate information and research sources. 
* A small collection of [[reference work|reference book]]s (called ''ready reference'') that are most often used, so that the librarians can reach them quickly, especially when they are on the phone, and so that the books will be returned in time for someone else to use later the same day. The library's full reference collection is usually nearby as well.
* Newspaper clipping files and other rare or restricted items that must be returned to the reference desk.
* Index cards with the answers to frequently asked questions, and/or drawers with folders of pamphlets and photocopies of pages that, from previous experience, were difficult to find.  These enable librarians to find such information quickly without leaving the desk—even faster than they could look it up in a reference book or using the Internet.
* Books and other items that are being held for library users who asked the librarian by phone to set them aside for them to pick up later the same day, or within the next few days.
* Books from the circulating collection that have been set aside for students working on a special assignment, and are temporarily designated to be used only within the library until the project is due.
* Printed lists of items in the library that are not in the catalogue, such as newspapers, school yearbooks, old telephone directories, college course catalogues, and local history sources.

==Services==
Services that are often available at a library reference desk include:
* A sign up sheet for reserving computers with Internet access, or [[Word processor|word processing]] software.
* The ability to place the book 'on hold', which prevents the person who has borrowed it from renewing it.  The person who placed the 'hold' is notified when the book has been returned. (Some libraries provide this service at the [[Library circulation|circulation]] desk.)
* The ability to request [[interlibrary loan]] of books and other material from other branch libraries in the same library system, or from a cooperating library anywhere in the world. (Some libraries provide this service at the circulation desk.)
* The opportunity to recommend that the library purchase something for its collection that it doesn't have, which may be needed or of interest to other library users.

The [[librarian]] who staffs the reference desk can usually do the following by virtue of their professional training and experience:
* The librarian can look up a brief, factual answer to a specific question.
* The librarian can use the catalogue to find out whether the library owns an item with a particular title or author, or that contains a short story, chapter, song, or poem with a particular title, or to compile a list of books by a particular author or on a particular subject.
* The librarian can briefly teach the user how to use the catalogue and how to use its advanced features, or recommend the proper subject words or terms that are used in the catalogue for the topic the user has in mind.
* The librarian can often take the library user directly to the shelves with books on a certain topic without using the catalogue.
* The librarian is familiar with the contents of hundreds of [[reference work|reference book]]s, and can recommend books that might contain the answer to a particular question.
* The librarian can teach the library user to use online [[database]]s such as [[magazine]] and [[newspaper]] articles, and recommend words and search strategies for the topic the user has in mind.
* The librarian can recommend reliable [[Website|web sites]], give advice on searching the Internet for information, and evaluate the reliability of the information on web sites.
* If the library doesn't have information on a given topic, or if the library user wants more information, the librarian can refer the library user to another library or to an organization that can be contacted by phone or mail.
*Offer aid with devices such as tablets and e-readers.  This can range from general assistance with questions on how to navigate e-reader and tablet devices to instructing classes.  Questions can vary from what devices are compatible with the library's e-book platform, how to check out books, and how to read electronic books.

==Staff qualifications==
In the [[United States]], those who staff library reference desks are usually required to have a master's degree in library science&lt;ref name="BLS Librarians" /&gt; from a program accredited by the [[American Library Association]].&lt;ref name="librarian education"&gt;{{cite web|title=Librarians: How to Become a Librarian|url=http://www.bls.gov/ooh/education-training-and-library/librarians.htm#tab-4|website=Bureau of Labor Statistics|accessdate=1 April 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, if there is a lack of qualified applicants, particularly in rural areas, a person with an associate degree, a certificate in library technology, or a bachelor's degree in library science may perform these duties. In many academic libraries, student assistants are used as the primary contact, sometimes at an "information desk."

In [[Sri Lanka]], librarians at reference desks typically have master's degrees from the Sri Lankan Library Association's accredited programs.

==Electronic reference services==
With the development of the Web, [[Digital Reference Services|digital reference services]] are beginning to take over some of the roles of the traditional reference desk in a library. There is disagreement over whether or not this development is desirable or inevitable.&lt;ref&gt;[http://chronicle.com/weekly/v53/i33/33a03701.htm  Are Reference Desks Dying Out?] by Scott Carlson, ''Chronicle of Higher Education'' April 20, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Ask a Librarian]]
*[[Digital reference]]
*[[Library#The Internet|Internet search engines and libraries]]
*[[Reference scenario]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://ucla245.pbwiki.com/ UCLA DIS 245 "Info Access" Wiki on Reference Services, edited by John V. Richardson Jr. and Debbie Weismann]
*[http://www.cilip.org.uk/publications/updatemagazine/archive/archive2005/june/chan.htm 24 Hour Reference Service article by Ben Chan]
*[http://www.michaellorenzen.com/eric/digital-reference.html Trends and Issues in Digital Reference Services]
*[http://www.michaellorenzen.com/eric/reference-services.html Building and Maintaining Digital Reference Services]
*[http://www.michaellorenzen.com/mbwa.html Management by Wandering Around: Reference Rovering and Quality Reference Service]
*[http://www.ala.org/ala/mgrps/divs/rusa/resources/guidelines/index.cfm Reference and User Services Association Guidelines]
*[http://polaris.gseis.ucla.edu/jrichardson/DIS245/personal.htm Personal Relations Between Librarians and Readers] by Samuel Swett Green

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Library resources]]
[[Category:Reference]]</text>
      <sha1>mpjtz2sbuktpeelmlltnbxk0c6jswlx</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Reference interview</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5550409</id>
    <revision>
      <id>862228893</id>
      <parentid>848678013</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-10-03T00:36:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Nyttend</username>
        <id>1960810</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* The virtual reference interview */ Libraries can't exist without a technology called [[writing]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="10284">A '''reference interview''' is a conversation between a [[librarian]] and a [[library]] user, usually at a [[library reference desk|reference desk]], in which the librarian responds to the user's initial explanation of his or her information need by first attempting to clarify that need and then by directing the user to appropriate information resources.

==Definition==
Bopp &amp; Smith (1995) defines the reference interview as the "conversation between a member of the library reference staff and a library user for the purpose of clarifying the user’s needs and aiding the user in meeting those needs".{{sfnp|Bopp|Smith|1995|p=37}} 

According to ODLIS, the reference interview is "the interpersonal communication that occurs between a reference librarian and a library user to determine the person's specific information need(s), which may turn out to be different from the reference question as initially posed...A reference interview may occur in person, by telephone, or electronically (usually via e-mail) at the request of the user, but a well-trained reference librarian will sometimes initiate communication if a hesitant user appears to need assistance".{{sfnp|Reitz|2014}}

== Parts of a reference interview ==

The reference interview is structured to help the librarian provide answers to the library user. In general, the interview is composed of the following stages.{{sfnp|Ross|Nilsen|Dewdney|2002|p=3}}

#Welcoming
#Gathering general information from the user and getting an overview of the problem
#Confirming the exact question
#Intervention, such as giving information, advice or instructions
#Finishing, including feedback and summary

These stages may occur in loops, for example when a clarification of the question leads to the need to establish more background information on the query topic. These steps are designed to put the user at their ease, and then help ensure that they have correctly explained what they require. When the reference librarian believes that the query is fully understood, they attempt to provide resources that help satisfy it. An important and often overlooked final step is checking that the information or service provided was indeed what the library user required.

==Reference interview techniques==

The purpose behind the reference interview structure is to ensure that the library user's [[information need]] is satisfied. The librarian can use a number of interview techniques to help identify the user's exact need. Poor reference interview skills may lead to misinterpretation of the real question, a lack of real help and an unsatisfied library user.{{sfnp|Nilsen|2005|p=3}}

Librarians use many techniques to help identify a user’s information need. With body language, repetition and paraphrasing of what the user says, the interviewer can encourage the user to give more information about what they need. Asking open questions establishes context and helps to identify exactly what is required. A lack of follow-up, or checking that the user found what they required, is arguably one of the most common mistakes made in the reference interview.{{sfnp|Nilsen|2005|p=6}}

==Forming the query==

One of the biggest problems with providing an effective reference service is that of badly formed queries. In this instance, the user's reference question doesn't match up to the information they actually need.{{sfnp|Fields|2006|pp=405-420}} Badly formed queries may lead to user frustration, as they perceive that the reference interview is not solving their problem. 

Many of the techniques used in the reference interview are geared towards developing a badly formed query until a sense of the user's true information need is gained. A great degree of care must be taken when helping users to develop their query. The librarian typically has little insight into the social and psychological barriers that might be preventing the user from explaining their question accurately. Anything from anxiety from an approaching deadline to lack of confidence with language can get in the way.{{sfnp|Murphy|2005|pp=247-252}}

==The virtual reference interview==
{{main| Virtual reference}}
 
As libraries have begun to adopt electronic technology into their operations, the idea of the virtual reference interview has come to light. Virtual reference is a reference service initiated electronically, often in real-time. The user and librarian do not meet face-to-face. Virtual reference services can be conducted, for example, in internet chat, videoconferencing, email, [[cobrowsing|co-browsing]] and [[instant messaging]]. 

Uptake of virtual reference has not been as swift as some had predicted. The complexity of virtual reference may be to blame, as users want information quickly and with the minimum of fuss.{{sfnp|Stormont|2007|p=119}} Some evidence suggests that the problem lies with poor uptake and training among library staff.{{sfnp|Nilsen|2005|p=8}}

==Library users and reference services==

Library users are not always comfortable with reference services, let alone satisfied with them. [[Unobtrusive measures|Unobtrusive user studies]] suggest that only around 55% to 65% of users leave a reference interview satisfied with the result and willing to return.{{sfnp|Nilsen|2005|p=3}} Demographics, social factors and users’ preconceptions about libraries all contribute to this figure. Embarrassment, shyness, and anxiety can prevent a user from approaching the reference desk, and poor signposting and explanation of services can mean that some customers aren't aware that the reference service exists. To be as effective as possible, libraries must be proactive in publicizing their services and reducing the stigma of asking for help.{{sfnp|Robinson|Reid|2007|pp=405-424}}

==Usefulness of the reference interview==

For a long time, the value of the reference interview has stood unquestioned. More recently, with technological developments streamlining some of the tasks which once comprised the interview, some researchers are beginning to question the validity of the reference interview, and the investment that a reference librarian represents.{{sfnp|Ryan|2008|pp=389-399}} Others argue that reference services should broaden their target audience. As people increasingly use the internet to make major, life-affecting decisions, so they also require the services of  professionals who are able to provide help in this environment.{{sfnp|Janes|2003|pp=22-25}} If this proves to be the case, it will become more vital that the reference interview be conducted professionally and successfully. In the age of [[information overload]], a successful reference interview may empower users to confidently make such decisions in their lives.

== See also ==
*[[Information seeking behavior]]
*[[Library reference desk]]
*[[Reference scenarios]]

== References ==
{{reflist|2}}

== Citations ==
{{refbegin|2}}
* {{cite book|last1=Bopp|first1=Richard E.|last2=Smith|first2=Linda C.|title=Reference and Information Services: An Introduction|edition=second|location=Englewood, Colorado|publisher=Libraries Unlimited|year=1995|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Childers|first=T.|title=The Effectiveness of Information Service in Public Libraries: Suffolk County: Final Report.|year=1978|publisher=Drexel University, School of Library, and Information Science.|location=Philadelphia, PA}}
* {{cite journal|last=Fields|first=A.|year=2006|title=Ill-structured Problems and the Reference Consultation: The Librarian’s Role in Developing Student Expertise|journal=[[Reference Services Review]]|volume=34|issue=3|ref=harv}}
* {{cite journal|last=Janes|first=J.|year=2003|title=What is reference for?|journal=Reference Services Review|volume=31|issue=1|ref=harv}}
* {{cite journal|last=Murphy|first=S|year=2005|title=The Reference Narrative|journal=[[Reference &amp; User Services Quarterly]]|volume=44|issue=3|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Nilsen|first=K|year=2005|title=Virtual versus Face-to-Face Reference: Comparing Users' Perspectives on Visits to Physical and Virtual Reference Desks in Public and Academic Libraries|publisher=World Library and Information Congress: 71st IFLA General Conference and Council, IFLA.|ref=harv}}
* {{cite dictionary|editor-first=Joan M.|editor-last=Reitz|dictionary=ODLIS - Online Dictionary for Library and Information Science|article=Reference interview|year=2014|url=http://www.abc-clio.com/ODLIS/odlis_R.aspx#refinterview|accessdate=12 June 2012|ref=harv}}
* {{cite journal|last1=Robinson|first1=R|last2=Reid|first2=P|year=2007|title=Do academic enquiry services scare students?|journal=Reference Services Review|volume=35|issue=3|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last1=Ross|first1=C.|last2=Nilsen|first2=K.|last3=Dewdney|first3=P.|title=Conducting the Reference Interview: A How-To-Do-It Manual for Librarians|location=London|publisher=Facet Publishing|year=2002|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Ross|first=S. R|title=Why bother with a reference interview?|year=2009|publisher=London, Facet|location=London|pages=1–37}}
* {{cite journal|last=Ryan|first=S.|year=2008|title=Reference Transactions Analysis: The Cost-effectiveness of Staffing a Traditional Academic Reference Desk|journal=The Journal of Academic Librarianship|volume=34|issue=5|ref=harv}}
* {{cite journal|last1=Stormont|first1=S.|year=2007|title=Looking to Connect: Technical Challenges that Impede the Growth of Virtual Reference|journal=Reference &amp; User Services Quarterly|volume=47|issue=2|ref=harv}}
{{refend}}

== Further reading ==
* Jennerich, Elaine Z. and Jennerich, Edward J. (1997). ''The Reference Interview as a Creative Art''. Westport, CT: Libraries Unlimited.
* Katz, William A. (2001). ''Introduction to Reference Work, Vol. 1: Basic Information Services''. 8th Ed. New York : McGraw-Hill.
* Katz, William A. (2001). ''Introduction to Reference Work, Vol. 2: Reference Services and Reference Processes''. 8th Ed. New York : McGraw-Hill.

== External links ==
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20150106233918/http://www.olc.org/ore/2intro.htm Ohio Reference Excellence]
*[http://www.ala.org/rusa/resources/guidelines/guidelinesbehavioral Guidelines for Behavioral Performance of Reference and Information Service Providers]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Reference Interview}}
[[Category:Library resources]]
[[Category:Reference]]</text>
      <sha1>jtz95s1v23t68hz719xvc8biw93s15l</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Reference scenario</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8912106</id>
    <revision>
      <id>692556040</id>
      <parentid>692556016</parentid>
      <timestamp>2015-11-26T15:19:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Themightyquill</username>
        <id>1212157</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>added [[Category:Library science education]] using [[WP:HC|HotCat]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="2069">{{Unreferenced|date=August 2010}}
A '''reference scenario''' is an imagined situation where a [[library]] patron brings a question to a [[librarian]] and there is then a conversation, called in the field a [[reference interview]], where the librarian works to help the patron find what he or she wants.  These scenarios are used in training future librarians how to help patrons.  Basically, a scenario is as short as a couple of sentences, including a question and a situation that underlies that question.

A great deal of reference teaching puts students to researching the answers to made-up questions.  This focuses the student on learning about the reference sources at hand by using them to answer those questions.  Scenarios are something different.  They focus the student on the interaction with patrons.  In class practice sessions, one student can be the patron and the other the librarian, as long as the one practicing as the librarian doesn't know the whole scenario in advance.

Scenarios are valued because often the question asked is not the end of the patron's information hunt, but the start.  Patrons often start by voicing a question that they think the library can answer, rather than the question they are really seeking to answer.  Or they pose a question that the librarian doesn't understand.  Reference librarian skills are very much about mediating a gap between what the patron wants and what the library can provide.  This can involve the librarian making him or herself a partner in the patron's search, teaching them what the library really has to offer, or even just clarifying a confusing word: Does the patron want information about soaps to clean with or soaps as in soap operas?

== See also ==

*[[Reference work]]
*[[Library reference desk]]

== Further reading ==

* Ross, Catherine, Kirsti Nilsen, and Patricia Dewdney. ''Conducting the Reference Interview: A How-To-Do-It Manual for Librarians''.  New York: Neal Schumann, 2002.

{{DEFAULTSORT:Reference Scenario}}
[[Category:Reference]]
[[Category:Library science education]]</text>
      <sha1>8mpvwtqxn5cqo2wz2r3rtqdxtpu52om</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Roving reference</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>47089125</id>
    <revision>
      <id>723854025</id>
      <parentid>704089367</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-06-05T18:14:44Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Dcirovic</username>
        <id>11795905</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* top */refs using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="2318">'''Roving reference''', also called '''roaming reference''', is a library service model in which, instead of being positioned at a static [[reference desk]], a [[librarian]] moves throughout the library to locate patrons with questions or concerns and offer them help in finding or using library resources.&lt;ref name=ifla&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://archive.ifla.org/VII/dg/dgrw/dp99-05.htm|publisher=IFLA|title=Roving Reference: A New Approach to User Services|author1=Courtois, Martin |author2=Liriano, Maira |date=31 May 1999}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
Roving reference as a library service practice was first formalized in the late 1980s and early 1990s. A 1999 report from the [[International Federation of Library Associations]] identified several advantages and disadvantages with roving reference in the pre-mobile era. The roving model allowed librarians to engage with "the majority of users who have questions in mind [who] do not approach the reference desk for assistance".&lt;ref name=ifla/&gt; However, libraries reported that some staff were uncomfortable with the practice, and that there were concerns about user privacy.&lt;ref name=ifla/&gt;

Beginning in the 2000s, librarians used laptops or laptop carts to engage in technology-supported roaming reference. Since the development of mobile technologies, roving reference can be facilitated with the use of such technologies, such as [[tablet computer]]s, which allow librarians to readily check the [[online public access catalogue]] or the library's electronic databases while away from their desk.&lt;ref&gt;Smith, Annie; Stevens, Mark (2012). "We're Going Mobile: Roving Reference in an Academic Library" Utah Library Association.&lt;/ref&gt; This has contributed to the increased popularization of roving-reference programs as supplements for more traditional reference desks. The model has also been extended to service beyond the library building (library outreach), for example in a dormitory or faculty building at an academic institution.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|editors=Bowers, Jennifer; Forbes, Carrie|title=Rethinking Reference for Academic Libraries: Innovative Developments and Future Trends|year=2014|publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield|chapter=Roving Reference|author=Wilkinson, Zara|pages=85&amp;ndash;98|isbn=9781442244535}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Reference]]</text>
      <sha1>o2hwe4sogfl9kolos9dnzxv0r3p6q3x</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>The Map Library</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5928902</id>
    <revision>
      <id>842034289</id>
      <parentid>546585224</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-05-19T19:43:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>RafaelS1979</username>
        <id>26363365</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* top */clean up using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="2195">{{Unreferenced|date=November 2010}}
{{MapLibrary|Congo sat.png|Republic of Congo}}
:''The Map Library should not be confused with the [[Map Library]] of [[The British Museum]].''

'''''The Map Library''''' is a project of '''The Map Maker Trust''' [[Charitable organization|charity]], and supported by '''Map Maker Ltd.''', for the supplying of free [[GIS]] data. The project website also hosts free conversion software for [[raster graphics|raster]] and [[vector graphics|vector]] files. As of November 2008, the only data sets available were for the continents of [[Africa]] and [[Central America]].

== Statement of purpose ==
From the website...

:''The idea behind the Map Library is that the lack of good, simple maps is a serious obstacle to development in all kinds of fields, from health care to urban management, from de-mining to environmental protection. The library's purpose is two fold: to make public domain mapping data more readily available for developing countries, and to provide free, easy to use software to facilitate map making by non-experts. The Map Library delivers data and software both on the internet and by post on CD for those with poor or no internet access.''

== Data format and conversion ==
The project data is managed in part by two pieces of software, each supporting different file formats and conversions.

* '''''Raster Converter''''' handles [[ECW (file format)|ECW]] files: these can be converted to [[BMP file format|BMP]], [[TIFF]], and with external libraries, [[JPEG]], and [[JPEG 2000]].
* '''''Vector Converter''''' handles MLB ("map-library") files: these files can be converted to data files for [[ArcView]], [[AutoCAD]], and several other formats.

== Data sources ==
The project uses data from [[NASA]] mapping projects, [[Famine Early Warning Systems Network]], and the [[National Geospatial-Intelligence Agency]].

== See also ==
*[[Commons:Category:Images Generated From Map Library Sources]]

== External links ==
*[http://www.maplibrary.org/ The Map Library]
*[http://www.mapmaker.com/ Map Maker Ltd.]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Map Library}}
[[Category:Web Map Services]]
[[Category:Reference]]
[[Category:Discipline-oriented digital libraries]]</text>
      <sha1>cnvxwfbb1p6vltuakf5buvt0v1p1ah6</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
